<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10.xsd" version="0.10" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <dbname>enwiki</dbname>
    <base>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.32.0-wmf.16</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="118" case="first-letter">Draft</namespace>
      <namespace key="119" case="first-letter">Draft talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2300" case="first-letter">Gadget</namespace>
      <namespace key="2301" case="first-letter">Gadget talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2302" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition</namespace>
      <namespace key="2303" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Amelia Earhart</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>85234</id>
    <revision>
      <id>854173544</id>
      <parentid>854173400</parentid>
      <timestamp>2018-08-09T13:10:59Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Shawnmb</username>
        <id>428284</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor/>
      <comment>/* Gardner Island hypothesis */ Typo fix</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="200604">{{Other uses}}
{{Pp-semi-indef}}
{{Pp-move-indef}}
{{Use mdy dates|date=April 2018}}
{{Use American English|date=April 2018}}

{{Infobox person
|name                 = Amelia Earhart
|image                = Amelia Earhart standing under nose of her Lockheed Model 10-E Electra, small.jpg
|image_size           =
|caption              = Earhart beneath the nose of her [[Lockheed Model 10-E Electra]], March 1937, [[Oakland, California]]
|birth_name           = Amelia Mary Earhart
|birth_date           = {{birth date|1897|07|24}}
|birth_place          = [[Atchison, Kansas]], U.S.
|disappeared_date     = {{Disappeared date and age|1937|7|2|1897|7|24}}
|disappeared_place    = Pacific Ocean, en route to [[Howland Island]] from [[Lae]], [[Papua New Guinea]]
|disappeared_status   = [[Declared death in absentia|Declared dead ''in absentia'']]&lt;br /&gt;{{Death date and age|1939|1|5|1897|7|24}}
|spouse               = {{marriage|[[George P. Putnam]]|February 7, 1931|}}
|known_for            = Many early aviation records, including first woman to [[transatlantic flight|fly solo across the Atlantic Ocean]]
|signature            = Amelia Earhart (signature).png
| website             = {{Official website}}
}}

'''Amelia Mary Earhart''' ({{IPAc-en|ˈ|ɛər|h|ɑr|t}}, born July 24, 1897; disappeared July 2, 1937) was an American [[aviation pioneer]] and author.{{sfn|Morey|1995|p=11}}{{refn|Charles Kuralt said on [[CBS]] television program ''Sunday Morning'', referring to Earhart: "She was a pioneer in aviation ... she led the way so that others could follow and go on to even greater achievements," further stating, "trailblazers prepare the rest of us for the future."{{sfn|Oakes|1985}}|group=Note}} Earhart was [[women in aviation|the first female aviator]] to fly solo across the Atlantic Ocean.{{sfn|Pearce|1988|p=95}}{{refn|Earhart set several records, being the first woman to fly across the Atlantic, first as a passenger and later, as a solo pilot; the period term for a female pilot was "aviatrix", and is still in use.&lt;ref&gt;Ferdinando, Lisa. [http://www.voanews.com/content/clinton-celebrates-american-pioneer-amelia-earhart-143507376/179233.html "Clinton Celebrates Pioneer Aviatrix Amelia Earhart."] {{webarchive|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20120614174340/http://www.voanews.com/content/clinton-celebrates-american-pioneer-amelia-earhart-143507376/179233.html |date=June 14, 2012 }} ''Voice of America'', March 19, 2012.&lt;/ref&gt;|group=Note}} She received the [[Distinguished Flying Cross (United States)|United States Distinguished Flying Cross]] for this accomplishment.{{sfn|Goldstein|Dillon|1997|pp=111, 112}} She set many other records,{{sfn|Oakes|1985}} wrote best-selling books about her flying experiences and was instrumental in the formation of [[Ninety-Nines|The Ninety-Nines]], an organization for female pilots.{{sfn|Lovell|1989|p=152}} In 1935, Earhart became a visiting faculty member at [[Purdue University]] as an advisor to [[Purdue University School of Aeronautics and Astronautics|aeronautical engineering]] and a career counselor to women students. She was also a member of the [[National Woman's Party]] and an early supporter of the [[Equal Rights Amendment]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.feminism101.com/timelineera.html "Timeline: Equal Rights Amendment, Phase One: 1921–1972."] {{webarchive|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20121208094346/http://www.feminism101.com/timelineera.html |date=December 8, 2012 }} ''feminism101.com''. Retrieved: June 4, 2012.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Francis, Roberta W.[https://web.archive.org/web/20110721112813/http://www.equalrightsamendment.org/era.htm "The History Behind the Equal Rights Amendment."] ''equalrightsamendment.org'', July 21, 2011. Retrieved: June 4, 2012.&lt;/ref&gt;

During an attempt to make a [[circumnavigation]]al flight of the globe in 1937 in a Purdue-funded [[Lockheed Model 10-E Electra]], Earhart and navigator [[Fred Noonan]] [[List of aerial disappearances|disappeared]] over the central Pacific Ocean near [[Howland Island]]. Fascination with her life, career, and disappearance continues to this day.{{refn|Quote: "She vanished nearly 60 years ago, but fascination with Amelia Earhart continues through each new generation."&lt;ref&gt;[https://web.archive.org/web/20070210133356/http://sss.cuesta.com/c/article.html?article@AE+s@YMPhLU1xRL1uA "The Mystery of Amelia Earhart."] ''Social Studies School Service'', February 10, 2007. Retrieved: July 12, 2017.&lt;/ref&gt; |group=Note}}

== Early life ==

=== Childhood ===

[[File:ameliachild.jpg|left|thumb|Earhart as a child]]

Earhart was the daughter of Samuel "Edwin" Stanton Earhart (1867–1930) and Amelia "Amy" ({{née|[[Otis family|Otis]]}}; 1869–1962).&lt;ref&gt;[https://web.archive.org/web/20060901135618/http://oasis.harvard.edu:10080/oasis/deliver/~sch00228 "A/E11/M-129, Earhart, Amy Otis, 1869–1962. Papers, 1944, n.d.: A Finding Aid."] ''Harvard University Library.'', September 1, 2006. (archived). Retrieved: June 3, 2012.&lt;/ref&gt; She was born in [[Atchison, Kansas|Atchison]], Kansas, in the [[Amelia Earhart Birthplace|home of her maternal grandfather]], Alfred Gideon Otis (1827–1912), who was a former [[United States federal judge|federal judge]], the president of the Atchison Savings Bank and a leading citizen in the town. Amelia was the second child of the marriage, after an infant was stillborn in August 1896.{{sfn|Goldstein|Dillon|1997|p=8}} She was of part [[German American|German]] descent. Alfred Otis had not initially favored the marriage and was not satisfied with Edwin's progress as a lawyer.{{sfn|Goldstein|Dillon|1997|p=9}}

According to family custom, Earhart was named after her two grandmothers, Amelia Josephine Harres and Mary Wells Patton.{{sfn|Goldstein|Dillon|1997|p=8}} From an early age, Amelia was the ringleader while her sister Grace Muriel Earhart (1899–1998), two years her junior, acted as the dutiful follower.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.ninety-nines.org/grace-muriel-earhart-morrissey.htm "Grace Muriel Earhart Morrissey."] {{webarchive|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20151130001159/http://www.ninety-nines.org/grace-muriel-earhart-morrissey.htm |date=November 30, 2015 }} ''The Ninety-Nines''. Retrieved: June 3, 2012.&lt;/ref&gt; Amelia was nicknamed "Meeley" (sometimes "Millie") and Grace was nicknamed "Pidge"; both girls continued to answer to their childhood nicknames well into adulthood.{{sfn|Goldstein|Dillon|1997|p=8}} Their upbringing was unconventional since Amy Earhart did not believe in molding her children into "nice little girls".{{sfn|Goldstein|Dillon|1997|pp=8–9}} Meanwhile their maternal grandmother disapproved of the "[[Bloomers (clothing)|bloomers]]" worn by Amy's children and although Earhart liked the freedom they provided, she was aware other girls in the neighborhood did not wear them.

=== Early influence ===

[[File:United States postage stamp honoring Amelia Earhart (1963).jpg|thumb|right|1963 U.S. Postal stamp honoring Earhart]]

A spirit of adventure seemed to abide in the Earhart children, with the pair setting off daily to explore their neighborhood.{{refn|Quote: "... the judge nevertheless adored his brave and intelligent granddaughter and in her [Earhart's] love of adventure, she seemed to have inherited his pioneering spirit."{{sfn|Randolph|1987|p=16}}|group=Note}} As a child, Earhart spent long hours playing with sister Pidge, climbing trees, hunting rats with a rifle and "belly-slamming" her sled downhill.&lt;ref&gt;[https://web.archive.org/web/20120412224805/http://www-tc.pbs.org/wgbh/americanexperience/media/uploads/special_features/download_files/amelia_transcript.pdf "American Experience: Amelia Earhart Program Transcript."] ''americanexperience'', April 12, 2012. Retrieved: September 23, 2017.&lt;/ref&gt; Although the love of the outdoors and "rough-and-tumble" play was common to many youngsters, some biographers have characterized the young Earhart as a [[tomboy]].{{sfn|Rich|1989|p=4}} The girls kept "worms, moths, [[Tettigoniidae|katydids]] and a tree toad"{{sfn|Lovell|1989|p=14}} in a growing collection gathered in their outings. In 1904, with the help of her uncle, she cobbled together a home-made ramp fashioned after a roller coaster she had seen on a trip to [[St. Louis, Missouri|St. Louis]] and secured the ramp to the roof of the family toolshed. Earhart's well-documented first flight ended dramatically. She emerged from the broken wooden box that had served as a sled with a bruised lip, torn dress and a "sensation of exhilaration". She exclaimed, "Oh, Pidge, it's just like flying!"{{sfn|Goldstein|Dillon|1997|p=9}}

Although there had been some missteps in Edwin Earhart's career up to that point, in 1907 his job as a claims officer for the [[Rock Island Railroad]] led to a transfer to [[Des Moines, Iowa|Des Moines]], Iowa. The next year, at the age of 10,&lt;ref name="Biography"&gt;[http://www.ameliaearhart.com/about/bio.html "Biography.] {{webarchive|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20120525154635/http://www.ameliaearhart.com/about/bio.html |date=May 25, 2012 }} ''The Official Website of Amelia Earhart (The Family of Amelia Earhart)''. Retrieved: June 4, 2012.&lt;/ref&gt; Earhart saw her first [[fixed-wing aircraft|aircraft]] at the [[Iowa State Fair]] in Des Moines.{{sfn|Goldstein|Dillon|1997|p=14}}{{sfn|Morrissey|1963|pp=17–18}} Her father tried to interest her and her sister in taking a flight. One look at the rickety "flivver" was enough for Earhart, who promptly asked if they could go back to the merry-go-round.{{sfn|Randolph|1987|p=18}} She later described the biplane as "a thing of rusty wire and wood and not at all interesting".{{sfn|Lovell|1989|p=15}}

=== Education ===

The two sisters, Amelia and Muriel (she went by her middle name from her teens on), remained with their grandparents in Atchison, while their parents moved into new, smaller quarters in Des Moines. During this period, Earhart received a form of home-schooling together with her sister, from her mother and a governess. She later recounted that she was "exceedingly fond of reading"{{sfn|Hamill|1976|p=51}} and spent countless hours in the large family library. In 1909, when the family was finally reunited in Des Moines, the Earhart children were enrolled in public school for the first time with Amelia Earhart entering the seventh grade at the age of 12 years.

=== Family fortunes ===

[[File:Amelia-in-evening-clothes (cropped).jpg|thumb|Earhart in evening clothes]]

While the family's finances seemingly improved with the acquisition of a new house and even the hiring of two servants, it soon became apparent that Edwin was an alcoholic. Five years later in 1914, he was forced to retire and although he attempted to rehabilitate himself through treatment, he was never reinstated at the Rock Island Railroad. At about this time, Earhart's grandmother Amelia Otis died suddenly, leaving a substantial estate that placed her daughter's share in a trust, fearing that Edwin's drinking would drain the funds. The Otis house was auctioned along with all of its contents; Earhart was heartbroken and later described it as the end of her childhood.{{sfn|Garst|1947|p=35}}

In 1915, after a long search, Earhart's father found work as a clerk at the [[Great Northern Railway (U.S.)|Great Northern Railway]] in St. Paul, Minnesota, where Earhart entered [[Central High School (Saint Paul, Minnesota)|Central High School]] as a junior. Edwin applied for a transfer to [[Springfield, Missouri|Springfield]], Missouri, in 1915 but the current claims officer reconsidered his retirement and demanded his job back, leaving the elder Earhart with nowhere to go. Facing another calamitous move, Amy Earhart took her children to Chicago, where they lived with friends. Earhart made an unusual condition in the choice of her next schooling; she canvassed nearby high schools in Chicago to find the best science program. She rejected the high school nearest her home when she complained that the chemistry lab was "just like a kitchen sink".{{sfn|Blau|1977|pp=10–11}} She eventually enrolled in [[Hyde Park Career Academy|Hyde Park High School]] but spent a miserable semester where a yearbook caption captured the essence of her unhappiness, "A.E. – the girl in brown who walks alone".{{sfn|Rich|1989|p=11}}

Earhart graduated from Chicago's Hyde Park High School in 1916.{{sfn|Long|Long|1999|p=33}} Throughout her troubled childhood, she had continued to aspire to a future career; she kept a scrapbook of newspaper clippings about successful women in predominantly male-oriented fields, including film direction and production, law, advertising, management and mechanical engineering.&lt;ref name="Biography" /&gt; She began junior college at [[Penn State Abington|Ogontz School]] in [[Rydal, Pennsylvania|Rydal]], Pennsylvania, but did not complete her program.{{sfn|Kerby|1990|pp=18–19}}{{refn|Although a good student, Earhart cut short her time at Ogontz when she became a nursing assistant in Canada.|group=Note}}

During Christmas vacation in 1917, Earhart visited her sister in [[Toronto]]. [[World War I]] had been raging and Earhart saw the returning wounded soldiers. After receiving training as a [[Certified Nursing Assistant|nurse's aide]] from the [[Red Cross]], she began work with the [[Voluntary Aid Detachment]] at [[1 Spadina Crescent|Spadina Military Hospital]]. Her duties included preparing food in the kitchen for patients with special diets and handing out prescribed medication in the hospital's dispensary.&lt;ref name="nurseaide"&gt;Popplewell, Brett. [https://www.thestar.com/News/Ideas/article/451270 "The city Amelia loved".] {{webarchive|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20090611122605/http://www.thestar.com/News/Ideas/article/451270 |date=June 11, 2009 }} ''[[Toronto Star]]'', June 29, 2008. Retrieved: June 30, 2008.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://ids.lib.harvard.edu/ids/view/1391197?buttons=Y "Portrait of Earhart as a volunteer nurse in Toronto."] {{webarchive|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20170924140105/http://ids.lib.harvard.edu/ids/view/1391197?buttons=Y |date=September 24, 2017 }} ''Schlesinger Library on the History of Women in America'' [[Radcliffe Institute for Advanced Study]]. Retrieved: September 23, 2017.&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Spanish flu pandemic of 1918 ===

When the 1918 [[Spanish flu]] pandemic reached Toronto, Earhart was engaged in arduous nursing duties that included night shifts at the Spadina Military Hospital.{{sfn|Lovell|1989|p=27}}{{sfn|Earhart|1932|p=21}} She became a patient herself, suffering from pneumonia and [[Maxillary sinus|maxillary]] [[sinusitis]].{{sfn|Lovell|1989|p=27}} She was hospitalized in early November 1918, owing to pneumonia, and discharged in December 1918, about two months after the illness had started.{{sfn|Lovell|1989|p=27}} Her [[sinus (anatomy)|sinus]]-related symptoms were pain and pressure around one eye and copious mucus drainage via the nostrils and throat.{{sfn|Backus|1982|pp=49–50}} While staying in the hospital during the pre-antibiotic era, she had painful minor operations to wash out the affected maxillary sinus,{{sfn|Lovell|1989|p=27}}{{sfn|Earhart|1932|p=21}}{{sfn|Backus|1982|pp=49–50}} but these procedures were not successful and Earhart subsequently suffered from worsening headaches. Her convalescence lasted nearly a year, which she spent at her sister's home in [[Northampton, Massachusetts|Northampton]], Massachusetts.{{sfn|Earhart|1932|p=21}} She passed the time by reading poetry, learning to play the banjo and studying mechanics.{{sfn|Lovell|1989|p=27}} Chronic sinusitis significantly affected Earhart's flying and activities in later life,{{sfn|Backus|1982|pp=49–50}} and sometimes even on the airfield she was forced to wear a bandage on her cheek to cover a small drainage tube.{{sfn|Rich|1989|pp=31–32}}

=== Early flying experiences ===

At about that time, Earhart and a young woman friend visited an air fair held in conjunction with the [[Canadian National Exhibition]] in Toronto. One of the highlights of the day was a flying exhibition put on by a World War I [[Flying ace|ace]].{{sfn|Earhart|1937|p=2}} The pilot overhead spotted Earhart and her friend, who were watching from an isolated clearing, and dived at them. "I am sure he said to himself, 'Watch me make them scamper,'" she said. Earhart stood her ground as the aircraft came close. "I did not understand it at the time," she said, "but I believe that little red airplane said something to me as it swished by."{{sfn|Earhart|1937|p=3}}

By 1919 Earhart prepared to enter [[Smith College]] but changed her mind and enrolled at [[Columbia University]], in a course in medical studies among other programs.{{sfn|Thames|1989|p=7}} She quit a year later to be with her parents, who had reunited in California.

[[File:Neta amelia kinner airster s.jpg|thumb|left|[[Neta Snook]] and Amelia Earhart in front of Earhart's [[Kinner Airster]], {{circa|1921}}]]

In [[Long Beach, California|Long Beach]], on December 28, 1920, Earhart and her father visited an airfield where [[Frank Hawks]] (who later gained fame as an [[air racing|air racer]]) gave her a ride that would forever change Earhart's life. "By the time I had got two or three hundred feet [60–90&amp;nbsp;m] off the ground," she said, "I knew I had to fly."{{sfn|Earhart|1937|p=4}} After that 10-minute flight (which cost her father $10), she immediately determined to learn to fly. Working at a variety of jobs including photographer, truck driver, and [[stenographer]] at the local telephone company, she managed to save $1,000 for flying lessons. Earhart had her first lesson on January 3, 1921, at Kinner Field near Long Beach. Her teacher was [[Neta Snook|Anita "Neta" Snook]], a pioneer female aviator who used a surplus [[Curtiss JN-4]] "Canuck" for training. Earhart arrived with her father and a singular request: "I want to fly. Will you teach me?"{{sfn|Marshall|2007|p=21}} In order to reach the airfield, Earhart had to take a bus to the end of the line, then walk four miles (6&amp;nbsp;km). Earhart's mother also provided part of the $1,000 "stake" against her "better judgement".&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.aviationhistory.org/ah_Amelia_Earhart.html "Lady Lindy, Amelia Earhart's life history."] {{webarchive|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20061205024527/http://aviationhistory.org/ah_Amelia_Earhart.html |date=December 5, 2006 }} ''aviationhistory.org''. Retrieved: October 12, 2009.&lt;/ref&gt;

Earhart's commitment to flying required her to accept the frequent hard work and rudimentary conditions that accompanied early aviation training. She chose a leather jacket, but aware that other aviators would be judging her, she slept in it for three nights to give the jacket a "worn" look. To complete her image transformation, she also cropped her hair short in the style of other female flyers.{{sfn|Blau|1977|pp=15–16}} Six months later, Earhart purchased a secondhand bright yellow [[Kinner Airster]] [[biplane]] she nicknamed "The Canary". On October 22, 1922, Earhart flew the Airster to an altitude of {{convert|14000|ft|m}}, setting a world record for female pilots. On May 15, 1923, Earhart became the 16th woman in the United States to be issued a pilot's license (#''6017''){{sfn|Long|Long|1999|p=36}} by the [[Fédération Aéronautique Internationale]] (FAI).&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.u-s-history.com/pages/h1658.html "Aerospace: Amelia Earhart 1897–1937."] {{webarchive|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20061113084605/http://www.u-s-history.com/pages/h1658.html |date=November 13, 2006 }} ''U-S-History.com''. Retrieved: June 3, 2012.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="6017@npg.si.edu"&gt;[http://www.npg.si.edu/exhibit/earhart/pop-ups/02.html "Amelia Earhart's pilot's license, leather and paper, Issued May 16, 1923 (One Life: Amelia Earhart)."] {{webarchive|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20170528125615/http://www.npg.si.edu/exhibit/earhart/pop-ups/02.html |date=May 28, 2017 }} ''National Portrait Gallery, Smithsonian Institution''. Retrieved: September 23, 2017.&lt;/ref&gt; {{refn|The notation for Amelia Earhart's pilot's license as xhibited in the Smithsonian Institution is: "This is Amelia Earhart's first pilot's license. She was only the 16th woman in the United States to receive a pilot's license from the Fédération Aéronautique Internationale, the governing body of sports aviation."|group=Note}}
{{Clear}}

== Aviation career and marriage ==

[[File:Amelia Earhart, circa 1928.jpg|thumb|Amelia Earhart, Los Angeles, 1928 &lt;br /&gt;X5665{{snd}}1926 "[[California Institute of Technology|CIT]]-9 Safety Plane"]]

=== Financial crisis ===

Throughout the early 1920s, following a disastrous investment in a failed [[gypsum]] mine, Earhart's inheritance from her grandmother, which was now administered by her mother, steadily diminished until it was exhausted. Consequently, with no immediate prospects for recouping her investment in flying, Earhart sold the "Canary" as well as a second Kinner and bought a yellow [[Kissel Motor Car Company|Kissel]] "Speedster" two-passenger automobile, which she named the "Yellow Peril". Simultaneously, Earhart experienced an exacerbation of her old sinus problem as her pain worsened and in early 1924 she was hospitalized for another sinus operation, which was again unsuccessful. After trying her hand at a number of unusual ventures that included setting up a photography company, Earhart set out in a new direction.{{sfn|Goldstein|Dillon|1997|p=33}}

=== Boston ===

Following her parents' divorce in 1924, she drove her mother in the "Yellow Peril" on a transcontinental trip from California with stops throughout the West and even a jaunt up to [[Banff, Alberta]]. The meandering tour eventually brought the pair to [[Boston]], [[Massachusetts]], where Earhart underwent another sinus operation which was more successful. After recuperation, she returned to Columbia University for several months but was forced to abandon her studies and any further plans for enrolling at the [[Massachusetts Institute of Technology]], because her mother could no longer afford the tuition fees and associated costs. Soon after, she found employment first as a teacher, then as a [[social worker]] in 1925 at [[Denison House (Boston)|Denison House]], a Boston [[Settlement movement|settlement house]].&lt;ref&gt;[https://web.archive.org/web/20080401003450/http://www.lib.purdue.edu/spcol/aearhart/biog.php "Amelia Earhart Biographical Sketch".] ''George Palmer Putnam Collection of Amelia Earhart Papers'', Purdue University, April 1, 2008. Retrieved: September 23, 2017.&lt;/ref&gt; At this time, she lived in [[Medford, Massachusetts|Medford]], Massachusetts.

When Earhart lived in Medford, she maintained her interest in aviation, becoming a member of the American Aeronautical Society's Boston chapter and was eventually elected its vice president.{{sfn|Rich|1989|p=43}} She flew out of Dennison Airport (later the [[Naval Air Station Squantum]]) in [[Quincy, Massachusetts|Quincy]], Massachusetts, and helped finance its operation by investing a small sum of money.{{sfn|Long|Long|1999|p=38}} Earhart also flew the first official flight out of Dennison Airport in 1927.&lt;ref&gt;Chaisson, Stephanie. [https://archive.is/20120909002251/http://www.patriotledger.com/archive/x1709132033 "Squantum has a hold on its residents."] ''[[The Patriot Ledger]]'', [[Quincy, Massachusetts]],  July 12, 2007. Retrieved: September 23, 2017.&lt;/ref&gt; Along with acting as a sales representative for Kinner aircraft in the Boston area, Earhart wrote local [[columnist|newspaper columns]] promoting flying and as her local celebrity grew, she laid out the plans for an organization devoted to female flyers.{{sfn|Randolph|1987|p=41}}

=== Transatlantic flight in 1928 ===

[[File:Amelia Earhart Commemoration Stone - Burry Port.jpg|thumb|Commemoration Stone for Amelia Earhart's 1928 transatlantic flight, next to the quay side in [[Burry Port]], [[Wales]]]]

&lt;!--Copyright concerns, do not re-add until cleared [[File:Earhart in Southampton.jpg|thumb|right|Amelia Earhart being greeted by Mrs. Foster Welch, Mayor of [[Southampton]], June 20, 1928]]--&gt;[[File:Amelia Earhart 1928.jpg|left|thumb|Photo of Amelia Earhart prior to her transatlantic crossing of June 17, 1928]]
After [[Charles Lindbergh]]'s solo flight across the [[Atlantic Ocean|Atlantic]] in 1927, Amy Guest (1873–1959) expressed interest in being the first woman to fly (or be flown) across the Atlantic Ocean. After deciding that the trip was too perilous for her to undertake, she offered to sponsor the project, suggesting that they find "another girl with the right image". While at work one afternoon in April 1928, Earhart got a phone call from Capt. Hilton H. Railey, who asked her, "Would you like to fly the Atlantic?"

The project coordinators (including book publisher and publicist [[George P. Putnam]]) interviewed Earhart and asked her to accompany pilot [[Wilmer Stultz]] and copilot/mechanic Louis Gordon on the flight, nominally as a passenger, but with the added duty of keeping the flight log. The team departed from [[Trepassey, Newfoundland and Labrador|Trepassey Harbor]], [[Newfoundland and Labrador|Newfoundland]], in a [[Fokker F.VII]]b/3m on June 17, 1928, landing at [[Pwll]] near [[Burry Port]], South Wales, exactly 20 hours and 40 minutes later.{{sfn|Bryan|1979|p=132}} There is a commemorative [[blue plaque]] at the site.&lt;ref&gt;Dorrell, Richard. [https://www.geograph.org.uk/photo/3540051 "Amelia Earhart memorial, Pwll."] {{webarchive|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20171102215908/http://www.geograph.org.uk/photo/3540051 |date=November 2, 2017 }} ''geograph.org.uk'', July 4, 2013. Retrieved: July 9, 2017.&lt;/ref&gt; Since most of the flight was on instruments and Earhart had no training for this type of flying, she did not pilot the aircraft. When interviewed after landing, she said, "Stultz did all the flying—had to. I was just baggage, like a sack of potatoes." She added, "... maybe someday I'll try it alone."{{sfn|Goldstein|Dillon|1997|p=54}}

Earhart reportedly received a rousing welcome on June 19, 1928, when she landed at [[Woolston, Hampshire|Woolston]] in [[Southampton]], England.&lt;ref&gt;''Southampton: A pictorial peep into the past''. Southern Newspapers Ltd, 1980.&lt;/ref&gt; She flew the [[Avro Avian]] 594 Avian III, SN: R3/AV/101 owned by [[Lady Mary Heath]] and later purchased the aircraft and had it shipped back to the United States (where it was assigned "unlicensed aircraft identification mark" 7083).&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.goldenwingsmuseum.com/collection/AC-Pages/Avro%20Avian.html "1927 Avro Avian."] {{webarchive|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20171102220027/http://www.goldenwingsmuseum.com/collection/AC-Pages/Avro%20Avian.html |date=November 2, 2017 }} ''goldenwingsmuseum.com.'' Retrieved: July 1, 2013.&lt;/ref&gt;

When the Stultz, Gordon and Earhart flight crew returned to the United States, they were greeted with a [[ticker-tape parade]] along the [[Canyon of Heroes]] in Manhattan, followed by a reception with [[President of the United States|President]] [[Calvin Coolidge]] at the [[White House]].

=== Celebrity image ===

[[File:AmeliaEarnhardHoover.jpg|left|thumb|Earhart walking with President [[Herbert Hoover|Hoover]] in the grounds of the [[White House]] on January 2, 1932]]

Trading on her physical resemblance to [[Charles Lindbergh|Lindbergh]],{{sfn|Goldstein|Dillon|1997|p=55}} whom the press had dubbed "Lucky Lindy", some newspapers and magazines began referring to Earhart as "Lady Lindy".{{sfn|Glines|1997|p=44}}{{refn|Putnam himself may have coined the term "Lady Lindy".|group=Note}} The United Press was more [[grandiloquence|grandiloquent]]; to them, Earhart was the reigning "Queen of the Air".{{sfn|Rich|1989|p=177}} Immediately after her return to the United States, she undertook an exhausting lecture tour in 1928 and 1929. Meanwhile, Putnam had undertaken to heavily promote her in a campaign that included publishing a book she authored, a series of new lecture tours and using pictures of her in mass market endorsements for products including luggage, [[Lucky Strike]] cigarettes (this caused image problems for her, with ''[[McCall's]]'' magazine retracting an offer){{sfn|Pearce|1988|p=76}} and women's clothing and sportswear. The money that she made with "Lucky Strike" had been earmarked for a $1,500 donation to Commander [[Richard Evelyn Byrd|Richard Byrd]]'s imminent South Pole expedition.{{sfn|Pearce|1988|p=76}}

The marketing campaign by both Earhart and Putnam was successful in establishing the Earhart mystique in the public psyche.&lt;ref&gt;Crouch, Tom D. [https://web.archive.org/web/20070929121928/http://www.americanheritage.com/rss/articles/web/20070702-fred-noonan-lockheed-electra-george-putnam-tighar-ric-gillespie-david-jourdan.shtml "Searching for Amelia Earhart."] ''Invention &amp; Technology'', Summer 2007 via americanheritage.com. (archived). Retrieved: July 2, 2010.&lt;/ref&gt; Rather than simply endorsing the products, Earhart actively became involved in the promotions, especially in women's fashions. For a number of years she had sewn her own clothes, but the "active living" lines that were sold in 50 stores such as [[Macy's]] in metropolitan areas were an expression of a new Earhart image.&lt;ref&gt;V Morell (1998) Amelia Earhart. [[National Geographic (magazine)|National Geographic]] '''193'''(1), 112–135&lt;/ref&gt; Her concept of simple, natural lines matched with wrinkle-proof, washable materials was the embodiment of a sleek, purposeful but feminine "A.E." (the familiar name she went by with family and friends).{{sfn|Rich|1989|p=177}}{{sfn|Lovell|1989|p=135}} The luggage line that she promoted (marketed as Modernaire Earhart Luggage) also bore her unmistakable stamp.

A wide range of promotional items bearing the Earhart name appeared.

=== Promoting aviation ===

[[File:Aa earhart subj e.jpg|thumb|Studio portrait of Amelia Earhart, {{circa|1932}}. Putnam specifically instructed Earhart to disguise a "[[gap-toothed]]" smile by keeping her mouth closed in formal photographs.]]

Celebrity endorsements helped Earhart finance her flying.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.ameliaearhartmuseum.org/ "Biography of Amelia Earhart."] {{webarchive|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20061205052158/http://ameliaearhartmuseum.org/ |date=December 5, 2006 }} ''Amelia Earhart Birthplace Museum''. Retrieved: July 2, 2010.&lt;/ref&gt; Accepting a position as associate editor at ''Cosmopolitan'' magazine, she turned this forum into an opportunity to campaign for greater public acceptance of aviation, especially focusing on the role of women entering the field.{{sfn|Glines|1997|p=45}} In 1929, Earhart was among the first aviators to promote commercial air travel through the development of a passenger airline service; along with Charles Lindbergh, she represented [[Transcontinental Air Transport]] (TAT, later [[TWA]]) and invested time and money in setting up the first regional shuttle service between New York and Washington, D.C., the [[Ludington Airline]]. She was a Vice President of National Airways, which conducted the flying operations of the Boston-Maine Airways and several other airlines in the northeast.&lt;ref&gt;''Boston and Maine Railroad Employees Magazine'', Volume 8, Number 10, July 1933, copy in Purdue University Special Collections.&lt;/ref&gt; By 1940, it had become [[Northeast Airlines]].

=== Competitive flying ===

Although Earhart had gained fame for her transatlantic flight, she endeavored to set an "untarnished" record of her own.{{sfn|Rich|1989|p=73}} Shortly after her return, piloting Avian ''7083'', she set off on her first long solo flight that occurred just as her name was coming into the national spotlight. By making the trip in August 1928, Earhart became the first woman to fly solo across the North American continent and back.&lt;ref name="Mendieta"&gt;Mendieta, Carlene. [http://www.ameliaflight.com/ameliaflight/flight.po "Amelia Earhart's Flight Across America: Rediscovering a Legend."] {{webarchive|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20070929221217/http://www.ameliaflight.com/ameliaflight/flight.po |date=September 29, 2007 }} ''ameliaflight.com''. Retrieved: May 21, 2007.&lt;/ref&gt; Her piloting skills and professionalism gradually grew, as acknowledged by experienced professional pilots who flew with her. General Leigh Wade flew with Earhart in 1929: "She was a born flier, with a delicate touch on the stick."{{sfn|Rich|1989|p=85}}

Earhart subsequently made her first attempt at competitive air racing in 1929 during the first Santa Monica-to-Cleveland [[Women's Air Derby]] (nicknamed the "Powder Puff Derby" by [[Will Rogers]]), which left Santa Monica on August 18 and arrived at Cleveland on August 26. During the race, she settled into fourth place in the "heavy planes" division. At the second last stop at Columbus, her friend [[Ruth Nichols]], who was coming third, had an accident while on a test flight before the race recommenced. Nichols' aircraft hit a tractor at the start of the runway and flipped over, forcing her out of the race.{{sfn|Lauber|1989|p=47}} At Cleveland, Earhart was placed third in the heavy division.{{sfn|Jessen|2002|p=193}}&lt;ref&gt;''San Bernardino County Sun''. August 26, 1929.&lt;/ref&gt;

In 1930, Earhart became an official of the [[National Aeronautic Association]] where she actively promoted the establishment of separate women's records and was instrumental in the [[Fédération Aéronautique Internationale]] (FAI) accepting a similar international standard.{{sfn|Glines|1997|p=45}} In 1931, she set a world altitude record of 18,415 feet (5,613&amp;nbsp;m), flying a [[Pitcairn PCA-2]]&lt;ref&gt;[https://airandspace.si.edu/collection-objects/model-static-pitcairn-pca-2-beech-nut "Model, Static, Pitcairn PCA-2 ("Beech-Nut")."] {{webarchive|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20170924183750/https://airandspace.si.edu/collection-objects/model-static-pitcairn-pca-2-beech-nut |date=September 24, 2017 }} ''[[National Air and Space Museum]]''. Retrieved: September 23, 2017.&lt;/ref&gt; [[autogyro]] borrowed from [[Beech-Nut]] Chewing Gum&lt;ref&gt;Nesbit, Roy Conyers. [https://books.google.com/books?id=dTewDQAAQBAJ&amp;pg=PA5&amp;lpg=PA5&amp;dq=Pitcairn#v=onepage&amp;q=Pitcairn&amp;f=false "Missing: Believed Killed: Amelia Earhart, Amy Johnson, Glenn Miller &amp; The Duke of Kent."] ''Pen &amp; Sword Military'', 2010. Retrieved: September 23, 2017.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.historynet.com/aviators-amelia-earharts-autogiro-adventures.htm 'Aviators: Amelia Earhart's Autogiro Adventures.'] {{webarchive|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20110612205958/http://www.historynet.com/aviators-amelia-earharts-autogiro-adventures.htm |date=June 12, 2011 }} ''[[HistoryNet]]''. Retrieved: September 23, 2017.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |last1 = Reuther |first1 = Ronald T. |last2 = Larkins |first2 = William T. |title = Oakland Aviation |year = 2008 |publisher = Arcadia Publishing |isbn = 978-0-7385-5600-0 |pages = 20–21 }}&lt;/ref&gt;{{sfn|Van Pelt|2008|pages=20–21}} While to a reader today it might seem that Earhart was engaged in flying "stunts", she was, with other female flyers, crucial to making the American public "air minded" and convincing them that "aviation was no longer just for daredevils and supermen."{{sfn|Corn|1983|p=75}}

During this period, Earhart became involved with The [[Ninety-Nines]], an organization of female pilots providing moral support and advancing the cause of women in aviation. She had called a meeting of female pilots in 1929 following the Women's Air Derby. She suggested the name based on the number of the charter members; she later became the organization's first president in 1930.{{sfn|Lovell|1989|p=152}} Earhart was a vigorous advocate for female pilots and when the 1934 [[Bendix Trophy Race]] banned women, she openly refused to fly screen actress [[Mary Pickford]] to Cleveland to open the races.{{sfn|Oakes|1985|p=31}}

=== Marriage to George Putnam ===

[[File:Amelia Earhart and husband George Putnam 1931.jpg|thumb|left|Earhart and Putnam in 1931]]

Earhart was engaged to Samuel Chapman, a chemical engineer from Boston; she broke off the engagement on November 23, 1928.{{sfn|Lovell|1989|pp=130, 138}} During the same period, Earhart and publisher [[George P. Putnam]] had spent a great deal of time together. Putnam, who was known as GP, was divorced in 1929 and sought out Earhart, proposing to her six times before she finally agreed to marry him.{{refn|Quote: "Amelia eventually said yes – or rather nodded yes – to GP's sixth proposal of marriage.{{sfn|Pearce|1988|p=81}}|group=Note}} After substantial hesitation on her part, they married on February 7, 1931, in Putnam's mother's house in Noank, Connecticut. Earhart referred to her marriage as a "partnership" with "dual control". In a letter written to Putnam and hand delivered to him on the day of the wedding, she wrote, "I want you to understand I shall not hold you to any midaevil {{Sic}} code of faithfulness to me nor shall I consider myself bound to you similarly."{{refn|Quote: "It was pencilled longhand ... a slip or two in spelling meticulously corrected." The later typewritten note has the word medieval incorrectly spelled. The original note has some slight variances in the header, use of commas and the salutation but is spelled correctly.{{sfn|Lovell|1989|pp=165–166}}|group=Note}}&lt;ref&gt;[https://web.archive.org/web/20041107204646/http://ncbuy.com/news/wireless_news.html?qdate=2003-02-25&amp;nav=VIEW&amp;id=0823D7UCP05030225 "Newly Discovered Amelia Earhart Letter Shows Her Wild Side."] ''Wireless Flash News'', February 25, 2003. Retrieved: September 23, 2017.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Patterson-Neubert, Amy. [http://news.uns.purdue.edu/html4ever/030224.Mobley.Earhart.html "Public to get first look at Amelia Earhart's private life."] {{webarchive|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20060725091511/http://news.uns.purdue.edu/html4ever/030224.Mobley.Earhart.html |date=July 25, 2006 }} ''Purdue News'', 2003. Retrieved: July 2, 2010.&lt;/ref&gt;

Earhart's ideas on marriage were liberal for the time as she believed in equal responsibilities for both breadwinners and pointedly kept her own name rather than being referred to as "Mrs. Putnam". When ''The New York Times'', per the rules of its stylebook, insisted on referring to her as Mrs. Putnam, she laughed it off. Putnam also learned that he would be called "Mr. Earhart".{{sfn|Pearce|1988|p=82}} There was no honeymoon for the newlyweds as Earhart was involved in a nine-day cross-country tour promoting autogyros and the tour sponsor, [[Beech-Nut]] chewing gum. Although Earhart and Putnam never had children, he had two sons by his previous marriage to Dorothy Binney (1888–1982),&lt;ref&gt;[https://web.archive.org/web/20040604061051/http://www.rootsweb.com/~flslchs/DorothyPutnam.htm "Dorothy Binney Putnam Upton Blanding Palmer 1888–1982."] ''St. Lucie Historical Society, Inc.'' (archived). Retrieved: September 23, 2017.&lt;/ref&gt; a chemical heiress whose father's company, [[Binney &amp; Smith]], invented [[Crayola]] crayons:&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.rootsweb.com/~flslchs/EdwinBinney.htm "Edwin Binney 1866–1934."] {{webarchive|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20060713052246/http://www.rootsweb.com/~flslchs/EdwinBinney.htm |date=July 13, 2006 }} ''St. Lucie Historical Society, Inc.'' Retrieved: June 3, 2012.&lt;/ref&gt; the explorer and writer David Binney Putnam (1913–1992) and George Palmer Putnam, Jr. (1921–2013).{{sfn|Lovell|1989|pp=154, 174}} Earhart was especially fond of David, who frequently visited his father at their family home, which was on the grounds of [[The Apawamis Club]] in [[Rye (city), New York|Rye, New York]]. George had contracted [[polio]] shortly after his parents' separation and was unable to visit as often.

== Transatlantic solo flight in 1932 ==

[[File:P2270017.JPG|thumb|left|Amelia Earhart Museum, Derry]]

[[File:Lockheed Vega 5b Smithsonian.jpg|thumb|right|[[Lockheed Vega 5B]] flown by Amelia Earhart as seen on display at the [[National Air and Space Museum]]]]

[[File:NLA HarbourGrace tango7174.jpg|thumb|Monument in [[Harbour Grace, Newfoundland and Labrador]]]]

On the morning of May 20, 1932, 34-year-old Earhart set off from [[Harbour Grace, Newfoundland and Labrador|Harbour Grace]], [[Newfoundland and Labrador|Newfoundland]], with a copy of the ''[[Telegraph-Journal]]'', given to her by journalist [[Stuart Trueman]],&lt;ref name=telegraph&gt;"Eighty years since famed flight; Anniversary Amelia Earhart's stop in Saint John may have been brief but pivotal in record-breaking feat". ''[[The Telegraph-Journal]]'', May 19, 2012.&lt;/ref&gt; intended to confirm the date of the flight.&lt;ref name=telegraph /&gt; She intended to fly to Paris in her single engine [[Lockheed Vega 5B]] to emulate [[Charles Lindbergh]]'s solo flight five years earlier.{{sfn|Parsons|1983|pp=95–97}}{{refn|Earhart's Vega 5B was her third, after trading in two Vega 1s at the [[Lockheed Aircraft Company]]'s [[Burbank Airport|Burbank]] plant.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.dmairfield.org/airplanes/NC7952/index.html "Lockheed Vega NV7952."] {{webarchive|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20111117190444/http://dmairfield.org/airplanes/NC7952/index.html |date=November 17, 2011 }} ''Davis-Monthan Aviation Field Register'', September 11, 2011. Retrieved: September 23, 2017.&lt;/ref&gt;|group=Note}} Her technical advisor for the flight was famed [[Norwegian American]] aviator [[Bernt Balchen]] who helped prepare her aircraft. He also played the role of "decoy" for the press as he was ostensibly preparing Earhart's Vega for his own Arctic flight.{{refn|Bernt Balchen had been instrumental in other transatlantic and Arctic record-breaking flights during that period.{{sfn|Butler|1997|p=263}}|group=Note}} After a flight lasting 14 hours, 56 minutes during which she contended with strong northerly winds, icy conditions and mechanical problems, Earhart landed in a pasture at [[Culmore]], north of [[Derry]], [[Northern Ireland]]. The landing was witnessed by Cecil King and T. Sawyer. When a farm hand asked, "Have you flown far?" Earhart replied, "From America".&lt;ref&gt;Goddard, Seth. [https://web.archive.org/web/20021005082222/http://www.life.com/Life/heroes/newsletters/nlearhart.html "Life Hero of the Week Profile: Amelia Earhart; First Lady of the Sky."] ''Time-Life (life.com)'', October 5, 2002 (archived). Retrieved: September 23, 2017.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[https://web.archive.org/web/20060310224954/http://www.derrycity.gov.uk/museums/emelia.asp "Amelia Earhart Centre."]| ''Derry City Council Heritage and Museum Service''. Retrieved: September 23, 2017.&lt;/ref&gt;

As the first woman to fly solo nonstop across the Atlantic, Earhart received the [[Distinguished Flying Cross (United States)|Distinguished Flying Cross]] from [[United States Congress|Congress]], the Cross of Knight of the [[Légion d'honneur|Legion of Honor]] from the [[Cabinet of France|French Government]] and the Gold Medal of the [[National Geographic Society]]&lt;ref&gt;Sherman, Stephen. [http://acepilots.com/wwi/hfa.html "The Hall of Fame of the Air; An illustrated newspaper feature from 1935 – 1940."] {{webarchive|url=http://archive.wikiwix.com/cache/20151103032937/http://acepilots.com/wwi/hfa.html |date=November 3, 2015 }} ''acepilots.com'', April 11, 2012. Retrieved: July 9, 2017.&lt;/ref&gt; from President [[Herbert Hoover]]. As her fame grew, she developed friendships with many people in high offices, most notably First Lady [[Eleanor Roosevelt]]. Roosevelt shared many of Earhart's interests and passions, especially women's causes. After flying with Earhart, Roosevelt obtained a student permit but did not further pursue her plans to learn to fly. The two friends communicated frequently throughout their lives.{{refn|Franklin D. Roosevelt was not in favor of his wife becoming a pilot. Eleanor Roosevelt would later feature prominently in another aviation-related cause when she took a famous flight with a young Black aviator, helping establish the credentials of the "Tuskegee Airmen".{{sfn|Glines|1997|p=47}}|group=Note}} Another famous flyer, [[Jacqueline Cochran]], who was considered to be Earhart's greatest rival by both media and the public, also became a confidante and friend during this period.{{sfn|Leder|1989|p=49}}

=== Additional solo flights ===

On January 11, 1935, Earhart became the first aviator to fly solo from [[Honolulu]], Hawaii to [[Oakland, California|Oakland]], California.{{refn|The first flight between California and Hawaii was completed on June 28–29, 1927 by the Army Air Corps tri-motor [[Bird of Paradise (aircraft)|Bird of Paradise]].|group=Note}}&lt;ref&gt;[https://www.thisdayinaviation.com/11-january-1935/ "11–12 January 1935."] {{webarchive|url=http://archive.wikiwix.com/cache/20170713151230/https://www.thisdayinaviation.com/11-january-1935/ |date=July 13, 2017 }}  ''This Day in Aviation'', January 11, 2017. Retrieved: July 13, 2017,&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://aviation.hawaii.gov/aviation-pioneers/amelia-earhart/ 'Hawaii Aviation; Amelia Earhart."] {{webarchive|url=http://archive.wikiwix.com/cache/20170714094102/http://aviation.hawaii.gov/aviation-pioneers/amelia-earhart/ |date=July 14, 2017 }}  ''aviation.hawaii.gov''. Retrieved: September 23, 2017.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[https://airandspace.si.edu/collection-objects/earhart-amelia-lockheed-model-5c-vega-special-6th-earhart-aircraft-nr-965y "Earhart, Amelia; Lockheed Model 5C Vega Special (6th Earhart Aircraft, NR-965Y). (photograph)."] {{webarchive|url=http://archive.wikiwix.com/cache/20170714075743/https://airandspace.si.edu/collection-objects/earhart-amelia-lockheed-model-5c-vega-special-6th-earhart-aircraft-nr-965y |date=July 14, 2017 }} ''[[National Air and Space Museum]]''. Retrieved: July 13, 2017.&lt;/ref&gt; Although this transoceanic flight had been attempted by many others, notably by the unfortunate participants in the 1927 [[Dole Air Race]] that had reversed the route, her trailblazing{{sfn|Goldstein|Dillon|1997|p=132}} flight had been mainly routine, with no mechanical breakdowns. In her final hours, she even relaxed and listened to "the broadcast of the Metropolitan Opera from New York".{{sfn|Goldstein|Dillon|1997|p=132}}
[[File:Amelia Earhart LOC hec.40747.jpg|left|thumb|300x300px|In a [[Stearman-Hammond Y-1]] ]]
That year, once more flying her Lockheed Vega airliner that Earhart had tagged "old Bessie, the fire horse",{{refn|"Old Bessie" started out as a Vega 5 built in 1928 as c/n 36, but was modified with a replacement fuselage to become a 5B.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |last = Allen |first = Richard Sanders |title = Revolution in the sky: those fabulous Lockheeds, the pilots who flew them |year = 1964 |publisher = S. Greene Press |pages = 199, 200, 202 }}&lt;/ref&gt;|group=Note}}&lt;ref&gt;[https://parksfield.org/airplanes/NR965Y/ "Parks Airport Lockheed Vega 5C Special NX/NR/NC965Y."] {{webarchive|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20170924151638/https://parksfield.org/airplanes/NR965Y/ |date=September 24, 2017 }} ''parksfield.org''. Retrieved: July 13, 2017.&lt;/ref&gt; she flew solo from Los Angeles to Mexico City on April 19. The next record attempt was a nonstop flight from Mexico City to New York. Setting off on May 8, her flight was uneventful although the large crowds that greeted her at [[Newark, New Jersey|Newark]], New Jersey were a concern,{{sfn|Lovell|1989|p=218}} because she had to be careful not to taxi into the throng.

Earhart again participated in long-distance air racing, placing fifth in the 1935 [[Bendix Trophy]] Race, the best result she could manage, due to the stock Lockheed Vega, topping out at {{convert|195|mi/h|km/h|abbr=on}}, was outclassed by purpose-built air racers that reached more than {{convert|300|mi/h|km/h|abbr=on}}.{{sfn|Oakes|1985|p=35}} The race had been a particularly difficult one as a competitor, Cecil Allen, died in a fiery takeoff mishap and rival Jacqueline Cochran was forced to pull out due to mechanical problems, the "blinding fog",{{sfn|Goldstein|Dillon|1997|p=145}} and violent thunderstorms that plagued the race.

Between 1930 and 1935, Earhart had set seven women's speed and distance aviation records in a variety of aircraft including the Kinner Airster, Lockheed Vega, and Pitcairn Autogiro. By 1935, recognizing the limitations of her "lovely red Vega" in long, transoceanic flights, Earhart contemplated, in her own words, a new "prize ... one flight which I most wanted to attempt – a circumnavigation of the globe as near its waistline as could be".{{sfn|Earhart|1937|p=37}} For the new venture, she would need a new aircraft.
{{Clear}}

== Move from New York to California ==

While Earhart was away on a speaking tour in late November 1934, a fire broke out at the Putnam residence in Rye, destroying many family treasures and Earhart's personal mementos.{{sfn|Lovell|1989|p=209}} Putnam had already sold his interest in the New York based publishing company to his cousin, [[Palmer Cosslett Putnam|Palmer Putnam]]. Following the fire, the couple decided to move to the West Coast, where Putnam took up his new position as head of the editorial board of [[Paramount Pictures]] in [[Hollywood|North Hollywood]].{{sfn|Sloate|1990|p=64}}{{refn|Amelia preferred the more benign weather of the west coast for flying and based her later years' operation from California rather than the east coast.|group=Note}} While speaking in California in late 1934, Earhart had contacted Hollywood "stunt" pilot [[Paul Mantz]] in order to improve her flying, focusing especially on long-distance flying in her Vega and wanted to move closer to him.

At Earhart's urging, Putnam purchased a small house in June 1935 adjacent to the clubhouse of the Lakeside Golf Club in [[Toluca Lake, Los Angeles|Toluca Lake]], a [[San Fernando Valley]] celebrity enclave community nestled between the [[Warner Brothers]] and [[Universal Studios|Universal Pictures]] studio complexes where they had earlier rented a temporary residence.&lt;ref&gt;Altman, Elizabeth. [http://digital-library.csun.edu/cdm4/item_viewer.php?CISOBOX=1&amp;CISOPTR=1617&amp;CISOROOT=/SFVH&amp;REC=3 "Amelia Earhart home, Toluca Lake, 2003."] {{webarchive|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20120325084331/http://digital-library.csun.edu/cdm4/item_viewer.php?CISOBOX=1&amp;CISOPTR=1617&amp;CISOROOT=%2FSFVH&amp;REC=3 |date=March 25, 2012 }} Oviatt Library Digital Archives, Delmar T. Oviatt Library, Urban Archives Center, California State University, Northridge, California. Photo: {{asof|2003|09|29}}. Retrieved: September 23, 2011.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="TLCoChist"&gt;[https://web.archive.org/web/20110717070506/http://www.tolucalakechamber.com/History.htm  "History."] ''TolucaLakeChamber.com'', July 17, 2011. Retrieved: September 15, 2010.&lt;/ref&gt; Earhart and Putnam would not move in immediately, however; they decided to do considerable remodeling and enlarge the existing small structure to meet their needs. This delayed the occupation of their new home for several months.{{sfn|Butler|1997|p=341}}

In September 1935, Earhart and Mantz formally established a business partnership that they had been considering since late 1934 by creating the short-lived Earhart-Mantz Flying School, which Mantz controlled and operated through his aviation company, United Air Services. The company was located at the [[Burbank Airport]], about five miles (8&amp;nbsp;km) from Earhart's Toluca Lake home. Putnam handled publicity for the school that primarily taught instrument flying using [[Link Trainer]]s.{{sfn|Long|Long|1999|p=53–54}}

== World flight in 1937 ==
&lt;!--Copyright concerns, do not re-add until cleared [[File:Earhart and electra.jpeg|thumb|Amelia Earhart and [[Lockheed 10E|Lockheed Electra 10E]] NR 16020, c. 1937]]--&gt;

[[File:Earhart-electra 10.jpg|thumb|upright=1.5|Amelia Earhart's [[Lockheed 10E|Lockheed Electra 10E]]. During its modification, the aircraft had most of the cabin windows blanked out and had specially fitted fuselage fuel tanks. The round [[Direction finding|RDF]] [[loop antenna]] can be seen above the cockpit. This image was taken at Luke Field on March 20, 1937; the plane would crash later that morning.]]

=== Planning ===

In 1935, Earhart joined Purdue University as a visiting faculty member to counsel women on careers and as a technical advisor to its Department of Aeronautics.{{sfn|Goldstein|Dillon|1997|p=145}}{{refn|Her job at Purdue was outlined by [[Edward C. Elliott]], the President of Purdue University.|group=Note}} Early in 1936, Earhart started planning a round-the-world flight. Although others had flown around the world, her flight would be the longest at 29,000 miles (47,000&amp;nbsp;km) because it followed a roughly equatorial route. With financing from Purdue,{{refn|Purdue University established the Amelia Earhart Fund for Aeronautical Research at $50,000 to fund the purchase of the Lockheed Electra 10E.{{sfn|Goldstein|Dillon|1997|p=150}}|group=Note}} in July 1936, a [[Lockheed Model 10 Electra|Lockheed Electra 10E]] was built at [[Lockheed Aircraft Company]] to her specifications, which included extensive modifications to the fuselage to incorporate many additional fuel tanks.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.pacificwrecks.com/aircraft/electra/1055.html "Lockheed Model 10E Electra c/n: 1055 Reg: NR16020."] {{webarchive|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20120710172423/http://pacificwrecks.com/aircraft/electra/1055.html |date=July 10, 2012 }} ''PacificWrecks.com'', January 5, 2011. Retrieved: September 23, 2017.&lt;/ref&gt; Earhart dubbed the twin engine monoplane her "flying laboratory". The plane was built at Lockheed's [[Burbank, California]] plant, and after delivery it was hangared it at Mantz's United Air Services, which was just across the airfield from the Lockheed plant.{{sfn|Long|Long|1999|p=59}}

Although the Electra was publicized as a "flying laboratory", little useful science was planned and the flight was arranged around Earhart's intention to circumnavigate the globe along with gathering raw material and public attention for her next book.&lt;ref&gt;[https://www.nytimes.com/1936/04/20/archives/miss-earhart-to-get-flying-laboratory-purdue-announces-50000-fund.html?scp=1 "Miss Earhart to get 'Flying Laboratory'."] {{webarchive|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20130520205402/http://select.nytimes.com/gst/abstract.html?res=F20A1FF83C5E167B93C2AB178FD85F428385F9&amp;scp=1 |date=May 20, 2013 }} ''The New York Times'', April 20, 1936, p. 3. Retrieved: September 23, 2017.&lt;/ref&gt; Earhart chose Captain Harry Manning as her navigator; he had been the captain of the {{SS|President Roosevelt|1921|2}}, the ship that had brought Earhart back from Europe in 1928.{{sfn|Goldstein|Dillon|1997|p=150}} Manning was not only a navigator, but he was also a skilled radio operator who knew Morse code.{{sfn|Long|Long|1999|p=62}}

[[File:Amelia Earhart in Darwin on 28 June 1937.jpg|left|thumb|Earhart and Noonan by the Lockheed L10 Electra at Darwin, Australia on June 28, 1937]]

Through contacts in the Los Angeles aviation community, [[Fred Noonan]] was subsequently chosen as a second [[flight officer|navigator]] because there were significant additional factors that had to be dealt with while using celestial navigation for aircraft.{{sfn|Long|Long|1999|p=65}}{{sfn|Post|Gatty|1931|pp=45–56}} He had vast experience in both marine (he was a licensed ship's captain) and [[air navigation|flight navigation]]. Noonan had recently left [[Pan American World Airways|Pan Am]], where he established most of the company's [[China Clipper]] seaplane routes across the Pacific. Noonan had also been responsible for training Pan American's navigators for the route between [[San Francisco]] and [[Manila]].{{sfn|Grooch|1936|pp=177, 189}}{{refn|Noonan also navigated the China Clipper on its first flight to Manila, departing Alameda under the command of Captain Ed Musick, on November 22, 1935.|group=Note}} The original plans were for Noonan to navigate from Hawaii to Howland Island, a particularly difficult portion of the flight; then Manning would continue with Earhart to Australia and she would proceed on her own for the remainder of the project.

=== First attempt ===
&lt;!--Copyright concerns, do not readd until cleared [[File:Mantz, Ae,Manning, Noonan.jpg|thumb|L–R, [[Paul Mantz]], Amelia Earhart, Harry Manning and [[Fred Noonan]], [[Oakland, California|Oakland]], California, March 17, 1937]]--&gt;

On March 17, 1937, Earhart and her crew flew the first leg from [[Oakland, California|Oakland]], California to [[Honolulu]], Hawaii. In addition to Earhart and Noonan, Harry Manning and Mantz (who was acting as Earhart's technical advisor) were on board. Due to lubrication and galling problems with the propeller hubs' variable pitch mechanisms, the aircraft needed servicing in Hawaii. Ultimately, the Electra ended up at the United States Navy's Luke Field on [[Ford Island]] in [[Pearl Harbor]]. The flight resumed three days later from Luke Field with Earhart, Noonan and Manning on board. During the takeoff run, there was an uncontrolled [[ground loop (aviation)|ground-loop]], the forward landing gear collapsed, both propellers hit the ground, the plane skidded on its belly, and a portion of the runway was damaged.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url = https://tighar.org/Projects/Earhart/Archives/Documents/Luke_Field_Crash_Report/LukeFieldProceedings.htm |title = Archived copy |accessdate = November 30, 2017 |deadurl = no |archiveurl = https://web.archive.org/web/20171201041705/https://tighar.org/Projects/Earhart/Archives/Documents/Luke_Field_Crash_Report/LukeFieldProceedings.htm |archivedate = December 1, 2017 |df = mdy-all }} Crash description: "As the airplane gathered speed it swung slightly to the right. Miss Earhart corrected this tendency by throttling the left hand motor. The airplane then began to swing to the left with increasing speed, characteristic of a ground-loop. It tilted outward, right wing low and for 50 or 60 feet was supported on the right wheel only. The right-hand landing-gear suddenly collapsed under this excessive load followed by the left. The airplane spun sharply to the left sliding on its belly and amid a shower of sparks from the mat and came to rest headed about 200 degrees from it's {{sic}} initial course." Finding: "the airplane crashed on the landing mat due to the collapse of the landing gear as the result of an uncontrolled ground loop; that lack of factual evidence makes it impossible to establish the reason for the ground loop".&lt;/ref&gt; The cause of the ground-loop is controversial. Some witnesses at Luke Field, including the Associated Press journalist, said they saw a tire blow.{{sfn|Rich|1989|p=245}} Earhart thought either the Electra's right tire had blown and/or the right landing gear had collapsed. Some sources, including Mantz, cited pilot error.{{sfn|Rich|1989|p=245}}

With the aircraft severely damaged, the flight was called off and the aircraft was shipped by sea to the Lockheed Burbank facility for repairs.{{sfn|Leder|1989|p=48}}

=== Second attempt ===

[[File:Amelia Earhart flight route.svg|right|thumb|The planned flight route]]

While the Electra was being repaired Earhart and Putnam secured additional funds and prepared for a second attempt. This time flying west to east, the second attempt began with an unpublicized flight from Oakland to [[Miami]], Florida, and after arriving there Earhart publicly announced her plans to circumnavigate the globe. The flight's opposite direction was partly the result of changes in global wind and weather patterns along the planned route since the earlier attempt. On this second flight, Fred Noonan was Earhart's only crew member. The pair departed Miami on June 1 and after numerous stops in South America, Africa, the [[Indian subcontinent]] and Southeast Asia, arrived at [[Lae]], [[Territory of New Guinea|New Guinea]], on June 29, 1937. At this stage about 22,000 miles (35,000&amp;nbsp;km) of the journey had been completed. The remaining 7,000 miles (11,000&amp;nbsp;km) would be over the Pacific.
{| class="wikitable collapsible collapsed" style="margin: 1em auto 1em auto;"
|+ '''Earhart's 1937 flight route'''
!width=12em| Date !! Departure city&lt;ref&gt;Waitt, Ted. [http://www.searchforamelia.org/ "The Search for Amelia."] {{webarchive|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20130703131716/http://searchforamelia.org/ |date=July 3, 2013 }} ''Waitt Institute for Discovery''. Retrieved: June 19, 2013.&lt;/ref&gt; !! Arrival city !! [[Nautical miles|Nautical&lt;br /&gt;miles]] !! Notes{{sfn|Earhart|1937}}
|-
| May 20, 1937 || [[Oakland, California|Oakland]], [[California]] || [[Burbank, California|Burbank]], California ||style="text-align:right"| 283 ||
|-
| May 21, 1937 || Burbank, California || [[Tucson, Arizona|Tucson]], [[Arizona]] ||style="text-align:right"| 393 ||
|-
| May 22, 1937 || Tucson, Arizona || [[New Orleans]], [[Louisiana]] ||style="text-align:right"| 1070 || Arrived at [[Lakefront Airport]]&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url = http://www.nola.com/politics/index.ssf/2013/09/new_orleans_art_deco_lakefront.html |title = New Orleans' Art Deco Lakefront Airport terminal sheds its Cold War shell |author =  |date =  |website = nola.com |accessdate = April 4, 2018 |deadurl = no |archiveurl = https://web.archive.org/web/20171215223900/http://www.nola.com/politics/index.ssf/2013/09/new_orleans_art_deco_lakefront.html |archivedate = December 15, 2017 |df = mdy-all }}&lt;/ref&gt;
|-
| May 23, 1937 || New Orleans, Louisiana || [[Miami]], [[Florida]] ||style="text-align:right"| 586 ||
|-
| June 1, 1937 || Miami, Florida || [[San Juan, Puerto Rico|San Juan]], [[Puerto Rico]] ||style="text-align:right"| 908 ||
|-
| June 2, 1937 || San Juan, Puerto Rico || [[Caripito]], [[Venezuela]] ||style="text-align:right"| 492 || Out of [[Fernando Luis Ribas Dominicci Airport|Isla Grande Airport]]
|-
| June 3, 1937 || Caripito, Venezuela || [[Paramaribo]], [[Surinam (Dutch colony)|Surinam]] ||style="text-align:right"| 610 ||
|-
| June 4, 1937 || Paramaribo, Surinam || [[Fortaleza]], [[Brazil]] ||style="text-align:right"| 1142 ||
|-
| June 5, 1937 || Fortaleza, Brazil || [[Natal, Rio Grande do Norte|Natal]], Brazil ||style="text-align:right"| 235 ||
|-
| June 7, 1937 || Natal, Brazil || [[Saint-Louis, Senegal|Saint-Louis]], [[Senegal]] ||style="text-align:right"| 1727 || [[Transatlantic flight]]
|-
| June 8, 1937 || Saint-Louis, Senegal || [[Dakar]], Senegal ||style="text-align:right"| 100 ||
|-
| June 10, 1937 || Dakar, Senegal || [[Gao]], [[French Sudan]] ||style="text-align:right"| 1016 ||
|-
| June 11, 1937 || Gao, French Sudan || [[N'Djamena|Fort-Lamy]], [[French Equatorial Africa|F.E. Africa]] ||style="text-align:right"| 910 ||
|-
| June 12, 1937 || Fort-Lamy, F.E. Africa || [[El Fasher]], [[Anglo-Egyptian Sudan]] ||style="text-align:right"| 610 ||
|-
| June 13, 1937 || El Fasher, Anglo-Egyptian Sudan || [[Khartoum]], Anglo-Egyptian Sudan ||style="text-align:right"| 437 ||
|-
| June 13, 1937 || Khartoum, Anglo-Egyptian Sudan || [[Massawa]], [[Ethiopian Empire|Ethiopia]] ||style="text-align:right"| 400 ||
|-
| June 14, 1937 || Massawa, Ethiopia || [[Assab]], [[Italian Eritrea]] ||style="text-align:right"| 241 ||
|-
| June 15, 1937 || Assab, Italian Eritrea || [[Karachi]], [[British Raj|British India]] ||style="text-align:right"| 1627 || First ever non-stop flight from the Red Sea to India
|-
| June 17, 1937 || Karachi, British India || [[Kolkata|Calcutta]], British India ||style="text-align:right"| 1178 ||
|-
| June 18, 1937 || Calcutta, British India || [[Akyab]], [[British rule in Burma|Burma]] ||style="text-align:right"| 291 ||
|-
| June 19, 1937 || Akyab, Burma || [[Yangon|Rangoon]], Burma ||style="text-align:right"| 268 ||
|-
| June 20, 1937 || Rangoon, Burma || [[Bangkok]], [[Thailand|Siam]] ||style="text-align:right"| 315 ||
|-
| June 20, 1937 || Bangkok, Siam || [[Singapore]], [[Straits Settlements]] ||style="text-align:right"| 780 ||
|-
| June 21, 1937|| Singapore, Straits Settlements || [[Bandung|Bandoeng]], [[Dutch East Indies]] ||style="text-align:right"| 541 ||
|-
| June 25, 1937 || Bandoeng, Dutch East Indies || [[Surabaya|Soerabaja]], Dutch East Indies ||style="text-align:right"| 310 || Delayed due to [[monsoon]]
|-
| June 25, 1937 || Soerabaja, Dutch East Indies || Bandoeng, Dutch East Indies ||style="text-align:right"| 310 || Returned for repairs, Earhart ill with [[dysentery]]
|-
| June 26, 1937 || Bandoeng, Dutch East Indies || Soerabaja, Dutch East Indies ||style="text-align:right"| 310 ||
|-
| June 27, 1937 || Soerabaja, Dutch East Indies || [[Kupang|Koepang]], Dutch East Indies ||style="text-align:right"| 668 ||
|-
| June 28, 1937 || Koepang, Dutch East Indies || [[Darwin, Northern Territory|Darwin]], [[Australia]] ||style="text-align:right"| 445 || Direction finder repaired, parachutes removed and sent home
|-
| June 29, 1937 || Darwin, Australia || [[Lae]], [[Territory of New Guinea|New Guinea]] ||style="text-align:right"| 1012 ||
|-
| July 2, 1937 || Lae, New Guinea || [[Howland Island]] ||style="text-align:right"| 2556 || Did not arrive
|-
| July 3, 1937 || Howland Island || [[Honolulu]], [[Territory of Hawaii|Hawaii]] ||style="text-align:right"| 1900 || Planned leg
|-
| July 4, 1937 || Honolulu, Hawaii || Oakland, California ||style="text-align:right"| 2400 || Planned leg
|}

=== Departure from Lae ===

On &lt;time datetime="1937-07-02T00:00Z"&gt;July 2, 1937, midnight [[GMT]]&lt;/time&gt;, Earhart and Noonan took off from [[Lae Airfield]] ({{Coord|06|43|59|S|146|59|45|E|type:airport}}&lt;ref&gt;[http://gc.kls2.com/airport/AYLA.OLD Lae Airfield (AYLA)] {{webarchive|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20121018133354/http://gc.kls2.com/airport/AYLA.OLD |date=October 18, 2012 }} at Great Circle Mapper&lt;/ref&gt;) in the heavily loaded Electra. Their intended destination was [[Howland Island]] ({{Coord|0|48|24|N|176|36|59|W|type:isle_region:UM-84|display=inline,title}}&lt;ref&gt;{{cite gnis |id = 1393033 |name = Howland Island |accessdate = February 24, 2009 }}&lt;/ref&gt;), a flat sliver of land 6,500&amp;nbsp;ft (2,000&amp;nbsp;m) long and 1,600&amp;nbsp;ft (500&amp;nbsp;m) wide, 10&amp;nbsp;ft (3&amp;nbsp;m) high and {{convert|2556|mi|nmi km}} away.{{refn|From the given coordinates, the great circle distance is {{convert|4124|km|mi nmi}}. See http://www.movable-type.co.uk/scripts/latlong.html|group=Note}}

The aircraft departed Lae with about 1100 gallons of gasoline.{{sfn|Chater|1937}} In March 1937, [[Kelly Johnson (engineer)|Kelly Johnson]] had recommended engine and altitude settings for the Electra. One of the recommended schedules was:&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url = https://tighar.org/Publications/TTracks/2001Vol_17/johnson.pdf |title = The Kelly Johnson Telegrams |accessdate = November 22, 2017 |deadurl = no |archiveurl = https://web.archive.org/web/20130124152117/http://tighar.org/Publications/TTracks/2001Vol_17/johnson.pdf |archivedate = January 24, 2013 |df = mdy-all }}&lt;/ref&gt;{{refn|Initially, Johnson recommended a more efficient flight plan that had a lower altitude for the first 6 hours. {{harvtxt|Long|Long|1999|pp=68, 72}} shows that the flight to Honolulu would overtake a Pan Am flight that left earlier. To avoid problems, Earhart would fly at 8,000 feet while the slower Pan Am flight would stay below 6,000 feet. Johnson was asked to adapt the plan for 8,000 feet. The given schedule is for the 8,000-foot altitude, but Earhart may have used the slightly more efficient first schedule or some other schedule.|group=Note}}

{| class="wikitable"
|-
! Altitude !! RPM !! inches !! Cambridge{{refn|The Cambridge Instrument Co., Inc. indicator showed the fuel/air ratio for the engine. A WWII Cambridge indicator (order number AC-20911, part number 11622-1) had a range from .110 to .066. High numbers are rich mixtures; lower numbers are lean mixtures. US Patent 2,237,558.|group=Note}} !! Fuel consumption [gph] !! Hours !! fuel used [gal] !! octane{{refn|Johnson did not specify the fuel's octane rating. {{harvtxt|Chater|1937}} says the plane at Lae had 40 gallons of 100 octane with the rest being 87 octane. Lae did not have 100 octane fuel.|group=Note}}
|-
| climb || 2050 || 28.5 || .078 || na || na || 40? || 100
|-
| 8000 || 1900 || 28.0 || .073 || 60 || 3 || 220 || 87
|-
| 8000 || 1800 || 26.5 || .072 || 51 || 3 || 373 || 87
|-
| 8000 || 1700 || 25.0 || .072 || 43 || 3 || 502 || 87
|-
| 10000 || 1600 || 24.0 or full throttle || .072 || 38 || {{#expr:(1100-502)/38round1}} (calculated) || 1100 || 87
|}

Earhart used part of the above schedule for the Oakland to Honolulu leg of the first world flight attempt. Johnson estimated that 900 gallons of fuel would provide 40% more range than required for that leg. Using 900 gallons was 250 gallons less than the Electra's maximum fuel tank capacity; that meant a weight savings of {{convert|{{#expr:250*6}}|lb|kg}}, so Earhart included Mantz as a passenger on that leg. The Oakland to Honolulu leg had Earhart, Noonan, Manning, and Mantz on board. The flight from Oakland to Honolulu took 16 hours.&lt;ref name="radio" /&gt; The Electra also loaded 900 gallons of fuel for the shorter Honolulu to Howland leg (with only Earhart, Noonan, and Manning on board), but the airplane crashed on take off; the crash ended the first world flight attempt.&lt;ref&gt;Luke Field Crash Report, {{cite web |url = https://tighar.org/Projects/Earhart/Archives/Documents/Luke_Field_Crash_Report/LukeFieldProceedings.htm |title = Archived copy |accessdate = November 30, 2017 |deadurl = no |archiveurl = https://web.archive.org/web/20171201041705/https://tighar.org/Projects/Earhart/Archives/Documents/Luke_Field_Crash_Report/LukeFieldProceedings.htm |archivedate = December 1, 2017 |df = mdy-all }}&lt;/ref&gt;

Around &lt;time datetime="1937-07-02T15:00+10:00"&gt;3&amp;nbsp;pm Lae time&lt;/time&gt;, Earhart reported her altitude as 10000 feet but that they would reduce altitude due to thick clouds. Around &lt;time datetime="1937-07-02T17:00+10:00"&gt;5&amp;nbsp;pm&lt;/time&gt;, Earhart reported her altitude as 7000 feet and speed as 150 knots.{{sfn|Collopy|1937}}

Their last known position report was near the [[Nukumanu Islands]], about {{convert|800|mi|nmi km}} into the flight.

During the flight, Noonan may have been able to do some [[celestial navigation]] to determine his position. The plane would cross the [[International Dateline]] during the flight; failing to account for the dateline could account for a 1° or 60 mile position error.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url = http://www.datelinetheory.com/p/effects-of-date-line.html |title = Effects of the Date Line |author =  |date =  |website = www.datelinetheory.com |accessdate = April 4, 2018 |deadurl = no |archiveurl = https://web.archive.org/web/20170923142524/http://www.datelinetheory.com/p/effects-of-date-line.html |archivedate = September 23, 2017 |df = mdy-all }}&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Radio equipment ===

The Electra had radio equipment for both communication and navigation, but details about that equipment are not clear. The Electra failed to establish two-way radio communications with ''Itasca'' and failed to radiolocate ''Itasca''. Many explanations have been proposed for those failures.

The plane had a modified [[Western Electric]] model 13C transmitter. The 50-watt transmitter was crystal controlled and capable of transmitting on 500&amp;nbsp;kHz, 3105&amp;nbsp;kHz, and 6210&amp;nbsp;kHz.&lt;ref name="radio"&gt;{{cite web |url = https://tighar.org/Projects/Earhart/Archives/Research/ResearchPapers/Worldflight/prepdepart.html |title = Preparations and Departure, World Flight 1 |author =  |date =  |website = tighar.org |accessdate = April 4, 2018 |deadurl = no |archiveurl = https://web.archive.org/web/20171201035410/https://tighar.org/Projects/Earhart/Archives/Research/ResearchPapers/Worldflight/prepdepart.html |archivedate = December 1, 2017 |df = mdy-all }}&lt;/ref&gt; Crystal control means that the transmitter cannot be tuned to other frequencies; the plane could transmit only on those three frequencies. The transmitter had been modified at the factory to provide the 500&amp;nbsp;kHz capability.

The plane had a modified Western Electric model 20B receiver. Ordinarily, the receiver covered four frequency bands: 188–420&amp;nbsp;kHz, 550–1500&amp;nbsp;kHz, 1500–4000&amp;nbsp;kHz, and 4000–10000&amp;nbsp;kHz. The receiver was modified to lower the frequencies in the second band to 485–1200&amp;nbsp;kHz. That modification allowed the reception of 500&amp;nbsp;kHz signals; such signals were used for marine distress calls and radionavigation.&lt;ref name="radio" /&gt;{{refn|The 485&amp;nbsp;1200&amp;nbsp;kHz may be a guess based on the subsequent model 20BA having that range.|group=Note}} The model 20B receiver has two antenna inputs: a low frequency antenna input and a high frequency antenna input. The receiver's band selector also selects which antenna input is used; the first two bands use the low frequency antenna, and the last two bands select the high frequency antenna.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url = https://tighar.org/Projects/Earhart/Archives/Research/ResearchPapers/ElectraRadios/ElectraRadios.htm |title = Archived copy |accessdate = December 4, 2017 |deadurl = no |archiveurl = https://web.archive.org/web/20171102220035/http://tighar.org/Projects/Earhart/Archives/Research/ResearchPapers/ElectraRadios/ElectraRadios.htm |archivedate = November 2, 2017 |df = mdy-all }} "The antenna input circuit of the Model 20 receivers was designed to accept connections from two separate antennas: one for low-frequency Bands 1 and 2, the other for high-frequency bands 3 and 4."&lt;/ref&gt;

It is unknown whether the model 20B receiver had a [[beat frequency oscillator]] that would enable the detection of continuous wave transmissions such as Morse code and radiolocation beacons.&lt;ref name="radio" /&gt; Neither Earhart nor Noonan were capable of using Morse code.{{sfn|Chater|1937}} They relied on voice communications. Manning, who was on the first world flight attempt but not the second, was skilled at Morse and had acquired an FCC aircraft radiotelegraph license for 15 words per minute in March 1937, just prior to the start of the first flight.{{sfn|Long|Long|1999|p=62}}&lt;!-- Consequently, the first flight would have had CW-capable equipment and an operator with the knowledge to use it. Even if the BFO were there, Earhart and Noonan may not have known how to use it. Earhart could find Hawaii broadcast bands (&lt;1600 kHz), but she expected voice modulation when using the RDF. She thought she had to be talking/whistling to enable a fix on her, but she only had to transmit a carrier. That suggests either the receiver didn't have a BFO or that Earhart did not understand how to use it. --&gt;

A separate automatic radio direction finder receiver, a prototype Hooven Radio Compass,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite patent |inventor-last = Hooven |inventor-first = Frederick J. |title = Radio Compass System |country-code = US |patent-number = 2220904 |publication-date = July 16, 1936 |issue-date = November 12, 1940 }}&lt;/ref&gt; had been installed in the plane in October 1936, but that receiver was removed before the flight to save weight.&lt;ref&gt;"A bit of history", {{cite web |url = https://tighar.org/Projects/Earhart/Archives/Forum/Highlights61_80/highlights69.html |title = Archived copy |accessdate = November 23, 2017 |deadurl = no |archiveurl = https://web.archive.org/web/20171201033431/https://tighar.org/Projects/Earhart/Archives/Forum/Highlights61_80/highlights69.html |archivedate = December 1, 2017 |df = mdy-all }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Letter, Hooven to Goerner, December 5, 1966, {{cite web |url = https://earharttruth.wordpress.com/2017/05/15/hoovens-1966-letter-to-fred-goerner-quite-clear-removal-of-his-radio-compass-doomed-earhart/ |title = Archived copy |accessdate = November 25, 2017 |deadurl = no |archiveurl = https://web.archive.org/web/20171201032942/https://earharttruth.wordpress.com/2017/05/15/hoovens-1966-letter-to-fred-goerner-quite-clear-removal-of-his-radio-compass-doomed-earhart/ |archivedate = December 1, 2017 |df = mdy-all }}&lt;/ref&gt; The Hooven Radio Compass was replaced with a Bendix coupling unit that allowed a conventional loop antenna to be attached to an existing receiver (i.e., the Western Electric 20B). The loop antenna is visible above the cockpit on Earhart's plane.&lt;!-- early pictures show the Hooven antenna dome; later pictures show the loop --&gt;

Alternatively, the loop antenna may have been connected to a Bendix RA-1 auxiliary receiver with direction finding capability up to 1500&amp;nbsp;kHz.{{refn|The loop antenna and not the receiver ordinarily limit RDF. An RA-1B receiver has a band that stops at 1500&amp;nbsp;kHz; the next band starts at 1800&amp;nbsp;kHz (A model frequency range) or 2500&amp;nbsp;kHz (B model) (see http://aafradio.org/docs/Bendix_1941_brochure.pdf page 2). If the loop antenna could do direction finding above 1800&amp;nbsp;kHz, then the receiver could be used for direction finding at those higher frequencies. Long claims the loop antenna was limited to 1430&amp;nbsp;kHz.|group=Note}}{{refn|{{harvtxt|Long|Long|1999|pp=61–63}} has Bendix representative Cyril Remmlein coming from Washington D.C. to Burbank on February 25, 1937 to install the RA-1 and direction finding equipment. Manning would be able to work the radio from the copilot's seat or the cabin. Manning would have to be in the cabin to pay out the trailing wire antenna and to select the transmitting antennas. The book claims the loop antenna was a Navy RDF-1-B direction finder loop with a custom loop coupler control box connected to a Bendix RA-1 receiver.|group=Note}} It is not clear that such a receiver was installed, and if it were, it may have been removed before the flight.&lt;ref name="radio" /&gt; {{harvtxt|Long|Long|1999|p=115}} describes Joe Gurr training Earhart to use a Bendix receiver and other equipment to tune radio station [[KFI]] on 640&amp;nbsp;kHz and determine its direction.

Whichever receiver was used, there are pictures of Earhart's radio direction finder loop antenna and its 5-band Bendix coupling unit.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url = https://tighar.org/smf/index.php?topic=770.15 |title = RDF Loop Control |author =  |date =  |website = tighar.org |accessdate = April 4, 2018 |deadurl = no |archiveurl = https://web.archive.org/web/20171202052735/https://tighar.org/smf/index.php?topic=770.15 |archivedate = December 2, 2017 |df = mdy-all }}&lt;/ref&gt; The details of the loop and its coupler are not clear. {{harvtxt|Long|Long|1999|pp=63, 68}} claim the coupling unit adapted a standard RDF-1-B loop to the RA-1 receiver, and that the system was limited to frequencies below 1430&amp;nbsp;kHz. During the first world flight attempt's leg from Honolulu to Howland (when Manning was a navigator), ''Itasca'' was supposed to transmit a CW homing beacon at either 375&amp;nbsp;kHz or 500&amp;nbsp;kHz.{{sfn|Long|Long|1999|pp=68–69}} At least twice during the world flight, Earhart failed to determine radio bearings at 7500&amp;nbsp;kHz. If the RDF equipment was not suitable for that frequency, then attempting such a fix would be operator error and fruitless. However, the earlier 7-band Navy RDF-1-A covered 500&amp;nbsp;kHz–8000&amp;nbsp;kHz.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url = http://aafradio.org/docs/1936_NRL_Aircraft_Radio_Training_Manual_DF_Chapter.pdf |title = Archived copy |accessdate = December 1, 2017 |deadurl = no |archiveurl = https://web.archive.org/web/20150802083006/http://aafradio.org/docs/1936_NRL_Aircraft_Radio_Training_Manual_DF_Chapter.pdf |archivedate = August 2, 2015 |df = mdy-all }} page 129&lt;/ref&gt; The later 3-band DU-1 covered 200&amp;nbsp;kHz–1600&amp;nbsp;kHz.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url = http://aafradio.org/docs/DU-1.pdf |title = Archived copy |accessdate = December 1, 2017 |deadurl = no |archiveurl = https://web.archive.org/web/20170808181522/http://aafradio.org/docs/DU-1.pdf |archivedate = August 8, 2017 |df = mdy-all }} §&amp;nbsp;2.2&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=https://archive.org/details/AircraftRadioEquipment |title=Aircraft Radio Equipment 1944 |first= |last= United States. Bureau of Naval Personnel |date=1944 |location=Washington, D.C. |publisher=U.S. Government Printing Office |series=Navy Training Courses |accessdate=April 4, 2018 |via=Internet Archive }}&lt;/ref&gt; It is not clear where the RDF-1-B or Earhart's coupler performance sits between those two units.{{refn|Putnam said upper limit was 1400&amp;nbsp;kHz; Long and Long say 1430&amp;nbsp;kHz; on 26 June 1937 1930&amp;nbsp;GMT, San Francisco station of the Coast Guard quote Earhart: "Following information from Earhart this date quote homing device covers from 200 to 1500 and 2400 to 4800&amp;nbsp;kHz any frequencies not repeat not near ends of bands suitable unquote". https://tighar.org/wiki/Failure_to_communicate|group=Note}} In addition, the RDF-1-A and DU-1 coupler designs have other differences. The intention is to have the ordinary receive antenna connected to the coupler's antenna input; from there, it is passed on to the receiver. In the RDF-1-A design, the coupler must be powered on for that design function to work.{{refn|When the selector switch is in the "R" (receive) position, the antenna signal is routed through a vacuum tube. If the vacuum tube is not powered, there would only be stray coupling.|group=Note}} In the later DU-1 design, the coupler need not be powered.{{refn|In the "R" position for the DU-1, the antenna signal is capacitively connected (via {{math|''C''-101}}) to the output.|group=Note}}

There were problems with the RDF equipment during the world flight. During the transatlantic leg of the flight (Brazil to Africa), the RDF equipment did not work.{{refn|Noonan wrote a letter on June 8, 1937 stating the RDF did not work when closing with Africa. (Should be in Long &amp; Long near page 142.) Also letter to [[Eugene Pallette]] dated June 9, 1937, "And our radio was out of order – it would be, in such a jam." https://tighar.org/Projects/Earhart/Archives/Documents/Letters/NoonanPallette.pdf|group=Note}} The radio direction finding station at Darwin expected to be in contact with Earhart when she arrived there, but Earhart stated that the RDF was not functioning; the problem was a blown fuse.{{refn|C. L. A. Abbott letter dated August 3, 1937 and quoting A. R. Collins: "When Miss Earhart arrived at Darwin it was necessary to ask why there had been no radio communication with the Government Direction Finding Wireless Station under my control.  (Miss Earhart had been advised of the facilities and the Station's wave length prior to departure from Koepang).  Miss Earhart regretted that the D/F receiver installed in her aircraft was not functioning therefore an inspection of this received {{sic}} was carried out and a ground test arranged between the aircraft and the D/F wireless station.  It was discovered that the fuse for the D/F generator had blown and upon renewal in Miss Earhart's presence the ground test was completed.  Miss Earhart was advised to inspect fuse in event of further trouble."|group=Note}} During a test flight at Lae, Earhart could hear radio signals, but she failed to obtain an RDF bearing.{{sfn|Chater|1937}} While apparently near Howland Island, Earhart reported receiving a 7500&amp;nbsp;kHz signal from ''Itasca'', but she was unable to obtain an RDF bearing.{{refn|''Itasca'' radio log.}}

The antennas and their connections on the Electra are not certain.&lt;ref&gt;Michael Everette, TIGHAR, Electra radios, {{cite web |url = https://tighar.org/Projects/Earhart/Archives/Research/ResearchPapers/ElectraRadios/ElectraRadios.htm |title = Archived copy |accessdate = December 4, 2017 |deadurl = no |archiveurl = https://web.archive.org/web/20171102220035/http://tighar.org/Projects/Earhart/Archives/Research/ResearchPapers/ElectraRadios/ElectraRadios.htm |archivedate = November 2, 2017 |df = mdy-all }}&lt;/ref&gt; A dorsal Vee antenna was added by Bell Telephone Laboratories. There had been a trailing wire antenna for 500&amp;nbsp;kHz, but the Luke Field accident collapsed both landing gear and wiped off the ventral antennas.&lt;ref&gt;Luke Field crash report&lt;/ref&gt; After the accident, the trailing wire antenna was removed, the dorsal antenna was modified, and a ventral antenna was installed. It is not certain, but it is likely that the dorsal antenna was only connected to the transmitter (i.e., no "break in" relay), and the ventral antenna was only connected to the receiver.&lt;ref&gt;TIGHAR, Electra radios; Gillespie, highlights&lt;/ref&gt; Once the second world flight started, problems with radio reception were noticed while flying across the US; Pan Am technicians may have modified the ventral antenna while the plane was in Miami.&lt;ref&gt;where?&lt;/ref&gt; At Lae, problems with transmission quality on 6210&amp;nbsp;kHz were noticed.&lt;ref&gt;{{Harvtxt|Chater|1937}}: "THE CONDITION OF RADIO EQUIPMENT OF EARHART'S PLANE IS AS FOLLOWS – TRANSMITTER CARRIER WAVE ON 6210 KC WAS VERY ROUGH AND I ADVISED MISS EARHART TO PITCH HER VOICE HIGHER TO OVERCOME DISTORTION CAUSED BY ROUGH CARRIER WAVE, OTHERWISE TRANSMITTER SEEMED TO BE WORKING SATISFACTORILY".&lt;/ref&gt; Once the flight took off from Lae, Lae did not receive radio messages on 6210&amp;nbsp;kHz (Earhart's daytime frequency) until four hours later (at &lt;time datetime="1937-07-02T14:18+10:00" title="04:18Z"&gt;2:18&amp;nbsp;pm&lt;/time&gt;); Lae's last reception was at &lt;time datetime="1937-07-02T17:18+10:00" title="07:18Z"&gt;5:18&amp;nbsp;pm&lt;/time&gt; and was a strong signal; Lae received nothing after that; presumably the plane switched to 3105&amp;nbsp;kHz (Earhart's nighttime frequency).{{sfn|Chater|1937}} ''Itasca'' heard Earhart on 3105&amp;nbsp;kHz, but did not hear her on 6210&amp;nbsp;kHz.&lt;ref&gt;Radio logs, Position 1 first heard Earhart at &lt;time datetime="1937-07-02T02:45-11:30" title="14:15Z"&gt;2 July 02:45 am&lt;/time&gt;. Position 2 log, "DO NOT HR U ON 6210" at &lt;time datetime="1937-07-02T08:47-11:30" title="20:17Z"&gt;08:47&amp;nbsp;am&lt;/time&gt;.&lt;/ref&gt; TIGHAR postulates that the ventral receiving antenna was scraped off while the Electra taxied to the runway at Lae; consequently, the Electra lost its ability to receive HF transmissions.{{refn|Earhart never reported receiving signals on 3105 or 6210&amp;nbsp;kHz; she did report receiving a 7500&amp;nbsp;kHz signal on the direction finder.|group=Note}}

=== Nearing Howland Island ===

[[File:USCGS Itasca.jpg|thumb|USCGC ''Itasca'' was at Howland Island to support the flight.]]

The [[USCGC Itasca (1929)|USCGC ''Itasca'']] was on station at Howland. Its task was to communicate with Earhart's Electra and guide them to the island once they arrived in the vicinity. Noonan and Earhart expected to do voice communications on 3105&amp;nbsp;kHz during the night and 6210&amp;nbsp;kHz during the day.

Through a series of misunderstandings or errors (the details of which are still controversial), the final approach to Howland Island using [[radio navigation]] was not successful. Fred Noonan had earlier written about problems affecting the accuracy of radio direction finding in navigation.{{refn|Noonan, Fred. Memo to Operations Manager, Pacific Division, Pan American Airlines, April 29, 1935: "The inaccuracies of direction finding bearings can be very definitely cataloged: twilight effects, faint signals, wide splits of minima and inaccurate calibration."|group=Note}} Another cited cause of possible confusion was that the ''Itasca'' and Earhart planned their communication schedule using time systems set a half-hour apart, with Earhart using Greenwich Civil Time (GCT) and the ''Itasca'' under a Naval time zone designation system.&lt;ref name="Hoversten"&gt;Hoversten 2007, pp. 22–23.&lt;/ref&gt;

The Electra expected ''Itasca'' to transmit signals that the Electra could use as an RDF beacon to find the ''Itasca''.  In theory, the plane could listen for the signal while rotating its [[loop antenna]]. A sharp minimum indicates the direction of the RDF beacon. The Electra's RDF equipment had failed due to a blown fuse during an earlier leg flying to Darwin; the fuse was replaced.&lt;ref&gt;Abbott, 1937, {{cite web |url = https://tighar.org/Projects/Earhart/Archives/Documents/Letters/Abbott8_3_37.pdf |title = Archived copy |accessdate = November 19, 2017 |deadurl = no |archiveurl = https://web.archive.org/web/20161019053024/http://tighar.org/Projects/Earhart/Archives/Documents/Letters/Abbott8_3_37.pdf |archivedate = October 19, 2016 |df = mdy-all }}&lt;/ref&gt; Near Howland, Earhart could hear the transmission from ''Itasca'' on 7500&amp;nbsp;kHz, but she was unable to determine a minimum, so she could not determine a direction to ''Itasca''. Earhart was also unable to determine a minimum during an RDF test at Lae.{{sfn|Chater|1937}} One likely theory is that Earhart's RDF equipment did not work at 7500&amp;nbsp;kHz; most RDF equipment at the time was not designed to work above 2000&amp;nbsp;kHz. When operated above their design frequency, loop antennas lose their directionality.&lt;ref&gt;{{harvtxt|Long|Long|1999|p=116}} stating, "However, the frequencies of the Bendix receiver's bands 4 and 5 were completely out of the design range of the direction-finder, and the loop could not process the signals to obtain bearings."&lt;/ref&gt;{{refn|{{harvtxt|Chater|1937}} shows that ''Itasca'' transmitters were calibrated for 7500, 6210, 3105, 500, and 425&amp;nbsp;kHz. Chater also reports that Earhart tested the Lockheed's 600&amp;nbsp;m (500&amp;nbsp;kHz) longwave receiver. Earhart's instructions to ''Itasca'' said "NOW UNDERSTAND ITASCA VOICING THREE ONE NAUGHT FIVE ON HOUR AND HALF HOUR WITH LONG CONTINUOUS SIGNAL ON APPROACH".|group=Note}}&lt;!-- Another explanation is that Itasca could only transmit CW on 7500&amp;nbsp;kHz. If Earhart's receiver did not have a beat frequency oscillator (BFO) or the BFO was not enabled, then it would be difficult to recognize Itasca's transmissions. --&gt;

''Itasca'' had its own RDF equipment, but that equipment did not work above 550&amp;nbsp;kHz,{{sfn|Chater|1937}} so ''Itasca'' could not determine the direction to the Electra's HF transmissions at 3105 and 6210&amp;nbsp;kHz. The Electra had been equipped to transmit a 500&amp;nbsp;kHz signal that ''Itasca'' could use for radio direction finding, but some of that equipment had been removed. The equipment originally used a long trailing wire antenna. While the plane was in flight, the wire antenna would be paid out at the tail; efficient transmissions at 500&amp;nbsp;kHz needed a long antenna. The antenna was bulky and heavy, so the trailing wire antenna was removed to save weight. If nothing else had been done, the plane would have been unable to transmit an RDF signal that ''Itasca'' could use. Such a modification was made, but without voice communication from ''Itasca'' to the plane, the ship could not tell the plane to use its 500&amp;nbsp;kHz signal.{{refn|The ''Itasca'' did request RDF transmission on 500&amp;nbsp;kHz. ''Itasca'' radio log for position 2 page 3 at 8:11&amp;nbsp;am: &lt;code&gt;{{#tag:abbr|KHAQQ|title=Earhart's plane}} {{#tag:abbr|FM|title=from}} ITASCA DID U GET {{#tag:abbr|TT|title=that}} XMISION ON {{#tag:abbr|7.5 MEGS|title=7500 kHz}} {{#tag:abbr|GA|title=go ahead}} ON 500 {{#tag:abbr|KCS|title=kilohertz}} SO TT WE MAY BE ABLE TO TAKE A BEARING ON U IMPOSSIBLE TO TAKE A BEARING ON 3105 - PLS ACKNWLDGE THIS XMISION {{#tag:abbr|WID|title=with}} {{#tag:abbr|A3|title=voice transmission}} ON 3105 GA / UNANSWRD&lt;/code&gt;.|group=Note}} Even if ''Itasca'' could get a bearing to the plane, the ''Itasca'' could not tell the plane that bearing, so the plane could not head to the ship.

Some sources have noted Earhart's apparent lack of understanding of her direction-finding system, which had been fitted to the aircraft just prior to the flight. The system was equipped with a new receiver from [[Bendix Corporation|Bendix]] that operated on five wavelength "bands", marked 1 to 5. The loop antenna was equipped with a tuneable [[loading coil]] that changed the effective length of the antenna to allow it to work efficiently at different wavelengths. The tuner on the antenna was also marked with five settings, 1 to 5, but, critically, these were not the same frequency bands as the corresponding bands on the radio. The two were close enough for settings 1, 2 and 3, but the higher frequency settings, 4 and 5, were entirely different. The upper bands (4 and 5) could not be used for direction finding.&lt;ref&gt;{{harvtxt|Long|Long|1999|p=116}} states, "Earhart though she could take a radio bearing with her direction-finder loop on any signal between 200 and 10,000 kilocycles. She could not."&lt;/ref&gt; Earhart's only training on the system was a brief introduction by Joe Gurr at the Lockheed factory, and the topic had not come up. A card displaying the band settings of the antenna was mounted so it was not visible. Gurr explained that higher frequency bands would offer better accuracy and longer range.{{sfn|Long|Long|1999|p=116}}

Motion picture evidence from Lae suggests that an [[Antenna (radio)|antenna]] mounted underneath the fuselage may have been torn off from the fuel-heavy Electra during taxi or takeoff from Lae's turf runway, though no antenna was reported found at Lae. Don Dwiggins, in his biography of Paul Mantz (who assisted Earhart and Noonan in their flight planning), noted that the aviators had cut off their long-wire antenna, due to the annoyance of having to crank it back into the aircraft after each use.

=== Radio signals ===
&lt;!--Copyright concerns, do not readd until cleared [[File:Amelia 1936.jpg|thumb|right|Earhart in the [[Lockheed Model 10 Electra|Electra]] cockpit, c. 1936]]--&gt;

During Earhart and Noonan's approach to Howland Island, the ''Itasca'' received strong and clear voice transmissions from Earhart identifying as KHAQQ but she apparently was unable to hear voice transmissions from the ship. Signals from the ship would also be used for direction finding, implying that the aircraft's direction finder was also not functional.

The first calls, routine reports stating the weather as cloudy and overcast, were received at &lt;time datetime="1937-07-02T02:45-11:30" title="14:15Z"&gt;2:45&lt;/time&gt; and just before &lt;time datetime="1937-07-02T05:00-11:30" title="16:30Z"&gt;5&amp;nbsp;am on July 2&lt;/time&gt;. These calls were broken up by static, but at this point the aircraft would still be a long distance from Howland.{{sfn|Fleming|2011|p=2}}

At &lt;time datetime="1937-07-02T06:14-11:30" title="17:44Z"&gt;6:14&amp;nbsp;am&lt;/time&gt; another call was received stating the aircraft was within {{convert|200|miles|km}}, and requested that the ship use its direction finder to provide a bearing for the aircraft. Earhart began whistling into the microphone to provide a continual signal for them to home in on.{{sfn|Fleming|2011|p=3}} It was at this point that the radio operators on the ''Itasca'' realized that their RDF system could not tune in the aircraft's 3105&amp;nbsp;kHz frequency; radioman Leo Bellarts later commented that he "was sitting there sweating blood because I couldn't do a darn thing about it." A similar call asking for a bearing was received at &lt;time datetime="1937-07-02T06:45-11:30" title="18:15Z"&gt;6:45&amp;nbsp;am&lt;/time&gt;, when Earhart estimated they were {{convert|100|miles|km}} out.{{sfn|Fleming|2011|p=4}}

An ''Itasca'' radio log (position 1) at 7:30–7:40&amp;nbsp;am states:
{{quote|quote=EARHART ON &lt;abbr title="now"&gt;NW&lt;/abbr&gt; SEZ RUNNING OUT OF GAS ONLY 1/2 HOUR LEFT CANT &lt;abbr title="hear"&gt;HR&lt;/abbr&gt; US AT ALL / WE HR HER AND ARE SENDING ON 3105 &lt;abbr title="and"&gt;ES&lt;/abbr&gt; 500 SAME TIME CONSTANTLY&lt;ref name="pos1page2"&gt;{{cite web |url = https://tighar.org/Projects/Earhart/Archives/Research/Bulletins/37_ItascaLogs/pos1page2.pdf |title = Radio Log: Itasca |accessdate = November 20, 2017 |deadurl = no |archiveurl = https://web.archive.org/web/20161021165353/http://tighar.org/Projects/Earhart/Archives/Research/Bulletins/37_ItascaLogs/pos1page2.pdf |archivedate = October 21, 2016 |df = mdy-all }}&lt;/ref&gt;}}

Another ''Itasca'' radio log (position 2) at &lt;time datetime="1937-07-02T07:42-11:30" title="19:12Z"&gt;7:42&amp;nbsp;am&lt;/time&gt; states:
&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;abbr title="Earhart's plane"&gt;KHAQQ&lt;/abbr&gt; &lt;abbr title="calling"&gt;CLNG&lt;/abbr&gt; ITASCA WE MUST BE ON YOU BUT CANNOT SEE U BUT GAS IS RUNNING LOW BEEN UNABLE TO REACH YOU BY RADIO WE ARE FLYING AT A 1000 FEET&lt;ref name="pos2page2"&gt;{{cite web |url = https://tighar.org/Projects/Earhart/Archives/Research/Bulletins/37_ItascaLogs/pos2page2.pdf |title = Archived copy: Radio Entries and Times |accessdate = November 20, 2017 |deadurl = no |archiveurl = https://web.archive.org/web/20161021164910/http://tighar.org/Projects/Earhart/Archives/Research/Bulletins/37_ItascaLogs/pos2page2.pdf |archivedate = October 21, 2016 |df = mdy-all }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

Earhart's &lt;time datetime="1937-07-02T07:58-11:30" title="19:28Z"&gt;7:58&amp;nbsp;am&lt;/time&gt; transmission said she couldn't hear the ''Itasca'' and asked them to send voice signals so she could try to take a radio bearing. This transmission was reported by the ''Itasca'' as the loudest possible signal, indicating Earhart and Noonan were in the immediate area. They couldn't send voice at the frequency she asked for, so [[Morse code]] signals were sent instead. Earhart acknowledged receiving these but said she was unable to determine their direction.&lt;ref&gt;Jacobson, Randall S., PhD. [http://tighar.org/Projects/Earhart/Research/ResearchPapers/Worldflight/finalflight3.html "The Final Flight. Part 3: At Howland Island."] {{webarchive|url=https://www.webcitation.org/query?url=http%3A%2F%2Ftighar.org%2FProjects%2FEarhart%2FArchives%2FResearch%2FResearchPapers%2FWorldflight%2Ffinalflight3.html&amp;date=2012-07-25 |date=July 25, 2012 }} ''tighar.org'', 2009. Retrieved: July 10, 2010.&lt;/ref&gt;

In her last known transmission at &lt;time datetime="1937-07-02T08:43-11:30" title="20:13Z"&gt;8:43&amp;nbsp;am&lt;/time&gt; Earhart broadcast "We are on the line 157 337. We will repeat this message. We will repeat this on 6210 kilocycles. Wait." However, a few moments later she was back on the same frequency (3105&amp;nbsp;kHz) with a transmission that was logged as a "questionable": "We are running on line north and south."&lt;ref&gt;[http://tighar.org/Projects/Earhart/forum/FAQs/navigation.html "Earhart Navigation FAQ".] {{webarchive|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20100803152139/http://tighar.org/Projects/Earhart/forum/FAQs/navigation.html |date=August 3, 2010 }} ''tighar.org''. Retrieved: July 10, 2010.&lt;/ref&gt; Earhart's transmissions seemed to indicate she and Noonan believed they had reached Howland's charted position, which was incorrect by about five nautical miles (10&amp;nbsp;km). The ''Itasca'' used her oil-fired boilers to generate smoke for a period of time but the fliers apparently did not see it. The many scattered clouds in the area around Howland Island have also been cited as a problem: their dark shadows on the ocean surface may have been almost indistinguishable from the island's subdued and very flat profile.

Whether any post-loss radio signals were received from Earhart and Noonan remains unclear. If transmissions were received from the Electra, most if not all were weak and hopelessly garbled. Earhart's voice transmissions to Howland were on 3105&amp;nbsp;kHz, a frequency restricted in the United States by the FCC to aviation use.{{refn|Quote: "Frequencies between 2,504 to 3,497.5 kc were allocated to "Coastal harbor, government, aviation, fixed, miscellaneous".&lt;ref&gt;''American Radio Relay League 1945'', p. 453.&lt;/ref&gt;|group=Note}} This frequency was thought to be not fit for broadcasts over great distances. When Earhart was at cruising altitude and midway between Lae and Howland (over {{convert|1000|mi|km}} from each) neither station heard her scheduled transmission at &lt;time datetime="1937-07-02T08:15Z"&gt;0815 GCT&lt;/time&gt;.{{sfn|Long|Long|1999|p=20}} Moreover, the 50-watt transmitter used by Earhart was attached to a less-than-optimum-length V-type antenna.&lt;ref&gt;Everette, Michael. [http://tighar.org/Projects/Earhart/Research/ResearchPapers/ElectraRadios/ElectraRadios.htm "Electric Radio Communications Equipment Installed on Board Lockeed Electra NR16020."] {{webarchive|url=https://www.webcitation.org/query?url=http%3A%2F%2Ftighar.org%2FProjects%2FEarhart%2FArchives%2FResearch%2FResearchPapers%2FElectraRadios%2FElectraRadios.htm&amp;date=2012-07-25 |date=July 25, 2012 }} ''tighar.org'', 2009. Retrieved: July 10, 2010.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;''American Radio Relay League 1945'', pp. 196–199.&lt;/ref&gt;{{refn| The height of the antenna is important, a horizontally polarized antenna operating at a small fraction of its wavelength above the ground will be less efficient than that same antenna operating at [[cruising altitude]].|group=Note}}

The last voice transmission received on Howland Island from Earhart indicated she and Noonan were flying along a line of position (running N–S on 157–337 degrees) which Noonan would have calculated and drawn on a chart as passing through Howland.{{sfn|Safford|2003|p=145}}{{refn|Safford disputes a "sun line" theory and proposes that Noonan asked Earhart to fly 157–337 magnetic or to fly at right angles to the original track on north–south courses.|group=Note}} After all contact was lost with Howland Island, attempts were made to reach the flyers with both voice and [[Morse code]] transmissions. Operators across the Pacific and the United States may have heard signals from the downed Electra but these were unintelligible or weak.&lt;ref&gt;Brandenberg, Bob. [http://tighar.org/Projects/Earhart/Research/ResearchPapers/Brandenburg/BettyProb182531a.pdf "Probability of Betty Hearing Amelia on a Harmonic Gardner Sunset: 0538Z Sunrise: 1747Z."] {{webarchive|url=https://www.webcitation.org/query?url=http%3A%2F%2Ftighar.org%2FProjects%2FEarhart%2FArchives%2FResearch%2FResearchPapers%2FBrandenburg%2FBettyProb182531a.pdf&amp;date=2012-07-25 |date=July 25, 2012 }} ''tighar.org'', 2007. Retrieved: July 10, 2010.&lt;/ref&gt;{{refn|A teenager in the northeastern United States claims to have heard post-loss transmissions from Earhart and Noonan but modern analysis has shown there was an extremely low probability of any signal from Amelia Earhart being received in the United States on a harmonic of a frequency she could transmit upon.|group=Note}}

Some of these reports of transmissions were later determined to be [[hoax]]es but others were deemed authentic. Bearings taken by [[Pan American Airways]] stations suggested signals originating from several locations, including [[Nikumaroro|Gardner Island]] (Nikumaroro), 360 miles (580&amp;nbsp;km) to the SSE.{{sfn|Gillespie|2006|p=115}}{{sfn|Strippel|1995|p=18}} It was noted at the time that if these signals were from Earhart and Noonan, they must have been on land with the aircraft since water would have otherwise shorted out the Electra's electrical system.{{sfn|Gillespie|2006|p=190}}{{refn|The essential components were all mounted low, including the generator, batteries, dynamotor and transmitter.|group=Note}}{{sfn|Gillespie|2006|p=140}}{{refn|In order to operate the radio for any length of time, the aircraft would have had to be standing more or less upright on its landing gear with the right engine running in order to charge the 50-watt transmitter's battery, which would have consumed six gallons of fuel per hour.|group=Note}} Sporadic signals were reported for four or five days after the disappearance but none yielded any understandable information.{{sfn|Goldstein|Dillon|1997|p=241}}{{refn|The first two days were marked by rumors and misinformation regarding radio transmission capabilities of the Lockheed Model 10 Electra that were finally resolved by the aircraft company.|group=Note}} The captain of {{USS|Colorado|BB-45|6}} later said: "There was no doubt many stations were calling the Earhart plane on the plane's frequency, some by voice and others by signals. All of these added to the confusion and doubtfulness of the authenticity of the reports."{{sfn|Gillespie|2006|p=146}}

=== Search efforts ===

Beginning approximately one hour after Earhart's last recorded message, the USCGC ''Itasca'' undertook an ultimately unsuccessful search north and west of Howland Island based on initial assumptions about transmissions from the aircraft. The [[United States Navy]] soon joined the search and over a period of about three days sent available resources to the search area in the vicinity of Howland Island. The initial search by the ''Itasca'' involved running up the 157/337 line of position to the NNW from Howland Island. The ''Itasca'' then searched the area to the immediate NE of the island, corresponding to the area, yet wider than the area searched to the NW. Based on bearings of several supposed Earhart radio transmissions, some of the search efforts were directed to a specific position on a line of 281 degrees (approximately northwest) from Howland Island without evidence of the flyers.{{sfn|Goldstein|Dillon|1997|p=251}} Four days after Earhart's last verified radio transmission, on July 6, 1937, the captain of the battleship ''Colorado'' received orders from the Commandant, [[United States Naval Districts#14th Naval District|Fourteenth Naval District]] to take over all naval and coast guard units to coordinate search efforts.{{sfn|Goldstein|Dillon|1997|p=251}}

Later search efforts were directed to the [[Phoenix Islands]] south of Howland Island.{{sfn|Goldstein|Dillon|1997|p=248}} A week after the disappearance, naval aircraft from the ''Colorado'' flew over several islands in the group including Gardner Island (now called [[Nikumaroro]]), which had been uninhabited for over 40 years. The subsequent report on Gardner read: "Here signs of recent habitation were clearly visible but repeated circling and zooming failed to elicit any answering wave from possible inhabitants and it was finally taken for granted that none were there... At the western end of the island a [[tramp trade|tramp steamer]] (of about 4000 tons)... lay high and almost dry head onto the coral beach with her back broken in two places. The lagoon at Gardner looked sufficiently deep and certainly large enough so that a seaplane or even an airboat could have landed or takenoff {{sic}} in any direction with little if any difficulty. Given a chance, it is believed that Miss Earhart could have landed her aircraft in this lagoon and swum or waded ashore."{{refn|Memo from Senior Aviator, USS ''Colorado'', to the [[Bureau of Aeronautics|Chief of the Bureau of Aeronautics]], "Aircraft Search of Earhart Plane". Their commander Capt Friedell made no note of "recent habitation" in his official summary.&lt;ref&gt;''Finding Amelia'' DVD, Annapolis, Maryland: Naval Institute Press, 2006. DVD: Contents: Reports: Lambrecht.pdf, p. 3.&lt;/ref&gt;|group=Note}} They also found that Gardner's shape and size as recorded on charts were wholly inaccurate. Other Navy search efforts were again directed north, west and southwest of Howland Island, based on a possibility the Electra had ditched in the ocean, was afloat, or that the aviators were in an emergency raft.{{sfn|Goldstein|Dillon|1997|p=254}}

The official search efforts lasted until July 19, 1937.{{sfn|Safford|2003|pp=61–62, 67–68}} At $4&amp;nbsp;million, the air and sea search by the Navy and [[Coast Guard]] was the most costly and intensive in U.S. history up to that time but [[search and rescue]] techniques during the era were rudimentary and some of the search was based on erroneous assumptions and flawed information. Official reporting of the search effort was influenced by individuals wary about how their roles in looking for an American hero might be reported by the press.{{sfn|Goldstein|Dillon|1997|p=254–255}}{{refn| FDR himself had to respond to accusations that the search was justified.|group=Note}} Despite an unprecedented search by the United States Navy and Coast Guard, no physical evidence of Earhart, Noonan or the Electra 10E was found. The aircraft carrier {{USS|Lexington|CV-2|6}}, the battleship {{USS|Colorado|BB-45|6}}, the {{USCGC|Itasca|1929|2}}, the Japanese oceanographic survey vessel ''Koshu'' and the Japanese seaplane tender [[Japanese seaplane tender Kamoi|''Kamoi'']] searched for six–seven days each, covering {{convert|150000|sqmi|km2}}.{{sfn|Goldstein|Dillon|1997|p=245–254}}{{sfn|King|Jacobson|Burns|Spading|2001|pp=32–33}}

Immediately after the end of the official search, Putnam financed a private search by local authorities of nearby Pacific islands and waters, concentrating on the Gilberts. In late July 1937, Putnam chartered two small boats and while he remained in the United States, directed a search of the [[Phoenix Islands]], [[Christmas Island (Kiribati)|Christmas (Kiritimati) Island]], [[Tabuaeran|Fanning (Tabuaeran) Island]], the [[Gilbert Islands]] and the [[Marshall Islands]], but [[List of aerial disappearances|no trace of the Electra or its occupants was found]].{{sfn|Goldstein|Dillon|1997|p=257}}

Back in the United States, Putnam acted to become the trustee of Earhart's estate so that he could pay for the searches and related bills. In probate court in Los Angeles, Putnam requested to have the "[[declared death in absentia|declared death ''in absentia'']]" seven-year waiting period waived so that he could manage Earhart's finances. As a result, Earhart was declared legally dead on January 5, 1939.{{sfn|Van Pelt|2005|p=205}}

== Speculation on disappearance ==

There has been considerable speculation on what happened to Earhart and Noonan. Most historians hold to the simple "crash and sink" theory, but a number of other possibilities have been proposed, including several conspiracy theories.

{{wide image|Earhart locations.png|700px|Earhart's flight was intended to be from [[Lae Airfield]] to [[Howland Island]], a trip of {{convert|2556|miles|nmi km|-2}}. This leg was the longest of the planned flight, the length was close to the maximum range of the plane, and the destination was a small island in a large ocean.}}

Some have suggested that Earhart and Noonan survived and landed elsewhere, but were either never found or killed, making en-route locations like [[Tarawa]] unlikely.  Proposals have included the uninhabited [[Gardner Island]] ({{convert|400|miles|km|-1}} from the vicinity of Howland), the Japanese-controlled [[Marshall Islands]] ({{convert|870|miles|km|-1}} at the closest point of [[Mili Atoll]]), and the Japanese-controlled [[Northern Mariana Islands]] ({{convert|2700|miles|km|-2}} from Howland).

=== Crash and sink theory ===

Many researchers believe that Earhart and Noonan ran out of fuel while searching for Howland Island, ditched at sea, and perished. The plane would have carried enough fuel to reach Howland with some extra to spare. The extra fuel would cover some contingencies such as headwinds and searching for Howland. The plane could fly a compass course toward Howland through the night. In the morning, the time of apparent sunrise would allow the plane to determine its line of position (a sun line that ran 157°–337°). From that line, the plane could determine how much further it must travel before reaching a parallel sun line that ran through Howland.&lt;ref name="sunline"&gt;{{cite journal |title = We are on the line 157 337 … |journal = TIGHAR Tracks |volume = 18 |issue = 2 |date = March 2002 |url = https://tighar.org/Publications/TTracks/2002Vol_18/line.pdf |deadurl = no |archiveurl = https://web.archive.org/web/20170821002848/http://tighar.org/Publications/TTracks/2002Vol_18/line.pdf |archivedate = August 21, 2017 |df = mdy-all }}&lt;/ref&gt; At 6:14 AM ''Itasca'' time, Earhart estimated they were 200 miles away from Howland.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url = https://tighar.org/Publications/TTracks/1995Vol_11/said.pdf |title = TIGHAR Tracks |accessdate = November 8, 2017 |deadurl = no |archiveurl = https://web.archive.org/web/20130124152213/http://tighar.org/Publications/TTracks/1995Vol_11/said.pdf |archivedate = January 24, 2013 |df = mdy-all }}&lt;/ref&gt; As the plane closed with Howland, it expected to be in radio contact with ''Itasca''. With the radio contact, the plane should be able to use radio direction finding (RDF) to head directly for the ''Itasca'' and Howland. Unfortunately, the plane was not receiving a radio signal from ''Itasca'', so it would be unable to determine an RDF bearing to the ship.{{refn|Earhart apparently did not understand the limitations of the RDF equipment. Earhart asked ''Itasca'' to transmit an RDF beacon at 7500&amp;nbsp;kHz, but the plane's RDF system could not determine the direction of such a HF signal. Earhart had failed to find a minimum (the transmitter direction) during a test of the RDF at Lae {{harv|Chater|1937}}, and the plane also failed to find a minimum while listening to ''Itasca'' while near Howland.|group=Note}} Although ''Itasca'' was receiving HF radio signals from the plane, it did not have HF RDF equipment, so it could not determine a bearing to the plane.{{refn|RDF equipment on ''Itasca'' could handle 270&amp;nbsp;kHz to 550&amp;nbsp;kHz {{harv|Chater|1937}}; Earhart had removed the 500&amp;nbsp;kHz trailing wire antenna from the plane and did not transmit on 500&amp;nbsp;kHz. The plane transmitted on 3105 and 6210&amp;nbsp;kHz.|group=Note}} The communications going to the plane were almost non-existent.{{refn|The plane apparently only heard transmissions on 7500&amp;nbsp;kHz, but ''Itasca'' could only transmit Morse code (not voice) on that frequency. Neither Earhart nor Noonan were skilled at Morse. {{harvtxt|Chater|1937}} at Lae states, "Miss Earhart and Captain Noonan spent a considerable time in the radio office and as previously mentioned it was learned that neither of them could read morse at any speed but could only distinguish letters made individually slowly and repeated often; in that case their direction finding apparatus would be useless or misleading unless they were taking a bearing on a station using radiophone which could give the station position on voice. We understand the ''Itasca'' was to do this but if the plane was unable to pick up the ''Itasca'' it is doubtful if the direction finder would be any use to her."|group=Note}} Consequently, the plane was not directed to Howland; it was left on its own with little fuel. Presumably, the plane reached the parallel sun line and started searching for Howland on that line of position. At 7:42 AM, Earhart reported, "We must be on you, but cannot see you – but gas is running low. Have been unable to reach you by radio. We are flying at 1,000 feet."&lt;ref name="sunline" /&gt;{{refn|At an altitude of 1000 feet, the plane would be able to see about 38 miles in clear weather. See Distance to Horizon Calculator at http://www.ringbell.co.uk/info/hdist.htm.|group=Note}} At 8:43 AM, Earhart reported, "We are on the line 157 337. We will repeat this message. We will repeat this on 6210 kilocycles. Wait."&lt;ref name="sunline" /&gt;

Navigator and aeronautical engineer [[Elgen Long]] and his wife Marie K. Long devoted 35 years of research to the "crash and sink" theory.&lt;ref&gt;Long, Elgen. [https://web.archive.org/web/20070212202807/http://www.elgenlong.com/amelia.php?view=main "Theory."] ''elgenlong.com'', 2006. Retrieved: September 23, 2017.&lt;/ref&gt; United States Navy Captain [[Laurance Safford]] (retired) who was responsible for the interwar Mid-Pacific Strategic Direction Finding Net, and the decoding of the Japanese [[Purple (cipher machine)|Purple]] cipher messages for the attack on Pearl Harbor, began a lengthy analysis of the Earhart flight during the 1970s. His research included the intricate radio transmission documentation. Safford came to the conclusion, "poor planning, worse execution".{{sfn|Strippel|1995|p=20}} Rear Admiral Richard R. Black, USN, who was in administrative charge of the Howland Island airstrip and was present in the radio room on the ''Itasca'', asserted in 1982 that "the Electra went into the sea about 10&amp;nbsp;am, July 2, 1937 not far from Howland".{{sfn|Strippel|1995}} British aviation historian Roy Nesbit interpreted evidence in contemporary accounts and Putnam's correspondence and concluded Earhart's Electra was not fully fueled at Lae.{{sfn|Strippel|1995|p=58}} William L. Polhemous, the navigator on [[Ann Pellegreno]]'s 1967 flight that followed Earhart and Noonan's original flight path, studied navigational tables for July 2, 1937, and thought Noonan may have miscalculated the "single line approach" intended to "hit" Howland.{{sfn|Strippel|1995|pp=58, 60}}

{{external media| float = right| video1 = [https://www.c-span.org/video/?95192-1/susan-butler-east-dawn ''Booknotes'' interview with Susan Butler on ''East to the Dawn'', December 14, 1997], [[C-SPAN]]}}

David Jourdan, a former Navy submariner and ocean engineer specializing in deep-sea recoveries, has claimed any transmissions attributed to Gardner Island were false. Through his company Nauticos he extensively searched a {{convert|1200|sqmi|km2|adj=on}} quadrant north and west of Howland Island during two deep-sea sonar expeditions (2002 and 2006, total cost $4.5&amp;nbsp;million) and found nothing. The search locations were derived from the line of position (157–337) broadcast by Earhart on July 2, 1937.&lt;ref name="Hoversten" /&gt; Nevertheless, Elgen Long's interpretations have led Jourdan to conclude, "The analysis of all the data we have – the fuel analysis, the radio calls, other things – tells me she went into the water off Howland."&lt;ref name="Hoversten" /&gt; Earhart's stepson George Palmer Putnam Jr. has been quoted as saying he believes "the plane just ran out of gas".&lt;ref&gt;Kleinberg, Eliot.
[https://groups.google.com/forum/#!topic/alt.obituaries/8-SuGX6ATRg "Amelia Earhart's disappearance still haunts her stepson, 83."] {{webarchive|url=http://arquivo.pt/wayback/20110122130054/https://groups.google.com/forum/ |date=January 22, 2011 }} ''Palm Beach Post'', December 27, 2004. Retrieved: July 1, 2013.&lt;/ref&gt; Susan Butler, author of the Earhart biography ''East to the Dawn'', says she thinks the aircraft went into the ocean out of sight of Howland Island and rests on the seafloor at a depth of {{convert|17000|ft|km|0}}.&lt;ref&gt;[https://www.pbs.org/opb/historydetectives/video/706_ameliaearhart.html "Amelia Earhart: Susan Butler interview."] {{webarchive|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20090731132917/http://www.pbs.org/opb/historydetectives/video/706_ameliaearhart.html |date=July 31, 2009 }} ''History Detectives'', Season 7 video. PBS. Retrieved: July 26, 2010.&lt;/ref&gt; Tom D. Crouch, Senior Curator of the [[National Air and Space Museum]], has said the Earhart/Noonan Electra is "18,000 ft. down" and may even yield a range of artifacts that could rival the finds of the ''[[RMS Titanic|Titanic]]'', adding that "the mystery is part of what keeps us interested. In part, we remember her because she's our favorite missing person."&lt;ref name="Hoversten" /&gt;

=== Gardner Island hypothesis ===
[[File:Nikumaroro Atoll 2014.jpg|thumb|Gardner ([[Nikumaroro]]) Island in 2014.  "Seven Site" is a focus of the search for Amelia Earhart's remains.|350px ]]
The Gardner Island hypothesis assumes that Earhart and Noonan, having not found Howland Island, would not waste time searching for Howland. Instead, they would turn to the south and look for other islands. The 157/337 radio transmission suggests they flew a course of 157° that would take them past Baker Island; if they missed Baker Island, then sometime later they would fly over the [[Phoenix Islands]], now part of the [[Kiribati|Republic of Kiribati]], about {{convert|350|nmi|km}} southsoutheast of Howland Island. The Gardner Island hypothesis has the plane making it to Gardner Island (now [[Nikumaroro]]), one of the Phoenix Islands.

A week after Earhart disappeared, Navy planes from {{USS|Colorado|BB-45|6}} (which had sailed from Pearl Harbor) searched Gardner Island. The planes saw signs of recent habitation and the wreck of the {{SS|Norwich City}}, but did not see any signs of Earhart's plane or people.  After the Navy ended its search, G. P. Putnam undertook a search in the Phoenix Group and other islands,&lt;ref&gt;[[#refRich1989|Rich 1989]], pp. 272–273.&lt;/ref&gt; but nothing was found.

In October 1937, Eric Bevington and Henry E. Maude visited Gardner with some potential settlers. A group walked all the way around the island, but did not find a plane or other evidence.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |url = http://tighar.org/Projects/Earhart/Archives/Documents/Bevington_Diary.html |title = The Earhart Project Research Document #11 Eric Bevington’s Journal |work = [[TIGHAR]] |accessdate = July 9, 2017 |deadurl = no |archiveurl = https://web.archive.org/web/20170719205728/http://tighar.org/Projects/Earhart/Archives/Documents/Bevington_Diary.html |archivedate = July 19, 2017 |df = mdy-all }}&lt;/ref&gt;

In December 1938, laborers landed on the island and started constructing the settlement.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |url = http://tighar.org/Projects/Earhart/Archives/Documents/Gallagher_Report.html |title = The Earhart Project Research Document #13 Gallagher’s Ninth Progress Report October – December, 1940 |work = [[TIGHAR]] |accessdate = July 9, 2017 |deadurl = no |archiveurl = https://web.archive.org/web/20170721002209/http://tighar.org/Projects/Earhart/Archives/Documents/Gallagher_Report.html |archivedate = July 21, 2017 |df = mdy-all }}&lt;/ref&gt; Around April 1940, a skull was discovered and buried, but British colonial officer [[Gerald Gallagher]], did not learn of it until September.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |url = http://tighar.org/Projects/Earhart/Archives/Documents/Bones_Chronology.html |title = The Earhart Project Research Document #12 The Bones Chronology |work = [[TIGHAR]] |accessdate = July 9, 2017 |deadurl = no |archiveurl = https://web.archive.org/web/20170716082016/https://tighar.org/Projects/Earhart/Archives/Documents/Bones_Chronology.html |archivedate = July 16, 2017 |df = mdy-all }}&lt;/ref&gt; Gallagher did a more thorough search of discovery area, including looking for artifacts such as rings. The search found more bones, a bottle, a shoe, and a sextant box. On September 23, 1940, Gallagher radioed his superiors that he had found a "skeleton ... possibly that of a woman", along with an old-fashioned [[sextant]] box, under a tree on the island's southeast corner. Gallagher stated the "Bones look more than four years old to me but there seems to be very slight chance that this may be remains of Amelia Earhardt." He was ordered to send the remains to [[Fiji]]. On 4 April 1941, Dr. D. W. Hoodless of the [[Fiji School of Medicine|Central Medical School]] examined the bones, took measurements, and wrote a report. Using [[Karl Pearson]]'s formulas for stature and the lengths of the [[femur]], [[tibia]], and [[humerus]], Hoodless concluded that the person was about {{convert|5|ft|5.5|in|cm}} tall.  Hoodless also wrote "it may be definitely stated that the skeleton is that of a MALE." [Emphasis in original.] Hoodless further stated, "Owing to the weather-beaten condition of all the bones it is impossible to be dogmatic in regard to the age of the person at the time of death, but I am of the opinion that he was not less than 45 years of age and that probably he was older: say between 45 and 55 years." Hoodless offered to make more detailed measurements if needed, but suggested any further examination be done by the Anthropological Department at [[University of Sydney|Sydney University]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |url = http://tighar.org/Projects/Earhart/Archives/Documents/Bones_Chronology3.html |title = The Earhart Project Research Document #12 The Bones Chronology, Cont. |work = [[TIGHAR]] |accessdate = July 9, 2017 |deadurl = no |archiveurl = https://web.archive.org/web/20170814094546/http://tighar.org/Projects/Earhart/Archives/Documents/Bones_Chronology3.html |archivedate = August 14, 2017 |df = mdy-all }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite report |first=D. W. |last=Hoodless |date=4 April 1941 |title=Report on Portion of a Human Skeleton |location=Suva, Fiji |url=https://tighar.org/Projects/Earhart/Archives/Documents/Bones_Chronology5.html}}&lt;/ref&gt; These bones were misplaced in Fiji long ago and cannot be reexamined.&lt;ref&gt;Gast, Phil. [http://www.cnn.com/2011/US/03/03/earhart.dna.research/?hpt=T1 "DNA tests on bone fragment inconclusive in Amelia Earhart search"] {{webarchive|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20121025162530/http://www.cnn.com/2011/US/03/03/earhart.dna.research/?hpt=T1 |date=October 25, 2012 }}. [[CNN]], March 4, 2011.&lt;/ref&gt;

In 1998, an analysis of the measurement data by forensic anthropologists found instead that the skeleton had belonged to a "tall white female of northern European ancestry".&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |last1 = Burns |first1 = Karen Ramey |last2 = Jantz |first2 = Richard L. |last3 = King |first3 = Thomas F. |last4 = Gillespie |first4 = Richard E. |title = Amelia Earhart’s Bones and Shoes? Current Anthropological Perspectives on an Historical Mystery |url = https://tighar.org/Publications/TTracks/14_2/14_2bones.pdf |publisher = TIGHAR |accessdate = July 6, 2017 |format = PDF |date = December 5, 1998 |deadurl = no |archiveurl = https://web.archive.org/web/20170517195826/https://tighar.org/Publications/TTracks/14_2/14_2bones.pdf |archivedate = May 17, 2017 |df = mdy-all }}&lt;/ref&gt; However, a 2015 review of both analyses concluded that "the most robust scientific analysis and conclusions are those of the original British finding indicating that the Nikumaroro bones belonged to a robust, middle-aged man, not Amelia Earhart."&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |last1 = Cross |first1 = Pamela J. |last2 = Wright |first2 = Richard |title = The Nikumaroro bones identification controversy: First-hand examination versus evaluation by proxy — Amelia Earhart found or still missing? |journal = Journal of Archaeological Science: Reports |date = September 2015 |volume = 3 |pages = 52–59 |doi = 10.1016/j.jasrep.2015.05.015 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

A 2018 study by American anthropologist [[Richard Jantz]] (one of the authors of the 1998 TIGHAR report) estimated the size of Earhart's skeleton based on photographs and reanalyzed the earlier data using modern forensic techniques. Based on measurements of 2,700 Americans who died in the mid-20th century, the study concluded that Earhart's bone measurements more closely matched the Nikumaroro bones than 99% of the reference sample.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |last1 = Jantz |first1 = Richard L. |authorlink = Richard Jantz |title = Amelia Earhart and the Nikumaroro Bones: A 1941 Analysis versus Modern Quantitative Techniques |journal = Forensic Anthropology |date = 2018 |volume = 1 |issue = 2 |pages = 1–16 |doi = 10.5744/fa.2018.0009 |url = http://journals.upress.ufl.edu/fa/article/view/525/519 |access-date = February 9, 2018 |deadurl = no |archiveurl = https://web.archive.org/web/20180308043330/http://journals.upress.ufl.edu/fa/article/view/525/519 |archivedate = March 8, 2018 |df = mdy-all }}&lt;/ref&gt; However, others criticized the study for being based on little factual evidence (in particular seven measurements from the skeleton done in 1941, combined with estimates about Earhart's size based on photos) and doubted the accuracy of those measurements.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web |url = https://www.theguardian.com/science/2018/mar/16/have-we-really-found-amelia-earhart-bones |title = Have we really found Amelia Earhart's bones? |last = Raff |first = Jennifer |date = March 16, 2018 |website = the Guardian |language = en |access-date = April 2, 2018 |deadurl = no |archiveurl = https://web.archive.org/web/20180402031912/https://www.theguardian.com/science/2018/mar/16/have-we-really-found-amelia-earhart-bones |archivedate = April 2, 2018 |df = mdy-all }}&lt;/ref&gt;

During [[World War II]], [[US Coast Guard]] [[LORAN]] Unit 92, a radio navigation station built in the summer and fall of 1944, and operational from mid-November 1944 until mid-May 1945, was located on Gardner Island's southeast end. Dozens of U.S. Coast Guard personnel were involved in its construction and operation, but were mostly forbidden from leaving the small base or having contact with the Gilbertese colonists then on the island, and found no artifacts known to relate to Earhart.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.loran-history.info/Gardner_Island/gardner.htm "Loran-History, Loran Unit 92, Gardner Island"]. {{webarchive|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20110903105046/http://www.loran-history.info/Gardner_Island/gardner.htm |date=September 3, 2011 }} loran-history.info. Retrieved: August 30, 2011.&lt;/ref&gt;

In 1988, The International Group for Historic Aircraft Recovery ([[TIGHAR]]) began an investigation&lt;ref&gt;[http://tighar.org/Projects/Earhart/Expeditions/Exped.html "Earhart Project Expeditions"] {{webarchive|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20100805030431/http://tighar.org/Projects/Earhart/Expeditions/Exped.html |date=August 5, 2010 }}. tighar.org, May 14, 2010. Retrieved: August 25, 2010.&lt;/ref&gt; of the Earhart/Noonan disappearance and since then has sent ten&lt;ref&gt;Nuwer, Rachel. [http://www.bbc.com/future/story/20130628-will-we-ever-find-amelia-earhart "Will We Ever Discover What Happened to Amelia Earhart?"] {{webarchive|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20130701173739/http://www.bbc.com/future/story/20130628-will-we-ever-find-amelia-earhart |date=July 1, 2013 }} BBC, June 28, 2013. Retrieved: June 29, 2013.&lt;/ref&gt; research expeditions to Gardner Island/Nikumaroro. They have suggested Earhart and Noonan may have flown without further radio transmissions&lt;ref&gt;Jacobson, Randall S., PhD [http://tighar.org/Projects/Earhart/Research/ResearchPapers/Worldflight/finalflight4.html "The Final Flight. 4: The Airplane Returns to Earth"] {{webarchive|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20100805002237/http://tighar.org/Projects/Earhart/Research/ResearchPapers/Worldflight/finalflight4.html |date=August 5, 2010 }}. tighar.org, 2009. Retrieved: July 10, 2010.&lt;/ref&gt; for two and a half hours along the line of position Earhart noted in her last transmission received at Howland, then found the then-uninhabited Gardner Island, landed the Electra on an extensive reef flat near the wreck of a large freighter (the {{SS|Norwich City}}) on the northwest side of the atoll, and ultimately perished. In 2012, a photograph taken in October 1937 of the reef at Nikumaroro after her disappearance was enhanced. According to the analysts who viewed it, "a blurry object sticking out of the water in the lower left corner of the black-and-white photo is consistent with a strut and wheel of a Lockheed Electra landing gear".&lt;ref&gt;Lee, Matthew. [http://www.huffingtonpost.com/2012/03/20/hillary-clinton-amelia-earhart_n_1366648.html "Hillary Clinton Wades Into Amelia Earhart Mystery"] {{webarchive|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20140828161650/http://www.huffingtonpost.com/2012/03/20/hillary-clinton-amelia-earhart_n_1366648.html |date=August 28, 2014 }}. The Huffington Post, March 20, 2012.&lt;/ref&gt;

TIGHAR's research has produced a range of archaeological and anecdotal evidence supporting this hypothesis.&lt;ref name="Common Myths"&gt;[http://www.tighar.org/Projects/Earhart/forum/FAQs/AEmyths.html "Common Earhart Myths"] {{webarchive|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20101225101248/http://tighar.org/Projects/Earhart/forum/FAQs/AEmyths.html |date=December 25, 2010 }}. tighar.org, 2009. Retrieved: November 28, 2009.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.tighar.org/Projects/Earhart/Overview/AEhypothesis.html "The TIGHAR Hypothesis"] {{webarchive|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20091209074351/http://tighar.org/Projects/Earhart/Overview/AEhypothesis.html |date=December 9, 2009 }}. tighar.org, Summer 2009. Retrieved: November 28, 2009.&lt;/ref&gt;  TIGHAR has sent a number of expeditions to Nikumaroro looking for evidence, although they have found nothing conclusive; expeditions include ones in 2007, 2010, 2012, and 2017.&lt;ref&gt;Pyle, Richard. [http://usatoday30.usatoday.com/news/nation/2007-07-12-2214476002_x.htm "New search begins in Earhart mystery"]. ''USA Today'', July 12, 2007. Retrieved: June 29, 2013.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Gast, Phil.[http://www.cnn.com/2011/US/03/03/earhart.dna.research/?hpt=T1 "DNA tests on bone fragment inconclusive in Amelia Earhart search"] {{webarchive|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20121025162530/http://www.cnn.com/2011/US/03/03/earhart.dna.research/?hpt=T1 |date=October 25, 2012 }} CNN, March 3, 2011, Retrieved: March 3, 2011.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://tighar.org/Projects/Earhart/Archives/Expeditions/NikuV/dailies3.html "TIGHAR 2007 Expedition Updates"] {{webarchive|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20130830120940/http://tighar.org/Projects/Earhart/Archives/Expeditions/NikuV/dailies3.html |date=August 30, 2013 }} tighar.org, August 2007. Retrieved: June 29, 2013.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Lorenzi, Rossella. [http://news.discovery.com/history/us-history/amelia-earhart-plane-located-120817.htm "Pieces of Amelia Earhart's plane located?"] {{webarchive|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20130317112739/http://news.discovery.com/history/us-history/amelia-earhart-plane-located-120817.htm |date=March 17, 2013 }} Discovery Communications, November 18, 2012. Retrieved: March 10, 2013.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Zap, Claudine. [https://news.yahoo.com/blogs/lookout/sonar-image-may-show-amelia-earhart-plane-153437423.html "Sonar image may show Amelia Earhart's plane"] {{webarchive|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20160305055409/http://news.yahoo.com/blogs/lookout/sonar-image-may-show-amelia-earhart-plane-153437423.html |date=March 5, 2016 }}. Yahoo! News. Retrieved: May 30, 2013.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Sample, Ian. [https://www.theguardian.com/world/2013/may/31/pacific-wreck-amelia-earharts-plane?INTCMP=SRCH "Pacific sonar 'streak' may be wreck of Amelia Earhart's plane"] {{webarchive|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20170308190747/https://www.theguardian.com/world/2013/may/31/pacific-wreck-amelia-earharts-plane?INTCMP=SRCH |date=March 8, 2017 }}. ''The Guardian'' Retrieved: May 31, 2013.&lt;/ref&gt;  Artifacts discovered by TIGHAR on Nikumaroro have included improvised tools; an aluminum panel, possibly from an Electra, made using 1930s manufacturing specifications; an oddly cut piece of clear Plexiglas the same thickness and curvature of an Electra window; and a size 9 Cat's Paw heel dating from the 1930s, which resembles Earhart's footwear in world flight photos.&lt;ref&gt;Pyle, Richard. [http://www.huffingtonpost.com/huff-wires/20070331/search-for-amelia/ "Diary a clue to Amelia Earhart mystery"] {{webarchive|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20131021210215/http://www.huffingtonpost.com/huff-wires/20070331/search-for-amelia/ |date=October 21, 2013 }}. Associated Press. The Huffington Post, March 31, 2007. Retrieved: June 29, 2013.&lt;/ref&gt;{{refn| According to records, Noonan was {{convert|6|ft|m|abbr=on}} tall and Earhart was {{convert|5|ft|8|in|m|abbr=on}} and wore a size 6 shoe according to her sister.|group=Note}} Recently rediscovered photos of Earhart's Electra just before departure in Miami show an aluminum panel over a window on the right side. &lt;!---Previous author stated numerous other photos also show this panel. If so, why is the media consistently reporting the panel as a recent discovery? What other photos?----&gt;Ric Gillespie, head of TIGHAR, claimed the found aluminum panel artifact has the same dimensions and rivet pattern as the one shown in the photo "to a high degree of certainty".&lt;ref&gt;[http://news.discovery.com/history/us-history/aluminum-fragment-appears-to-belong-to-earharts-plane-141028.htm "Amelia Earhart plane fragment identified"]. {{webarchive|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20141029224614/http://news.discovery.com/history/us-history/aluminum-fragment-appears-to-belong-to-earharts-plane-141028.htm |date=October 29, 2014 }} ''U.S. History'', October 28, 2014.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Lorenzi, Rossella. [http://news.discovery.com/history/us-history/aluminum-fragment-appears-to-belong-to-earharts-plane-141028.htm "Amelia Earhart plane fragment identified"]. {{webarchive|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20141029224614/http://news.discovery.com/history/us-history/aluminum-fragment-appears-to-belong-to-earharts-plane-141028.htm |date=October 29, 2014 }} ''Discovery Newsletter'', October 28, 2014.&lt;/ref&gt; Based on this new evidence, Gillespie returned to the atoll in June 2015, but operations using a [[remotely operated underwater vehicle]] to investigate a sonar detection of a possible wreckage were hampered by technical problems. Further, a review of sonar data concluded it was most likely a coral ridge.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |url = https://tighar.org/Publications/TTracks/2015Vol_31/October2015WEB.pdf |title = Niku VIII Final Report |work = [[TIGHAR]] Tracks |date = November 2015 |accessdate = July 9, 2017 |deadurl = no |archiveurl = https://web.archive.org/web/20171102220029/https://tighar.org/Publications/TTracks/2015Vol_31/October2015WEB.pdf |archivedate = November 2, 2017 |df = mdy-all }}&lt;/ref&gt; The evidence remains circumstantial, but Earhart's surviving stepson, George Putnam Jr., has expressed support for TIGHAR's research.&lt;ref&gt;Cruikshank, Joe. [http://nl.newsbank.com/cgi-bin/ngate/TCNP?ext_docid=1154F5669639D990&amp;ext_hed=The%20search%20for%20Amelia%20Earhart's%20plane%20continues&amp;ext_theme=tcnp&amp;pubcode=TCNP "The Search for Earhart's Plane Continues"]. ''Treasure County Palm News'', November 4, 2006. Retrieved: April 1, 2007.&lt;/ref&gt;

In July 2017, staff from the [[New England Air Museum]] notified TIGHAR that the unique rivet pattern of the aluminum panel precisely matched the top of the wing of a C-47B in the museum inventory;{{citation needed|date=April 2018}} particularly significant since a C-47B crashed on a nearby island during World War II and villagers acknowledged bringing aluminum from that wreck to Gardner Island.&lt;ref&gt;[https://tighar.org/Publications/TTracks/12_1/sydney.html "The Crash At Sydney Island"] tighar.org, March 1996. Retrieved: April 20, 2018.&lt;/ref&gt; As of April 2018, TIGHAR has not published this new information.

A few news articles have considered TIGHAR's theory, and generally consider it the most plausible of the "Earhart survived" theories, although not proven over crash-and-sink.&lt;ref&gt;''The Times'' September 12, 2016, page 3 – "Pioneer pilot may have died a castaway on Pacific island"&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.avionews.com/index.php?corpo=see_news_home.php&amp;news_id=1076879&amp;pagina_chiamante=corpo%3Dindex.php "The end of Amelia Earhart (2): several theories"] {{webarchive|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20071008060544/http://www.avionews.com/index.php?corpo=see_news_home.php&amp;news_id=1076879&amp;pagina_chiamante=corpo=index.php |date=October 8, 2007 }}. ''Avio News'' (WAPA), July 16, 2007. Retrieved: July 17, 2007.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url = https://www.yahoo.com/news/pacific-island-bones-likely-those-amelia-earhart-study-192040909.html |title = Pacific island bones likely those of Amelia Earhart: study |author =  |date =  |website = yahoo.com |accessdate = April 4, 2018 |deadurl = no |archiveurl = https://web.archive.org/web/20180311135233/https://www.yahoo.com/news/pacific-island-bones-likely-those-amelia-earhart-study-192040909.html |archivedate = March 11, 2018 |df = mdy-all }}&lt;/ref&gt; Other news articles have criticized TIGHAR as seizing on unlikely possibilities as circumstantial evidence; for example, an article criticized the suggestion that a can of freckle ointment found on Nikumaroro might have been Earhart's, when the Electra was "virtually a flying gas station" with little room for amenities, as Earhart and Noonan carried extra gas tanks in every scrap of available space.&lt;ref name="irvingdb"&gt;Irving, Clive (July 9, 2017).  [http://www.thedailybeast.com/amelia-earhart-captured-and-killed-new-evidence-debunks-history-channels-crazy-theory "Amelia Earhart Captured and Killed? New Evidence Debunks History Channel’s Crazy Theory"] {{webarchive|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20170709230904/http://www.thedailybeast.com/amelia-earhart-captured-and-killed-new-evidence-debunks-history-channels-crazy-theory |date=July 9, 2017 }}.  ''[[The Daily Beast]]''. Retrieved July 10, 2017.&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Japanese capture theory ===

Another theory is that Earhart and Noonan were captured by Japanese forces, perhaps after somehow navigating to somewhere within the Japanese [[South Pacific Mandate]].

In 1966, [[CBS]] [[Correspondent]] Fred Goerner published a book claiming that Earhart and Noonan were captured and executed when their aircraft crashed on the island of [[Saipan]], part of the [[Northern Mariana Islands]] archipelago.&lt;ref&gt;[https://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F06E1D9133BF935A2575AC0A962958260 "Obituary: Fred Goerner, Broadcaster, 69."] {{webarchive|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20081206170118/http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F06E1D9133BF935A2575AC0A962958260 |date=December 6, 2008 }} ''The New York Times'', September 16, 1994.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.time.com/time/magazine/article/0,9171,836416-2,00.html "Sinister Conspiracy?"] {{webarchive|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20071001002131/http://www.time.com/time/magazine/article/0,9171,836416-2,00.html |date=October 1, 2007 }} ''Time'', September 16, 1966. Retrieved: July 2, 2009.&lt;/ref&gt;{{refn|Goerner's book was immediately challenged, but the ''Time'' article on it does include a quote from Admiral [[Chester W. Nimitz]], who ''allegedly'' told Goerner in March 1965: "I want to tell you Earhart and her navigator did go down in the Marshalls and were picked up by the Japanese."|group=Note}}{{sfn|Goerner|1966|p=304}}{{refn|Goerner disclosed in his book that Nimitz refused permission to be quoted.|group=Note}}  Saipan is more than 2,700 miles away from Howland Island, however.  Later proponents of the Japanese capture hypothesis have generally suggested the [[Marshall Islands]] instead, which while still distant from the intended location (~800 miles), is slightly more possible.&lt;ref name="irvingdb" /&gt;

In 1990, the [[NBC-TV]] series ''[[Unsolved Mysteries]]'' broadcast an interview with a Saipanese woman who claimed to have witnessed Earhart and Noonan's execution by Japanese soldiers. No independent confirmation has ever emerged for any of these claims.&lt;ref&gt;[[#refStrippel1995|Strippel 1995]], p. 52.&lt;/ref&gt; Various purported photographs of Earhart during her captivity have been identified as either fraudulent or having been taken before her final flight.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url = http://tighar.org/Projects/Earhart/Archives/Forum/FAQs/captured.htm |title = Isn't it possible that Earhart could have been captured by the Japanese? |work = [[TIGHAR]] |accessdate = July 5, 2017 |deadurl = no |archiveurl = https://web.archive.org/web/20170709060205/http://tighar.org/Projects/Earhart/Archives/Forum/FAQs/captured.htm |archivedate = July 9, 2017 |df = mdy-all }}&lt;/ref&gt;

A slightly different version of the Japanese capture hypothesis is not that the Japanese captured Earhart, but rather that they shot down her plane.  Henri Keyzer-Andre, a former [[Pan American World Airways|Pan Am]] pilot, propounded this view in his 1993 book ''Age Of Heroes: Incredible Adventures of a Pan Am Pilot and his Greatest Triumph, Unravelling the Mystery of Amelia Earhart''.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web |url = http://www.publishersweekly.com/978-0-8038-9351-1 |title = Nonfiction Book Review: Age of Heroes Incredible Adve by Henri Keyzer-Andre, Author, Hy Steirman, Author Hastings House Book Publishers $22.5 (302p) |isbn = 978-0-8038-9351-1 |publisher = Publishers Weekly |access-date = March 28, 2016 |deadurl = no |archiveurl = https://web.archive.org/web/20160924170941/http://www.publishersweekly.com/978-0-8038-9351-1 |archivedate = September 24, 2016 |df = mdy-all }}&lt;/ref&gt;

Since the end of [[World War II]], a location on [[Tinian]], which is five miles (8&amp;nbsp;km) southwest of Saipan, had been rumored to be the grave of the two aviators. In 2004, an archaeological dig at the site failed to turn up any bones.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url = http://www.tighar.org/Projects/Earhart/Tinian/tigharstinian.htm |title = TIGHARs on Tinian |work = [[TIGHAR]] |date = November 15, 2004 |accessdate = July 5, 2017 |deadurl = no |archiveurl = https://web.archive.org/web/20101225133456/http://tighar.org/Projects/Earhart/Tinian/tigharstinian.htm |archivedate = December 25, 2010 |df = mdy-all }}&lt;/ref&gt;

A recent proponent of this theory is Mike Campbell, who published the 2012 book ''Amelia Earhart: The Truth at Last'' in its favor.&lt;ref name="wapocampbell"&gt;[https://www.washingtonpost.com/news/retropolis/wp/2017/07/11/a-bogus-photo-decades-of-obsession-and-the-endless-debate-over-amelia-earhart/ A 'bogus photo,' decades of obsession and the endless debate over Amelia Earhart] {{webarchive|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20171022085918/https://www.washingtonpost.com/news/retropolis/wp/2017/07/11/a-bogus-photo-decades-of-obsession-and-the-endless-debate-over-amelia-earhart/ |date=October 22, 2017 }}.  ''The Washington Post''.  July 11, 2017.&lt;/ref&gt;  Campbell cites claims from Marshall Islanders to have witnessed a crash, as well as a U.S. Army Sergeant who found a suspicious gravesite near a former Japanese prison on [[Saipan]].&lt;ref&gt;Day, Linwood, McGuire. [https://www.newspapers.com/newspage/51729231/ "San Matean Says Japanese Executed Amelia Earhart."] {{webarchive|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20170924183133/https://www.newspapers.com/newspage/51729231/ |date=September 24, 2017 }} ''San Mateo Times'', Volume 60, Issue 127, May 27, 1960. Retrieved: September 24, 2017.&lt;/ref&gt;{{sfn|Campbell|2016|pp=221–228}}

A number of Earhart's relatives have been convinced that the Japanese were somehow involved in Amelia's disappearance, citing unnamed witnesses including Japanese troops and Saipan natives.{{sfn|Goldstein|Dillon|1997|pp=244, 266}}&lt;ref name="NevadaAppeal"&gt;Henley, David C. [http://www.nevadaappeal.com/article/20091031/NEWS/910319978/1001/ "Cousin: Japanese captured Amelia Earhart"]. ''Nevada Appeal'', October 31, 2009. Retrieved: November 7, 2009. {{webarchive |url=https://web.archive.org/web/20131005021033/http://www.nevadaappeal.com/article/20091031/NEWS/910319978/1001/ |date=October 5, 2013 }}&lt;/ref&gt; According to one cousin, the Japanese cut the Lockheed Electra into scrap and threw the pieces into the ocean, to explain why the airplane was not found in the Marshall Islands.&lt;ref name="NevadaAppeal" /&gt;

In 2017, a [[History Channel]] documentary, ''[[Amelia Earhart: The Lost Evidence]]'', proposed that a photograph in the National Archives of [[Jaluit Atoll]] in the [[Marshall Islands]] was actually a picture of a captured Earhart and Noonan.  The picture showed a Caucasian male on a dock who appeared to look like Noonan and a woman sitting on the dock but facing away from the camera, who was judged to have a physique and haircut resembling Earhart's.  The documentary theorizes that the photo was taken after Earhart and Noonan crashed at [[Mili Atoll]].  The documentary also said that physical evidence recovered from Mili matches pieces that could have fallen off an Electra during a crash or subsequent overland move to a barge.  ''The Lost Evidence''  proposed that a Japanese ship seen in the photograph was the ''Koshu Maru'', a Japanese military ship.  ''The Lost Evidence'' was quickly discredited, however, after Japanese blogger Kota Yamano found the original source of the photograph in the Archives in the [[National Diet Library]] Digital Collection.  The original source of the photo was a Japanese travel guide published in October 1935, implying that the photograph was taken in 1935 or before, and thus would be unrelated to Earhart and Noonan's 1937 disappearance.  Additionally, the researcher who discovered the photo also identified the ship in the right of the photo as another ship called ''Koshu'' seized by [[Allies of World War I|Allied]] Japanese forces in World War I and not the ''Koshu Maru''.&lt;ref name="nprdebunk"&gt;{{cite news |last1 = Domonoske |first1 = Camila |title = Japanese Blogger Points Out Timeline Flaw In Supposed Earhart Photo |url = https://www.npr.org/sections/thetwo-way/2017/07/11/536620463/japanese-blogger-points-out-timeline-flaw-in-supposed-earhart-photo |accessdate = July 11, 2017 |work = NPR |language = en |deadurl = no |archiveurl = https://web.archive.org/web/20170711162559/http://www.npr.org/sections/thetwo-way/2017/07/11/536620463/japanese-blogger-points-out-timeline-flaw-in-supposed-earhart-photo |archivedate = July 11, 2017 |df = mdy-all }}&lt;/ref&gt;

A common criticism of all versions of the Japanese capture hypothesis is that the Japanese-controlled Marshall Islands were considerably distant from Howland Island.  To reach and land there would have required Earhart and Noonan, though low on fuel, to change her northeast course as she neared Howland Island and fly hundreds of miles northwest, a feat "not supported by the basic rules of geography and navigation."&lt;ref name="smithsonian"&gt;{{cite magazine |last = Katz |first = Brigit |date = July 5, 2017 |title = Smithsonian Curator Weighs In on Photo That Allegedly Shows Amelia Earhart in Japanese Captivity |url = http://www.smithsonianmag.com/smart-news/smithsonian-curator-photo-allegedly-shows-amelia-earhart-japanese-captivity-180963964/ |magazine = Smithsonian |access-date = September 3, 2017 }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="irvingdb" /&gt;  Additionally, had the Japanese found a crashed Earhart and Noonan, they would have had substantial motivation to rescue the famous aviators and be hailed as heroes.&lt;ref name="irvingdb" /&gt;

=== Myths, legends, and claims ===

The unresolved circumstances of Earhart's disappearance, along with her fame, attracted a great body of other claims relating to her last flight. Several unsupported theories have become known in popular culture.

==== Spies for FDR ====

The World War II-era movie ''[[Flight for Freedom]]'' (1943) is a story of a fictional female aviator (obviously inspired by Earhart) who engages in a spying mission in the Pacific.  The movie helped further a myth that Earhart was spying on the Japanese in the Pacific at the request of the [[Franklin D. Roosevelt]] administration.{{refn| Some authors have speculated that Earhart and Noonan were shot down by Japanese aircraft because she was thought to be spying on Japanese territory so America could supposedly plan an attack.|group=Note}} By 1949, both the [[United Press]] and U.S. Army Intelligence had concluded that this rumor was groundless. [[Jacqueline Cochran|Jackie Cochran]], another pioneering aviator and one of Earhart's friends, made a postwar search of numerous files in Japan and was convinced that the Japanese were not involved in Earhart's disappearance.{{sfn|Cochran|1954|p=160}}

==== Tokyo Rose ====

A rumor that claimed that Earhart had made propaganda radio broadcasts as one of the many women compelled to serve as [[Tokyo Rose]] was investigated closely by George Putnam. According to several biographies of Earhart, Putnam investigated this rumor personally but after listening to many recordings of numerous Tokyo Roses, he did not recognize her voice among them.{{sfn|Goldstein|Dillon|1997|p=282}}

==== New Britain ====

The theory that Earhart may have turned back mid-flight has been posited. She would then have tried to reach the airfield at [[Rabaul]], [[New Britain]] (northeast of mainland [[Papua New Guinea]]), approximately {{convert|2200|mi|km}} from Howland.&lt;ref&gt;"The Enduring Mystery of Amelia Earhart's Disappearance Maybe Finally Coming To an End". ''The Atlantic Flyer'', September 2007, p. 3.&lt;/ref&gt;

In 1990, Donald Angwin, a veteran of the [[Australian Army]]'s World War II [[New Britain campaign|campaign in New Britain]], contacted researchers to suggest that a wrecked aircraft he had witnessed in jungle about {{convert|40|mi|km}} southwest of Rabaul, on April 17, 1945, may have been Earhart's Electra.&lt;ref name="Billings"&gt;Billings, David. [http://www.wingsoverkansas.com/earhart/article.asp?id=850 "Aircraft Search Project in Papua New Guinea."] {{webarchive|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20121104062733/http://www.wingsoverkansas.com/earhart/article.asp?id=850 |date=November 4, 2012 }} ''Wings Over Kansas'', 2000. Retrieved: March 27, 2012.&lt;/ref&gt; Angwin, who was a corporal in the [[11th Battalion (Australia)|11th Battalion]] at the time,&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.ww2roll.gov.au/Veteran.aspx?serviceId=A&amp;veteranId=762092 "Angwin, Donald Arthur."] {{webarchive|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20160304003206/http://www.ww2roll.gov.au/Veteran.aspx?serviceId=A&amp;veteranId=762092 |date=March 4, 2016 }} ''Commonwealth of Australia: Military Forces'', 2002. Retrieved: March 27, 2012.&lt;/ref&gt; reported that he and other members of a forward patrol on Japanese-occupied New Britain had found a wrecked twin-engined, unpainted all-metal aircraft. The soldiers recorded a rough position on a map, along with serial numbers seen on the wreckage. While the map was located in the possession of another veteran in 1993, subsequent searches of the area indicated failed to find a wreck.&lt;ref name="Billings" /&gt;

While Angwin died in 2001, David Billings, an Australian aircraft engineer, has continued to investigate his theory. Billings claims that the serial numbers written on the map, &lt;small&gt;"600H/P S3HI C/N1055"&lt;/small&gt;, represent:
* a {{convert|600|hp|kW|abbr=on}} [[Pratt &amp; Whitney R-1340]]-S3H1 model engine; and
* "Constructor's Number 1055", an airframe identifier.
These would be consistent with a Lockheed Electra 10E, such as that flown by Earhart, although they do not contain enough information to identify the wreck in question as NR16020.&lt;ref name="Billings" /&gt;

Pacific Wrecks, a website that documents World War II-era aircraft crash sites, notes that no Electra has been reported lost in or around Papua New Guinea. Gillespie wrote that the {{convert|2000|mi|km|adj=on}} distance from Earhart's last known position to New Britain was impossible for the aircraft to fly, requiring more than 13 hours of flight when there were only four hours of fuel remaining.&lt;ref name="Pacific Wrecks"&gt;[http://pacificwrecks.com/aircraft/electra/earhart/ "Amelia Earhart Myths from the Pacific War."] {{webarchive|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20120403190537/http://pacificwrecks.com/aircraft/electra/earhart/ |date=April 3, 2012 }} ''Pacific Wrecks'', 2011. Retrieved: March 27, 2012.&lt;/ref&gt;

==== Assuming another identity ====

In November 2006, the [[National Geographic Channel]] aired episode two of the ''Undiscovered History'' series about a claim that Earhart survived the world flight, moved to [[New Jersey]], changed her name, remarried and became [[Irene Craigmile Bolam]]. This claim had originally been raised in the book ''Amelia Earhart Lives'' (1970) by author Joe Klaas, based on the research of Major Joseph Gervais.&lt;ref&gt;Gillespie, Ric. [http://tighar.org/Projects/Earhart/Books/BookReviews/earhartsurvive.html "Is This Amelia Earhart?"] {{webarchive|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20100907000705/http://tighar.org/Projects/Earhart/Books/BookReviews/earhartsurvive.html |date=September 7, 2010 }} ''tighar.org'', 2009. Retrieved: July 10, 2010.&lt;/ref&gt; Irene Bolam, who had been a banker in New York during the 1940s, denied being Earhart, filed a lawsuit requesting $1.5&amp;nbsp;million in damages and submitted a lengthy [[affidavit]] in which she rebutted the claims. The book's publisher, [[McGraw-Hill]], withdrew the book from the market shortly after it was released and court records indicate that the company reached an out-of-court settlement with her.&lt;ref&gt;Gillespie, Ric. [http://tighar.org/Projects/Earhart/Books/BookReviews/earhartsurvive.html "Amelia Earhart Survived by Colonel Rollin Reineck, USAF (ret.), 2003."] {{webarchive|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20100907000705/http://tighar.org/Projects/Earhart/Books/BookReviews/earhartsurvive.html |date=September 7, 2010 }} ''tighar.org''. Retrieved: July 10, 2010.&lt;/ref&gt; Subsequently, Bolam's personal life history was thoroughly documented by researchers, eliminating any possibility that she was Earhart. Kevin Richlin, a professional criminal forensic expert hired by ''[[National Geographic (magazine)|National Geographic]]'', studied photographs of both women and cited many measurable facial differences between Earhart and Bolam.{{sfn|Strippel|1995|pp=52–53}}

== Legacy ==

{{external media| float = right| video1 = [https://www.c-span.org/video/?308058-1/amelia-earhart-exhibit Tour of the "One Life: Amelia Earhart" exhibit at the Smithsonian's National Portrait Gallery, September 5, 2012], [[C-SPAN]]| video2 = [https://www.c-span.org/video/?322919-1/tour-amelia-earhart-collection-purdue-university Tour of the George Palmer Putnam Collection of Amelia Earhart Papers at Purdue University, November 18, 2014], [[C-SPAN]]| video3 = [https://www.c-span.org/video/?307184-1/75th-anniversary-disappearance-amelia-earhart Presentation by Dr. White Wallenborn on the 75th anniversary of the disappearance of Amelia Earhart, July 21, 2012], [[C-SPAN]]}}
Earhart was a widely known international celebrity during her lifetime. Her shyly charismatic appeal, independence, persistence, coolness under pressure, courage and goal-oriented career along with the circumstances of her disappearance at a comparatively early age have driven her lasting [[celebrity|fame]] in [[popular culture]]. Hundreds of articles and scores of books have been written about her life, which is often cited as a motivational tale, especially for girls. Earhart is generally regarded as a [[Feminism|feminist]] icon.{{sfn|Hamill|1976|p=49}}

Earhart's accomplishments in aviation inspired a generation of female aviators, including the more than 1,000 women pilots of the [[Women Airforce Service Pilots]] (WASP) who ferried military aircraft, towed gliders, flew target practice aircraft, and served as transport pilots during World War II.{{sfn|Regis|2008|pp=102–105}}{{sfn|Haynsworth|Toomey|1998}}

The home where Earhart was born is now the [[Amelia Earhart Birthplace Museum]] and is maintained by The Ninety-Nines, an international group of female pilots of whom Earhart was the first elected president.&lt;ref name="Amelia Earhart Birthplace Museum—Atchison, KS"&gt;[http://theyellowbrickroadtrip.blogspot.com/2009/04/amelia-earhart-birthplace-museum.html "The Yellow Brick Road Trip."] {{webarchive|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20111007022626/http://theyellowbrickroadtrip.blogspot.com/2009/04/amelia-earhart-birthplace-museum.html |date=October 7, 2011 }} ''theyellowbrickroadtrip.blogspot.com''. Retrieved: July 2, 2009.&lt;/ref&gt;

A small section of Earhart's Lockheed Electra starboard engine [[nacelle]] recovered in the aftermath of the Hawaii crash has been confirmed as authentic and is now regarded as a control piece that will help to authenticate possible future discoveries. The evaluation of the scrap of metal was featured on an episode of ''[[History Detectives]]'' on Season 7 in 2009.&lt;ref&gt;[https://www.pbs.org/opb/historydetectives/investigations/706_ameliaearhart.html "Amelia Earhart's plane."] {{webarchive|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20091207055342/http://www.pbs.org/opb/historydetectives/investigations/706_ameliaearhart.html |date=December 7, 2009 }} ''[[History Detectives]]'', 2009. Retrieved: July 24, 2010.&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Memorial flights ===

Two notable memorial flights by female aviators subsequently followed Earhart's original [[circumnavigation]]al route.
* In 1967, [[Ann Pellegreno|Ann Dearing Holtgren Pellegreno]] and a crew of three flew a similar aircraft (a Lockheed 10A Electra) to complete a world flight that closely mirrored Earhart's flight plan. On the 30th anniversary of her disappearance, Pellegreno dropped a wreath in Earhart's honor over tiny Howland Island and returned to Oakland, completing the {{convert|28000|mi|km|adj=on}} commemorative flight on July 7, 1967.&lt;ref&gt;Van Pelt, Lori. ''Amelia Earhart: The Sky's No Limit'' (American Heroes). New York: Macmillan, 2005. {{ISBN|0-7653-1061-9}}, pp. 219–220.&lt;/ref&gt;
* In 1997, on the 60th anniversary of Earhart's world flight, San Antonio businesswoman [[Linda Finch]] retraced the final flight path flying the same make and model of aircraft as Earhart, a restored 1935 Lockheed Electra 10E. Finch touched down in 18 countries before finishing the trip two and a half months later when she arrived back at Oakland Airport on May 28, 1997.&lt;ref&gt;[https://www.pbs.org/newshour/bb/transportation/may97/earhart_5-28a.html "Wings of Dreams - May 28, 1997" (transcript).]  ''PBS''. Retrieved: June 19, 2008.&lt;/ref&gt;

In 2001, another commemorative flight retraced the route undertaken by Earhart in her August 1928 transcontinental record flight. Dr. Carlene Mendieta flew an original Avro Avian, the same type that was used in 1928.&lt;ref name="Mendieta" /&gt;

In 2013, [[Amelia Rose Earhart]], a pilot and a reporter from [[Denver]], [[Colorado]], announced that she would be recreating the 1937 flight in the middle of 2014 in a single engine [[Pilatus PC-12]]NG. She completed the flight without incident on July 11, 2014.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.flywithamelia.org/ "2014 Round-the-world Flight."] {{webarchive|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20140202101145/http://www.flywithamelia.org/ |date=February 2, 2014 }} ''Amelia Flight'', June 2014.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Lee, Henry K. [http://blog.sfgate.com/stew/2014/07/11/amelia-rose-earhart-completes-round-the-world-flight/#25033101=0 "Amelia Rose Earhart completes round-the-world flight."] {{webarchive|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20140713135937/http://blog.sfgate.com/stew/2014/07/11/amelia-rose-earhart-completes-round-the-world-flight/ |date=July 13, 2014 }} ''San Francisco Chronicle'' blogs, July 11, 2014.&lt;/ref&gt;

In June and July 2017, Brian Lloyd flew his [[Mooney M20]]K 231 around the world to commemorate Earhart's attempted circumnavigation 80 years earlier. Lloyd followed a route similar to the one taken by Earhart.&lt;ref&gt;[http://projectameliaearhart.org/ "Project Amelia Earhart."] {{webarchive|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20170918154212/http://projectameliaearhart.org/ |date=September 18, 2017 }} ''projectameliaearhart.org''. Retrieved: September 24, 2017.&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Other honors ===
{{refimprove|section|date=June 2018}}&lt;!--many entries in the list are not cited--&gt;
Countless other tributes and memorials have been made in Amelia Earhart's name, including a 2012 tribute by [[United States Secretary of State|U.S. Secretary of State]] [[Hillary Clinton]], speaking at a State Department event celebrating the ties of Earhart and the United States to its Pacific neighbors, noting: "Earhart ... created a legacy that resonates today for anyone, girls and boys, who dreams of the stars."&lt;ref&gt;[http://iipdigital.usembassy.gov/st/english/article/2012/03/201203202478.html "Earhart broke social and aviation barriers, Clinton say.."] {{webarchive|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20131014132529/http://iipdigital.usembassy.gov/st/english/article/2012/03/201203202478.html |date=October 14, 2013 }} ''[[U.S. Department of State]]'', March 20, 2012.&lt;/ref&gt; In 2013, [[Flying Magazine|''Flying'' magazine]] ranked Earhart No. 9 on its list of the "51 Heroes of Aviation".&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.flyingmag.com/photo-gallery/photos/51-heroes-aviation?pnid=41846 "51 Heroes of Aviation: Amelia Earhrt."] {{webarchive|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20150615031723/http://www.flyingmag.com/photo-gallery/photos/51-heroes-aviation?pnid=41846 |date=June 15, 2015 }} ''Flying'', September 2013.&lt;/ref&gt; The following list is not considered definitive, but serves also to give significant examples of tributes and honors.
&lt;!---Countless other tributes and memorials have been made in Amelia Earhart's name. Please consider using the talk page before adding to this list, which is already comprehensive. ----&gt;
* Amelia Earhart Centre And Wildlife Sanctuary was established at the site of her 1932 landing in Northern Ireland, Ballyarnet Country Park, Derry.
* The "Earhart Tree" on [[Banyan Drive]] in Hilo, Hawaii, was planted by Earhart in 1935.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news |url=https://www.sfgate.com/hawaii/alohafriday/article/Amelia-Earhart-Hawaii-celebrates-the-great-2463264.php |title=Amelia Earhart: Hawaii celebrates the great aviator |last=Cooper |first=Jeanne |date=2010-07-23 |work=[[San Francisco Chronicle]] |access-date=2018-06-30 |df=mdy-all}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* The [[Zonta International]] Amelia Earhart Fellowship Awards were established in 1938.
[[File:Earhart Light.jpg|thumb|right|"Earhart Light" on [[Howland Island]] in August 2008]]
* Earhart Light (also known as the Amelia Earhart Light), a navigational day beacon on Howland Island (has not been maintained and is crumbling).&lt;ref&gt;[https://news.google.com/newspapers?nid=1310&amp;dat=19630817&amp;id=wpYzAAAAIBAJ&amp;sjid=DOMDAAAAIBAJ&amp;pg=6634,3172509 "Earhart beacon shines from lonely island."] ''Eugene Register-Guard,'' August 17, 1963. Retrieved: March 20, 2012.&lt;/ref&gt;
* The Amelia Earhart Memorial Scholarships (established in 1939 by The Ninety-Nines), provides scholarships to women for advanced pilot certificates and ratings, jet type ratings, college degrees and technical training.
* The Purdue University Amelia Earhart Scholarship, first awarded in 1940, is based on academic merit and leadership and is open to juniors and seniors enrolled in any school at the West Lafayette campus. After being discontinued in the 1970s, a donor resurrected the award in 1999.
* In 1942, a United States [[Liberty ship]] named {{SS|Amelia Earhart}} was launched. It was wrecked in 1948.
* Amelia Earhart Field (1947), formerly Masters Field and [[Miami]] Municipal Airport, after closure in 1959, [[Amelia Earhart Park]] was dedicated in an area of undeveloped federal government land located north and west of the former Miami Municipal Airport and immediately south of [[Opa-locka Airport]].
* Amelia Earhart Airport (1958),&lt;ref&gt;[https://books.google.com/books?id=JMvnAAAAMAAJ&amp;q=%22Amelia+Earhart+Airport%22&amp;dq=%22Amelia+Earhart+Airport%22&amp;lr=&amp;as_drrb_is=b&amp;as_minm_is=1&amp;as_miny_is=1955&amp;as_maxm_is=12&amp;as_maxy_is=1958&amp;as_brr=0&amp;ei=fCIlTIrrHKLUNKrz2eYH&amp;cd=1 "Kansas City Airport."] ''Kansas Government Journal'', Volume 44, 1958, p. 20. Retrieved: June 25, 2010.&lt;/ref&gt; located in [[Atchison, Kansas]].
* Amelia Earhart Commemorative Stamp (8¢ airmail postage) was issued in 1963 by the United States Postmaster-General.
* The [[Civil Air Patrol]] Amelia Earhart Award (since 1964) is awarded to cadets who have completed the first 11 achievements of the cadet program along with receipt of the General Billy Mitchell Award.
* Amelia Earhart Residence Hall opened in 1964 as a [[residence hall]] for women at Purdue University and became coed in 2002. An eight-foot sculpture of Earhart, by Ernest Shelton, was placed in front of the Earhart Hall Dining Court in 2009.&lt;ref&gt;[http://news.uns.purdue.edu/x/2009a/090415BlackwelderEarhart.html "Purdue unveils Amelia Earhart sculpture."] {{webarchive|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20100717194947/http://news.uns.purdue.edu/x/2009a/090415BlackwelderEarhart.html |date=July 17, 2010 }} ''Purdue University News Service'', April 16, 2009. Retrieved: June 25, 2010.&lt;/ref&gt;
* Member of [[National Aviation Hall of Fame]] (1968).
* Member of [[National Women's Hall of Fame]] (1973).
* Crittenton Women's Union (Boston) Amelia Earhart Award recognizes a woman who continues Earhart's pioneering spirit and who has significantly contributed to the expansion of opportunities for women. (since 1982)
* Earhart Corona, a [[Corona (planetary geology)|corona]] on [[Venus]] was named by the [[International Astronomical Union|IAU]] in 1982 (initially as Earhart crater).&lt;ref&gt;{{GPN|1704|Earhart Corona}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* The Amelia Earhart Birthplace,&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.ameliaearhartmuseum.org/ "The Amelia Earhart Birthplace Museum."] {{webarchive|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20061205052158/http://ameliaearhartmuseum.org/ |date=December 5, 2006 }} ''ameliaearhartmuseum.org''. Retrieved: June 25, 2010.&lt;/ref&gt; Atchison, Kansas (a museum and historic site, owned and maintained by The Ninety-Nines since 1984).
* UCI Irvine Amelia Earhart Award (since 1990).
* Member of [[Motorsports Hall of Fame of America]] (1992).
* [[3895 Earhart]], a minor planet discovered in 1987, was named in 1995 after her, by its discoverer, [[Carolyn S. Shoemaker]].
* Earhart Foundation, located in [[Ann Arbor, Michigan]]. Established in 1995, the foundation funds research and scholarship through a network of 50 "Earhart professors" across the United States.
* Amelia Earhart Festival (annual event since 1996), located in Atchison, Kansas.
* Amelia Earhart Pioneering Achievement Award, Atchison, Kansas: Since 1996, the Cloud L. Cray Foundation provides a $10,000 women's scholarship to the educational institution of the honoree's choice.
* Amelia Earhart Earthwork in Warnock Lake Park, Atchison, Kansas. Stan Herd created the {{convert|1|acre|m2|adj=on}} landscape mural in 1997 from permanent plantings and stone to celebrate the 100th anniversary of Earhart's birth. Located at {{Coord|39.537621|N|95.145158|W|region:US_type:landmark}} and best viewed from the air.
* [[Amelia Earhart Bridge]] (1997), located in Atchison, Kansas.
* Greater Miami Aviation Association Amelia Earhart Award for outstanding achievement (2006); first recipient: noted flyer [[Patty Wagstaff|Patricia "Patty" Wagstaff]].
* On December 6, 2006, California Governor [[Arnold Schwarzenegger]] and First Lady [[Maria Shriver]] inducted Earhart into the [[California Hall of Fame]] located at [[The California Museum for History, Women and the Arts]].
* [[USNS Amelia Earhart (T-AKE-6)|USNS ''Amelia Earhart'' (T-AKE-6)]] was named in her honor in May 2007.
* Amelia Earhart full size bronze statue was placed at the [[Spirit of Flight Center]] located in [[Lafayette, Colorado]] in 2008.
&lt;!-- undated: --&gt;
[[File:Amelia Earhart Plaque at Portal of the Folded Wings.jpg|thumb|Earhart Tribute at [[Portal of the Folded Wings Shrine to Aviation|Portal of the Folded Wings]]; note error in birth date]]
* The Amelia Earhart General Aviation Terminal, a satellite terminal at Boston's [[Logan Airport]] (formerly used by [[American Eagle Airlines|American Eagle]], now unused)
* [[Amelia Earhart Dam]] on the [[Mystic River]] in eastern [[Massachusetts]].
* Schools named after Earhart are found throughout the United States including the Amelia Earhart Elementary School, in [[Alameda, California|Alameda]], California, Amelia Earhart Elementary School, in [[Hialeah, Florida|Hialeah]], Florida, Amelia Earhart Middle School, [[Riverside, California]] and Amelia Earhart International Baccalaureate World School, in [[Indio, California]].
* Amelia Earhart Hotel, located in [[Wiesbaden, Germany]], originally used as a hotel for women, then as temporary military housing is now operated as the [[U.S. Army Corps of Engineers, Europe District]] Headquarters with offices for the [[Army Contracting Agency]] and the [[Defense Contract Management Agency]].
* Amelia Earhart Road, located in [[Oklahoma City, Oklahoma|Oklahoma City (headquarters of The Ninety-Nines), Oklahoma]].
* Earhart Road, located next to the [[Oakland International Airport]] North Field in [[Oakland, California]].
* Amelia Earhart Playhouse, at [[Wiesbaden Army Airfield]].&lt;ref&gt;[https://web.archive.org/web/20100203194347/http://www.wiesbaden.army.mil/sites/mwr/amelia_earhart.asp "Amelia Earhart Playhouse."] ''wiesbaden.army.mil'', February 3, 2010 (archived). Retrieved: January 21, 2010.&lt;/ref&gt;
* To commemorate her first transatlantic flight, on the Millennium Coastal Path at Pwll, Burry Port, South Wales is a [[blue plaque]] sponsored by [[Llanelli]] Community Heritage.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.llanellich.org.uk/Blue-Plaques/85-amelia-earhart.html "Amelia Earhart plaque."] {{webarchive|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20150402151748/http://www.llanellich.org.uk/Blue-Plaques/85-amelia-earhart.html |date=April 2, 2015 }} ''Llanelli Community Heritage''. Retrieved: March 10, 2013.&lt;/ref&gt;
* In 2015, {{Interlanguage link multi|Earhart (crater)|uk|3=Кратер Амелії Ергарт|lt=a newly discovered lunar crater}} was provisionally named after Amelia Earhart.&lt;ref&gt;O'Neill, Ian. [http://news.discovery.com/space/hidden-moon-crater-named-after-amelia-earhart-150317.htm "Hidden Moon crater named after Amelia Earhart."] {{webarchive|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20150530103507/http://news.discovery.com/space/hidden-moon-crater-named-after-amelia-earhart-150317.htm |date=May 30, 2015 }} ''DNews'', March 17, 2015. Retrieved: May 29, 2015.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Rincon. Paul. [https://www.bbc.com/news/science-environment-31917302 "New lunar crater named after aviation pioneer Earhart."] {{webarchive|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20150414223747/http://www.bbc.com/news/science-environment-31917302 |date=April 14, 2015 }} ''BBC News'', March 17, 2015. Retrieved: May 29, 2015.&lt;/ref&gt;

== In popular culture ==

Earhart's life has spurred the imaginations of many writers and others; the following examples are given although many other mentions have also occurred in contemporary or current media:&lt;!---Countless other tributes and memorials have been made in Amelia Earhart's name. Please consider using the talk page before adding to this list, which is already comprehensive; submissions should be considered significant examples and will require verifiable reference sources.----&gt;
* "[[Amelia Earhart's Last Flight]]", by "Yodelling Cowboy" [[David McEnery (musician)|Red River Dave McEnery]], is thought to be the first song ever performed on commercial television (at the 1939 World's Fair). He recorded it in 1941 and it was subsequently covered by artists including [[Kinky Friedman]] and the Country Gentlemen.
* The 1943 [[Rosalind Russell]] film ''[[Flight for Freedom]]'' derived from a treatment, "Stand by to Die", was a fictionalized treatment of Earhart's life.{{sfn|Strippel|1995|p=20}}
* Possibly the first tribute album dedicated to the legend of Earhart was by [[Plainsong (band)|Plainsong]], ''[[In Search of Amelia Earhart]]'' (Elektra K42120), released in 1972. Both the album and the Press Pak released by Elektra are highly prized by collectors and they have also gained a cult status.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.andyrobertsmusic.com/plains.html "In Search of Amelia Earhart/Now We Are Three."] {{webarchive|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20061014132758/http://www.andyrobertsmusic.com/plains.html |date=October 14, 2006 }} ''andyrobertsmusic.com''. Retrieved: July 2, 2010.&lt;/ref&gt;
* Singer [[Joni Mitchell]]'s song "Amelia" appears on her 1976 album ''[[Hejira (album)|Hejira]]'' and it also features in the video of her 1980 live album ''[[Shadows and Light (Joni Mitchell album)|Shadows and Light]]'' (1980) with clips of Earhart. Commenting on the origins of the song, which interweaves the story of a desert journey with aspects of Earhart's disappearance, Mitchell said: "I was thinking of Amelia Earhart and addressing it from one solo pilot to another ... sort of reflecting on the cost of being a woman and having something you must do."&lt;ref&gt;[https://web.archive.org/web/20041001000211/http://www.southcoasttoday.com/daily/12-96/12-07-96/b01ae065.htm "News Archive: Your link to SouthCoast Massachusetts and beyond."] ''[[The Standard-Times (New Bedford)|The Times Standard]]'', October 1, 2004 (archived). Retrieved: February 21, 2012.&lt;/ref&gt;
* "In Search of: Amelia Earhart", (1976) was episode 16 of the 1976–1982 ''[[In Search of... (TV series)|In Search Of]]'' series; this episode spurred a number of popular documentaries that followed.
* A 1976 television biographical drama titled ''[[Amelia Earhart (1976 film)|Amelia Earhart]]'' starring [[Susan Clark]] and [[John Forsythe]] included flying by Hollywood stunt pilot [[Frank Tallman]] whose late partner in Tallmantz Aviation, Paul Mantz, had tutored Earhart in the 1930s.
&lt;!----* In the 1978 novel ''Wings'' by [[Robert J. Serling]], Earhart appears as both an acquaintance and a romantic interest of the novel's protagonist, Barney Burton.&lt;ref&gt;Serling, Robert J. [https://books.google.com/books/about/Wings.html?id=MU2qAAAACAAJ&amp;redir_esc=y ''Wings'']. 1978.&lt;/ref&gt;----Not notable---&gt;
* The television documentary [[American Experience|"Amelia Earhart: The Price of Courage"]] (1993) from ''American Experience''.&lt;ref&gt;[https://www.pbs.org/wgbh/americanexperience/earhart/ "Amelia Earhart: The Price of Courage (1993)."] {{webarchive|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20100222072821/http://www.pbs.org/wgbh/americanexperience/earhart/ |date=February 22, 2010 }} ''American Experience''. Retrieved: February 23, 2010.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{IMDb episode|id=1027235|episode=American Experience: Amelia Earhart: The Price of Courage (1993)|accessdate=February 23, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* ''[[Amelia Earhart: The Final Flight]]'' (1994) starring [[Diane Keaton]], [[Rutger Hauer]] and [[Bruce Dern]] was initially released as a TV movie and it was subsequently released as a theatrical feature.&lt;ref&gt;McCallion, Bernadette. [https://movies.nytimes.com/movie/149352/Amelia-Earhart-The-Final-Flight/overview "Amelia Earhart: The Final Flight (1994)."] {{webarchive|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20130520205259/http://movies.nytimes.com/movie/149352/Amelia-Earhart-The-Final-Flight/overview |date=May 20, 2013 }} ''The New York Times''. Retrieved: December 26, 2011.&lt;/ref&gt;
* In the ''[[Star Trek: Voyager]]'' episode "[[The 37's]]" (first aired 1995), Earhart, portrayed by [[Sharon Lawrence]], was one of many humans abducted by an alien race in 1937, only to be found in cryo-stasis on a planet on the other side of the galaxy.
* Actress [[Amy Adams]] portrayed Earhart in ''[[Night at the Museum 2: Battle of the Smithsonian]]'' (2009).
* In ''[[Amelia (film)|Amelia]]'' (2009), Earhart is portrayed by [[Hilary Swank]], who also served as co-executive producer of the [[biopic]].&lt;ref&gt;Fleming, Michael. [http://www.variety.com/article/VR1117980470.html?categoryid=13&amp;cs=1&amp;query=Amelia+Earhart "Hilary Swank to play Amelia Earhart: Mira Nair to direct biopic from Ron Bass script."] {{webarchive|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20090825183240/http://www.variety.com/article/VR1117980470.html?categoryid=13&amp;cs=1&amp;query=Amelia+Earhart |date=August 25, 2009 }} ''Variety'', February 7, 2008. Retrieved: December 8, 2008.&lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;!-- * In 2011, the [[Great Canadian Theatre Company]] hosted a musical play titled ''Amelia: The Girl Who Wants To Fly''.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url = http://www.gctc.ca/plays/season11-12/amelia |title = ''Amelia: The Girl Who Wants to Fly'' |accessdate = October 6, 2011 |deadurl = bot: unknown |archiveurl = https://web.archive.org/web/20111230055337/http://www.gctc.ca/plays/season11-12/amelia |archivedate = December 30, 2011 |df = mdy }}. Great Canadian Theatre Company. Retrieved: October 6, 2011.&lt;/ref&gt;--Lots of plays exist, nothing makes this one noteworthy. --&gt;
* [[Google]] honored Earhart by putting up a doodle on its site for on July 24, 2012.&lt;ref&gt;[https://www.google.com/doodles/amelia-earharts-115th-birthday "Amelia Earhart's 115th birthday."] {{webarchive|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20171009044716/https://www.google.com/doodles/amelia-earharts-115th-birthday |date=October 9, 2017 }} ''Google'', 2012.  Retrieved: September 24, 2017.&lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;!-- * In 2017, the [[Barter Theatre]] presented a three-person play based on the life of Earhart.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |url = https://www.bartertheatre.com/shows/amelia-earhart/201612281052427621 |title = Amelia Earhart |work = bartertheatre.com |last = Miller |first = Kathryn Shultz |accessdate = July 9, 2017 }}Retrieved: September 24, 2017.&lt;/ref&gt;--Lots of plays exist, nothing makes this one noteworthy. --&gt;
* "The Odd Vanishing Of Amelia Earhart", released on August 25, 2017, was episode 5 of season 2 of [[BuzzFeed]] web series, ''[[BuzzFeed Unsolved]]: True Crime'' in which Earhart and the various conspiracy theories surrounding her disappearance were discussed.
* Earhart was one of several inspiring women represented by a new line of [[Barbie]] dolls introduced March 6, 2018.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.cnn.com/2018/03/06/us/barbie-dolls-inspiring-women-trnd/index.html|title=Barbie unveils dolls based on Amelia Earhart, Frida Kahlo, Katherine Johnson and Chloe Kim|last1=Leguizamon|first1=Mercedes|last2=Ahmed|first2=Saeed|work=[[CNN]]|date=March 7, 2018|accessdate=April 4, 2018}}&lt;/ref&gt;

== Records and achievements ==

[[File:Amelia-dressed-to-fly (cropped).jpg|thumb|Earhart's pilot license #6017 photo{{refn|Amelia Earhart's original pilot license is permanently housed at the Museum of Women Pilots in Oklahoma City.&lt;ref&gt;[https://web.archive.org/web/20140223115528/http://museumofwomenpilots.com/MusuemNews.html "Museum News &amp; Events"] ''Museum of Woman Pilots'', Oklahoma City (archived). Retrieved: September 24, 2017.&lt;/ref&gt; |group=Note}}&lt;ref name="6017@npg.si.edu" /&gt;]]
* Woman's world altitude record: 14,000&amp;nbsp;ft (1922)
* First woman to fly the [[Atlantic Ocean]] (1928)
* Speed records for 100&amp;nbsp;km (and with {{convert|500|lb|abbr=on}} cargo) (1931)
* First woman to fly an [[autogyro]] (1931)
* Altitude record for autogyros: 18,415&amp;nbsp;ft (1931)
* First person to cross the United States in an autogyro (1932)
* First woman to fly the Atlantic solo (1932)
* First person to fly the Atlantic twice (1932)
* First woman to receive the [[Distinguished Flying Cross (United States)|Distinguished Flying Cross]] (1932)
* First woman to fly nonstop, coast-to-coast across the U.S. (1933)
* Women's speed transcontinental record (1933)
* First person to fly solo between [[Honolulu]], [[Hawaii]] and [[Oakland, California]] (1935){{refn|
Note from author: "I have had them for many years, but do not remember where they came from. There is no identification on the backs. They appear to be typical snapshots and not the work of a professional. They have faded giving them a sepia appearance."&lt;ref&gt;Roddy, Bill. [https://wayback.archive-it.org/all/20130910005941/http://www.americahurrah.com/Earhart/AmeliaOahu.htm "Six snapshots taken at Wheeler Field, Oahu, January, 1935."] ''America Hurrah''. Retrieved: September 23, 2017.&lt;/ref&gt;|group=Note}}
* First person to fly solo from [[Los Angeles, California]] to [[Mexico City]], [[Mexico]] (1935)
* First person to fly solo nonstop from Mexico City, Mexico to [[Newark, New Jersey]] (1935)
* Speed record for east-to-west flight from Oakland, California to Honolulu, Hawaii (1937){{sfn|Sloate|1990|pp=116–117}}
* First person to fly solo from the [[Red Sea]] to [[Karachi]] (1937)

== Books by Earhart ==

Earhart was a successful and heavily promoted writer who served as aviation editor for ''[[Cosmopolitan (magazine)|Cosmopolitan]]'' magazine from 1928 to 1930. She wrote magazine articles, newspaper columns, essays and published two books based upon her experiences as a flyer during her lifetime:
* ''[[20 Hrs., 40 Min.]]'' (1928) was a journal of her experiences as the first woman passenger on a transatlantic flight.
* ''[[The Fun of It]]'' (1932) was a memoir of her flying experiences and an essay on women in aviation.
* ''[[Last Flight (book)|Last Flight]]'' (1937) featured the periodic journal entries she sent back to the United States during her world flight attempt, published in newspapers in the weeks prior to her final departure from [[New Guinea]]. Compiled by her husband GP Putnam after she disappeared over the Pacific, many historians consider this book to be only partially Earhart's original work.

== See also ==

{{Portal|Aviation|Biography|Feminism}}

{{Colbegin|colwidth=20em}}
* [[Amelia Earhart Park]]
* [[Antoine de Saint-Exupéry]]
* [[Aviation archaeology]]
* [[Cornelia Fort]]
* [[Douglas Corrigan]]
* [[Elsie Mackay]]
* [[Frances Wilson Grayson]]
* [[Harriet Quimby]]
* [[Jerrie Mock]]
* [[List of female explorers and travelers]]
* [[Coast Guard Air Station Miami]]
* [[List of missing people]]
* [[Nancy Harkness Love]]
* [[Eugene Luther Vidal]]
* [[99s Museum of Women Pilots]]
{{Colend}}

== References ==

=== Notes ===

{{Reflist|group=Note|30em}}

=== Citations ===
{{Reflist|30em}}

=== Bibliography of cited sources ===

{{Refbegin|30em}}
* {{cite book |ref = harv |last = Backus |first = Jean L. |title = Letters from Amelia, 1901–1937 |year = 1982 |publisher = Beacon Press |isbn = 978-0-8070-6702-4 }}
* {{cite book |ref = harv |last = Blau |first = Melinda |title = Whatever Happened to Amelia Earhart? |year = 1977 |publisher = Contemporary Perspectives |isbn = 978-0-8172-1057-1 }}
* {{cite book |ref = harv |last1 = Bryan |first1 = C. D. B. |title = The National Air and Space Museum |date = 1979 |publisher = Abrams |location = New York |isbn = 978-0-8109-0666-2 |edition = 1st }}
* {{cite book |ref = harv |last = Butler |first = Susan |title = East to the Dawn: The Life of Amelia Earhart |date = October 16, 1997 |publisher = Da Capo Press |isbn = 978-0-201-31144-0 }}
* {{cite book |ref = harv |last1 = Campbell |first1 = Mike |title = With our own eyes: eyewitnesses to the final days of Amelia Earhart |date = 2002 |publisher = Lucky Press |location = Lancaster, Ohio |isbn = 978-0-9706377-6-5 }}
* {{cite book |ref = harv |last1 = Campbell |first1 = Mike |title = Amelia Earhart: The Truth at Last |date = 2016 |publisher = Sunbury Press, Inc. |isbn = 978-1-62006-668-3 |edition = 2nd }}
* {{cite web |ref = harv |last = Chater |first = Eric H. |title = Letter to M. E. Griffin |date = July 25, 1937 |location = Lae, New Guinea |url = https://tighar.org/Projects/Earhart/Archives/Documents/Chater_Report.html }}
* {{cite book |ref = harv |last = Cochran |first = Jacqueline |title = Stars at Noon |location = Boston |publisher = Little, Brown and Company |year = 1954 }}
* {{cite letter |ref = harv |last = Collopy |first = James A. |date = August 28, 1937 |subject = Amelia Earhart |recipient = Civil Aviation Board |location = Lae, New Guinea |url = https://tighar.org/Projects/Earhart/Archives/Documents/Collopy_Letter.html |access-date = December 2, 2017 }}
* {{cite book |ref = harv |last1 = Corn |first1 = Joseph J. |title = The winged gospel : America's romance with aviation, 1900–1950. |date = 1983 |publisher = Oxford Univ. Pr. |location = New York |isbn = 0-19-503356-6 }}
* {{cite book |ref = harv |last = Earhart |first = Amelia |title = The Fun of It |url = https://books.google.com/books?id=OVeXAwAAQBAJ |date = 1932 |publisher = Chicago Review Press |isbn = 978-0-89733-658-1 }}
* {{cite book |ref = harv |last = Earhart |first = Amelia |title = Last Flight |edition = 1st |year = 1937 |publisher = Harcourt, Brace and Company }}
* {{cite book |ref = harv |last = Fleming |first = Candace |title = Amelia Lost: The Life and Disappearance of Amelia Earhart |year = 2011 |publisher = Schwartz &amp; Wade Books |isbn = 978-0-375-84198-9 }}
* {{cite book |ref = harv |last = Garst |first = Shannon |title = Amelia Earhart: Heroine of the Skies |year = 1947 |publisher = Julian Messner, Inc. |location = New York }}
* {{cite book |ref = harv |last = Gillespie |first = Ric |title = Finding Amelia: The True Story of the Earhart Disappearance |year = 2006 |publisher = Naval Institute Press |isbn = 978-1-59114-319-2 }}
* {{cite book |ref = harv |last = Glines |first = C.V. |title = 'Lady Lindy': The Remarkable Life of Amelia Earhart |journal = Aviation History |date = July 1997 |url = http://www.historynet.com/lady-lindy-the-remarkable-life-of-amelia-earhart-july-97-aviation-history-feature.htm }}
* {{cite book |ref = harv |last = Goerner |first = Fred G. |title = The Search for Amelia Earhart |year = 1966 |publisher = Doubleday }}
* {{cite book |ref = harv |last1 = Goldstein |first1 = Donald M. |last2 = Dillon |first2 = Katherine V. |title = Amelia: The Centennial Biography of an Aviation Pioneer |year = 1997 |publisher = Brassey's |isbn = 978-1-57488-134-9 }}
* {{cite book |ref = harv |last = Grooch |first = William Stephen |title = Skyway to Asia |location = New York |publisher = Longmans, Green and Co. |year = 1936 }}
* {{cite journal |ref = harv |last1 = Hamill |first1 = Pete |title = Leather and Pearls: The Cult of Amelia Earhart |journal = Ms. |date = September 1976 }}
* {{cite book |ref = harv |last1 = Haynsworth |first1 = Leslie |last2 = Toomey |first2 = David |title = Amelia Earhart's daughters: the wild and glorious story of American women aviators from World War II to the dawn of the space age |year = 1998 |publisher = Perennial |location = New York |isbn = 0-380-72984-9 |edition = 1st Perennial }}
* {{cite book |ref = harv |last = Jessen |first = Gene Nora |title = The Powder Puff Derby of 1929: The First All Women's Transcontinental Air Race |year = 2002 |publisher = Sourcebooks |isbn = 978-1-57071-769-7 }}
* {{cite book |ref = harv |last = Kerby |first = Mona |title = Amelia Earhart: Courage in the Sky |year = 1990 |publisher = Viking |isbn = 978 0670830244 }}
* {{cite book |ref = harv |last1 = King |first1 = Thomas F. |last2 = Jacobson |first2 = Randall S. |last3 = Burns |first3 = Karen R. |last4 = Spading |first4 = Kenton |title = Amelia Earhart's shoes: is the mystery solved? |date = 2001 |publisher = AltaMira Press |location = Walnut Creek, California |isbn = 0-7591-0130-2 }}
* {{cite book |ref = harv |last = Lauber |first = Patricia |title = Lost Star: The Story of Amelia Earhart |date = December 1, 1989 |publisher = Scholastic |isbn = 978-0-590-41159-2 }}
* {{cite book |ref = harv |last1 = Leder |first1 = Jane |title = Amelia Earhart: opposing viewpoints |date = 1989 |publisher = Greenhaven Press |location = San Diego, Calif. |isbn = 978-0-89908-070-3 }}
* {{cite book |ref = harv |last1 = Long |first1 = Marie K. |last2 = Long |first2 = Elgen M. |title = Amelia Earhart: The Mystery Solved |year = 1999 |publisher = Simon and Schuster |isbn = 978-0-7432-0217-6 }}
* {{cite book |ref = harv |last = Lovell |first = Mary S. |title = The Sound of Wings: The Life of Amelia Earhart |year = 1989 |publisher = St. Martin's Press |isbn = 978-1-4668-6648-5 }}
* Lubben, Kristen and Erin Barnett. ''Amelia Earhart: Image and Icon''. New York: International Center of Photography, 2007. {{ISBN|978-3-86521-407-2}}.
* {{cite journal |ref = harv |last1 = Marshall |first1 = Patti |title = Neta Snook |journal = Aviation History |date = January 2007 |volume = 17 |issue = 3 |pages = 21–22 |url = http://www.historynet.com/anita-neta-snook.htm }}
* {{cite book |ref = harv |last1 = Morey |first1 = Eileen |title = Amelia Earhart |date = 1995 |publisher = Lucent Books |location = San Diego, CA |isbn = 1-56006-065-4 }}
* &lt;cite id=refMorrissey1992&gt;Morrissey, Muriel Earhart. ''Amelia Earhart''. Santa Barbara, California: Bellerophon Books, 1992. {{ISBN|0-88388-044-X}}.&lt;/cite&gt;
* {{cite book |ref = harv |last = Morrissey |first = Muriel Earhart |title = Courage is the Price: The Biography of Amelia Earhart |year = 1963 |publisher = McCormick-Armstrong, Pub. Division }}
* {{cite book |ref = harv |last = Oakes |first = Claudia M. |title = United States women in aviation, 1930–1939 |year = 1985 |publisher = Smithsonian Institution Press |isbn = 978-0-87474-709-6 }}
* {{cite book |ref = harv |last1 = Parsons |first1 = Bill |title = The challenge of the Atlantic: a photo-illustrated history of early aviation in Harbour Grace, Nfld. |date = 1983 |publisher = Robinson-Blackmore |location = St. John's, Newfoundland, Canada |isbn = 0-920884-06-7 }}
* {{cite book |ref = harv |last = Pearce |first = Carol A. |title = Amelia Earhart |year = 1988 |publisher = Facts on File |isbn = 978-0-8160-1520-7 }}
* Pellegrino, Anne Holtgren. ''World Flight: The Amelia Trail''. Ames, Iowa: The Iowa State University Press, 1971. {{ISBN|0-8138-1760-9}}.
* {{cite book |ref = harv |last1 = Post |first1 = Wiley |last2 = Gatty |first2 = Harold |title = Around the world in eight days: the flight of the Winnie Mae |year = 1931 |publisher = Rand, McNally &amp; Company }}
* ''The Radio Amateur's Handbook''. West Hartford, Connecticut: American Radio Relay League, 1945. No ISBN.
* {{cite book |ref = harv |last1 = Randolph |first1 = Blythe |title = Amelia Earhart |date = 1987 |publisher = F. Watts |location = New York |isbn = 0-531-10331-5 }}
* {{cite book |ref = harv |last = Regis |first = Margaret |title = When Our Mothers Went to War: An Illustrated History of Women in World War II |year = 2008 |publisher = NavPublishing |isbn = 978-1-879932-05-0 }}
* {{cite book |ref = harv |last = Rich |first = Doris L. |title = Amelia Earhart: A Biography |year = 1989 |publisher = Smithsonian Institution Press |location = Washington, DC |isbn = 1-56098-725-1 }}
* {{cite book |ref = harv |last1 = Safford |first1 = Laurance F. |title = Earhart's flight into yesterday : the facts without the fiction |date = 2003 |publisher = Paladwr Press |location = McLean, Va. |isbn = 978-1-888962-20-8 }}
* &lt;cite id=refSaffordetal2003&gt;Safford, Laurance F. with Cameron A. Warren and Robert R. Payne. ''Earhart's Flight into Yesterday: The Facts Without the Fiction'', McLean, Virginia: Paladwr Press, 2003. {{ISBN|1-888962-20-8}}.&lt;/cite&gt;
* {{cite book |ref = harv |last1 = Sloate |first1 = Susan |title = Amelia Earhart : challenging the skies |date = 1990 |publisher = Fawcett Columbine |location = New York |isbn = 978-0-449-90396-4 |edition = 1st }}
* {{cite journal |ref = harv |date = November 1995 |volume = 31 |issue = 11 |journal = Air Classics |title = Researching Amelia: A detailed summary for the serious researcher into the disappearance of Amelia Earhart |last = Strippel |first = Richard G. }}
* {{cite book |ref = harv |last = Thames |first = Richard |title = Amelia Earhart |location = New York |publisher = Franklin Watts |year = 1989 |isbn = 0-531-10851-1 }}
* {{cite book |ref = harv |last1 = Van Pelt |first1 = Lori |title = Amelia Earhart: the sky's no limit |date = 2005 |publisher = Forge |location = New York |isbn = 978-0-7653-1061-3 |edition = 1. }}
* {{cite journal |ref = harv |last1 = Van Pelt |first1 = Lori |title = Amelia's Autogiro Adventures |journal = Aviation History |date = March 2008 }}
{{Refend}}

== Further reading ==

{{Refbegin|30em}}
* Barker, Ralph. ''Great Mysteries of the Air''. London: Pan Books, 1966. {{ISBN|0-330-02096-X}}.
* Briand, Paul. ''Daughter of the Sky''. New York: Duell, Sloan, Pearce, 1960. No ISBN.
* Brink, Randall. ''Lost Star: The Search for Amelia Earhart''. New York: W.W. Norton &amp; Company, 1994. {{ISBN|978-0393026832}}.
* Burke, John. ''Winged Legend: The Story of Amelia Earhart''. New York: Ballantine Books, 1971. {{ISBN|0-425-03304-X}}.
* Cady, Barbara. ''They Changed the World: 200 Icons Who Have Made a Difference''. New York: Black Dog &amp; Leventhal Publishers, 2003. {{ISBN|1-57912-328-7}}.
* Chapman, Sally Putnam, with Stephanie Mansfield. ''Whistled Like a Bird: The Untold Story of Dorothy Putnam, George Putnam and Amelia Earhart''. New York: Warner Books, 1997. {{ISBN|0-446-52055-1}}.
* Cochran, Jacqueline and Maryann Bucknum Brinkley. ''Jackie Cochran: The Autobiography of the Greatest Woman Pilot in Aviation History''. Toronto: Bantam Books, 1987. {{ISBN|0-553-05211-X}}.
* Devine, Thomas E. ''Eyewitness: The Amelia Earhart Incident''. Frederick, Colorado: Renaissance House, 1987. {{ISBN|0-939650-48-7}}.
* Goodridge, Walt F. ''Amelia Earhart on Saipan Tour Booklet''. Saipan, Marshall Islands: @Walt F. J. Goodridge, 2017. {{ISBN| 978-1-5489-9290-3}}.
* Hoverstein, Paul. "An American Obsession". ''Air &amp; Space Smithsonian''. Vol. 22, No. 2, June/July 2007.
* Landsberg. Alan. ''In Search of Missing Persons''. New York: Bantam Books, 1978. {{ISBN|0-553-11459-X}}.
* Loomis, Vincent V. ''Amelia Earhart, the Final Story''. New York: Random House, 1985. {{ISBN|978-0-394-53191-5}}.
* Moolman, Valerie. ''Women Aloft'' (The Epic of Flight series). Alexandria, Virginia: Time-Life Books, 1981. {{ISBN|0-8094-3287-0}}.
* O'Leary, Michael. "The Earhart Discovery: Fact or Fiction?" '' Air Classics'', Vol 28, No. 8, August 1992.
* Reuther, Ronald T. and William T. Larkins. ''Images of America: Oakland Aviation''. Mount Pleasant, South Carolina: Arcadia Publishing, 2008. {{ISBN|978-0-7385-5600-0}}.
* Turner, Mary. ''The Women's Century: A Celebration of Changing Roles 1900–2000''. Kew, Richmond, Surrey, UK: The National Archives, 2003. {{ISBN|1-903365-51-1}}.
* Ware, Susan. ''Still Missing: Amelia Earhart and the Search for Modern Feminism''. New York: W. W. Norton &amp; Company, 1993. {{ISBN|0-393-03551-4}}.
* Wright, Monte Duane. ''Most Probable Position, A History of Aerial Navigation to 1941''. Lawrence, Kansas: University Press of Kansas, 1972. {{ISBN|0-7006-0092-2}}.
{{Refend}}

== External links ==

{{Commons category|Amelia Earhart}}
{{Wikiquote|Amelia Earhart}}
* [http://www.ameliaearhart.com/ The Official Website of Amelia Earhart (The Family of Amelia Earhart)]
* [http://www.ameliaearhartmuseum.org/ Amelia Earhart Birthplace Museum]
* {{cite web |url = http://www.npg.si.edu/exhibit/earhart/index.html |title = One Life: Amelia Earhart |publisher = [[Smithsonian Institution]]&lt;!-- |date = June 29, 2012 |last1 = [[National Portrait Gallery]] |first1 =  |author-link1 =  |year =  |website =  |series =  |location =  |archive-url =  |archive-date =  |dead-url =  |access-date =  |quote = Films from the University of South Carolina Moving Image Research Collections. Photographs from the George Palmer Putnam Collection. --&gt; }}
* [https://www.ninety-nines.org/amelia-earhart.htm Amelia Earhart – A Timeline] – [[Ninety-Nines]]
* Michals, Debra.  [https://www.womenshistory.org/education-resources/biographies/amelia-earhart “Amelia Earhart”] National Women’s History Museum. 2015.
* Papers :
:* [https://www.archives.gov/news/topics/earhart Records Relating to Amelia Earhart] – [[National Archives]]
:* [http://www.lib.purdue.edu/spcol/aearhart/ George Palmer Putnam Collection of Amelia Earhart Papers] at [[Purdue University]] Libraries
::* [http://earchives.lib.purdue.edu/cdm/ref/collection/earhart/id/3669 Third Class Radiotelephone license]
:* [http://memory.loc.gov/cgi-bin/query/r?ammem/wright:@field(DOCID+@lit(wright002423)) General Correspondence: Earhart, Amelia, 1932–1934], The Wilbur and Orville Wright Papers at the [[Library of Congress]]
:* [http://nrs.harvard.edu/urn-3:RAD.SCHL:sch00107 Papers, 1835–1977.] [http://radcliffe.harvard.edu/schlesinger-library Schlesinger Library], Radcliffe Institute, Harvard University.
* Audio &amp; Visual
:* {{YouTube|wnNrED6yWSw|Amelia Earhart Before Last Flight at Burbank Airport}}  [http://news.nationalgeographic.com/2015/06/150610-amelia-earhart-last-photo-shoot-aviation-discovery0 1937 Film]
:* [http://memory.loc.gov/cgi-bin/query/r?ammem/afccalbib:@field(DOCID+@lit(afccal000004)) Amelia Earhart Speech] – American English Dialect Recordings, [[Library of Congress]]
:* {{YouTube|hkbMpmV9Te8|Amelia Earhart: On The Future Of Women In Flying (listen online)}}
:* {{YouTube|lJg_-IwsmBE|Amelia Earhart interview following the 1932 transatlantic flight}}
:* [https://www.pbs.org/wgbh/americanexperience/films/earhart/player/ Amelia Earhart] — An ''[[American Experience]]'' documentary
* Search
:* [https://wayback.archive-it.org/all/20120916025945/http://www.uscg.mil/history/webcutters/Itasca_1930.pdf CG cutter Itasca and the search for Earhart]
:*: "At 8:00 a.m. the plane reported reception of the cutter's signals, but was unable to obtain a minimum for a bearing."
:*: "The flying conditions within a radius of 40 miles of Howland Island were excellent with an east wind of 8 to 13 miles per hour, the sea smooth and ceiling unlimited as far as could be observed."
:* [http://coastguard.dodlive.mil/files/2012/07/Earhart_001.jpg Page of ''Itasca log'' on day of flight]
:* [https://web.archive.org/web/20071214211600/http://www.nauticalcurrents.com/amelia_earhart_mem_flt.html Amelia Earhart Memorial flight Recreation]
* Time at Howland Island
:: [https://www.timeanddate.com/time/zone/usa/howland-island Timezone for all of 1937 is UTC-10:30 (HST)]
:: [https://www.timeanddate.com/sun/usa/howland-island?month=7&amp;year=1937 Sunrise is 7:15 AM] &lt;!-- too late for sun line? --&gt;
::: [http://aa.usno.navy.mil/data/docs/celnavtable.php USNO navigation link]
:::: [http://aa.usno.navy.mil/cgi-bin/aa_flamenav.pl?ID=AA&amp;calc=7&amp;qq1=1937&amp;qq2=7&amp;qq3=2&amp;qq4=17&amp;qq5=45&amp;qq6=0&amp;qqo=all&amp;yy0=1&amp;yy1=0&amp;yy2=48.4&amp;xx0=-1&amp;xx1=176&amp;xx2=37&amp;ZZZ=END navigation at Howland at UTC 1745]
:: ''Itasca'' apparently used UTC-11:30. See [https://tighar.org/smf/index.php?topic=433.0 TIGHAR topic 433.0].
* [http://timeandnavigation.si.edu/multimedia-asset/amelia-earhart-holding-bendix-radio-direction-finder-loop-antenna Picture of Earhart with RDF loop]
* {{PM20|FID=pe/004419}}

{{National Women's Hall of Fame}}
{{Aviation accidents and incidents in 1937}}
{{Authority control}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Earhart, Amelia}}
[[Category:Amelia Earhart| ]]
[[Category:20th-century American women writers]]
[[Category:20th-century American writers]]
[[Category:1897 births]]
[[Category:1930s deaths]]
[[Category:1930s missing person cases]]
[[Category:American aviation record holders]]
[[Category:American female aviators]]
[[Category:American feminists]]
[[Category:American people of German descent]]
[[Category:Aviation pioneers]]
[[Category:Aviators from Kansas]]
[[Category:Chevaliers of the Légion d'honneur]]
[[Category:Cornell family]]
[[Category:Dudley–Winthrop family]]
[[Category:Harmon Trophy winners]]
[[Category:Missing aviators]]
[[Category:Missing people]]
[[Category:Motorsports Hall of Fame of America inductees]]
[[Category:Otis family]]
[[Category:People declared dead in absentia]]
[[Category:People from Atchison, Kansas]]
[[Category:People from Toluca Lake, Los Angeles]]
[[Category:Purdue University faculty]]
[[Category:Recipients of the Distinguished Flying Cross (United States)]]
[[Category:Women aviation record holders]]
[[Category:Writers from Kansas]]
[[Category:Victims of aviation accidents or incidents in 1937]]</text>
      <sha1>tkhemyam384qq2mktvxsxsyc8jykszw</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
