<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10.xsd" version="0.10" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <dbname>enwiki</dbname>
    <base>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.32.0-wmf.16</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="118" case="first-letter">Draft</namespace>
      <namespace key="119" case="first-letter">Draft talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2300" case="first-letter">Gadget</namespace>
      <namespace key="2301" case="first-letter">Gadget talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2302" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition</namespace>
      <namespace key="2303" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Bill Lear</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>906817</id>
    <revision>
      <id>854058795</id>
      <parentid>854050960</parentid>
      <timestamp>2018-08-08T17:39:43Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Ser Amantio di Nicolao</username>
        <id>753665</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor/>
      <comment>Removing from [[Category:American businesspeople]] using [[c:Help:Cat-a-lot|Cat-a-lot]]</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="18567">{{Infobox person
|name          = Bill Lear
|image         = Bill Lear.jpg
|birth_date    = {{birth date|1902|6|26}}
|birth_place   = [[Hannibal, Missouri]]
|death_date    = {{death date and age|1978|5|14|1902|6|26}}
|death_place   = [[Reno, Nevada]]
|death_cause   = [[Leukemia]]
|nationality   = [[United States|American]]
|known_for     = car radio, [[Lear Jet]]
|awards        = [[Collier Trophy]] (1949)&lt;br&gt;[[Horatio Alger Award]] (1954)&lt;br&gt;[[Elliott Cresson Medal]] (1972)
|education     =
|employer      = Learjet
|occupation    = Engineer, Inventor
|spouse        = Ethel Peterson Lear&lt;br&gt;Madeline Murphy Lear&lt;br&gt;Margret Radell&lt;br&gt;[[Moya Lear|Moya Olsen Lear]]
|partner       =
|children      = Mary Louise, William Jr., Patti, John, Shanda, David, and Tina
|parents       =
|relatives     =
|website       =
}}
'''William Powell Lear''' (June 26, 1902 – May 14, 1978) was an [[United States|American]] [[inventor]] and [[businessman]]. He is best known for founding the [[Lear Jet]] Corporation, a manufacturer of [[business jet]]s. He also invented the [[battery eliminator]] for the [[B battery]], and developed the [[8-track cartridge]], an [[audio tape]] system.&lt;ref name="patent pending"&gt;Stim and Pressman 2007, p. 20.&lt;/ref&gt; Throughout his career of 46 years, Lear received over 120 patents.&lt;ref name="ReferenceA"&gt;{{cite journal|last1=Brittain|first1=J.E.|title=William P. Lear and his contributions to radio and aviation.|journal=Proceedings of the IEEE|date=December 2003|volume=91|issue=12|pages=2068–2069|doi=10.1109/jproc.2003.819609}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Career==
===Radio engineer===
Lear was [[autodidact|self-taught]]: "He had read widely on [[wireless]], including the works of [[Nikola Tesla]], the scientist/inventor. He had even built a radio set, based on a twenty-five-cent Galena crystal which he sent away for, and he had learned the [[Morse code]], the fun ending with the ban on radio during World War I."&lt;ref name=Boesen/&gt;{{rp|15}}

One of his first ventures was with Lawrence Sorensen, selling loose radio couplers. Lear had been an "instructor in wireless" in the U.S. Navy so he confidently identified himself as a radio engineer to Clifford Reid in [[Quincy, Illinois]]. Reid was selling auto supplies and hired Lear to expand into radio. With contractor Julius Bergen, he founded Quincy Radio Labs and built speaker boxes for radios. Lear also helped develop WLAL which evolved into the powerful station KVOO.

Lear’s talents as engineer showed in 1924 when he moved to Chicago and built a B-[[battery eliminator]] for the Universal Battery Company with R. D. Morey. Then he met Waldorf Astoria Smith of the Carter Radio Company who helped him with radio theory including [[Ohm's law]].  Tom Fletcher of the QRS Company was so impressed by Lear’s radio set designed around a QRS [[rectifier]] tube that he hired him, offering 60% more pay than Universal Battery. Bill Grunow of the Grigsby-Grunow-Hinds Company topped that offer when Lear fixed the problem with 60,000 B-battery eliminators that they had manufactured. Lear also came up with an invention in 1924 when [[power inverter]]s installed at Stevens Hotel failed to perform for the Radio Manufacturers’ Association.

Lear built audio amplifiers and cases for the [[Magnavox]] speakers then coming out.  The Magnavox "majestic dynamic speakers" that he produced with Grunow were very popular. With Ernie Tyrman he built and sold radio sets, using methods patented by others, which they had not licensed. Anxious over prosecution for [[patent infringement]], they both developed [[peptic ulcer|ulcers]]. Tyrman died after surgery; consequently, Lear changed his diet. {{citation needed|date=November 2015}}

Lear Radio Laboratories was the source of an early step to [[miniaturization]] in electronics. Tuning coils in the [[radio frequency]] stage of a set were rather large and Lear knew how to reduce their size by using [[Litz wire]]. Wire braided from many fine strands has a large surface area giving it high conductivity at radio frequency. Lear borrowed $5,000 from his friend Algot Olson to make machines to wrap the strands, braid the wire, and wind the coils. The industry was set up in the basement of his mother’s old house on 65th street, and done with assistance of Don Mitchell, a railroad electrician. Lear called the company Radio Coil and Wire Corporation. They took an order of 50,000 coils from [[Eugene F. McDonald]] of [[Zenith Electronics]] when they demonstrated them. These small coils were one-quarter the size of coils with solid wire.&lt;ref name=Boesen/&gt;{{rp|15–23}}

Lear traded his Radio Coil business for a one-third interest in [[Paul Galvin (businessman)|Paul Galvin]]'s Galvin Manufacturing Company. At that time the radio had not yet been developed for use in automobiles, but Lear and Howard Gates of Zenith made a pair; Lear designed the circuit and layout, Gates did the metal work and Lear assembled them. When Lear presented Galvin with the prototype, it was first dismissed.  Later the idea was surfaced by Galvin and a 200-unit production run was made. Galvin and Lear mulled over names for the product on a cross-country trip and came up with "Motorola" which was a blend of "motor" and the then popular suffix -ola used with audio equipment of the time (for example "[[Victrola]]"). The product was such a success that Galvin changed the name of the company to [[Motorola]].&lt;ref name="patent pending"/&gt;&lt;ref name=Boesen/&gt;{{rp|23, 24}}

[[File:Eight track.jpg|100px|left|8-track tape]]

===Music cartridges===
Lear developed the [[8-track tape|Lear Jet Stereo 8]] music cartridge in 1964, better-known as the "8-track". This was an eight track variation of the [[Stereo-Pak#Differences between 4-track and 8-track cartridges|four track]] [[Stereo-Pak|Muntz Stereo-Pak]] tape cartridge, marketed by [[Madman Muntz|Earl "Madman" Muntz]] in California in 1962, itself a version of a 3-track system, [[Fidelipac]]. The 8-track was a commercial success that provided good audio quality and was easily adapted to vehicle and home use.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.videointerchange.com/audio_history.htm "Vintage Audio History."] ''Video Interchange''. Retrieved: April 14, 2009.&lt;/ref&gt; It was a solution to the need for a convenient music source for his new business jets. The consumer version of players for these tapes first appeared in September 1965 in 1966 model Ford automobiles with [[RCA]] and Lear offering the first pre-recorded Stereo 8 Music Cartridges.

===Transportation===
In 1968, Lear also started work on a closed circuit steam turbine to power cars and buses, and built a transit bus and converted a [[Chevrolet Monte Carlo]] sedan to use this turbine system. It used a proprietary working fluid dubbed '''Learium''', possibly a [[chlorofluorocarbon]] similar to DuPont Freon.&lt;ref&gt;Ethridge. John. [https://books.google.ca/books?id=NNQDAAAAMBAJ&amp;pg=PA116&amp;lpg=PA116&amp;dq=%22lear%22+steam+car+monte#v=onepage&amp;q=%22lear%22%20steam%20car%20monte&amp;f=false  "PM takes a ride in tomorrow's bus, today."] ''Popular Mechanics,'' August 1972. Retrieved: August 31, 2011.&lt;/ref&gt;

In 1969, Lear and his friend [[Art Linkletter]] offered their support for [[Craig Breedlove]]'s supersonic car project.
[[File:Learjet 25 der NASA.jpg|thumb|Learjet 25, an example of the Lear executive jets that still bear his name]] {{citation needed|date=November 2015}}

===Aviation===
In 1931, Lear bought his first aircraft, a Fleet [[biplane]] for $2,500 from a woman in Dearborn, Michigan. The challenges of aerial navigation led Lear into the development of radio direction finders and [[avionics]] products.

Lear founded Lear Developments, a company specializing in aerospace instruments and electronics.&lt;ref name = "Billboard 1965"&gt;Zhito, Lee. [https://books.google.com/books?id=lSgEAAAAMBAJ&amp;pg=PA6 "Lear: Wizard of the Cartridge Age."]  ''Billboard,'' Volume 17, Issue 16, April 17, 1965, p. 6.&lt;/ref&gt; Lear developed [[radio direction finder]]s, [[autopilot]]s, and the first fully automatic aircraft landing system. He was awarded the [[Collier Trophy]] for this contribution in 1949.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.aerofiles.com/collier-trophy.html Collier Trophy awards]&lt;/ref&gt;

Lear also developed and marketed a line of panel-mounted radios for [[general aviation]]. His "LearAvian" series of portable radios, which incorporated [[radio direction finder]] circuits as well as [[broadcast band]] coverage, were especially popular. The company earned about $100 million during WW II for its products. {{citation needed|date=November 2015}}

Lear changed the name of Lear Developments to Lear Incorporated and in 1949 opened a manufacturing facility in [[Santa Monica, California]].

In 1960, Lear moved to [[Switzerland]] and founded the Swiss American Aviation Company (SAAC). The company's goal was to redesign the [[FFA P-16]] [[jet fighter]] into a small business jet, designated as [[SAAC-23]]. After two crashes during test flights of the FFA P-16, the Swiss government had cancelled its order for the aircraft and no other customers had been found.&lt;ref&gt;Rashke 1985, p. 219.&lt;/ref&gt;

During the short existence of SAAC, His Majesty King [[Michael I of Romania]] met Bill Lear and agreed to work as a test pilot for the Swiss part of the company. This was during the forced [[exile]] of the King, that lasted for 50 years, until 1997.&lt;ref&gt;ASR Principele Radu al României - Mașinile Regelui, Editura Curtea Veche, București, 2012, {{ISBN|978-606-588-353-6}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In 1962, Lear sold his interest in Lear Incorporated to the Siegler Corporation after failing to persuade Lear Incorporated's board to go into the aircraft manufacturing business. The remaining company was thereafter known as [[Lear Siegler]].

Bill Lear next moved to [[Wichita, Kansas]], to manufacture the resulting converted design as the [[Lear Jet]]. On October 7, 1963, Lear Jet started test flights on the [[Learjet 23]], the first [[Mass production|mass-produced]] [[business jet]]. The first Lear Jet was sold in 1963; it could carry eight passengers at 560&amp;nbsp;mph and cost about $650,000 fully equipped, about $400,000 less than its competitors at the time. Although the Lear Jet was quite successful and remains in production, Bill Lear was eventually forced to sell Lear Jet Corp. to the Gates Rubber Co. in 1967 due to other financial losses.&lt;ref&gt;AAHS "Folded Wings" obit, 3rd Quarter 1978.&lt;/ref&gt;

In the early 1970s, Lear backed the [[Foxjet ST600]] with its first order. The [[Very Light Jet]] project failed, but the VLJ concept became popular again 30 years later.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.eaa.org/news/2010/2010-05-13_foxjet.asp "Foxjet Now a Historic Lawn Ornament."] {{webarchive |url=https://web.archive.org/web/20100516011940/http://www.eaa.org/news/2010/2010-05-13_foxjet.asp |date=May 16, 2010 }} ''eaa.org.'' Retrieved: September 14, 2011.&lt;/ref&gt;

In 1976, Lear sold an option to his LearStar concept to [[Canadair]], a [[Montreal]] aircraft manufacturer.&lt;ref&gt;Rashke 1985, p. 331.&lt;/ref&gt; The idea was to design an executive aircraft which would bring together a [[Supercritical airfoil|supercritical wing]] with [[Lycoming Engines|Lycoming]]'s new [[turbofan]] engine. However, the concept was only a very rough outline,&lt;ref&gt;Rashke 1985, pp. 333–338.&lt;/ref&gt; prepared by a consultant.&lt;ref&gt;Logie 1992, p. 55.&lt;/ref&gt; Although Canadair took up its option, Lear eventually realized that the Canadians had simply been interested in using his reputation and skills at promotion, to "penetrate the market," Canadair's design had little relation to his concept and Lear had no role in its development.&lt;ref&gt;Rashke 1985, p. 339.&lt;/ref&gt; However, the [[Canadair Challenger]] business jet was to have a long career, with several variants. [[Bombardier Aerospace]], by that time the parent company of [[Canadair]], acquired Lear Jet in 1990.

One of Lear's most innovative projects was his last&amp;nbsp;— a revolutionary aircraft called the [[LearAvia Lear Fan|LearAvia Lear Fan 2100]], a seven-passenger aircraft whose single [[Pusher configuration|pusher propeller]] was powered by two turbine engines. The fuselage of this aircraft was made of lightweight [[composite material]]s, instead of the more typical [[aluminum]] alloys. The Lear Fan was ultimately never completed. At the time of his death he begged his wife, Moya, to finish it; with the help of investors, she attempted to do so, but the aircraft failed to obtain [[Federal Aviation Administration|FAA]] certification and so was never put into production.

==Personal life==

Lear was born on June 26, 1902 in [[Hannibal, Missouri]] to Ruben Marion Lear, a carpenter, and Gertrude Elizabeth Powell Lear. His mother left his father and they stayed with aunt Gussie Bornhouser in [[Dubuque, Iowa]]. Later Otto Kirmse took them in and was a step-father to Bill Lear.&lt;ref name="ReferenceA"/&gt; The family relocated to [[Chicago]] where Lear attended Kershaw Grammar School. On Sundays, young Lear attended the Moody Tabernacle (now [[Moody Church]]). "From listening to [[Paul Rader (evangelist)|Paul Rader]], of the Moody Tabernacle, he learned grammar and how to speak. He found out how to meet people, how to shake hands, and what to say when he did so... He learned about hypocrisy, too" and ceased any further church affiliation.&lt;ref name=Boesen&gt;Boesen, Victor (1971) ''They Said It Couldn't Be Done: The Incredible Story of Bill Lear''. New York: [[Doubleday (publisher)|Doubleday]] {{ISBN|0-385-01841-X}}.&lt;/ref&gt;{{rp|10,11}}

While in Chicago, Lear had also been employed briefly at a local air field.&lt;ref name="ReferenceA"/&gt; One summer he spent with his father in [[Tulsa]], re-building a Model-T car. Too independent to move back with his mother in Chicago, Lear struck out cross country. He joined the [[U.S. Navy]] and was sent to [[Great Lakes Naval Training Station]]. Later after discharge, and with a young family, "he decided to complete his high school education. Starting a radio repair shop in his home, which he could tend nights, Lear enrolled at [[Tulsa Central High School]], taking eight solids, heavy on the math. He was at the point of wrapping up the entire four-year curriculum in one when he was again dismissed for showing up teachers."&lt;ref name=Boesen/&gt;{{rp|12–18}}

Marriages and children:
* With his first wife, Ethel Peterson Lear, Mary Louise was born in January 1925.
* He married his second wife, Madeline Murphy, in October 1926. Their son, William Lear Jr., was born on May 24, 1928.&lt;ref&gt;Pew, Glenn. [http://www.avweb.com/avwebflash/news/bill_lear_dead_learjet_201714-1.html "Bill Lear Jr. Dead At 81."] ''Avweb,'' December 18, 2009. Retrieved: September 14, 2011.&lt;/ref&gt; Daughter Patti was born in 1930.
* Lear's third marriage, to Margret Radell, was childless.
* In 1941, Lear married his fourth wife, [[Moya Lear|Moya Marie Olsen]]. They would have four children together: John Olsen Lear, Shanda, David and Tina.

Although Lear had a reputation for being difficult,&lt;ref&gt;Close, Dan. [http://www.wingsoverkansas.com/history/article.asp?id=103 "Love Him or Hate Him. Bill Lear was a Creator".] ''The Wichita Eagle'', April 29, 1985. Retrieved: July 7, 2007.&lt;/ref&gt; he had a sense of humor, as evidenced by naming his second daughter Shanda Lear ({{IPAc-en|ʃ|æ|n|d|ə|_|l|ɪər|}}), which is homophonic with "[[chandelier]]".&lt;ref name=Cummings-Democracy-2013&gt;Cummings [https://books.google.com/books?id=stF7j_stVYMC&amp;pg=PA83 2013, p. 83.]&lt;/ref&gt;

The 75-year-old Lear died of [[leukemia]] in [[Reno, Nevada]] on May 14, 1978.  His remains were cremated and scattered at sea.

==Tributes and honors==
In 1944, [[Harry Bruno]] included William P. Lear in a list of 87 "all-time greats in American aviation ... [who] gambled their necks, their brains and their money — that aviation might grow."&lt;ref&gt;[[Harry Bruno]] (1944) ''Wings over America: The Story of American Aviation'', page 325, Garden City, New York: Halcyon House&lt;/ref&gt;
* 1949, [[Collier Trophy]] for F-5 [[autopilot]]
* 1954, member [[Horatio Alger Association of Distinguished Americans]]
* 1967, appeared as himself in the film [[In Like Flint]]&lt;ref&gt;{{IMDb name|id=0495164|name=Bill Lear|accessdate=March 15, 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* 1972, [[Elliott Cresson Medal]]
* 1974, [[Tony Jannus Award]] for his distinguished contributions to aviation.
* 1978, [[National Aviation Hall of Fame]]&lt;ref name=AviationHOF&gt;[http://www.nationalaviation.org/lear-sr-william/ "William Powell Lear, Sr."] ''National Aviation Hall of Fame.'' Retrieved: April 6, 2011.&lt;/ref&gt;
*1981, [[International Air &amp; Space Hall of Fame]]&lt;ref&gt;Sprekelmeyer, Linda, editor. ''These We Honor: The International Aerospace Hall of Fame''. Donning Co. Publishers, 2006. [[International Standard Book Number|ISBN]] [[Special:BookSources/978-1-57864-397-4|978-1-57864-397-4]].&lt;/ref&gt;
* 1993, [[National Inventors Hall of Fame]] &lt;ref name="ReferenceA"/&gt;
* 2003, Hannibal Municipal Airport was renamed the [[Hannibal Regional Airport|Hannibal Regional Airport, William P. Lear Field]] in his honor.

==Notes==
{{Reflist|30em}}

==References==
{{Refbegin}}
* Cummings, Alex Sayf. ''Democracy of Sound: Music Piracy and the Remaking of American Copyright in the Twentieth Century''. New York: Oxford University Press, 2013. {{ISBN|978-0-19-932372-2}}.
* Logie, Stuart. ''Winging it: The Making of Canadair's Challenger.'' Toronto, Ontario: Macmillan Canada. 1992. {{ISBN|0-77159-145-4}}.
* Rashke, Richard. ''Stormy Genius: The Life of Aviation's Maverick, Bill Lear''. Boston: [[Houghton Mifflin]] Co., 1985. {{ISBN|0-395-35372-6}}.
* Stim, Richard and David Pressman. [https://books.google.com/books?id=Zj4Rlm2nZCQC "Patent Pending in 24 Hours."] Berkeley, California: Nolo, 2007. {{ISBN|1-4133-0511-3}}.
{{Refend}}

==External links==
{{Portal|Biography}}
* [http://www.nationalaviation.org/lear-sr-william/ William Powell Lear, Sr. at the National Aviation Hall of Fame]
* [https://www.horatioalger.org/members/member-detail/?id=003j000000f21ACAAY William P. Lear, 1954 Horatio Alger Award] from [[Horatio Alger Association of Distinguished Americans]].
* {{Find a Grave|8958894}}
* [https://m.imdb.com/name/nm0495164/ W P Lear Sr. at IMDB.]

{{Authority control}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Lear, Bill}}
[[Category:1902 births]]
[[Category:1978 deaths]]
[[Category:American aerospace engineers]]
[[Category:American inventors]]
[[Category:Businesspeople in aviation]]
[[Category:Bombardier Inc.]]
[[Category:People from Hannibal, Missouri]]
[[Category:National Aviation Hall of Fame inductees]]
[[Category:20th-century American businesspeople]]
[[Category:National Inventors Hall of Fame inductees]]</text>
      <sha1>8s4t101k7r8bjncvmghutw1z8k7xdrw</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
