<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10.xsd" version="0.10" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <dbname>enwiki</dbname>
    <base>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.32.0-wmf.16</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="118" case="first-letter">Draft</namespace>
      <namespace key="119" case="first-letter">Draft talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2300" case="first-letter">Gadget</namespace>
      <namespace key="2301" case="first-letter">Gadget talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2302" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition</namespace>
      <namespace key="2303" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Billy Bishop</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>244899</id>
    <revision>
      <id>853172203</id>
      <parentid>852975090</parentid>
      <timestamp>2018-08-02T22:19:15Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>InternetArchiveBot</username>
        <id>27015025</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>Rescuing 1 sources and tagging 0 as dead. #IABot (v2.0beta5)</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="42653">{{Use dmy dates|date=April 2018}}
{{For|other people with similar names|William Bishop (disambiguation){{!}}William Bishop}}
{{Infobox military person
|name= Billy Bishop
|image= Winged warfare - hunting the Huns in the air (1918) (14783541522).jpg
|image_size= 
|alt= 
|caption= Lieutenant Billy Bishop, 1918
|birth_name= William Avery Bishop
|nickname= "Billy", "Bish"
|birth_date= {{birth date|1894|2|8|df=y}}
|birth_place= [[Owen Sound, Ontario]], Canada
|death_date= {{death date and age|1956|9|11|1894|2|8|df=y}}
|death_place= [[West Palm Beach, Florida]], U.S.
|placeofburial= 
|allegiance= Canada&lt;br/&gt;United Kingdom
|branch= [[Canadian Expeditionary Force]]&lt;br/&gt;[[Royal Air Force]]&lt;br/&gt;[[Royal Canadian Air Force]]
|serviceyears= 1914–1918&lt;br/&gt;1936–1944
|rank= [[Air Marshal]]
|unit= 
|commands= [[No. 60 Squadron RAF]]&lt;br/&gt;[[No. 85 Squadron RAF]]
|battles= [[First World War]]
* [[Western Front (World War I)|Western Front]]
* [[Battle of Vimy Ridge]]
[[Second World War]]
|awards= [[Victoria Cross]]&lt;br/&gt;[[Companion of the Order of the Bath]]&lt;br/&gt;[[Distinguished Service Order]] &amp; [[Medal bar|Bar]]&lt;br/&gt;[[Military Cross]]&lt;br/&gt;[[Distinguished Flying Cross (United Kingdom)|Distinguished Flying Cross]]&lt;br/&gt;[[Mentioned in Despatches]]&lt;br/&gt;[[Canadian Efficiency Decoration]]&lt;ref name="Review Yearbook page 201-203"&gt;Royal Military College of Canada – Review Yearbook (Kingston, Ontario Canada)- Class of 1957 page 201-203&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;br/&gt;[[Legion of Honour|Chevalier of the Legion of Honour]] (France)&lt;br/&gt;[[Croix de guerre 1914–1918|Croix de guerre]] (France)
|relations= 
|laterwork= 
}}
'''William Avery Bishop''', {{postnominals|country=CAN|size=100%|sep=,|VC|CB|DSO1|MC|DFC|ED}} (8 February 1894&amp;nbsp;– 11 September 1956) was a Canadian [[flying ace]] of the [[First World War]], [[Victoria Cross]] recipient, and [[Air Marshal]]. He was officially credited with 72 victories, making him the top Canadian ace of the war. During the [[World War II|Second World War]], Bishop was instrumental in setting up and promoting the [[British Commonwealth Air Training Plan]].
{{TOC limit|limit=2}}

==Early life==
Bishop was born in [[Owen Sound, Ontario]].&lt;ref&gt;McCaffery 1988, p. 2.&lt;/ref&gt; He was the third of four children born to William A. and Margaret Bishop.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |author= Gill-Johnson, Mindy;  Marshall, Tabitha &amp; Greenhous, Brereton |url=http://www.thecanadianencyclopedia.ca/en/article/william-avery-bishop/ |title=Billy Bishop |work=The Canadian Encyclopedia |accessdate=7 September 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt; His father, a lawyer and graduate of [[Osgoode Hall Law School]] in [[Toronto]], Ontario, was the Registrar of [[Grey County, Ontario|Grey County]].&lt;ref name="McCaffery3"&gt;McCaffery 1988, p. 3.&lt;/ref&gt; Attending [[Owen Sound Collegiate and Vocational Institute]], Bishop earned the reputation of a fighter, defending himself and others easily against bullies.&lt;ref name="McCaffery3"/&gt; He avoided team sports, preferring solitary pursuits such as swimming, horse riding, and shooting.&lt;ref&gt;Greenhous 2002, p. 29.&lt;/ref&gt; Bishop was less successful at his studies; he would abandon any subject he could not easily master, and was often absent from class.&lt;ref name="McCaffery4"&gt;McCaffery 1988, p. 4.&lt;/ref&gt;

At 15, Bishop had his first experience with aviation: he built an aircraft out of cardboard, wood crates and string, and "flew" off the roof of his three-story house. He was dug, unharmed, out of the wreckage by his sister.&lt;ref name="McCaffery4"/&gt;

In 1911,&lt;ref name="Review Yearbook page 201-203"/&gt; Billy Bishop entered the [[Royal Military College of Canada]] (RMC) in [[Kingston, Ontario]], where his brother Worth had graduated in 1903.&lt;ref&gt;Greenhous 2002, p. 30.&lt;/ref&gt; At RMC, Bishop was known as "Bish" and "Bill". Bishop failed his first year at RMC, having been caught cheating.&lt;ref&gt;Greenhous 2002, p. 31.&lt;/ref&gt;
[[File:BillyBishopCadet.jpg|left|thumb|Bishop as an RMC cadet, c. 1914]]

==First World War==
When the [[World War I|First World War]] broke out later in 1914, Bishop left RMC and joined [[The Mississauga Horse]] cavalry regiment.&lt;ref&gt;McCaffery 1988, pp. 10–11.&lt;/ref&gt; He was commissioned as an officer but was ill with [[pneumonia]] when the regiment was sent overseas.&lt;ref name="McCaffery14"&gt;McCaffery 1988, p. 14.&lt;/ref&gt; After recovering, he was transferred to the 7th Canadian Mounted Rifles, a [[mounted infantry]] unit, then stationed in [[London, Ontario]].&lt;ref&gt;Greenhous 2002, p. 34.&lt;/ref&gt; Bishop showed a natural ability with a gun, and excelled on the firing range. His seemingly "super-human" eyesight allowed him to put bullets in a target placed so far away others saw only a dot.&lt;ref&gt;McCaffery 1988, pp. 17–18.&lt;/ref&gt; They left Canada for England on 6 June 1915 on board the requisitioned cattle ship ''Caledonia''.&lt;ref&gt;McCaffery 1988, p. 18.&lt;/ref&gt; On 21 June, off the coast of Ireland, the ship's convoy came under attack by [[U-boat]]s. Two ships were sunk and 300 Canadians died, but Bishop's ship was unharmed, arriving in [[Plymouth]] harbour on 23 June.&lt;ref&gt;McCaffery 1988, pp. 20–21.&lt;/ref&gt;

===As an observer===
Bishop quickly became frustrated with the mud of the [[Trench warfare|trenches]] and the lack of action. In July 1915, after watching an RFC aircraft return from a mission, Bishop said "it's clean up there! I'll bet you don't get any mud or horse shit on you up there. If you die, at least it would be a clean death."&lt;ref&gt;McCaffery 1988, p. 22.&lt;/ref&gt; While in France in 1915 he transferred to the [[Royal Flying Corps]]. As there were no places available for pilots in the flight school, he chose to be an observer.&lt;ref&gt;McCaffery 1988, pp. 24–25.&lt;/ref&gt; On 1 September, he reported to 21 (Training) Squadron at [[Netheravon Airfield|Netheravon]] for elementary air instruction.&lt;ref name="Greenhous38"&gt;Greenhous 2002, p. 38.&lt;/ref&gt; The first aircraft he trained in was the [[Avro 504]], flown by [[Roger Neville]].&lt;ref name="McCaffery26"&gt;McCaffery 1988, p. 26.&lt;/ref&gt; Bishop was adept at taking aerial photographs, and was soon in charge of training other observers with the camera.&lt;ref name="Greenhous38"/&gt; The squadron was ordered to France in January 1916 and arrived at [[Boisdinghem]] airfield, near [[Saint-Omer]], equipped with [[Royal Aircraft Factory R.E.7|R.E.7]] [[reconnaissance]] aircraft.&lt;ref&gt;McCaffery 1988, pp. 28–29.&lt;/ref&gt; Bishop' first combat mission was as an aerial spotter for British artillery.&lt;ref&gt;McCaffery 1988, p. 29.&lt;/ref&gt; At first, the aircraft could not get airborne until they had offloaded their bombload and machine guns.&lt;ref&gt;McCaffery 1988, pp. 31–32.&lt;/ref&gt; Bishop and pilot Neville flew over German lines near Boisdinghem and when the German howitzer was found, they relayed coordinates to the British, who then bombarded and destroyed the target.&lt;ref&gt;McCaffery 1988, pp. 34–35.&lt;/ref&gt; In the following months, Bishop flew on reconnaissance and bombing flights, but never fired his machine guns on an enemy aircraft.&lt;ref name="McCaffery36"&gt;McCaffery 1988, p. 36.&lt;/ref&gt; During one takeoff in April 1916, his aircraft engine failed, and he badly injured his knee.&lt;ref name="McCaffery39"&gt;McCaffery 1988, p. 39.&lt;/ref&gt; The injury was aggravated while on leave in London in May 1916, and Bishop was admitted to the hospital in [[Bryanston Square]].&lt;ref name="McCaffery39"/&gt; While there he met and befriended socialite [[Susan Jeune, Baroness St Helier|Lady St. Helier]], who was a friend to both [[Winston Churchill]] and Secretary for Air [[Lord Hugh Cecil]].&lt;ref&gt;Greenhous 2002, p. 43.&lt;/ref&gt; After Bishop's father suffered a small stroke, St. Helier arranged for Bishop to recuperate in Canada,&lt;ref&gt;Greenhous 2002, p. 45.&lt;/ref&gt; thereby missing the [[Battle of the Somme (1916)|Battle of the Somme]].{{Cn|date=September 2017}}

Bishop returned to England in September 1916, and, with the influence of St. Helier,&lt;ref&gt;Greenhous 2002, p. 46.&lt;/ref&gt; was accepted for training as a pilot at the [[Central Flying School]] at Upavon on [[Salisbury Plain]]. His first solo flight was in a [[Farman MF.11|Maurice Farman "Shorthorn"]].&lt;ref&gt;McCaffery 1988, pp. 42–45.&lt;/ref&gt;

===Aerial combat===
[[File:Lieutenant-Colonel Bishop.jpg|thumb|right|Bishop and a Nieuport 17 fighter in [[Filescamp, France]]]]

In November 1916 after receiving his wings, Bishop was attached to [[No. 37 Squadron RAF|No. 37 Squadron RFC]] at [[RFC Sutton's Farm|Sutton's Farm]], Essex flying the [[Royal Aircraft Factory B.E.2|BE.2c]]. Bishop disliked the flying at night over London, searching for German airships, and he soon requested a transfer to France.&lt;ref&gt;McCaffery 1988, p. 46.&lt;/ref&gt;

On 17 March 1917, Bishop arrived at 60 Squadron at Filescamp Farm near [[Arras]], where he flew the [[Nieuport 17]] fighter.&lt;ref&gt;McCaffery 1988, pp. 47, 51.&lt;/ref&gt; At that time, the average life expectancy of a new pilot in that sector was 11 days, and German aces were shooting down British aircraft 5 to 1.&lt;ref&gt;McCaffery 1988, p. 49.&lt;/ref&gt; Bishop's first patrol on 22 March was less than successful. He had trouble controlling his run-down aircraft, was nearly shot down by anti-aircraft fire, and became separated from his group.&lt;ref&gt;McCaffery 1988, pp. 57–58.&lt;/ref&gt; On 24 March, after crash landing his aircraft during a practice flight in front of General [[John Frederick Andrews Higgins|John Higgins]], Bishop was ordered to return to flight school at Upavon. Major [[Alan Scott (British Army officer)|Alan Scott]], the new commander of 60 Squadron, convinced Higgins to let him stay until a replacement arrived.&lt;ref&gt;McCaffery 1988, pp. 60–61.&lt;/ref&gt; The next day, Bishop claimed his first victory when his was one of four Nieuports that engaged three [[Albatros D.III]] Scouts near St Leger.&lt;ref&gt;McCaffery 1988, p. 64.&lt;/ref&gt; Bishop shot down and mortally wounded a Lieutnant Theiller (Shores (1991) has 12-kill ace Theiller as being killed vs 70 Squadron Sopwiths on 24 March; therefore this claim does not match with known losses), but his engine failed in the process. He landed in [[no man's land]], {{convert|300|yd|m}} from the German front line. After running to the Allied trenches, Bishop spent the night on the ground in a rainstorm.&lt;ref name="McCaffery65"&gt;McCaffery 1988, p. 65.&lt;/ref&gt; There Bishop wrote a letter home, starting, "I am writing this from a dugout 300 yards from our front line, after the most exciting adventure of my life."&lt;ref name="McCaffery65"/&gt; General Higgins personally congratulated Bishop and rescinded his order to return to flight school.&lt;ref&gt;McCaffery 1988, p. 66.&lt;/ref&gt; On 30 March 1917, Bishop was named a [[Flight commander (position)|flight commander]].&lt;ref&gt;McCaffery 1988, p. 67.&lt;/ref&gt; The next day he scored his second victory.&lt;ref&gt;McCaffery 1988, p. 68.&lt;/ref&gt; Bishop, in addition to the usual patrols with his squadron comrades, soon flew many unofficial "lone-wolf" missions deep into enemy territory, with the blessing of Major Scott. As a result, his total of enemy aircraft shot down increased rapidly. On 8 April, he scored his fifth victory and became an ace.&lt;ref&gt;McCaffery 1988, p. 79.&lt;/ref&gt; To celebrate, Bishop's mechanic painted the aircraft's nose blue, the mark of an ace. Former 60 Squadron member Captain [[Albert Ball]], at that time the Empire's highest scoring ace, had had a red spinner fitted.&lt;ref&gt;McCaffery 1988, p. 81.&lt;/ref&gt;

[[File:BillyBishop.jpg|thumb| Bishop c. August 1917, in the cockpit of his [[Nieuport 17]], [[France]]]]

Bishop's no-holds-barred style of flying always had him "at the front of the pack," leading his pilots into battle over hostile territory. &lt;!-- rm till ref found: One fellow pilot account claims "normal formation is two at the front and three at the rear, except Billy was always at least ½ mile ahead, how he got that far I do not know".--&gt;Bishop soon realized that this could eventually see him shot down; after one patrol, a mechanic counted 210 bullet holes in his aircraft.&lt;ref&gt;McCaffery 1988, pp. 95–96.&lt;/ref&gt; His new method of using the surprise attack proved successful; he claimed 12 aircraft in April alone, winning the [[Military Cross]] and a promotion to captain for his participation in the [[Battle of Vimy Ridge]].&lt;ref&gt;McCaffery 1988, p. 96.&lt;/ref&gt; The successes of Bishop and his blue-nosed aircraft were noticed by the Germans, and they began referring to him as "Hell's Handmaiden". [[Ernst Udet]] called him "the greatest English scouting ace" and one ''[[Jasta]]'' had a bounty on his head.&lt;ref&gt;McCaffery 1988, p. 102.&lt;/ref&gt;

On 30 April, Bishop survived an encounter with ''[[Jasta 11]]'' and [[Manfred von Richthofen]], the Red Baron.&lt;ref&gt;McCaffery 1988, pp. 104–106.&lt;/ref&gt; In May, Bishop won the [[Distinguished Service Order]] for shooting down two aircraft while being attacked by four others.{{Cn|date=September 2017}}

On 2 June 1917, Bishop flew a solo mission behind enemy lines to attack a German-held [[aerodrome]], where he claimed that he shot down three aircraft that were taking off to attack him and destroyed several more on the ground. For this feat, he was awarded the [[Victoria Cross]] (VC), although it has been suggested that he may have embellished his success. His VC (awarded 30 August 1917 &lt;ref name= "Dieter p. "&gt;{{harvnb|Dieter|2017|p=}}&lt;/ref&gt;) was one of two awarded in violation of the warrant requiring witnesses (the other being the [[Tomb of the Unknown Soldier|Unknown Soldier]]),&lt;ref&gt;Greenhous 2002, p. 13.&lt;/ref&gt; and since the German records have been lost and the archived papers relating to the VC were lost as well, there is no way of confirming whether there were any witnesses. It seems to have been common practice at this time to allow Bishop to claim victories without requiring confirmation or verification from other witnesses.&lt;ref&gt;Shores et al. 1991, p. 76.&lt;/ref&gt;

In July, 60 Squadron received new [[Royal Aircraft Factory S.E.5]]s, a faster and more powerful aircraft with better pilot visibility. In August 1917, Bishop passed the late Albert Ball in victories to become (temporarily) the highest scoring ace in the RFC and the third top ace of the war, behind only the Red Baron and [[René Fonck]].&lt;ref&gt;McCaffery 1960, p. 143.&lt;/ref&gt;

===Leave to Canada===
Bishop returned home on leave to Canada in fall 1917, where he was acclaimed a hero and helped boost the morale of the Canadian public, who were growing tired of the war.&lt;ref&gt;McCaffery 1960, p. 155.&lt;/ref&gt; On 17 October 1917, Bishop married his longtime fiancée, Margaret Eaton Burden.&lt;ref name="Review Yearbook page 201-203"/&gt; After the wedding, he was assigned to the British War Mission in [[Washington, D.C.]] to help the Americans build an air force. While stationed there, he wrote his [[autobiography]] entitled ''Winged Warfare''.&lt;ref name="CAFOPA"&gt;McDonnell, Capt. Darach [http://www.gwpda.org/comment/bishop.html "The Flying Career of William Avery Bishop."] ''gwpda.org,'' 23 April 2006. Retrieved: 10 November 2009.&lt;/ref&gt;

===Return to Europe===
[[File:Billy Bishop plaque.jpg|thumb|right|Billy Bishop plaque in Owen Sound]]

Upon his return to England in April 1918, Bishop was promoted to Major and given command of [[No. 85 Squadron RAF|No. 85 Squadron]], the "Flying Foxes".&lt;ref&gt;McCaffery 1960, p. 167.&lt;/ref&gt; This was a newly formed squadron and Bishop was given the freedom to choose many of the pilots. The squadron was equipped with SE5a scout planes and left for [[Petit Synthe, France]] on 22 May 1918.&lt;ref&gt;McCaffery 1960, pp. 178–179.&lt;/ref&gt; On 27 May, after familiarizing himself with the area and the opposition, Bishop took a solo flight to the Front. He downed a German observation plane in his first combat since August 1917,&lt;ref&gt;McCaffery 1960, p. 184.&lt;/ref&gt; and followed with two more the next day.&lt;ref name="McCaffery185"&gt;McCaffery 1960, p. 185.&lt;/ref&gt; From 30 May to 1 June Bishop downed six more aircraft, including German ace [[Paul Billik]], bringing his score to 59 and reclaiming his top scoring ace title from [[James McCudden]], who had claimed it while Bishop was in Canada,&lt;ref name="McCaffery185"/&gt; and he was now the leading Allied ace.&lt;ref&gt;McCaffery 1960, p. 186.&lt;/ref&gt;

The [[Government of Canada]] was becoming increasingly worried about the effect on morale if Bishop were to be killed, so on 18 June he was ordered to return to England to help organize the new Canadian Flying Corps.&lt;ref&gt;McCaffery 1960, p. 192.&lt;/ref&gt; Bishop was not pleased with the order coming so soon after his return to France. He wrote to his wife: "This is ever so annoying."&lt;ref&gt;McCaffery 1960, p. 191.&lt;/ref&gt; The order specified that he was to leave France by noon on 19 June. On that morning, Bishop decided to fly one last solo patrol. In just 15 minutes of combat, he added another five victories to his total. He claimed to have downed two [[Pfalz D.III]]a scout planes, caused another two to collide with each other, and shot down a German reconnaissance aircraft.&lt;ref&gt;McCaffery 1960, pp. 194–195.&lt;/ref&gt;

On 5 August, Bishop was promoted to Lieutenant-Colonel and was given the post of "Officer Commanding-designate of the Canadian Air Force Section of the General Staff, Headquarters Overseas Military Forces of Canada."&lt;ref name="CAFOPA"/&gt; He was on board a ship returning from a reporting visit to Canada when news of the [[armistice]] arrived. Bishop was discharged from the [[Canadian Expeditionary Force]] on 31 December and returned to Canada.&lt;ref name="CAFOPA"/&gt;

By the end of the war, he had claimed some 72 air victories, including two balloons, 52 and two shared "destroyed" with 16 "out of control".&lt;ref&gt;Shores et al. 1991, pp. 77–78.&lt;/ref&gt; A number of reputable historians, including [[Hugh Halliday]] and Brereton Greenhous (both of whom have had the status of official historians for the [[Royal Canadian Air Force]]) have suggested the actual total was far lower. Brereton Greenhous felt the actual total of enemy aircraft destroyed was only 27.&lt;ref&gt;Halliday, Hugh ''Valour Reconsidered:  Inquiries Into The Victoria Cross'', p.145&lt;/ref&gt;

==Post-war career==
After the war, Bishop toured the principal cities in the United States and lectured on aerial warfare. He established an importing firm, Interallied Aircraft Corporation,&lt;ref&gt;Special, "Court Decision May Bar British Planes From U. S.", ''Chicago Daily Tribune'', Saturday 10 July 1920, Volume LXXIX, Number 165, page 1.&lt;/ref&gt; and a short-lived passenger air service with fellow ace [[William George Barker|William Barker]], but after legal and financial problems, and a serious crash, the partnership and company were dissolved.&lt;ref name="CAFOPA"/&gt; In 1921, Bishop and his family moved to Britain, where he had various business interests connected with flying. In 1928, he was the guest of honour at a gathering of German air aces in [[Berlin]] and was made an Honorary Member of the Association. ln 1929 he became Chairman of British Air Lines.&lt;ref name="Review Yearbook page 201-203"/&gt; However, the family's wealth was wiped out in the crash of 1929 and they had to move back to Canada, where he became Vice-President of the [[McColl-Frontenac Oil Company]].&lt;ref name="CAFOPA"/&gt;

===Second World War===
[[File:Air Marshall William Avery Bishop.png|thumb|[[Air Marshal]] William Avery Bishop, 1942]]

In January 1936, Bishop was appointed the first Canadian [[Air vice-marshal]]. Shortly after the outbreak of war in 1939, he was promoted to the rank of [[Air marshal]] in the [[Royal Canadian Air Force]]. He served during the war as Director of the Royal Canadian Air Force and was placed in charge of recruitment.&lt;ref name="Review Yearbook page 201-203"/&gt; He was so successful in this role that many applicants had to be turned away.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.firstworldwar.com/bio/bishop.htm "Who's Who: William Bishop."] ''firstworldwar.com.'' Retrieved: 7 September 2008.&lt;/ref&gt; Bishop created a system for training pilots across Canada and became instrumental in setting up and promoting the British Commonwealth Air Training Plan, which trained over 167,000 airmen in Canada during the [[World War II|Second World War]]. In 1942, he appeared as himself in the film ''[[Captains of the Clouds]]'', a [[Hollywood]] tribute to the RCAF.&lt;ref&gt;[https://www.imdb.com/title/tt0034578/ IMdb listing Captains of the Clouds]&lt;/ref&gt;

By 1944 the stress of the war had taken a serious toll on Bishop's health, and he resigned his post in the RCAF to return to private enterprise in [[Montreal]], Quebec, before retiring in 1952.&lt;ref name="CAFOPA"/&gt; His son later commented that he looked 70 years old on his 50th birthday in 1944. However, Bishop remained active in the aviation world, predicting the phenomenal growth of commercial aviation postwar. His efforts to bring some organization to the nascent field led to the formation of the [[International Civil Aviation Organization]] (ICAO) in Montreal. He wrote a second book at this time, ''Winged Peace'', advocating international control of global air power.&lt;ref&gt;Bashow, Lieutenant-Colonel David. [http://www.billybishop.net/incomparable.html "The Incomparable Billy Bishop: The Man and the Myths."] ''billybishop.net,'' 14 February 2006. Retrieved: 14 October 2011.&lt;/ref&gt;

With the outbreak of the [[Korean War]], Bishop again offered to return to his recruitment role, but he was in poor health and was politely refused by the RCAF. He died in his sleep on 11 September 1956, at the age of 62, while wintering in [[Palm Beach, Florida]].&lt;ref name="CAFOPA"/&gt; His funeral service was held with full Air Force Honours in Toronto, Ontario. The body was cremated and the ashes interred in the family plot in [[Greenwood Cemetery (Owen Sound, Ontario)|Greenwood Cemetery]], Owen Sound, Ontario. A memorial service for Air Marshal Bishop was held in [[St Paul's Church, Bristol]], England on 19 September 1956.&lt;ref name="Review Yearbook page 201-203"/&gt;

==Family==
On 17 October 1917, at [[Timothy Eaton Memorial Church]] in Toronto, Bishop married his longtime fiancée, Margaret Eaton Burden, daughter of Mr C. E. Burdon, a granddaughter of [[Timothy Eaton]] and sister of ace [[Henry John Burden]]. They had a son William and a daughter Margaret.&lt;ref name="Review Yearbook page 201-203"/&gt; Both of the Bishop children became aviators:

* William Arthur Christian Avery Bishop (1923 London, England – 2013 Toronto) was presented with his wings by his father during the Second World War; Arthur would go on to become a [[Supermarine Spitfire|Spitfire]] pilot and served with [[No. 401 Squadron RCAF|No 401 Squadron RCAF]] in 1944. After the war, he became a  journalist, advertising executive, entrepreneur and author. He married Priscilla (Cilla) Jean Aylen and had two children (Diana and William)
* Margaret Marise (Jackie) Willis-O’Connor (1926 London – 2013 Ottawa) was a wireless radio operator during World War II, whom Bishop presented with a Wireless Sparks Badge in 1944.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.acesofww2.com/Canada/aces/bishop.html "Arthur Christian William Avery "Bish" Bishop."] {{webarchive |url=https://web.archive.org/web/20100922155615/http://www.acesofww2.com/Canada/aces/bishop.html |date=22 September 2010 }} ''acesofww2.com.'' Retrieved: 14 October 2011.&lt;/ref&gt;

==Honours and tributes==

===Official citations===
[[File:Billy bishop medals.jpg|thumb|right|Billy Bishop's decorations (now part of Canadian War Museum collection) include (left to right) Victoria Cross, Distinguished Service Order with Bar, Military Cross, Distinguished Flying Cross, 1914–1915 Star, British War Medal 1914–1920.]]
Bishop's decorations include the [[Victoria Cross]], [[Distinguished Service Order]] &amp; Bar, [[Military Cross]], [[Distinguished Flying Cross (UK)|Distinguished Flying Cross]], [[légion d'honneur]] and the [[Croix de guerre 1914–1918 (France)|Croix de Guerre]] with palm. He was made a Companion of the [[Order of the Bath]] in the [[1944 Birthday Honours|King's Birthday Honours List]] of 1 June 1944.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.cmp-cpm.forces.gc.ca/dhh-dhp/gal/vcg-gcv/bio/bishop-wa-eng.asp "William Avery Bishop."] ''Forces Canada''. Retrieved: 30 March 2010.&lt;/ref&gt;

===Victoria Cross===
The citation for his VC, published in the ''[[London Gazette]]'' on 11 August 1917, read:

{{quote|For most conspicuous bravery, determination, and skill. Captain Bishop, who had been sent out to work independently, flew first of all to an enemy aerodrome; finding no machines about, he flew on to another aerodrome about three miles southeast, which was at least 12 miles the other side of the line. Seven machines, some with their engines running, were on the ground. He attacked these from about fifty feet, and a mechanic, who was starting one of the engines, was seen to fall. One of the machines got off the ground, but at a height of 60 feet, Captain Bishop fired 15 rounds into it at very close range, and it crashed to the ground. A second machine got off the ground, into which he fired 30 rounds at 150 yards range, and it fell into a tree. Two more machines then rose from the aerodrome. One of these he engaged at a height of 1,000 feet, emptying the rest of his drum of ammunition. This machine crashed 300 yards from the aerodrome, after which Captain Bishop emptied a whole drum into the fourth hostile machine, and then flew back to his station. Four hostile scouts were about 1,250 feet above him for about a mile of his return journey, but they would not attack. His machine was very badly shot about by machine gun fire from the ground.&lt;ref&gt;McCaffery 1960, pp. 153–154.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{London Gazette|issue=30228 |supp=y|pages=8211–8212|date=10 August 1917 }}&lt;/ref&gt;}}

===Distinguished Flying Cross===
His citation for the Distinguished Flying Cross read:
&lt;blockquote&gt; A most successful and fearless fighter in the air, whose acts of outstanding bravery have already been recognised by the awards of the Victoria Cross, Distinguished Service Order, Bar to the Distinguished Service Order, and Military Cross. For the award of the Distinguished Flying Cross now conferred upon him he has rendered signally valuable services in personally destroying twenty-five enemy machines in twelve days—five of which he destroyed on the last day of his service at the front. The total number of machines destroyed by this distinguished officer is seventy-two, and his value as a moral factor to the Royal Air Force cannot be over-estimated.&lt;ref name= "DSM"&gt;[http://www.canadiangreatwarproject.com/searches/medalDetail.asp?ID=2102 "Distinguished Service Order Medal detail".] ''Canadian Great War Project''. Retrieved: 30 March 2010.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

===Distinguished Service Order===
His citation for the Distinguished Service Order read:

&lt;blockquote&gt;For conspicuous gallantry and devotion to duty. While in a single-seater he attacked three hostile machines, two of which he brought down, although in the meantime he was himself attacked by four other hostile machines. His courage and determination have set a fine example to others.&lt;ref name= "DSM"/&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

===Distinguished Service Order Bar===
His citation for the Distinguished Service Order bar read:

&lt;blockquote&gt;For conspicuous gallantry and devotion to duty when engaging hostile aircraft. His consistent dash and great fearlessness have set a magnificent example to the pilots of his squadron. He has destroyed no less than 45 hostile machines within the past 5 months, frequently attacking enemy formations single-handed, and on all occasions displaying a fighting spirit and determination to get to close quarter with his opponents which have earned the admiration of all in contact with him.&lt;ref name= "DSM"/&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

===Other tributes===
[[File:BillyBishopMuseum.JPG|thumb|Billy Bishop Museum in Owen Sound]]

''[[Billy Bishop Goes to War]]'' Feature film and Canadian musical, written by [[John MacLachlan Gray]] in collaboration with the actor [[Eric Peterson]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://billybishopgoestowar.com/ Official Site]&lt;/ref&gt; ''A Hero to Me: The Billy Bishop Story&amp;nbsp;– WW1 Canadian flying Ace'', a documentary depicting the story of "Billy" Bishop from the perspective of his granddaughter Diana, was produced for Global Television and TVO in 2003.{{Cn|date=September 2017}}

In 1967, Bishop was inducted into the [[International Air &amp; Space Hall of Fame]].&lt;ref&gt;Sprekelmeyer, Linda, editor. ''These We Honor: The International Aerospace Hall of Fame''. Donning Co. Publishers, 2006. [[International Standard Book Number|ISBN]] [[Special:BookSources/978-1-57864-397-4|978-1-57864-397-4]].&lt;/ref&gt;

The boyhood home of Billy Bishop is now the [[Billy Bishop Home and Museum]] in Owen Sound, Ontario. The museum has exhibits on the family, Bishop himself and veterans. There is a permanent exhibit with information on Bishop at the [[Grey Roots Museum and Archives]], just south of Owen Sound.{{Cn|date=September 2017}}

On 12 August 1994, Canada Post issued "Billy Bishop, Air Ace" as part of the Great Canadians series. The stamps were designed by Pierre Fontaine, based on illustrations by Bernard Leduc. The 43¢ stamps are perforated 13.5 and were printed by Canadian Bank Note Company, Limited.&lt;ref&gt;[http://data4.collectionscanada.gc.ca/netacgi/nph-brs?s1=(military.A790,C790.)+Or+(null.B742.)&amp;l=50&amp;d=STMP&amp;p=1&amp;u=http://www.collectionscanada.gc.ca/archivianet/02011702_e.html&amp;r=46&amp;f=G&amp;Sect1=STMP "Canada Post stamp."] {{Webarchive|url=https://archive.is/20130101010413/http://data4.collectionscanada.gc.ca/netacgi/nph-brs?s1=(military.A790,C790.)+Or+(null.B742.)&amp;l=50&amp;d=STMP&amp;p=1&amp;u=http://www.collectionscanada.gc.ca/archivianet/02011702_e.html&amp;r=46&amp;f=G&amp;Sect1=STMP |date=1 January 2013 }} ''Collections Canada.'' Retrieved: 23 October 2012.&lt;/ref&gt;

The Air Force Association of Canada approved the establishment of a trophy to commemorate the late Air Marshal W.A. Bishop, VC, in recognition of his "outstanding contribution to the legacy of excellence in Canadian aviation".&lt;ref&gt;{{National Inventory of Canadian Military Memorials|id=7802|title=Air Marshal W.A. Bishop, VC trophy: Memorial 35059-047 Ottawa, ON|access-date=7 January 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Two airports in Ontario are named after Bishop. The airport in Owen Sound is officially named "[[Owen Sound Billy Bishop Regional Airport]]." [[Toronto]]'s island airport was renamed [[Billy Bishop Toronto City Airport]] in 2009. Although Owen Sound's mayor questioned the change, the proposal was approved by the [[Toronto Port Authority]] on 10 November 2009. Having two airports in the province with similar names was a concern.&lt;ref&gt;[https://www.google.com/hostednews/canadianpress/article/ALeqM5hYScmMf5wWCXYKQD9odDDQGiL5eg "Not everyone happy that Toronto Island airport to be renamed after Billy Bishop."] ''Canadian Press'', 3 September 2009. Retrieved: 3 September 2009.&lt;/ref&gt; Toronto's [[Pearson International Airport]] was originally named ''Bishop Field Toronto Airport Malton.''&lt;ref&gt;"City sleuth." ''Toronto Star'', 9 November 1981, p. A02.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="airport-naming"&gt;"Holiday May 22 to Honor King." ''Toronto Globe,'' 4 April 1939. p. 4.&lt;/ref&gt;

Bishop is memorialized across Canada:

* "Billy Bishop Private" is a roadway on private land at Ottawa Airport, [[Ottawa]], Ontario, where the "Billy Bishop Room" for visiting dignitaries also exists.
* "Billy Bishop Way" is a street near the [[Toronto/Downsview Airport|Downsview Airport]] in Toronto, Ontario.
* "Billy Bishop Park" is a public park in [[Ottawa]], created with the help of the [[Royal Canadian Legion]] Branch 638 (Kanata)&lt;ref&gt;{{National Inventory of Canadian Military Memorials|id=8514|title=Billy Bishop Park: Memorial 35040-005 Kanata, ON|access-date=7 January 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* "[[Mount Bishop (Elk Range)|Mount Bishop]]", a {{Convert|2850|m|ft|adj=mid|-high}} mountain on the [[Alberta]]&amp;nbsp;– [[British Columbia]] border.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|title=Place-names of Alberta|url=https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=mdp.39015070267029;view=1up;seq=24|year=1928|publisher=Geographic Board of Canada|location=Ottawa|page=20}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* "Bishop Building", the 1st Canadian Air Division and the Canadian NORAD Region Headquarters in [[Winnipeg]], Manitoba.
* "Billy Bishop Legion Branch 176" in [[Vancouver]], British Columbia.
* "CFB Borden Billy Bishop Centre", a hazardous materials training school at [[CFB Borden]] in Ontario.
* "Billy Bishop entrance" at [[Hamilton, Ontario]]'s Memorial School.
* "Billy Bishop Hangar" at the [[Brampton, Ontario]] Flying Club.&lt;ref&gt;Ogilvie, Megan. [https://www.thestar.com/news/gta/article/690313 "Island airport to be named after Billy Bishop."] ''Toronto Star'', 3 September 2009. Retrieved: 4 September 2009.&lt;/ref&gt;
* 943 Air Marshall William Avery "Billy" Bishop VC, CB, DSO, &amp; Bar, MC, DFC, ED (1894–1956) was added to the wall of honour at the [[Royal Military College of Canada]] in [[Kingston, Ontario]] in 2009.
* [[Air Force Association of Canada]]'s Air Marshal W. A. Bishop Memorial Trophy is one of the highest awards for [[aviation]] in Canada.
* Sqn 167 Air Marshall Bishop Squadron, Royal Canadian Air Cadets, Owen Sound, Ontario
* Bishop's former home in Ottawa, Ontario, constructed in 1905 in the Queen Anne Revival style, has been opened to the public in the annual [[Doors Open Ottawa]] showcase of buildings.&lt;ref&gt;[http://ottawa.ca/en/rec_culture/museum_heritage/celebrations/doors_open/2012buildings/index.htm "2012 Buildings: Diane A. Gagné Financial Services."] {{webarchive|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20120526121604/http://ottawa.ca/en/rec_culture/museum_heritage/celebrations/doors_open/2012buildings/index.htm |date=26 May 2012 }} ''Doors Open Ottawa.'' Retrieved: 27 May 2012.&lt;/ref&gt;

==Legacy and later controversy==
[[File:Wall of Honour, Royal Military College of Canada.jpg|thumb|left|220px|Wall of Honour, Royal Military College of Canada]]
Bishop's life was depicted in the Canadian play, ''[[Billy Bishop Goes to War]]''. It also led indirectly to a [[CBC Television]] documentary called ''[[The Kid Who Couldn't Miss]]'', produced by the [[National Film Board of Canada]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.nfb.ca/film/the-kid-who-couldnt-miss/ "The Kid Who Couldn't Miss."] ''NFB.ca.'' Retrieved: 14 October 2011.&lt;/ref&gt; The show, a "docudrama" combining known history for credibility with fictitious "mock interviews" with actors portraying Bishop and others, suggested that Bishop faked his famous attack on the German aerodrome.&lt;ref&gt;McCaffery 1960, p. 196.&lt;/ref&gt; In one particularly contentious scene, his mechanic claims that the damage to his fighter was confined to a small circle in a non-critical area, implying that Bishop had landed his aircraft off-field, shot holes in it, and flown home with claims of combat damage.{{citation needed|date=May 2016}}

In reality, his mechanic was his biggest supporter, and the scene was entirely fictitious.{{citation needed|date=May 2016}} The mechanic insisted that Bishop had not fabricated the damage.{{citation needed|date=May 2016}} Canadian authors Dan McCaffery and David Bashow have also presented strong circumstantial evidence that Bishop was not a fake.{{citation needed|date=May 2016}}

After years of controversy over Bishop's record, mainly because very few of his claimed victories were witnessed by anyone else or could be confirmed from the few surviving German records, the show led to an inquiry by the Canadian government in 1985. The Standing Senate Committee on Social Affairs, Science and Technology discredited the documentary, saying it was an unfair and inaccurate portrayal of Bishop. There is some dispute about whether Bishop or [[Mick Mannock]] had the highest score of any British Empire First World War fighter ace.{{citation needed|date=May 2016}} The ''Canadian Encyclopedia'' states: "Investigation by a Senate sub-committee exposed a number of minor errors in this apparent 'documentary' and confirmed that statements had been wrongly attributed and incidents shifted in time for dramatic effect. However, the senators were unable to demonstrate that Bishop's claims were valid, and consequently recommended only that the film be labelled as docu-drama".{{citation needed|date=May 2016}}

Some of Bishop's other claims have also been challenged. While combat reports and claims of both sides are littered with well-intentioned errors and accidental duplicate claims, there are two phases of Bishop's life in which German records can provide no supporting evidence. In his book on Victoria Cross airmen of the First World War, author Alex Revell quotes aviation historian Philip Markham's view about German records of the events of 2 June 1917 (the day of Bishop's VC award): "Not a shred of evidence to support Bishop's claims." Referring to Bishop's claims in early to mid-1918, Revell says another aviation historian, Ed Ferko, carried out extensive research on Germans records in 1987. Revell says that Ferko failed "to match a single victory claim made by Bishop against a known German loss for the day, time or place in question." However, distinguished First World War aviation historian Peter Kilduff says in his biography (Billy Bishop VC: Lone Wolf Hunter) that Bishop may have had as many as 21 matches in piecemeal German records. Kilduff, the author of 16 books, is renowned for his research in German records. Kilduff also makes a strong case for the unreliability of German records. He cites examples in which masses of data were destroyed by retreating German forces and instances of the German former air ministry having been guilty of "obfuscation" in denying losses when casualties had been incurred.&lt;ref&gt;Kilduff 2014, pp. 6, 7, 8.&lt;/ref&gt;

==References==
{{Reflist|30em}}

===Bibliography===
{{Refbegin}}
* Baker, David. ''William Avery "Billy" Bishop: The Man and the Aircraft He Flew''. London: The Outline Press, 1990. {{ISBN|1-871547-07-5}}.
* Barker, Ralph. ''The Royal Flying Corps in World War I''. London: Constable and Robinson, 2002. {{ISBN|1-84119-470-0}}.
* Bashow, Lieutenant-Colonel David. [http://www.njoural.forces.gc.ca/engraph/Vol3/no3/pdf/55-60_e.pdf "The Incomparable Billy Bishop: The Man and the Myths."]{{dead link|date=November 2016 |bot=InternetArchiveBot |fix-attempted=yes }} ''Canadian Military Journal'', Volume 3, Issue 4, Autumn 2002, pp.&amp;nbsp;55–60. Retrieved: 1 September 2008.
* {{cite book|first=William Avery|last= Bishop|title=Winged Warfare|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=ypbHAAAAMAAJ|year=1918|publisher=George H. Doran Company}}
* Bishop, William Avery. ''Winged Warfare'' London: Crécy Publishing, 2007 (originally published in 1918). {{ISBN|0-947554-90-4}}.
* Buzzell, Nora. ''[[The Register of the Victoria Cross]] Third Edition''. Cheltenham, Gloucestershire, UK: This England, 1997. {{ISBN|0-906324-27-0}}.
* {{cite web |ref=harv|last=Dieter|first=Captain Steven |date=2 June 2017|url = http://www.rcaf-arc.forces.gc.ca/en/news-template-standard.page?doc=billy-bishop-canada-s-first-air-force-victoria-cross-recipient/hvxiinij|title =Billy Bishop – Canada’s first Air Force Victoria Cross recipient|format = |publisher = [[Royal Canadian Air Force]]| accessdate = 6 August 2017 |quote=}}
* Greenhous, Brereton. [https://web.archive.org/web/20110706175222/http://www.journal.dnd.ca/vo3/no3/doc/61-64-eng.pdf "Billy Bishop – Brave Flyer, Bold Liar."] ''Canadian Military Journal'' Volume 3, Issue 3, Autumn 2002, pp.&amp;nbsp;61–64. Retrieved: 15 November 2009.
* Greenhous, Brereton. [https://books.google.com/books?id=huR5poB1g_0C&amp;pg=PP1 "The Making of Billy Bishop: The First World War Exploits of Billy Bishop, VC."] Toronto: Dundurn Press Ltd., 2002. {{ISBN|978-1-55002-390-9}}.
* Harvey, David. ''[[Monuments to Courage]]''. Uckfield, UK: Naval &amp; Military Press Ltd., 1999. {{ISBN|1-84342-356-1}}.
* McCaffrey, Dan. [https://books.google.com/books?id=RlPDAqRQV88C ''Billy Bishop: Canadian Hero''.] Toronto: James Lorimer &amp; Company Publishers, 1988. {{ISBN|1-55028-095-3}}.
* Shores, Norman, L.R. Franks and Russell Guest. ''Above the Trenches: A Complete Record of the Fighter Aces and the Units of the British Empire Air Forces 1915–1920''. London: Grub Street, 1991. {{ISBN|0-948817-19-4}}.
* Urwin, Gregory  J.W. "The Man Without Fear: The Combat story of Lieutenant Colonel William Avery Bishop." ''Air Classics'', Vol. 15, No. 9, September 1979.
{{Refend}}

==External links==
{{Commons category|Billy Bishop}}
* [http://constable.ca/caah/bbishop.htm William Avery "Billy" Bishop]
* [http://www.worldwar1.com/biocbish.htm Air Ace William "Billy" Bishop]
* [http://www.theaerodrome.com/aces/canada/bishop.html William Bishop]
* [http://www.billybishop.net/bishop.html Air Marshal William Avery Bishop] ''(biography &amp; controversy discussion)''
* [http://www.billybishop.org/ Billy Bishop Heritage Museum ''(Birthplace &amp; Childhood Home)'']
* [https://web.archive.org/web/20120407025056/http://www.legionmagazine.com/en/index.php/2005/01/high-heroes-of-the-great-war/ Legion Magazine Article on Billy Bishop written by his son Arthur Bishop]
* [http://www.ontarioplaques.com/Plaques/Plaque_Grey22.html Ontario Historic Plaque]
* [http://collections.civilization.ca/public/objects/common/webmedia.php?irn=1236200  Bishop's Medals At The Canadian War Museum]
* {{FadedPage|id=Bishop, William Avery (Colonel)|name=William Avery Bishop|author=yes}}

{{s-start}}
{{s-mil}}
|-
{{s-vac|last=[[Ernest Lloyd Janney]]&lt;br&gt;&lt;small&gt;As [[Officer Commanding|OC]] the Canadian Aviation Corps in 1915&lt;/small&gt;}}
{{s-ttl|title=[[Commander of the Royal Canadian Air Force|Officer Commanding the Canadian Air Force]]|years=1918}}
{{s-vac|next=[[Arthur Kellam Tylee]]&lt;br&gt;&lt;small&gt;As Air Officer Commanding&lt;/small&gt;}}
{{s-end}}
{{wwi-air}}
{{Commander of the Royal Canadian Air Force}}
{{Authority control}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Bishop, Billy}}
[[Category:Royal Canadian Air Force air marshals of World War II]]
[[Category:Royal Flying Corps officers]]
[[Category:Canadian World War I flying aces]]
[[Category:Canadian World War I recipients of the Victoria Cross]]
[[Category:Canadian recipients of the Military Cross]]
[[Category:Canadian Aviation Hall of Fame inductees]]
[[Category:Canadian expatriates in the United Kingdom]]
[[Category:Aviation history of Canada]]
[[Category:Canadian Companions of the Order of the Bath]]
[[Category:Recipients of the Croix de Guerre 1914–1918 (France)]]
[[Category:Recipients of the Distinguished Flying Cross (United Kingdom)]]
[[Category:Eaton's]]
[[Category:Canadian Anglicans]]
[[Category:Chevaliers of the Légion d'honneur]]
[[Category:People from Owen Sound]]
[[Category:Canadian people of English descent]]
[[Category:1894 births]]
[[Category:1956 deaths]]
[[Category:Royal Military College of Canada alumni]]
[[Category:Persons of National Historic Significance (Canada)]]
[[Category:Canadian Companions of the Distinguished Service Order]]
[[Category:Canadian Expeditionary Force officers]]
[[Category:Canadian aviation record holders]]</text>
      <sha1>7o8x7u9b6l4wp85lzk0ae44yzcil66k</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
