<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10.xsd" version="0.10" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <dbname>enwiki</dbname>
    <base>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.32.0-wmf.16</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="118" case="first-letter">Draft</namespace>
      <namespace key="119" case="first-letter">Draft talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2300" case="first-letter">Gadget</namespace>
      <namespace key="2301" case="first-letter">Gadget talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2302" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition</namespace>
      <namespace key="2303" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Christopher Reeve</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>73626</id>
    <revision>
      <id>856018280</id>
      <parentid>856018246</parentid>
      <timestamp>2018-08-22T09:55:04Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Iamthecheese44</username>
        <id>15183719</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>Unnecessary</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="78261">{{for|the similarly named actor who also played Superman|George Reeves}}
{{Use mdy dates|date=March 2017}}
{{Infobox person 
 | name             = Christopher Reeve
 | image            = C Reeve in Marriage of Figaro Opening night 1985.jpg
 | caption          = Reeve after the opening night of ''[[The Marriage of Figaro]]'' at the [[Circle in the Square Theatre]], New York City, 1985.
 | birth_name       = {{nowrap|Christopher D'Olier Reeve}}
 | birth_date       = {{birth date|1952|9|25}}
 | birth_place      = [[New York City]], U.S.
 | death_date       = {{death date and age|2004|10|10|1952|9|25}}
 | death_place      = [[Mount Kisco, New York]], U.S.
 | death_cause      = [[Paralysis]] / [[sepsis]]
 | nationality      = American 
 | alma_mater       = [[Cornell University]]&lt;br&gt;[[Juilliard School]]
 | home_town        = [[Princeton, New Jersey]], U.S.
 | known_for        = {{nowrap|''[[Superman]]''&lt;br/&gt;[[Christopher Reeve Foundation]]}}
 | boards           = [[Christopher Reeve Foundation]]
 | occupation       = [[Actor]], director, producer, screenwriter, author, activist, equestrian
 | years_active     = 1970–2004
 | height           = {{convert|6|ft|4|in|cm|abbr=on}}
 | website          = {{url|http://www.christopherreeve.org/}}
 | partner          = Gae Exton (1978–1987)
 | spouse           = {{marriage|[[Dana Reeve|Dana Morosini]]|1992}}
 | children         = 3
 | residence        = [[Pound Ridge, New York]], U.S.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.chrisreevehomepage.com/n-2006.html 2006 News Reports (Christopher Reeve Homepage)] Retrieved October 1, 2014.&lt;/ref&gt;
 | parents          = {{nowrap|[[F. D. Reeve]]&lt;br/&gt;Barbara Pitney Reeve ([[Married and maiden names|née]] Lamb)}}
 | family           = [[Franklin D'Olier]]&lt;br/&gt;(great-grandfather)&lt;br&gt;[[Mahlon Pitney]]&lt;br/&gt;(great-grandfather)
 | awards           = '''Screen Actor Guild Award''' (1998), '''Emmy Award''' (1997), '''Lasker Award''' (2003)
}}
'''Christopher D'Olier Reeve'''&lt;ref name=GBR&gt;{{cite web|last=Roberts |first=Gary Boyd |title=#77 Royal Descents, Notable Kin, and Printed Sources: An Assortment of Famous Actors |url=http://www.americanancestors.org/assortment-famous-actors/ |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20101203150008/http://www.americanancestors.org/assortment-famous-actors/ |dead-url=yes |archive-date=December 3, 2010 |work=[[New England Historic Genealogical Society]] |accessdate=May 3, 2011 |authorlink=Gary Boyd Roberts |df= }}&lt;/ref&gt; (September 25, 1952 – October 10, 2004) was an American [[actor]]. He achieved stardom for his acting achievements. In particular, he is best known for his motion picture portrayal of the classic [[DC comic]] book superhero [[Superman]], beginning with the acclaimed ''[[Superman (1978 film)|Superman]]'' (1978), for which he won a [[BAFTA Award]].

Reeve appeared in other critically acclaimed films such as ''[[The Bostonians (film)|The Bostonians]]'' (1984), ''[[Street Smart (film)|Street Smart]]'' (1987) and ''[[The Remains of the Day (film)|The Remains of the Day]]'' (1993). He received a [[Screen Actors Guild Award]] and a [[Golden Globe Award]] nomination for his performance in the television remake of ''[[Rear Window (1998 film)|Rear Window]]'' (1998).

On May 27, 1995, Reeve was left [[Tetraplegia|quadriplegic]] after being thrown from a horse during an [[Equestrianism|equestrian]] competition in [[Culpeper, Virginia]]. He used a wheelchair and needed a portable ventilator to breathe for the rest of his life. He lobbied on behalf of people with [[Spinal cord injury|spinal cord injuries]] and for human embryonic [[stem cell research]], founding the [[Christopher Reeve Foundation]] and co-founding the Reeve-Irvine Research Center.&lt;ref name=ReeveDies&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.cnn.com/2004/SHOWBIZ/Movies/10/11/obit.reeve/|archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20041013041321/http://www.cnn.com/2004/SHOWBIZ/Movies/10/11/obit.reeve/|archivedate=2004-10-13|title=Christopher Reeve dies at 52|work=[[CNN]]|location=Atlanta, Georgia|date=October 11, 2004|accessdate=November 3, 2006}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Early life and education==
Christopher Reeve was born on September 25, 1952, in New York City, the son of Barbara Pitney Lamb (b. 1929), a journalist, and [[F. D. Reeve|Franklin D'Olier Reeve]] (1928-2013), a teacher, novelist, poet, and scholar. Reeve was of almost entirely [[English people|English]] ancestry, with many family lines that had been in America since the early 1600s.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|first=Lisa|last=Birnbach|title=True Prep: It's a Whole New Old World|publisher=Knopf Doubleday Publishing Group|location=New York City|page=33|ISBN= 978-0-307-59398-6}}&lt;/ref&gt; His paternal grandfather, Colonel Richard Henry Reeve, had been the [[Chief executive officer|CEO]] of [[Prudential Financial]] (when it was called Prudential Life Insurance Company) for over 25 years.

Reeve's father was a [[Princeton University]] graduate studying for a [[master's degree]] in [[Russian language|Russian]] at [[Columbia University]] prior to the birth of his son, Christopher. Despite being born wealthy, Franklin Reeve spent summers working at the docks with [[stevedore|longshoremen]]. Reeve's mother had been a student at [[Vassar College]] but transferred to [[Barnard College]] to be closer to Franklin, whom she had met through a family connection. They had another son, Benjamin, born on October 6, 1953.&lt;ref&gt;Reeve, Christopher (1998), pp 54–58&lt;/ref&gt;

Franklin and Barbara divorced in 1956, and she moved with her two sons to [[Princeton, New Jersey]], where they attended Nassau Street School. Later that year, Franklin Reeve married Helen Schmidinger, a [[Columbia University]] graduate student. Barbara Pitney Lamb married Tristam B. Johnson, a [[stockbroker]], in 1959. Johnson enrolled Christopher and his brother, Benjamin, in Princeton Country Day School, which later merged with Miss Fine's School for Girls to become the co-educational [[Princeton Day School]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|first=Libby|last=Hughes|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=jphd-qqGEgIC&amp;lpg=PA21&amp;dq=%22Princeton%20Day%20School%22&amp;pg=PA21#v=onepage&amp;q=%22Princeton%20Day%20School%22&amp;f=false|title=Christopher Reeve|publisher=[[iUniverse]]|location=Bloomington, Indiana|date=2004|page=21|ISBN=9780595326075}}&lt;/ref&gt; Reeve excelled academically, athletically, and onstage; he was on the [[Honors student|honor roll]] and played soccer, baseball, tennis, and hockey. The sportsmanship award at Princeton Day School's invitational hockey tournament was named in Reeve's honor. Reeve admitted that he put pressure on himself to act older than he actually was in order to gain his father's approval.&lt;ref&gt;Reeve, Christopher (1998), pp 58–68&lt;/ref&gt;

Reeve found his passion for acting in 1962 at age nine when he was cast in an amateur version of the operetta ''[[The Yeomen of the Guard]]''; it was the first of many student plays.&lt;ref&gt;Reeve, Christopher (1998), pp 70–71&lt;/ref&gt; In mid-1968, at age fifteen, Reeve was accepted as an [[apprentice]] at the [[Williamstown Theatre Festival]] in [[Williamstown, Massachusetts]]. The other apprentices were mostly college students, but Reeve's older appearance and maturity helped him fit in with the others. In a workshop, he played a scene from ''[[A View from the Bridge]]'' that was chosen to be presented in front of an audience. After the performance, actress [[Olympia Dukakis]] said to him, "I'm surprised. You've got a lot of talent. Don't mess it up."&lt;ref&gt;Reeve, Christopher (1998), pp 147–150&lt;/ref&gt; The next summer, Reeve was hired at the Harvard Summer Repertory Theater Company in [[Cambridge, Massachusetts|Cambridge]] for $44 per week. He played a Russian sailor in ''[[The Hostage (play)|The Hostage]]'' and Belyayev in ''[[A Month in the Country (play)|A Month in the Country]]''. Famed theater critic Elliot Norton called his performance as Belyayev "startlingly effective." The 23-year-old lead actress in the play, a [[Carnegie Mellon]] graduate, turned out to be Reeve's first romance. She was engaged to a fellow Carnegie Mellon graduate at the time; they mutually ended the relationship when he made a surprise visit to her dorm room at seven in the morning and found Reeve with her. Reeve's romance with the actress fizzled a few months later when the age difference became an issue.&lt;ref&gt;Reeve, Christopher (1998), pp 152–154&lt;/ref&gt; Reeve was briefly involved with [[Scientology]] but opted out of becoming a member. He subsequently voiced criticism of the organization.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book | last = Reeve | first = Christopher | title = Nothing Is Impossible: Reflections on a New Life | edition = Hardcover |date=September 2002 | publisher = Random House | isbn = 0-375-50778-7 | chapter = Religion}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news | last =Staff | title =Superman Christopher Reeve blasts Scientology | work =[[The Age]] | date =February 5, 2003}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Cornell===
After graduating from [[Princeton Day School]] in June 1970, Reeve acted in plays in [[Boothbay, Maine]]. He planned to go to New York City to find a career in theater. Ultimately, however, at the advice of his mother, he applied for college. He was accepted into [[Brown University|Brown]], [[Carnegie Mellon University|Carnegie Mellon]], [[Columbia University|Columbia]], [[Cornell University|Cornell]], [[Northwestern University|Northwestern]], and [[Princeton University|Princeton]]. Reeve said that he chose Cornell primarily because it was distanced from New York City and because of the temptations of working as an actor immediately versus finishing college, as he had promised his mother and step-father.&lt;ref&gt;Reeve, Christopher (1998), p 154&lt;/ref&gt; Reeve joined the theater department in Cornell, and played [[Pozzo (Waiting for Godot)|Pozzo]] in ''[[Waiting for Godot]]'', Segismundo in ''[[Life is a Dream|Life Is a Dream]]'', [[Hamlet]] in ''[[Rosencrantz and Guildenstern Are Dead]]'', and Polixenes in ''[[The Winter's Tale]]''.&lt;ref&gt;Reeve, Christopher (1998), pp 155–156&lt;/ref&gt; 

Late in his [[freshman]] year, Reeve received a letter from Stark Hesseltine, a high-powered New York City agent who had discovered [[Robert Redford]] and who represented actors such as [[Richard Chamberlain]], [[Michael Douglas]], and [[Susan Sarandon]]. Hesseltine had seen Reeve in ''A Month in the Country'' and wanted to represent him. Reeve was very excited and kept re-reading the letter to make sure of what it said. Reeve was impatient with school and anxious to get on with his career. The two met, but Reeve was surprised to find that Hesseltine strongly supported his promise to his mother and step-father to complete college. They decided that instead of dropping out of school, Reeve would come to New York once a month to meet casting agents and producers to find work for the summer vacation.&lt;ref&gt;Reeve, Christopher (1998), pp 157–159&lt;/ref&gt;

Reeve received favorable responses to his introductions and auditions arranged by Hesseltine but had to forgo several desirable opportunities because they began before school ended. That summer, he toured in a production of ''Forty Carats'' with [[Eleanor Parker]].&lt;ref&gt;Reeve, Christopher (1998), pp 157–159&lt;/ref&gt; The next year, Reeve received a full summer contract with the San Diego Shakespeare Festival, with roles as [[Edward IV]] in ''[[Richard III (play)|Richard III]]'', Fenton in ''[[The Merry Wives of Windsor]]'', and Dumaine in ''[[Love's Labour's Lost]]'' at the [[Old Globe Theatre]].&lt;ref&gt;Reeve, Christopher (1998), pp 160–161&lt;/ref&gt;

Before his third year of college, Reeve took a three-month leave of absence. He flew to [[Glasgow]] and saw theatrical productions throughout the United Kingdom. The actors inspired him, and he often had conversations with them in bars after the performances. He helped actors at the [[Old Vic]] with their American accents by reading the newspaper aloud for them. He then flew to Paris, where he spoke fluent French for his entire stay: he had studied it from third grade until his second year in Cornell. He watched many performances and immersed himself in the culture before finally returning to New York to reunite with his girlfriend.&lt;ref&gt;Reeve, Christopher (1998), pp 162–166&lt;/ref&gt;

===Juilliard===
After returning to the U.S. from Europe, Reeve chose to focus solely on acting, although Cornell University had several general education requirements for graduation that he had yet to complete. He managed to convince theater director Jim Clause and the [[Dean (education)|dean]] of the College of Arts and Sciences that, as a theater major, he would achieve more at [[Juilliard School|Juilliard]] ([[List of Juilliard School people|Group 4]], 1973–1975) than at Cornell. They agreed that his first year at Juilliard would be counted as his senior year at Cornell.&lt;ref&gt;Reeve, Christopher (1998), p 167&lt;/ref&gt;

In 1973, approximately 2000 students auditioned for 20 places in the freshman class at Juilliard. Reeve's audition was in front of 10 faculty members, including [[John Houseman]], who had just won an [[Academy Award]] for ''[[The Paper Chase (film)|The Paper Chase]]''. Reeve and [[Robin Williams]] were the only students selected for Juilliard's Advanced Program.&lt;ref&gt;Walker, Andrew. [http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/in_depth/uk/2000/newsmakers/1849218.stm "Christopher Reeve: Living in hope"] [[BBC News]], March 1, 2002, accessed November 19, 2006&lt;/ref&gt; They had several classes together in which they were the only students. In their [[dialect]]s class with Edith Skinner, Williams had no trouble mastering all dialects naturally, whereas Reeve was more meticulous about it. Williams and Reeve developed a close friendship.&lt;ref&gt;Reeve, Christopher (1501), pp 167–172&lt;/ref&gt;

In a meeting with John Houseman, Reeve was told, "Mr. Reeve. It is terribly important that you become a serious classical actor. Unless, of course, they offer you a shitload of money to do something else."&lt;ref name=HoltReeve&gt;Holt, Patricia. [http://www.sfgate.com/cgi-bin/article.cgi?file=/chronicle/archive/1998/05/11/DD55495.DTL Reeve is 'Superman' For Real: Actor's memoir filled with humor and courage.] ''[[San Francisco Chronicle]]'', May 11, 1998, accessed November 20, 2006&lt;/ref&gt; Houseman then offered him the chance to leave school and join the Acting Company, among performers such as [[Kevin Kline]], [[Patti LuPone]], and [[David Ogden Stiers]]. Reeve declined, as he had not yet received his [[bachelor's degree]] from Juilliard.&lt;ref&gt;Reeve, Christopher (1998), pp 172–173&lt;/ref&gt;

In early 1974, Reeve and other Juilliard students toured the New York City [[junior high school]] system and performed ''The Love Cure.'' In one performance, Reeve, who played the hero, drew his sword out too high and accidentally destroyed a row of lights above him. The students applauded and cheered. Reeve later said that this was the greatest ovation of his career.&lt;ref&gt;Reeve, Christopher (1998), pp 173–174&lt;/ref&gt; After completing his first year at Juilliard, Reeve graduated from Cornell in the Class of '74.

In late 1975, he auditioned for the [[Broadway theatre|Broadway]] play ''[[A Matter of Gravity]].'' [[Katharine Hepburn]] watched his audition and cast him as her character's grandson in the play. With Hepburn's influence over the [[CBS]] network, Reeve worked out the schedules of the soap opera ''[[Love of Life]]'' and the play so that he would be able to do both. Because of his busy schedule, he ate candy bars and drank coffee in place of meals and hence suffered from exhaustion and [[malnutrition]]. On the first night of the play's run, Reeve entered the stage, said his first line, and then promptly fainted. Hepburn turned to the audience and said, "This boy's a goddamn fool. He doesn't eat enough red meat." The [[understudy]] finished the play for Reeve, and a doctor treated him. The doctor advised Reeve to eat a more healthful diet. He stayed with the play throughout its year-long run and was given very favorable reviews. He and Hepburn became very close. She said, "You're going to be a big star, Christopher, and support me in my old age." He replied, "I can't wait ''that'' long." Some gossip columns rumored a romance between the two. Reeve said, "She was sixty-seven and I was twenty-two, but I thought that was quite an honor...I believe I was fairly close to what a child or grandchild might have been to her." Reeve said that his father, who was a professor of literature and came to many of the performances, was the man who most captivated Hepburn. When the play moved to [[Los Angeles, California|Los Angeles]] in 1976, Reeve&amp;nbsp;— to Hepburn's disappointment&amp;nbsp;— dropped out. They stayed in touch for years after the play's run. Reeve later regretted not staying closer and just sending messages back and forth.&lt;ref&gt;Reeve, Christopher (1998), pp 179–186&lt;/ref&gt;

Reeve's first role in a Hollywood film was a very small part as a junior submarine officer in the 1978 naval disaster movie ''[[Gray Lady Down]]''. He then acted in the play ''My Life'' at the [[Circle Repertory Company]] with friend [[William Hurt]].&lt;ref&gt;Reeve, Christopher (1998), pp 187–188&lt;/ref&gt;

==Career==
===Superman===
&lt;!--[[File:Clarksupescompare.jpg|thumb|right|Reeve as both [[Superman]] (left) and [[Clark Kent]] (right)]]--&gt;
During ''My Life'', Stark Hesseltine told Reeve that he had been asked to audition for the leading role as [[Clark Kent]]/[[Superman]] in the big budget film, ''[[Superman (1978 film)|Superman]]'' (1978). [[Lynn Stalmaster]], the casting director, put Reeve's picture and résumé on the top of the pile three separate times, only to have the producers throw it out each time. Through Stalmaster's persistent pleading, a meeting between director [[Richard Donner]], producer [[Ilya Salkind]], and Reeve was set in January 1977 at the [[Sherry Netherland Hotel]] on Fifth Avenue.&lt;ref&gt;Reeve, Christopher (1998), pp 188–189&lt;/ref&gt; The morning after the meeting, Reeve was sent a 300-page script. He was thrilled that the script took the subject matter seriously, and that Richard Donner's motto was ''[[verisimilitude]]''. Reeve immediately flew to London for a [[screen test]], and on the way was told that [[Marlon Brando]] was going to play [[Jor-El]] and [[Gene Hackman]] was going to play [[Lex Luthor]]. Reeve still did not think he had much of a chance. Though standing {{convert|6|ft|4|in|cm|abbr=on}}, he was a self-described "skinny [[White Anglo-Saxon Protestant|WASP]]." On the plane ride to London, he imagined how his approach to the role would be. He later said, "By the late 1970s, the masculine image had changed... Now it was acceptable for a man to show gentleness and vulnerability. I felt that the new Superman ought to reflect that contemporary male image." He based his portrayal of Clark Kent on [[Cary Grant]] in his role in ''[[Bringing Up Baby]]''. After the screen test, his driver said, "I'm not supposed to tell you this, but you've got the part."&lt;ref&gt;Reeve, Christopher (1998), pp 195–197&lt;/ref&gt;

Reeve was a talented all-around athlete.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.chrisreevehomepage.com/biography.html |title=Christopher Reeve biography|publisher=Chrisreevehomepage.com |date= |accessdate=July 9, 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt; Portraying the role of Superman would be a stretch for the young actor, but he was tall enough for the role and had the necessary blue eyes and handsome features. However, his physique was slim. He refused to wear fake muscles under the suit and instead went through an intense two-month training regimen that former British weightlifting champion [[David Prowse]] supervised. Prowse played [[Darth Vader]] in the suit in the original ''[[Star Wars]]'' films. The training regimen consisted of running in the morning, followed by two hours of [[Weight training|weightlifting]] and ninety minutes on the [[trampoline]]. In addition, Reeve doubled his food intake and adopted a high [[protein]] diet. He added {{convert|30|lb|kg|spell=in}} of muscle to his thin {{convert|189|lb|kg}} frame. He later made even higher gains for ''[[Superman III]]'' (1983), though for ''[[Superman IV: The Quest for Peace]]'' (1987), he decided it would be healthier to focus more on [[cardiovascular]] workouts.&lt;ref&gt;Harrington, O'Connor and Kavitsky, [http://www.chrisreevehomepage.com/m-movie1.html Superman (1978)], Christopher Reeve Homepage, accessed October 10, 2006&lt;/ref&gt; One of the reasons Reeve could not work out as much for ''[[Superman IV: The Quest for Peace]]'' was an emergency [[appendectomy]] he had in June 1986. &lt;ref&gt;Rossen, Jake. ''Superman Vs. Hollywood: How Fiendish Producers, Devious Directors, and Warring Writers Grounded an American Icon.'' Chicago: Chicago Review P, 2008. Print.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Anderson, Susan Heller and David W. Dunlap. "NEW YORK DAY BY DAY; Appendectomy Centenary." ''The New York Times''. The New York Times Company, 26 Jun. 1986. Web. 16 Aug. 2018.&lt;/ref&gt;

Reeve was never a Superman or [[comic book]] fan, though he had watched ''[[Adventures of Superman (TV series)|Adventures of Superman]]'' starring [[George Reeves]]. Reeve found the role offered a suitable challenge because it was a dual role. He said, "there must be some difference stylistically between Clark and Superman. Otherwise, you just have a pair of glasses standing in for a character."&lt;ref&gt;Bergan, Ronald. [http://film.guardian.co.uk/news/story/0,12589,1325258,00.html Christopher Reeve.] ''[[The Guardian]]'', October 12, 2004, accessed November 20, 2006&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Reeve, Christopher (1998), p 200&lt;/ref&gt;

On the commentary track for the director's edition of ''[[Superman II: The Richard Donner Cut]]'', [[creative consultant]] [[Tom Mankiewicz]] spoke of how Reeve had talked to him about playing Superman and then playing Clark Kent. Mankiewicz then corrected Reeve, telling him that he was always, ''always'' playing Superman and that when he was Clark Kent, he was "playing Superman who was playing Clark Kent." Mankiewicz described it to Reeve as a role within the role.

The film grossed $300,218,018 worldwide (unadjusted for [[inflation]]).&lt;ref&gt;[[Box Office Mojo]], [http://www.boxofficemojo.com/movies/?id=superman.htm Superman (1978)], accessed October 23, 2006&lt;/ref&gt; Reeve received positive reviews for his performance:
* "Christopher Reeve's entire performance is a delight. Ridiculously good-looking, with a face as sharp and strong as an ax blade, his bumbling, fumbling Clark Kent and omnipotent Superman are simply two styles of gallantry and innocence."&amp;nbsp;– ''[[Newsweek]]''
* "Christopher Reeve has become an instant international star on the basis of his first major movie role, that of Clark Kent/Superman. Film reviewers&amp;nbsp;— regardless of their opinion of the film&amp;nbsp;— have been almost unanimous in their praise of Reeve's dual portrayal. He is utterly convincing as he switches back and forth between personae."&amp;nbsp;– ''[[Starlog]]''
* Won a [[BAFTA]] Film Award for Most Promising Newcomer to Leading Film Roles.

Christopher Reeve also guest starred in ''[[Smallville]]'', the successful American television show about Clark Kent/Superman's childhood. He appeared as Doctor Virgil Swann, who helped Clark Kent understand his heritage. Reeve appeared as Doctor Swann in Seasons 2 and 3, until the character was ultimately "killed off". He appeared in two episodes titled "Rosetta" and "Legacy", while his death was made known in the fourth-season episode "Sacred".

Reeve used his celebrity status for several philanthropic causes. Through the [[Make-A-Wish Foundation]], he visited terminally ill children. He joined the Board of Directors for the worldwide charity [[Save the Children]]. In 1979, he served as a [[track and field]] coach at the [[Special Olympics]] alongside [[O. J. Simpson]].&lt;ref&gt;Reeve, Christopher (1998), p 201&lt;/ref&gt;

====Sequels====
Much of ''[[Superman II]]'' was filmed at the same time as the [[Superman (1978 film)|first film]]. After most of the footage had been shot, the producers had a disagreement with director [[Richard Donner]] over various matters, including money and special effects, and they mutually parted ways. Film director [[Richard Lester]], who had worked with the producers previously on the two-parter ''[[The Three Musketeers]]'' (1973) and ''[[The Four Musketeers (1974 film)|The Four Musketeers]]'' (1974), replaced Donner. Lester had the script changed and re-shot some footage. The cast was unhappy, but Reeve later said that he liked Lester and considered ''[[Superman II]]'' to be his favorite of the series.&lt;ref name=Reeve201203&gt;Reeve, Christopher (1898), pp 201–203&lt;/ref&gt; Because of fan encouragement and the June 2006 [[theatrical release]] of ''[[Superman Returns]]'', [[Richard Donner]]'s version of ''[[Superman II]]'' titled ''[[Superman II: The Richard Donner Cut]]'', was released on [[DVD]] in Nov. 2006, at the same time as the DVD release of ''[[Superman Returns]]''. ''[[Superman II: The Richard Donner Cut]]'' was dedicated in memory of Reeve.

Lester directed ''[[Superman III]]'', released in 1983, solo. Reeve believed that producers [[Alexander Salkind]], his son [[Ilya Salkind]], and [[Pierre Spengler]] decreased the [[credibility]] of ''[[Superman III]]'' by turning it into a [[Richard Pryor]] comedy and hence making it a not very good film. He missed Richard Donner and believed that ''[[Superman III]]'''s only really good element was the automobile [[wrecking yard|junkyard]] scene in which Evil Superman fights Good Clark Kent in an internal battle.&lt;ref name=Reeve201203/&gt; Reeve's portrayal of the Evil Superman was highly praised, though the film was critically panned. Any negative review for ''[[Superman III]]'', however, was nothing compared to the totally negative reception its [[Superman IV: The Quest for Peace|successor]] would receive.

''[[Superman IV: The Quest for Peace]]'' was released in 1987. After ''[[Superman III]]'', Reeve vowed that he was done with Superman.&lt;ref&gt;Cosford, Bill. [http://nl.newsbank.com/nl-search/we/Archives?p_product=MH&amp;s_site=miami&amp;p_multi=MH&amp;p_theme=realcities&amp;p_action=search&amp;p_maxdocs=200&amp;p_topdoc=1&amp;p_text_direct-0=0EB35CC479B535BE&amp;p_field_direct-0=document_id&amp;p_perpage=10&amp;p_sort=YMD_date:D&amp;s_trackval=GooglePM After One Final Fling, Reeve Hangs Up His Cape.] ''[[Miami Herald]]'', June 19, 1983, pg 1L. Accessed November 19, 2006&lt;/ref&gt; However, he agreed to continue the role in a fourth film on the condition that he would have partial creative control over the script. The [[nuclear disarmament]] plot was his idea. [[Cannon Films]] purchased the production rights to the character of [[Superman]] from [[Alexander Salkind]] and his son [[Ilya Salkind]], the original producers of the film series, in the mid-1980s.&lt;ref&gt;Harper, Oliver. "Superman IV (1987) Retrospective / Review." ''YouTube.'' YouTube, 6 Jun. 2013. Web. 16 Aug. 2018.&lt;/ref&gt; [[Cannon Films]] were known for low-budget, poorly acted, poorly scripted action films.&lt;ref&gt;Lamble, Ryan. "10 Remarkable Things About Supeman IV: The Quest for Peace." ''Den of Geek!''. Dennis Publishing, 15 Nov. 2012. Web. 16 Aug. 2018.&lt;/ref&gt; They cut the budget of ''[[Superman IV: The Quest for Peace|Superman IV]]'' in half to $17 million. The film was both a critical failure and a [[box office bomb|box office disappointment]], becoming the lowest grossing [[Superman in film|Superman film]] to date. Reeve later said, "the less said about ''[[Superman IV]]'' the better."&lt;ref name=Reeve201203/&gt; Both of Reeve's children from his relationship with Gae Exton had uncredited appearances in a deleted scene in which Superman rescues a girl, played by his daughter Alexandra, and reunites her with her brother, played by his son Matthew, after Nuclear Man creates a tornado in [[Smallville (comics)|Smallville]].

Reeve would have made a fifth [[Superman]] film after the rights to the character reverted to [[Alexander Salkind]], [[Ilya Salkind]], and [[Pierre Spengler]] if said film had a budget the same size as that of ''[[Superman (1978 film)|Superman: The Movie]]''. Although there was potential for such a film in the late 1980s after [[Cannon Films]] went [[bankruptcy|bankrupt]], Reeve never received any script.&lt;ref&gt;capedwonder.superman. "Christopher Reeve at Dixie Trek - Part Two." ''YouTube''. YouTube, 24 Jul. 2012. Web. 20 Aug. 2018.&lt;/ref&gt;

In 1993, two years before Reeve's accident, the Salkinds sold the [[rights]] to the character of Superman again, this time to [[Warner Bros.]] at large.&lt;ref&gt;"Superman in film." ''Wikipedia''. Wikimedia Foundation, 29 Jul. 2018. Web. 20 Aug. 2018.&lt;/ref&gt;    "There was supposed to be a fifth Superman movie titled ''[[Superman Reborn]]'', but because of studio shifts, the terrible box office [''[[Superman IV]]''] got, and...Reeves's [sic] accident, it never saw the light of day."&lt;ref&gt;Adam Does Movies. "The Best &amp; Worst Superman Movies Ranked : Movie Feuds ep156." ''YouTube.'' YouTube, 17 Nov. 2015. Web. 20 Aug. 2018.&lt;/ref&gt;

===1980–1986===
&lt;!--[[File:Somewhere in Time scene.jpg|thumb|upright|With Jane Seymour in ''Somewhere in Time'' (1980)]]--&gt;
Reeve's first role after 1978's ''[[Superman (1978 film)|Superman]]'' was as Richard Collier in the 1980 [[romance film|romantic]] [[fantasy]] ''[[Somewhere in Time (film)|Somewhere in Time]]''. [[Jane Seymour (actress)|Jane Seymour]] played Elise McKenna, his love interest. The film was shot on [[Mackinac Island]] in mid-1979 and was Reeve's favorite film ever to shoot. After the film was completed, the plan was for a limited release and to build word of mouth, but early test screenings were favorable and the studio decided on a wide release, which ultimately proved to be the wrong strategy. Early reviews savaged the film as overly sentimental and [[melodramatic]], and an actors' [[strike action|strike]] prevented Reeve and Seymour from doing publicity. The film quickly closed, although [[Jean-Pierre Dorléac]] was nominated for an [[Academy Award for Best Costume Design]] in 1980. The film, commercially unsuccessful, was Reeve's first public disappointment. Almost 10 years after ''[[Somewhere in Time (film)|Somewhere in Time]]'' was released, it became a [[cult film]], thanks to screenings on cable networks and [[video rentals]]; its popularity began to grow, vindicating the belief of the creative team. INSITE, the International Network of ''Somewhere in Time'' Enthusiasts, did fundraising to sponsor a star on the [[Hollywood Walk of Fame]] in 1997 for Reeve. Jane Seymour became a personal friend of Reeve and in 1996 named one of her twin sons Kristopher in his honor.&lt;ref&gt;Reeve, Christopher (1998), pp 204–207&lt;/ref&gt;

In that same year, he made a guest appearance on ''[[The Muppet Show]]'', where he performed "[[East of the Sun (and West of the Moon)]]" on a piano for [[Miss Piggy]], who had a [[limerence|crush]] on him. Reeve denied being [[Superman]] but displayed the superpowers throughout that entire episode. He then returned to continue filming on the not yet finished production of ''[[Superman II]]''.

Gae Exton, Reeve's partner at the time, gave birth to their son, [[Matthew Reeve|Matthew Exton Reeve]], on December 20, 1979, at Welbeck Hospital in [[London]], [[England]]. After finishing ''[[Superman II]]'', the family left [[London]] and rented a house in [[Hollywood Hills]]. Soon after, Reeve grew tired of [[Hollywood]] and took the family to [[Williamstown, Massachusetts]], where he played the lead in the successful play ''[[The Front Page]]'', directed by [[Robert Allan Ackerman]]. Later in the year, Reeve played a disabled [[Vietnam veteran]] in the Broadway play ''Fifth of July''. In his research for the role, he was coached by an amputee on how to walk on [[artificial]] [[legs]].&lt;ref name=Reeve207212&gt;Reeve, Christopher (1998), pp 207–212&lt;/ref&gt;

After ''Fifth of July'', Reeve stretched his acting range further and played a homicidal novice [[playwright]] trying to kill his lover and [[mentor]] [[Michael Caine]] in [[Sidney Lumet]]'s [[dark comedy]] film ''[[Deathtrap (film)|Deathtrap]]'' based on the play by [[Ira Levin]]. The film was well received. After ''[[Superman II]]'', Reeve portrayed partially [[corrupt]] Catholic priest John Flaherty in ''[[Monsignor (film)|Monsignor]]''. Reeve felt this gave him the opportunity to play "a morally ambiguous character who was neither clearly good nor clearly bad, someone to whom life is much more complex than the characters I've played previously".&lt;ref name="Christopher Reeve Homepage"&gt;[http://www.chrisreevehomepage.com/m-monsignor.html Christopher Reeve Homepage]&lt;/ref&gt; Reeve blamed the failure of the film on poor [[editing]]. He said "the movie is sort of a series of outrageous incidents that you find hard to believe. Since they don't have a focus, and since they aren't justified and explained, they become laughable".&lt;ref name="Christopher Reeve Homepage"/&gt;

Reeve was then offered the role of Basil Ransom in ''[[The Bostonians (film)|The Bostonians]]'' alongside [[Vanessa Redgrave]]. Though Reeve ordinarily commanded over one million dollars per film, the producers could only afford to pay him one-tenth of that. Reeve had no complaints, as he was happy to be doing a role of which he could be proud. The film exceeded expectations and did very well at the [[box office]] for what was considered to be an [[art film|art house film]]. ''[[The New York Times]]'' called it "the best adaptation of a literary work yet made for the screen."&lt;ref name=Reeve207212/&gt; Katharine Hepburn called Reeve to tell him that he was "absolutely marvelous" and "captivating" in the film. When he told her that he was currently shooting ''[[Anna Karenina (1985 film)|Anna Karenina]]'', she said, "Oh, that's a terrible mistake."&lt;ref&gt;Reeve, Christopher (1998), p 183&lt;/ref&gt;

Reeve was a [[licensed]] [[aircraft pilot|pilot]] and flew solo across the [[Atlantic]] twice. During the filming of ''[[Superman III]]'', he raced his [[sailplane]] in his free time. He joined The Tiger Club, a group of [[aviator]]s who had served in the [[Royal Air Force]] in the [[Battle of Britain]]. They let him participate in mock dogfights in vintage [[World War I]] [[combat]] [[airplane|plane]]s. The producers of the film ''[[The Aviator (1985 film)|The Aviator]]'' approached him without knowing that he was a pilot and that he knew how to fly a [[Stearman Aircraft|Stearman]], the plane used in the film. Reeve readily accepted the role. The film was shot in [[Kranjska Gora]], and Reeve did all his own [[stunts]]. At this time, Gae Exton gave birth to their second [[child]], Alexandra Exton Reeve, in December 1983 at [[London Welbeck Hospital|Welbeck Hospital]] in London, England.&lt;ref&gt;Reeve, Christopher (1998), pp 216–219&lt;/ref&gt;

In 1984, Reeve appeared in ''[[The Aspern Papers]]'' with [[Vanessa Redgrave]]. He then played Tony in ''[[The Royal Family (play)|The Royal Family]]'' and the Count in ''[[Marriage of Figaro]]'', a very [[notability|famous]] [[opera buffa]] by [[Mozart]].

In 1985, Reeve hosted the television documentary ''[[Dinosaur!]]'' Fascinated with dinosaurs since he was a kid, as he says in the documentary, he flew himself to New York in his own plane to shoot on location at the [[American Museum of Natural History]]. Also, in 1985, [[DC Comics]] named Reeve as one of the honorees in the company's 50th-anniversary [[publication]] ''[[Fifty Who Made DC Great]]'' for his work on the [[Superman film series]].&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite comic| writer = Marx, Barry| cowriters = [[Joey Cavalieri|Cavalieri, Joey]] and Hill, Thomas| artist = Petruccio, Steven | editor = Marx, Barry| story = Christopher Reeve Superman Becomes a Blockbuster| title = Fifty Who Made DC Great| date = 1985| publisher = DC Comics| page = 44| panel = | id = }}&lt;/ref&gt;

In 1986, he was still struggling to find scripts that he liked. A script named ''[[Street Smart (film)|Street Smart]]'' had been lying in his house for years, and after re-reading it, he had [[Cannon Films]] [[green-light]] it. He starred opposite [[Morgan Freeman]], who was nominated for his first [[Academy Award]] for the film. The film received excellent [[reviews]] but performed poorly at the [[box office]], possibly because [[Cannon Films]] had failed to properly [[advertise]] it.&lt;ref&gt;Reeve, Christopher (1998), pp 221–224, 228&lt;/ref&gt;

===1987–1989===
After ''[[Superman IV]]'' in 1987, Reeve's relationship with Exton fell apart, and they separated. He moved to [[New York City|New York]] without his [[children]]. He became [[depression (mood)|depressed]] and decided that doing a [[comedy]] might be good for him. He was given a lead in ''[[Switching Channels]]''. [[Burt Reynolds]] and [[Kathleen Turner]] had a feud during filming, which made the time even more unbearable for Reeve. Reeve later stated that he made a fool of himself in the film and that most of his time was spent refereeing between Reynolds and Turner. The film did poorly, and Reeve believed that it marked the end of his [[movie star]] [[career]]. He spent the next years mostly doing plays. He tried out for the [[Richard Gere]] role in ''[[Pretty Woman]]'' but walked out on the [[audition]] because they had a half-hearted casting director fill in for [[Julia Roberts]].&lt;ref&gt;Reeve, Christopher (1998), pp 225–231&lt;/ref&gt;

Five months after separating from Gae Exton and after filming ''[[Switching Channels]]'', he went back to Williamstown with his children, Matthew and Alexandra, who were seven and three respectively. Reeve watched a group of singers called the Cabaret Corps perform, and took notice of one of the singers, [[Dana Reeve|Dana Morosini]]. The two began dating and were married in Williamstown in April 1992.&lt;ref&gt;Reeve, Christopher (1998), pp 82–94&lt;/ref&gt;

[[File:Ronald Reagan Christopher Reeve.jpg|thumb|Christopher Reeve, [[Frank Gifford]], [[Ronald Reagan]] at a reception and picnic in honor of the 15th anniversary of the [[Special Olympics]] program in the Diplomatic Reception room May 1983]]
In the late 1980s, Reeve became more active. He was taking horse-riding lessons and trained five to six days a week for competition in combined training events. He built a sailboat, ''The Sea Angel,'' and sailed from the [[Chesapeake Bay|Chesapeake]] to [[Nova Scotia]]. He campaigned for Senator [[Patrick Leahy]] and made speeches throughout the state. He served as a board member for the Charles Lindbergh Fund, which promotes environmentally safe technologies. He lent support to causes such as [[Amnesty International]], the [[Natural Resources Defense Council]], and [[People for the American Way]]. He joined the Environmental Air Force and used his Cheyenne II [[turboprop]] plane to take government officials and journalists over areas of environmental damage. In late 1987, in [[Santiago, Chile]], the [[country]]'s [[dictator]], [[Augusto Pinochet]], threatened to execute 77 [[actors]]. [[Ariel Dorfman]] asked Reeve to help save their lives. Reeve flew to [[Chile]] and helped lead a protest march. A [[cartoon]] then ran in a newspaper showing him carrying Pinochet by the collar with the caption, "Where will you take him, Superman?" For his heroics, he was awarded the ''Grand Cross of the Bernardo O'Higgins Order,'' the highest [[Chile]]an [[award|distinction]] for foreigners. He also received the ''Obie Prize'' and the Annual Walter Brielh Human Rights Foundation award.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.falkland-malvinas.com/Detalle.asp?NUM=3192 |title=Chile honours Christopher Reeve, Superman |publisher=Falkland-malvinas.com |date= |accessdate=July 9, 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt; Reeve's friend [[Ron Silver]] later started the [[Creative Coalition]], an organization designed to teach celebrities how to speak knowledgeably about political issues. Reeve was an early member of the group, along with [[Susan Sarandon]], [[Alec Baldwin]], and [[Blythe Danner]].&lt;ref&gt;Reeve, Christopher (1998), pp 235–239&lt;/ref&gt;

===1990–1994===
In 1990, Reeve starred in the Civil War film ''[[The Rose and the Jackal]]'', in which he played [[Allan Pinkerton]], the head of [[President of the United States|President]] [[Abraham Lincoln|Lincoln]]'s new Secret Service. Dana gave birth to William Elliot "Will" Reeve on June 7, 1992, at [[North Adams Regional Hospital]] in [[North Adams, Massachusetts]]. In October, Reeve was offered the part of Lewis in ''[[The Remains of the Day (film)|The Remains of the Day]]''. The [[screenplay|script]] was one of the best he had read, and he unhesitatingly took the part. The film was deemed an instant [[classic]] and was nominated for eight [[Academy Awards]].&lt;ref&gt;Reeve, Christopher (1998), pp 232–235&lt;/ref&gt;

In the early 1990s, Reeve was in three roles for television in which he was cast as a [[villain]].&lt;ref name="Christopher Reeve home page"&gt;[http://www.chrisreevehomepage.com/m-bumpnight.html Christopher Reeve home page]&lt;/ref&gt; The most notable of these was ''Bump in the Night'' based on the novel by Isabelle Holland in which Reeve played a child molester who abducts a young boy in New York City. The movie got fair to positive reviews.&lt;ref&gt;Weiskind, Ron. ''"Bump" Stars Go Against Type''. Pittsburgh Post-Gazette, January 4, 1991. P. 24&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://articles.latimes.com/1991-01-05/entertainment/ca-6785_1_suspense-movie Suspense Tale of Two Evils in 'Bump in the Night'] Los Angeles Times&lt;/ref&gt; Reeve felt it was important for parents of young children to see the film. It is on [[home video]] in the UK, but not in the US.&lt;ref name="Christopher Reeve home page"/&gt;

In another television movie, ''Mortal Sins'' (1992), Reeve for the second time played a Catholic priest, this time hearing the confessions of a serial murderer in a role reminiscent of that of [[Montgomery Clift]] in [[Hitchcock]]'s ''[[I Confess (film)|I Confess]]''.

In 1994, Reeve was elected as a co-president of the Creative Coalition. The organization's work was noticed nationwide, and the [[Democratic Party (United States)|Democratic Party]] asked Reeve to run for the [[United States Congress]]. He replied, "Run for Congress? And lose my influence in Washington?" At this time, he had received scripts for ''[[Picket Fences]]'' and ''[[Chicago Hope]]'' and was asked by [[CBS]] if he wanted to start his own television series. This meant moving to Los Angeles, which would place him even further from Matthew and Alexandra, who lived in London. In Massachusetts, Reeve could take a [[Concorde]] and see them anytime. He declined the offers. Reeve did not mind making trips, however; he went to [[New Mexico]] to shoot ''[[Speechless (1994 film)|Speechless]]'', co-starring [[Michael Keaton]] who, like Reeve, also portrayed a famous [[DC Comics]] superhero on film: [[Batman]]. Reeve then went to [[Point Reyes]] to shoot [[John Carpenter]]'s film ''[[Village of the Damned (1995 film)|Village of the Damned]]'', a [[remake]] of a 1960 British movie of the same name. Both of these films with this title were based on the 1957 novel ''[[The Midwich Cuckoos]]'' by [[John Wyndham]].&lt;ref&gt;"''The Midwich Cuckoos''." ''Wikipedia.'' Wikimedia Foundation, 24 Jul. 2018. Web. 17 Aug. 2018.&lt;/ref&gt;

Shortly before his accident, Reeve played a paralyzed police officer in the [[HBO]] movie ''[[Above Suspicion (1995 film)|Above Suspicion]]''. He did [[research]] at a [[Physical medicine and rehabilitation|rehabilitation]] hospital in [[Van Nuys]] and learned how to use a wheelchair to get in and out of cars. Reeve was then offered the lead in ''[[Kidnapped (1995 film)|Kidnapped]]'', to be shot in [[Ireland]]. He was excited to be going to Ireland, and he and Dana decided that they would conceive their second child there. Reeve also planned to direct his first big screen film, a romantic comedy entitled ''Tell Me True''. Not long after making these plans, the family went to [[Culpeper, Virginia]], for an equestrian competition.&lt;ref&gt;Reeve, Christopher (1998), pp 240–242&lt;/ref&gt;

===Roles turned down by Reeve===

====1978–1984====
Following the first Superman movie, Reeve realized that Hollywood producers wanted him to be an action star. He later said, "I found most of the scripts of that genre poorly constructed, and I felt the starring roles could easily be played by anyone with a strong physique." In addition, he did not feel that he was right for the other films he was offered and turned down the lead roles in ''[[American Gigolo]]'', ''[[The World According to Garp (film)|The World According to Garp]]'', ''[[Splash (film)|Splash]]'', ''[[Fatal Attraction]]'', ''[[Pretty Woman]]'', ''[[Romancing the Stone]]'', ''[[Lethal Weapon]],'' and ''[[Body Heat]]''. [[Katharine Hepburn]] recommended Reeve to [[David Lean]] for the role of [[Fletcher Christian]] in ''[[The Bounty (1984 film)|The Bounty]]'', a film version of ''Mutiny on the Bounty'' starring [[Anthony Hopkins]]. After considering it, Reeve decided that he would be miscast, and Lean went with his second choice, [[Mel Gibson]].&lt;ref&gt;Reeve, Christopher (1998), pp 203–204&lt;/ref&gt;

====2001====
Prior to the filming of ''[[Hannibal (film)|Hannibal]]'', Reeve was offered the part of primary antagonist Mason Verger, based on his work as a wheelchair-using police officer in ''[[Above Suspicion (1995 film)|Above Suspicion]]''. Not having read [[Hannibal (Harris novel)|the novel]], Reeve was initially enthusiastic about the opportunity. However, upon realizing that Verger was a quadriplegic, facially disfigured child rapist, Reeve withdrew from the project in disgust. The role was accepted by secondary choice [[Gary Oldman]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|last=Llenden|first=Joseph|date=June 2003|title=You Offered Me ''What''?! Roles Rejected By Great Actors|journal=[[Total Film]]|publisher=[[Future plc]]}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Johnson, Malcolm. [http://articles.courant.com/2004-10-12/news/0410120848_1_christopher-reeve-recalls-audition/2 "A Heroic Persona"]. ''[[Hartford Courant]]''. October 12, 2004. Retrieved July 22, 2012.&lt;/ref&gt;

==Injury==
{{see also|Superman curse}}
Reeve began his involvement in [[horse riding]] in 1985 after learning to ride for the film ''[[Anna Karenina (1985 film)|Anna Karenina]]''. He was initially [[allergic]] to horses, so he took [[antihistamines]]. He trained on [[Martha's Vineyard]], and by 1989, he began [[eventing]]. His allergies soon disappeared.&lt;ref&gt;Reeve, Christopher (1998), pp 6–9&lt;/ref&gt; He had suffered leg [[injuries]] as a teen while skiing, and he later broke three ribs in a riding accident he described, along with the leg injuries, on ''[[The Tonight Show]]'' in March 1987.

Reeve purchased a 12-year-old American [[thoroughbred]] horse named Eastern Express, nicknamed "Buck" while filming ''[[Village of the Damned (1995 film)|Village of the Damned]]''. He trained with Buck in 1994 and planned to do Training Level events in 1995 and move up to Preliminary in 1996. Though Reeve had originally signed up to compete at an event in [[Vermont]], his coach invited him to go to the Commonwealth Dressage and Combined Training Association finals at the Commonwealth Park equestrian center in [[Culpeper, Virginia]]. Reeve finished in fourth place out of 27 in the [[dressage]], before walking his cross-country course. He was concerned about jumps 16 and 17 but paid little attention to the third jump, which was a routine three-foot-three fence shaped like the letter 'W'.&lt;ref&gt;Reeve, Christopher (1998), pp 14–18&lt;/ref&gt;

On May 27, 1995, Reeve's horse made a [[Refusal (horse)|refusal]]. Witnesses said that the horse began the third fence jump and suddenly stopped. Reeve fell forward off the horse, holding on to the reins. His hands somehow became tangled in the [[reins]], and the [[bridle]] and [[Horse tack#Bits|bit]] were pulled off the horse. He landed head first on the far side of the fence, shattering his [[Atlas (anatomy)|first]] and [[Axis (anatomy)|second vertebrae]]. This [[cervical spinal injury]], which [[paralysis|paralyzed]] him from the neck down,&lt;ref&gt;Romano, Lois. [https://www.washingtonpost.com/wp-dyn/articles/A99660-1995Jun1.html Riding Accident Paralyzes Actor Christopher Reeve.] ''[[Washington Post]]'', June 1, 1995, pg. A01. Accessed November 19, 2006&lt;/ref&gt; also halted his breathing. Paramedics arrived three minutes later and immediately took measures to get air into his lungs. He was taken first to the local hospital, before being flown by helicopter to the [[University of Virginia Health System|University of Virginia Medical Center]].&lt;ref&gt;Reeve, Christopher (1998), pp 18–25&lt;/ref&gt; Afterwards, he had no recollection of the accident. Because of Reeve's injury, [[Armand Assante]] replaced him for the role of Alan Breck Stewart in ''[[Kidnapped (1995 film)|Kidnapped]]''.

===Recovery===
For the first few days after the [[accident]], Reeve suffered from [[delirium]], woke up sporadically and would mouth words to Dana such as "Get the gun" and "They're after us." After five days, he regained full consciousness, and his doctor explained to him that he had destroyed his first and second cervical vertebrae, which meant that his skull and spine were not connected. His lungs were filling with fluid and were suctioned by entry through the throat; this was said to be the most painful part of Reeve's recovery.&lt;ref&gt;Reeve, Christopher (1998), pp 27–30&lt;/ref&gt;

After considering his situation, believing that not only would he never walk again, but that he might never move a body part again, Reeve considered [[suicide]]. He mouthed to Dana, "Maybe we should let me go." She tearfully replied, "I am only going to say this once: I will support whatever you want to do because this is your life, and your decision. But I want you to know that I'll be with you for the long haul, no matter what. You're still you. And I love you." Reeve never considered [[euthanasia]] as an option again.&lt;ref&gt;Reeve, Christopher (1998), p 32&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Crews, Chip. [https://www.washingtonpost.com/wp-srv/style/features/reeve.htm The Role He Can't Escape.] ''[[Washington Post]]'', May 3, 1998, accessed November 19, 2006&lt;/ref&gt;

Reeve went through inner anguish in the [[Intensive care unit|ICU]], particularly when he was alone during the night. His approaching operation to reattach his skull to his spine in June 1995 "was frightening to contemplate. ... I already knew that I had only a fifty-fifty chance of surviving the surgery. ... Then, at an especially bleak moment, the door flew open and in hurried a squat fellow with a blue scrub hat and a yellow surgical gown and glasses, speaking in a Russian accent." The man announced that he was a [[proctologist]] and was going to perform a [[rectal exam]] on Reeve. It was [[Robin Williams]], reprising his character from the film ''[[Nine Months]]''. Reeve wrote: "For the first time since the accident, I laughed. My old friend had helped me know that somehow I was going to be okay."&lt;ref&gt;Reeve, Christopher (1998), p 36&lt;/ref&gt;

Dr. [[John A. Jane]] performed surgery to repair Reeve's neck [[vertebra]]e. He put wires underneath both [[Lamina of the vertebral arch|laminae]] and used bone from Reeve's hip to fit between the C1 and C2 [[vertebrae]]. He inserted a [[titanium]] pin and fused the wires with the vertebrae, then drilled holes in Reeve's skull and fitted the wires through to secure the skull to the [[spinal column]].&lt;ref&gt;Reeve, Christopher (1998), p 37&lt;/ref&gt;

===Rehabilitation===
On June 28, 1995, Reeve was taken to the [[Kessler Institute for Rehabilitation|Kessler Rehabilitation Center]] in [[West Orange, New Jersey]]. He was given several [[blood transfusion]]s in the first few weeks because of very low [[hemoglobin]] and [[protein]] levels. Many times his [[Medical ventilator|breathing tube]] would become disconnected and he would be at the mercy of nurses to come in and save his life.&lt;ref name=HoltReeve/&gt;

At the Institute, one of his aides was a [[Jamaica]]n man named Glenn Miller, nicknamed Juice, who helped him learn how to get into the shower and how to use a powered [[wheelchair]], which was activated by blowing air through a straw. Miller and Reeve would watch the film ''[[Cool Runnings]]'' and joke about Reeve directing the sequel, ''Bobsled Two''.&lt;ref&gt;Reeve, Christopher (1998), pp 98–109&lt;/ref&gt;

Whilst in [[Israel]], Reeve had shown significant improvement to his condition. Earlier, he had shown [[skill|ability]] to move his left hand [[index finger]], later progressing further by regaining back ability to move his arms and legs to a certain extent.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |url=https://www.nytimes.com/2002/09/12/us/actor-regains-some-movement-doctor-says.html?nytmobile=0 |title=Actor Regains Some Movement, Doctor Says |last=Blakeslee |first=Sandra |date=September 12, 2002 |work=The New York Times |access-date=July 16, 2018}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Research in Israel===
In July 2003, Christopher Reeve's continuing frustration with the pace of [[stem cell]] research in the U.S. led him to [[Israel]],&lt;ref name="U.S."&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.usnews.com/usnews/news/articles/030811/11spotlight.htm |title=Superhero Flies To Israel, by Larry Derfner |publisher=U.S. News &amp; World Report |date=August 11, 2003 |accessdate=July 9, 2013 |deadurl=yes |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20130921055954/http://www.usnews.com/usnews/news/articles/030811/11spotlight.htm |archivedate=September 21, 2013 }}&lt;/ref&gt; a country that was then, according to him, at the center of [[spinal cord injury research|research in spinal cord injury]].&lt;ref name="YouTube" /&gt;&lt;ref name="21c"&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.ujc.org/page.aspx?id=45235 |title=Christopher Reeve: Israel at Center of World Research on Paralysis, Israel21c|publisher=Ujc.org |date=July 27, 2003 |accessdate=July 9, 2013}}{{dead link|date=March 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt; Israel's Ministry of Foreign Affairs invited him to seek out the best treatment for his condition. During his visit, Reeve called the experience "a privilege" and said, "Israel has very proactive rehab facilities, excellent medical schools and teaching hospitals, and an absolutely first-rate research infrastructure."&lt;ref name="YouTube" /&gt;&lt;ref name="BBC"&gt;{{cite news|url=http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/low/entertainment/3112737.stm |title=Reeve boosted by Israel trip |publisher=BBC News |date=July 31, 2003 |accessdate=July 9, 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Throughout his intensive tour, Reeve visited [[Sheba Medical Center]], [[ALYN Hospital]], [[Weizmann Institute of Science]], and [[Technion – Israel Institute of Technology]], among many other places. After meeting dozens of Israeli [[patients]] who had undergone groundbreaking recovery processes and made remarkable progress, Reeve was in awe&lt;ref name="BBC" /&gt; and described the feeling as "almost overwhelming". He explained, "The research progresses more rapidly in Israel than almost anywhere else I can think of. The decision they made about stem cells, where they had a debate and decided that secular law must prevail over religious teachings, is something that we need to learn in the United States."&lt;ref name="YouTube"&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=keNu6kHg2T8 |title=Christopher Reeve: Trip to Israel July 2003 |publisher=Youtube.com |date=November 3, 2008 |accessdate=July 9, 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Reeve discussed his trip to Israel on [[CNN]]'s ''[[Larry King Live]]'' while he was in [[Tel Aviv]]. When asked what Israel is doing that other countries are not, Reeve responded, "They have a very progressive atmosphere here. They have [[socialized medicine]] so that doctors and patients do not have the problem of profit or trying to get insurance companies to pay for treatment. They also work very well together. They share their knowledge. This is a country of six million people about the size of [[Long Island]], and everyone works together very tremendously. The people of the country benefit from that."&lt;ref name="CNN"&gt;{{cite news|url=http://transcripts.cnn.com/TRANSCRIPTS/0307/30/lkl.00.html |title=Interview with Christopher Reeve, CNN: Larry King Live, Aired July 30, 2003 |publisher=Transcripts.cnn.com |date= |accessdate=July 9, 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Israelis were very receptive to Reeve's visit, calling him an inspiration to all and urging him never to give up hope.&lt;ref name="YouTube" /&gt;

==Activism==
Reeve left Kessler feeling inspiration from the other patients he had met. Because the [[mass media|media]] was constantly covering him,, he decided to use his name to put focus on [[Spinal cord injury|spinal cord injuries]]. In 1996, he appeared at the [[68th Academy Awards|Academy Awards]] to a long standing ovation and gave a speech about [[Hollywood]]'s duty to make movies that face the world's most important issues head-on. He also hosted the [[Paralympics]] in [[Atlanta]] and spoke at the [[Democratic National Convention]]. He traveled across the country to make speeches, never needing a [[teleprompter]] or a script. For these efforts, he was placed on the cover of ''[[Time (magazine)|TIME]]'' on August 26, 1996.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|author=iPad iPhone Android TIME TV Populist The Page |url=http://www.time.com/time/covers/0,16641,26-08-1996,00.html |title=TIME Magazine Cover: Christopher Reeve|publisher=Time.com |date=August 26, 1996 |accessdate=July 9, 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt; In the same year, he narrated the [[HBO]] film ''[[Without Pity: A Film About Abilities]]''. The film won the [[Emmy Award]] for "Outstanding Informational Special". He then acted in a small role in the film ''A Step Towards Tomorrow''.&lt;ref name="Biography"&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.chrisreevehomepage.com/biography.html |title=Biography |publisher=Chrisreevehomepage.com |date= |accessdate=July 9, 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Reeve was elected Chairman of the American Paralysis Association and Vice Chairman of the National Organization on Disability. He co-founded the Reeve-Irvine Research Center, which is now one of the leading spinal cord [[research centers]] in the world.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=About The Center|url=http://www.reeve.uci.edu/about.html|website=Reeve-Irvin Research Center|accessdate=September 4, 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt; He created the [[Christopher Reeve Foundation]], now the [[Christopher and Dana Reeve Foundation]], to speed up research through funding and to use grants to improve the quality of the lives of people with disabilities. The Foundation to date has given more than $65 million to research and more than $8.5 million in quality-of-life grants.&lt;ref&gt;Christopher Reeve Foundation, [https://web.archive.org/web/20051210041651/http://www.christopherreeve.org/site/c.geIMLPOpGjF/b.1029295/k.64F6/Quality_of_Life_Grants.htm Quality of Life Grants], accessed October 23, 2006&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Christopher Reeve Foundation, [https://web.archive.org/web/20061102130139/http://www.christopherreeve.org/atf/cf/%7B219882E9-DFFF-4CC0-95EE-3A62423C40EC%7D/AnnualReport_05.pdf Annual Report]&lt;/ref&gt; The Foundation has funded a new technology called "Locomotor Training" that uses a treadmill to mimic the movements of walking to help develop neural connections, in effect re-teaching the spinal cord how to send signals to the legs to walk. This technology has helped several paralyzed patients walk again.&lt;ref&gt;[[ABC News]], [https://www.yahoo.com/s/456999 Medical Miracle: To Walk Again]{{dead link|date=March 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt; Of Christopher Reeve, [[University of California, Irvine|UC Irvine]] said, "in the years following his injury, Christopher did more to promote research on spinal cord injury and other neurological disorders than any other person before or since".&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.reeve.uci.edu/chrisreeve/index.php Reeve–Irvine Research Center] {{webarchive |url=https://archive.is/20060217082626/http://www.reeve.uci.edu/chrisreeve/index.php |date=February 17, 2006 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Career after the accident==
In 1997, Reeve made his directorial debut with the [[HBO]] [[film]] ''[[In the Gloaming (film)|In the Gloaming]]'' with [[Robert Sean Leonard]], [[Glenn Close]], [[Whoopi Goldberg]], [[Bridget Fonda]], and [[David Strathairn]]. The film won four [[Cable Ace Award]]s and was nominated for five [[Emmy Award]]s including "Outstanding Director for a Miniseries or Special". Dana Reeve said, "There's such a difference in his outlook, his health, his overall sense of well-being when he's working at what he loves, which is creative work."&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.supermanhomepage.com/movies/movies.php?topic=chris-reeve |title=Christopher Reeve Biography |publisher=Supermanhomepage.com |date= |accessdate=July 9, 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt; In 1998, Reeve produced and starred in ''[[Rear Window (1998 film)|Rear Window]]'', a remake of [[Alfred Hitchcock]]'s [[Rear Window|1954 film]]. He was nominated for a [[Golden Globe]] and won a [[Screen Actors Guild Award]] for his performance. On April 25, 1998, [[Random House]] published Reeve's autobiography, ''[[Still Me]]''. The book spent eleven weeks on the [[New York Times Best Seller list]] and Reeve won a [[Grammy Award for Best Spoken Word Album]].&lt;ref&gt;[[Brown University]], [http://www.brown.edu/Administration/News_Bureau/2001-02/01-047.html Christopher Reeve to give Parents Weekend keynote lecture.] Press release, October 23, 2001, accessed November 24, 2006&lt;/ref&gt;

Throughout this time, Reeve kept his body as physically strong as possible by using specialized [[exercise machine]]s. He did this both because he believed that intense physical therapy could [[regeneration (biology)|regenerate]] the [[nervous system]], and because he wanted his body to be strong enough to support itself if a cure was found. In 2000, he began to regain some [[motor control|motor function]], and he was able to sense hot and cold [[temperature]]s on his body. His doctor, John McDonald of [[Washington University in St. Louis]], asked him if anything was new with his recovery. Reeve then moved his left index finger on command. "I don't think Dr. McDonald would have been more surprised if I had just walked on water," said Reeve in an interview.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|author=Oliver Burkeman |url=https://www.theguardian.com/g2/story/0,3604,793417,00.html |title=Man of steel |publisher=Guardian |date=September 17, 2002 |accessdate=July 9, 2013 |location=London}}&lt;/ref&gt; Also, during that year, he made [[guest appearance]]s on the long-running [[PBS]] series ''[[Sesame Street]]''.

In 2001, Reeve was elected to serve on the board of directors for the company TechHealth, headquartered in Tampa, Florida, which provides products and services to severely injured patients. While serving on the TechHealth board, Reeve participated in board meetings and advised the company on strategic direction. He refused compensation. He made phone calls to the company's catastrophically injured patients to cheer them up. Reeve served on TechHealth's board until his death in 2004. After his death, Dana Reeve took his board seat with TechHealth until her death in March 2006.

In 2002, the Christopher and Dana Reeve Paralysis Resource Center, a federal government facility created through a [[Centers for Disease Control]] and Prevention non-compete grant,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.chrisreevehomepage.com/sp-cdc01071.html |title=CDC Program Announcement 01071 |publisher=Chrisreevehomepage.com |date= |accessdate=July 9, 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt; was opened in [[Short Hills, New Jersey]]. Its mission is to teach paralyzed people to live more independently. Reeve said, "When somebody is first injured or as a disease progresses into paralysis, people don't know where to turn. Dana and I wanted a facility that could give support and information to people. With this new Center, we're off to an amazing start."&lt;ref name="Biography"/&gt;

[[File:Christopher Reeve MIT.jpg|thumb|Reeve discussing stem cell research at a conference at [[Massachusetts Institute of Technology|MIT]], March 2, 2003.]]
Reeve lobbied for expanded federal funding on [[embryonic stem cell research]] to include all embryonic stem cell lines in existence and for self-governance to make open-ended scientific inquiry of the research.&lt;ref&gt;Christopher Reeve Homepage. [http://www.chrisreevehomepage.com/testimony-nih.html Christopher Reeve Testimony: April 26, 2000]. Accessed November 30, 2006&lt;/ref&gt; President [[George W. Bush]] limited the federal funding to research only on human embryonic stem cell lines created on or before August 9, 2001, the day he announced his policy, and allotted approximately $100 million for it. Reeve initially called this "a step in the right direction", admitting that he did not know about the existing lines and would look into them further. He fought against the limit when scientists revealed that an early research technique that involved mixing the human stem cells with mouse cells contaminated most of the old lines.&lt;ref&gt;Viegas, Jennifer. [https://web.archive.org/web/20060721022401/http://dsc.discovery.com/news/2006/07/19/stemcells_hea.html?category=health&amp;guid=20060719143000 In-Depth: Bush Vetoes Stem Cell Bill.] ''Discovery News,'' July 19, 2006, accessed November 30, 2006&lt;/ref&gt; In 2002, Reeve lobbied for the [[Human Cloning]] Prohibition Act of 2001,&lt;ref&gt;The Library of Congress. [https://web.archive.org/web/20150904081347/http://thomas.loc.gov/cgi-bin/query/z?c107%3AS.1758%3A S. 1758 'Human Cloning Prohibition Act of 2001']. Accessed November 30, 2006&lt;/ref&gt; which would allow [[somatic cell nuclear transfer]] research but would ban [[reproductive cloning]]. He argued that stem cell implantation is unsafe unless the stem cells contain the patient's own [[DNA]] and that because somatic cell nuclear transfer is done without fertilizing an egg, it can be fully regulated.&lt;ref&gt;Christopher Reeve Homepage. [http://www.chrisreevehomepage.com/sp-testimony-bill1758.html Christopher Reeve Testimony: March 5, 2002]. Accessed November 30, 2006&lt;/ref&gt; In June 2004, Reeve provided a videotaped message on behalf of the Genetics Policy Institute to the delegates of the [[United Nations]] in defense of somatic cell nuclear transfer, which world [[treaty]] was considering banning.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.genpol.org |title=Genetics Policy Institute (GPI) |publisher=Genpol.org |date= |accessdate=July 9, 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt; In the final days of his life, Reeve urged [[California]] [[voting|voters]] to vote yes on [[California Constitution Article XXXV|Proposition 71]],&lt;ref&gt;[http://news.bbc.co.uk/1/hi/entertainment/film/3947029.stm Reeve stem cell appeal airs in US.] ''[[BBC News]]'', October 23, 2004. Accessed November 30, 2006&lt;/ref&gt; which would establish the [[California Institute for Regenerative Medicine]] and would allot $3 billion of state funds to stem cell research.&lt;ref&gt;Smart Voter. [http://www.smartvoter.org/2004/11/02/ca/state/prop/71/ Proposition 71: Stem Cell Research]. Accessed November 30, 2006&lt;/ref&gt; Proposition 71 was approved less than one month after Reeve's death.

On February 25, 2003, Reeve appeared in the television series ''[[Smallville (TV series)|Smallville]]'' as Dr. Swann in the episode "[[Smallville (Season 2)#Rosetta|Rosetta]]". In that episode, Dr. Swann brings to [[Clark Kent]] ([[Tom Welling]]) information about where he comes from and how to use his powers for the good of mankind. The scenes of Reeve and Welling feature music cues from 1978's ''[[Superman (1978 film)|Superman: The Movie]]'', composed by [[John Williams]] and arranged by [[Mark Snow]]. At the end of this episode, Reeve and Welling appeared in a short spot inviting people to support the [[Christopher Reeve Paralysis Foundation]]. "Rosetta" set ratings history for [[The WB Television Network|The WB]] network.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.isnnews.net/zocalo/archive/2-8.shtml The Zocalo Today.] ISN News, February 8, 2003, accessed November 3, 2006 "SMALLVILLE set ratings highs Tuesday, hitting an all-time high for any program on the WB in the key 18–34 [[demography|demographic]], with a 6.1 rating/15 share. According to [[significant figures|figures]] from [[Nielsen Media Research]], SMALLVILLE attracted 8.1 million total viewers."&lt;/ref&gt; The [[fandom|fan community]] met the episode with rave reviews and praised it as being among the series' best to this day.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.supermanhomepage.com/tv/tv.php?topic=reviews/smallville2-ep17 |title=Superman on Television |publisher=Superman Homepage |date= |accessdate=October 10, 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Reeve also appeared in the ''Smallville'' episode "[[Smallville (Season 3)#Legacy|Legacy]]", in which he met again with fellow stage actor [[John Glover (actor)|John Glover]], who played [[Lionel Luthor]] in the show.

In April 2004, [[Random House]] published Reeve's second book, ''Nothing Is Impossible''. This book is shorter than ''[[Still Me]]'' and focuses on Reeve's [[world view]]s and the life [[experience]]s that helped him shape them.

Also, in 2004, Reeve directed the [[A&amp;E Network|A&amp;E]] film ''[[Brooke Ellison#The Brooke Ellison Story|The Brooke Ellison Story]]''. The film is based on the true story of [[Brooke Ellison]], the first [[quadriplegic]] to graduate from [[Harvard University]].&lt;ref&gt;Le, Van. [http://www.thecrimson.com/article.aspx?ref=515190 Paralyzed Alum Invigorates N.Y. Race]. ''[[The Harvard Crimson]]'', October 24, 2006, accessed November 3, 2006&lt;/ref&gt; Reeve during this time was directing the [[animated film]] ''[[Everyone's Hero]]''. It was one of his dream projects and he died during the middle of production for the film. His wife Dana helped out, and his son Will was a cast member in the film. Dana and Will also had small roles in ''[[Brooke Ellison#The Brooke Ellison Story|The Brooke Ellison Story]]''.&lt;ref&gt;''The Brooke Ellison Story''. Dir. Christopher Reeve. Perf. Mary Elizabeth Mastrantonio, John Slattery, Lacey Chabert, and Vanessa Marano. A&amp;E Television Networks, 2004. YouTube streaming.&lt;/ref&gt;

==Health issues and death==
Reeve suffered from [[asthma]] and [[allergy|allergies]] since childhood. At age 16, he began to suffer from [[alopecia areata]], a condition that causes patches of hair to fall out from an otherwise healthy head of hair. Generally, he was able to comb it over and often the problem disappeared for long periods. Regarding this condition of Reeve's and his appearances in the [[Superman]] films, "[he] dyed his hair black to emulate the look of the Man of Steel for ''[[Superman (1978 film)|Superman: The Movie]]'' and ''[[Superman II]]''. However, rather than going that route in ''[[Superman III]]'' and ''[[Superman IV: The Quest for Peace]]'', [he] wore a wig"&lt;ref&gt;Thrash, Steven. "15 Shocking Things You Didn't Know About The Horrible Superman III." ''Screen Rant''. Valnet, 19 Sept. 2017. Web. 20 Aug. 2018.&lt;/ref&gt;  Later in life, the condition became more noticeable after he became paralyzed, and he would have his head shaved.&lt;ref&gt;Reeve, Christopher (2004), p 6&lt;/ref&gt;

More than once he had a severe [[adverse drug reaction|reaction]] to a drug. In Kessler, he tried a drug named Sygen which was theorized to help reduce damage to the spinal cord. The drug caused him to go into [[anaphylactic shock]], and his heart stopped. He claimed to have had an [[out-of-body experience]] and remembered saying, "I'm sorry, but I have to go now", during the event. In his autobiography, he wrote, "and then I left my body. I was up on the ceiling...I looked down and saw my body stretched out on the bed, not moving, while everybody—there were 15 or 20 people, the doctors, the EMTs, the nurses—was working on me. The noise and commotion grew quieter as though someone were gradually turning down the volume." After receiving a large dose of [[epinephrine]], he woke up and stabilized later that night.&lt;ref&gt;Reeve, Christopher (1998), pp 106–108&lt;/ref&gt;

In 2002 and 2004, Reeve survived several serious infections believed to have originated from his [[bone marrow]]. He recovered from three that could have been fatal.{{Citation needed|date=March 2017}}

In early October 2004, he was being treated for an infected [[pressure ulcer]] that was causing [[sepsis]], a complication he had experienced many times before. On October 4th, he spoke at the [[Shirley Ryan AbilityLab|Rehabilitation Institute of Chicago]] on behalf of the Institute's work. This was to be his last reported public appearance.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news| url=https://www.washingtonpost.com/wp-dyn/articles/A23222-2004Oct11.html | work=The Washington Post | first=Joe | last=Holley | title=A Leading Man for Spinal Cord Research | date=October 12, 2004}}&lt;/ref&gt;  On October 9, Reeve felt well and attended his son Will's [[hockey]] game. That night, he went into [[cardiac arrest]] after receiving an [[antibiotic]] for the [[infection]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|last1=McCormack|first1=David|title=Christopher Reeve's look-alike 22-year-old son joins ESPN's SportsCenter team as it attempts to appeal to more millennials|url=http://www.dailymail.co.uk/news/article-2928938/Christopher-Reeve-s-look-alike-22-year-old-son-joins-ESPN-s-SportsCenter-team-attempts-appeal-millennials.html|accessdate=September 4, 2015|work=Daily Mail|date=January 27, 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt; He fell into a [[coma]] and was taken to [[Northern Westchester Hospital]] in [[Mount Kisco, New York]]. Eighteen hours later, on October 10, 2004, Reeve died at age 52.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://abcnews.go.com/Entertainment/story?id=101123&amp;page=1 |title=Christopher Reeve obituary|work=ABC News  |date=October 11, 2004 |accessdate=July 9, 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt; His doctor, John McDonald, believed an adverse reaction to the antibiotic caused Reeve's death.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news| url=http://newmobility.com/review_article.cfm?id=996&amp;action=browse | archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20050402023315/http://newmobility.com/review_article.cfm?id=996&amp;action=browse | dead-url=yes | archive-date=2005-04-02 |title=Media Lies|magazine= New Mobility|date=April 2005| accessdate=October 14, 2006}}&lt;/ref&gt;

His remains were cremated at [[Ferncliff Cemetery]].&lt;ref&gt;http://ferncliffcemetery.com/visit-ferncliff/celebrities-notables/&lt;/ref&gt; A memorial service for Reeve was held at the [[Unitarian Universalist Association|Unitarian Church]] in [[Westport, Connecticut]], which his wife attended.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://findarticles.com/p/articles/mi_qa4071/is_200501/ai_n9465752 |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20080108071338/http://findarticles.com/p/articles/mi_qa4071/is_200501/ai_n9465752 |dead-url=yes |archive-date=2008-01-08 |work=UU World: The Magazine of the Unitarian Universalist Association |title=Christopher Reeve |year=2005 |first=Frank |last=Hall }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|title=Somewhere in Heaven: The Remarkable Love Story of Dana and Christopher Reeve|author=Andersen, Christopher |isbn=1-4013-2302-2}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Aftermath==
His widow, [[Dana Reeve]], headed the [[Christopher Reeve Foundation]] after his death. Although a non-smoker, she was diagnosed with [[lung cancer]] on 9&amp;nbsp;August 2005 and died at age&amp;nbsp;44 on 6&amp;nbsp;March 2006.&lt;ref name=DanaDies&gt;{{cite news| url=http://www.cnn.com/2006/SHOWBIZ/03/07/reeve.obit/ |title=Dana Reeve dies of lung cancer at 44|work=CNN|date=8 March 2006|accessdate=28 October 2006}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Christopher and Dana Reeve are survived by their son, William, and Reeve's children from his relationship with Gae Exton, Matthew and Alexandra. Matthew and Alexandra now serve on the board of directors for the [[Christopher and Dana Reeve Foundation]]. Christopher was survived by his parents and Dana by her father.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |website=Christopher Reeve Foundation |url=http://www.christopherreeve.org/site/c.geIMLPOpGjF/b.1029235/k.BE76/Board_of_Directors.htm |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20051103020309/http://www.christopherreeve.org/site/c.geIMLPOpGjF/b.1029235/k.BE76/Board_of_Directors.htm |dead-url=yes |archive-date=3 November 2005 |title=Board of Directors |accessdate=3 December 2006}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Filmography==
{{Main article|Christopher Reeve filmography}}

==References==
{{Reflist|20em}}

==Further reading==
* [http://www.capedwonder.com/ CapedWonder Superman Imagery], created by Jim Bowers.
* [http://www.chrisreevehomepage.com/ Christopher Reeve Homepage]
* Reeve, Christopher. ''Still Me'', Random House, 1998. {{ISBN|0-679-45235-4}}
* Reeve, Christopher ''Nothing is Impossible'', Random House, 2004. {{ISBN|0-345-47073-7}}

==External links==
{{Wikiquote}}
{{commonscatinline}}
* {{iMDb name|1659}}
* {{tcmdb name|id=159333|name=Christopher Reeve}}
* {{iobdb name|9946|Christopher Reeve}}
* [https://www.nytimes.com/2004/10/11/arts/11WIRE-REEVE.html N.Y. Times Obituary for Christopher Reeve]
* {{Find a Grave|9580089}}
* [http://www.christopherreeve.org/ Christopher and Dana Reeve Foundation]
* [http://www.paralysis.org/ Christopher and Dana Reeve Paralysis Resource Center : Home]
* [http://cagle.com/news/ChristopherReeve/1.asp Political Cartoons Honoring Reeve]{{dead link|date=March 2017}}
* [http://www.paulbrunton.org/christopher-reeve.php Christopher Reeve reads from "Discover Yourself" and "The Secret Path"]

{{Navboxes
|title = Awards for Christopher Reeve
|list =
{{Bafta Award for Most Promising Newcomer}}
{{Grammy Award for Best Spoken Word Album 1990s}}
{{ScreenActorsGuildAward MaleTVMiniseriesMovie 1994-2009}}
}}

{{Authority control}}
{{DEFAULTSORT:Reeve, Christopher}}
[[Category:1952 births]]
[[Category:2004 deaths]]
[[Category:20th-century American male actors]]
[[Category:20th-century Unitarians]]
[[Category:21st-century American male actors]]
[[Category:21st-century Unitarians]]
[[Category:American Christians]]
[[Category:American male equestrians]]
[[Category:American male film actors]]
[[Category:American male soap opera actors]]
[[Category:American male stage actors]]
[[Category:American people of English descent]]
[[Category:American people with disabilities]]
[[Category:American Unitarian Universalists]]
[[Category:BAFTA winners (people)]]
[[Category:Cornell University alumni]]
[[Category:Deaths from sepsis]]
[[Category:Emmy Award winners]]
[[Category:Former Presbyterians]]
[[Category:Former Scientologists]]
[[Category:Grammy Award winners]]
[[Category:Horse-related accidents and incidents]]
[[Category:Infectious disease deaths in New York (state)]]
[[Category:Juilliard School alumni]]
[[Category:Male actors from New York City]]
[[Category:New York (state) Democrats]]
[[Category:Outstanding Performance by a Male Actor in a Miniseries or Television Movie Screen Actors Guild Award winners]]
[[Category:People from Pound Ridge, New York]]
[[Category:People from Princeton, New Jersey]]
[[Category:People with tetraplegia]]
[[Category:Princeton Day School alumni]]
[[Category:Recipients of the Order of Bernardo O'Higgins]]</text>
      <sha1>gdkk95tsgfntrx7l7vwz4v35gta3kdm</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
