<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10.xsd" version="0.10" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <dbname>enwiki</dbname>
    <base>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.32.0-wmf.16</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="118" case="first-letter">Draft</namespace>
      <namespace key="119" case="first-letter">Draft talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2300" case="first-letter">Gadget</namespace>
      <namespace key="2301" case="first-letter">Gadget talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2302" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition</namespace>
      <namespace key="2303" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Clay Lacy</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>24313261</id>
    <revision>
      <id>855741275</id>
      <parentid>853005395</parentid>
      <timestamp>2018-08-20T14:26:03Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Joey1niner</username>
        <id>22222061</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>/* External links */</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="21644">{{Infobox aviator
| name    = Clay Lacy
| image   = ClayLacy.jpg
| image_size  = 250px
| caption = Lacy in 2007
| birth_place = {{birth date and age|1932|8|14}}&lt;br /&gt;[[Wichita, Kansas]], [[United States|U.S.]]
|first_flight_aircraft=Beechcraft Staggerwing
|famous_flights=Friendship One, Midway 2000
{{Infobox military person|embed=yes
 | allegiance = {{Flag|United States of America}}
 | branch = [[File:California Air National Guard USAF patch.PNG|25px]] [[California Air National Guard]]
 | serviceyears = 1954-1962
 }}
 |website     = http://www.claylacy.com/
}}

'''Hershel Clay Lacy''' (born August 14, 1932) is the founder and chief executive officer of Clay Lacy Aviation, established in 1968 as the first executive jet charter company in the Western United States.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last=Geere|title=Lucky Me|pages=12}}&lt;/ref&gt;  His professional resume' includes airline captain, military aviator, experimental test pilot, air race champion, world record-setter, aerial cinematographer and business aviation entrepreneur. Lacy has flown more than 300 aircraft types, logged more than 50,000 flight hours and accumulated more hours flying turbine aircraft than any other pilot in the world.

== Aviation career ==
Growing up in the farmland of Wichita, Kansas, during the Great Depression, Lacy developed an early fascination with flight. He learned how to build model airplanes at age five and created his first gasoline-powered flying model at age eight. At age 12, Lacy piloted his first aircraft at Cannonball Airport, built on his grandmother's farm about three miles outside the city limits of Wichita, where he worked in exchange for flying time.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last=Geere|title=Lucky Me|pages=16}}&lt;/ref&gt; In 1948, at age 16, he earned a flight instructor rating.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last=Geere|title=Lucky Me|pages=17}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Aviation Pioneers|url=http://www.wingsoverkansas.com/profiles/article.asp?id=52}}&lt;/ref&gt;

By age 19, Lacy had accumulated nearly 2,000 hours of flight time as both an instructor and ferry pilot. In January 1952, Lacy joined [[United Airlines]] as copilot on the [[Douglas DC-3]] aircraft and was stationed at [[Los Angeles International Airport]], where he was based for his entire airline career.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last=Geere|title=Lucky Me|pages=32}}&lt;/ref&gt; During his time with United Airlines, Lacy flew the [[Convair 340]], [[Douglas DC-3]], [[Douglas DC-4]], [[Douglas DC-6]], [[Douglas DC-7]], [[Douglas DC-8]], [[Douglas DC-10]], [[Boeing 727]] and [[Boeing 747-400]]. He retired seniority No. 1 in 1992 after 41½ years of incident-free flying.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last=Geere|title=Lucky Me|pages=45}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In 1954, Lacy took military leave from United Airlines to join the [[California Air National Guard]] at [[Van Nuys Airport]], where he flew the [[F86 Sabre|F-86 Sabre jet]] and became the officer in charge of instrument training. He was called to active duty in 1961 for one year during the [[Berlin Crisis of 1961|Berlin crisis]], flying the [[C-97 Stratofreighter]] on missions to Japan and Vietnam.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last=Geere|title=Lucky Me|pages=33}}&lt;/ref&gt;  He retired from military service three years later.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last=Geere|title=Lucky Me|pages=63}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In 1964, Lacy flew the first [[Learjet]] into [[Van Nuys Airport]] in proximity to Hollywood’s burgeoning entertainment industry, shaping a new era in corporate air transportation and mobility. In 1968, he founded Clay Lacy Aviation as the first jet charter company on the West Coast, known as one of the most experienced operators of private jets in the world.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last=Geere|title=Lucky Me|pages=162}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Between 1964 and 1972, Lacy found time between flying for United Airlines and running his private charter business to fly his [[P-51 Mustang]] in air races across the United States. In 1970, he placed first in the [[Reno Air Races|Reno National Air Races]] Unlimited class competition.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|last=McLaren|title=Setting World Records}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In the early 1970s, in partnership with Continental Camera Systems, Inc., Lacy helped revolutionize air-to-air cinematography with the Astrovision camera system. He is credited with more than 3,000 film projects for the military, motion pictures and television, including most airline commercials featuring air-to-air photography.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last=Geere|title=Lucky Me|pages=108}}&lt;/ref&gt;

During the 29-day United Airlines pilot strike of May 1985, Lacy was one of the first pilots to cross the picket line and go to work on May 17, 1985, thus undermining the unionized pilots attempts for better pay and work rules. This forever earned him a spot on the Master Scab List, and earned him the unceremonious title of "scab".&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Master Scab List|url=http://file.wikileaks.org/file/airline-pilot-scab-list-2004.pdf}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Lacy holds 29 world speed records, including a 36-hour, 54-minute, and 15-second around the world record in 1988 flying a Boeing 747SP called "[[Friendship One]]" that raised $530,000 for children's charities.

On July 17, 2010, Lacy was inducted into the [[National Aviation Hall of Fame]] for his achievements as an aviation pioneer. The same year, he was awarded the Pathfinder Award by the [[Seattle Museum of Flight]] and the [[Federal Aviation Administration]]'s [[Wright Brothers Master Pilot Award]]. In November 2011, Lacy was inducted into the Kansas Aviation Hall of Fame, housed at the Kansas Aviation Museum in Wichita, Kansas.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Clay Lacy Receives Aviation Awards|url=http://www.aeroclubsocal.org/News/claylacy.html}}&lt;/ref&gt;

== The Lear connection ==
During development of the [[Learjet]] in the early 1960s, Lacy formed a close personal relationship with the aircraft’s inventor [[William Powell Lear]]. At Lear’s invitation,  Lacy made several trips to his hometown of Wichita to tour the factory and share his knowledge and ideas.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last=Geere|title=Lucky Me|pages=62}}&lt;/ref&gt;

After participating in a Learjet demonstration flight in 1964 with friend and business partner [[Allen Paulson]], Lacy was appointed manager of sales for 11 Western states at the Learjet distributorship California Airmotive Corporation. The same year, Lacy resigned from the California Air National Guard to focus on the new business venture and become one of the first pilots to earn a Learjet type rating.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last=Geere|title=Lucky Me|pages=62–63}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In October 1964, Lacy flew a [[Learjet 23|Lear Model 23]] from Wichita to Los Angeles to become the first corporate jet based at Van Nuys Airport. The Learjet’s popularity in the entertainment industry began with American singer, actor and [[Rat Pack]] leader [[Frank Sinatra]] who was an early aircraft buyer.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last=Geere|title=Lucky Me|pages=80}}&lt;/ref&gt;

1965, Lacy and longtime friend and former California Air National Guard pilot [[John M. Conroy|Jack Conroy]] flew the Learjet on a record-setting transcontinental round-trip flight from Los Angeles to New York and back. The flight marked the first time a business jet made a round-trip flight across the United States between sunrise and sunset on the same day.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|last=Haughland|title=Jack Conroy's Fish Story}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The same year, actor, comedian and pilot [[Danny Kaye]] was appointed vice president of public relations for the distributorship, renamed Pacific Lear Jet. Lacy and Kaye flew several hundred hours in the Learjet together, making four charity flights to benefit the [[United Nations Children’s Fund]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|last=Kessler|title=The UNICEF Express}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In 1968, Lacy founded his own on-demand charter company, where he developed a clientele of Hollywood celebrities and prominent business people, a legacy that continues today.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|last=Hyland|title=Air-Born}}&lt;/ref&gt;

== Air races ==
Between 1964 and 1972, Lacy found time between flying for United Airlines and running his private charter business to fly his P-51 Mustang in every Unlimited class air race in the United States. He served as president of the national Professional Race Pilots Association from 1966 to 1970.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|last=McLaren|title=Setting World Records}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Flying with the character “Snoopy” painted on the tail of his signature purple race plane, Lacy consistently placed second and third in the competitions, but aspired to win first place in a major pylon race. In 1970, Lacy claimed victory as national air race champion in the Unlimited class.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last=Geere|title=Lucky Me|pages=92}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The following year, he also placed first in a cross country race from Milwaukee to St. Louis and in the St. Louis Fighter Pilot Air Tournament. He also won first place in The Great Race from London, England, to Victoria, British Columbia flying a Learjet.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last=Geere|title=Lucky Me|pages=92}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In 1970, Clay created worldwide attention when he and  Allen Paulson flew a four-engine Douglas DC-7 nicknamed Super Snoopy in the California 1000 Mile Air Race at Mohave, California. They finished in sixth place out of twenty at an average speed of 325 miles per hour, marking the first and only time a four-engine airliner ever competed in a pylon event.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last=Geere|title=Lucky Me|pages=93}}&lt;/ref&gt;

== Aerial cinematography ==
In partnership with Continental Camera Systems, in the early 1970s Lacy revolutionized air-to-air cinematography with Astrovision, a unique relay lens system with periscopes mounted on the top and bottom of the airplane’s fuselage. With full video monitoring to film above or below a Learjet, the system is able to rotate 360 degrees in any direction and tilt up and down with no speed or altitude restrictions. At its introduction, never before had any camera system provided such continuous and unrestricted use.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last=Geere|title=Lucky Me|pages=108–109}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Filming flying scenes and stunt work for major motion pictures has been part of Lacy’s lifelong work. Overall, he has filmed more than 3,000 projects for the military, feature films and television, including almost every airline commercial featuring air-to-air photography.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last=Geere|title=Lucky Me|pages=108}}&lt;/ref&gt; It was Lacy who recorded most of the action-packed aerial sequences in Paramount Pictures' ''[[Top Gun]]'' (1986). He is also known for his work on the movies ''[[Firefox (film)|Firefox]]'' (1982), ''[[Armageddon (1998 film)|Armageddon]]'' (1998), ''[[Cliffhanger (film)|Cliffhanger]]'' (1993) and ''[[Behind Enemy Lines (2001 film)|Behind Enemy Lines]]'' (2001).&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Clay Lacy|url=https://www.imdb.com/name/nm0479916/}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Lacy is a member of both the [[Screen Actors Guild]] and [[Directors Guild of America]], and was named “Outstanding Director of Mobile Camera Platform” by the [[Society of Camera Operators]] in 2004.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Clay Lacy|url=https://www.imdb.com/name/nm0479916/}}&lt;/ref&gt;

== Famous flights ==
With 29 world speed records under his belt, Lacy’s name has appeared in many newspaper headlines and aviation record books.

On September 19, 1962 in California’s Mojave Desert, Lacy and fellow Air National Guard pilot [[John M. Conroy|Jack Conroy]] attracted national attention when they made the first flight of the [[Pregnant Guppy]], a Boeing 377 Stratocruiser modified to carry the Saturn rocket booster in support of the U.S. space program. The aircraft carried its first payload for [[NASA]] to [[Cape Canaveral]] one year later.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last=Freeze|title=Living Legends of Aviation}}&lt;/ref&gt;

On June 8, 1966, Lacy piloted a Learjet 23 owned by [[Frank Sinatra]]. Earlier that day, he flew Sinatra and [[Dean Martin]] from [[Burbank, California|Burbank]] to [[Palm Springs, California|Palm Springs]] before flying out near [[Edwards Air Force Base]] to film a formation flight of five aircraft, including one of the two [[North American XB-70 Valkyrie|XB-70 Valkyries]]. The flight, intended as a promotional shoot for [[General Electric]], ended in disaster when an [[Lockheed F-104 Starfighter|F-104]] collided with the XB-70, resulting in the loss of both aircraft and deaths of F-104 pilot [[Joseph A. Walker|Joe Walker]] and XB-70 co-pilot Major Carl Cross.&lt;ref&gt;http://airportjournals.com/clay-lacy-the-planes-ive-flown-the-people-ive-known-part-2/&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;http://www.sunlakesaeroclub.org/updates_web_data/081231/Sinatra.htm&lt;/ref&gt;

In 1973, Lacy and fellow United Airlines pilot William Arnott made aviation and education history by organizing an around-the-world flight in a chartered United Airlines DC-8 jetliner for aeronautical students from [[Mount San Antonio College]] located in Walnut, California. Two years later in 1975, Lacy and the same crew flew students on an eight-day South American sojourn. These tour flights named “Classroom in the Sky” pioneered the concept of education from a jet plane.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last=Geere|title=Lucky Me|pages=122}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last=Freeze|title=Living Legends of Aviation}}&lt;/ref&gt;

One of Lacy’s most notable achievements was setting a new around-the-world speed record in 1988 with his 36-hour, 54-minute, 15-second flight in a Boeing United [[747SP]] called "[[Friendship One]]". With U.S. astronaut and Apollo 11 commander [[Neil Armstrong]] on board as guest of honor, along with other aviation notables and celebrities, this record-breaking flight raised $530,000 for children’s charities worldwide. Lacy and his wife Lois, along with long-time friends Bruce McCaw and Joe Clark, organized the flight, which averaged over 623 miles per hour and topped the previous record by 112 miles per hour.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last=Geere|title=Lucky Me|pages=122}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In 1995, Lacy was one of the first aircraft owners to equip his Gulfstream jets with Blended Winglet™ technology developed by [[Aviation Partners Inc.]], founded by Joe Clark and Dennis Washington. That June, in a Gulfstream IISP inscribed with the words “Wings of Change” across its side, Lacy and Clark set world speed records during a flight from Los Angeles to Paris. The flight culminated with display of the jet at the Paris Air Show. On the way home, they also established a world speed record from Moscow to Los Angeles. Lacy and Clark set yet another speed record in the Gulfstream IISP in 2003 on a flight from Los Angeles to Kitty Hawk, North Carolina.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last=Geere|title=Lucky Me|pages=123}}&lt;/ref&gt;

During Lacy’s 1999 "Midway 2000" flight to celebrate the New Year, he and 40 guests traveled over the Pacific Ocean to be among the first to enter the new millennium. Lacy piloted his Boeing 727 from Southern California by way of Hawaii and [[Midway Island]] to the [[International Dateline]]. Cruising just one-tenth of a mile west of the imaginary line where every day officially begins, the passengers then passed into January 1, 2000 while it was still 4 a.m. on December 31, 1999 on the West Coast. In a period of one hour, the group traveled through five date changes before celebrating the New Year on the ground in Midway Island 24 hours later.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last=Geere|title=Lucky Me|pages=123}}&lt;/ref&gt;

== Honors ==
&lt;div style="column-width:45em;-moz-column-width:45em;-webkit-column-width:45em"&gt;
* Aero Club of Northern California Crystal Eagle Award
* Air Transportation Association William A. Ong Memorial Award
* Aviation and Business Journal Lifetime Achievement Award
* City of Hope Spirit of Life Award
* Duncan Aviation Excellence Award
* Federal Aviation Administration Wright Brothers Master Pilot Certificate
* Flight Path Learning Center Honoree
* Flight Test Historical Foundation Achievement in Aviation Award
*[[International Air &amp; Space Hall of Fame|International Aerospace Hall of Fame]] Inductee (2009)&lt;ref&gt;Sprekelmeyer, Linda, editor. ''These We Honor: The International Aerospace Hall of Fame''. Donning Co. Publishers, 2006. [[International Standard Book Number|ISBN]] [[Special:BookSources/978-1-57864-397-4|978-1-57864-397-4]].&lt;/ref&gt;
* Living Legends of Aviation Lifetime Aviation Entrepreneur Award
*[[National Aviation Hall of Fame]] Inductee
* Professional Pilot Magazine Writer of the Year
* Seattle Museum of Flight Pathfinder Award
* Society of Camera Operators Cammy Lifetime Achievement Award
* Society of Experimental Test Pilots Member
* United Airlines Historical Foundation William S. Arnott Legacy Award
* Kansas Aviation Hall of Fame Inductee
* NBAA Meritorious Service to Aviation Award
&lt;/div&gt;

== Film credits (partial list) ==
Best known for: ''[[The Great Santini]]'' (1979), ''[[The Right Stuff (film)|The Right Stuff]]'' (1983), ''[[Octopussy]]'' (1983), ''[[Top Gun]]'' (1986), ''[[Cliffhanger (film)|Cliffhanger]]'' (1993), ''[[Armageddon (1998 film)|Armageddon]]'' (1998), ''[[Behind Enemy Lines (2001 film)|Behind Enemy Lines]]'' (2001)
&lt;div style="column-width:20em;-moz-column-width:20em;-webkit-column-width:20em"&gt;
* [[Ice Station Zebra]] (1968)
* [[The Day of the Jackal (film)|The Day of the Jackal]] (1973)
* [[Airport 1975]] (1974)
* [[Superman (1978 film)|Superman]] (1978)
* Operation Bluebook (1978)
* [[Capricorn One]] (1978)
* [[The Pilot (film)|The Pilot]] (1979)
* [[Airport 79]] (1979)
* [[The Great Santini]] (1979)
* Space (1980)
* [[The Last Chase]] (1981)
* [[Firefox (film)]] (1982)
* [[The Right Stuff (film)|The Right Stuff]] (1983)
* [[Deal of the Century (film)|Deal of the Century]] (1983)
* [[Octopussy]] (1983)                               	
* [[Call to Glory]] (1984)
* [[The NeverEnding Story (film)|The Never Ending Story]] (1984)
* [[White Nights (1985 film)|White Nights]] (1985)                                    	
* [[Top Gun]] (1986)                                   	
* Dragnet (1987)                                    	
* [[Look Who's Talking]] (1989)
* Revenge (1990)
* [[Flight of the Intruder]] (1991)                 	
* McBain's War (1991)                                    	
* Sinatra (1992)
* [[Cliffhanger (film)|Cliffhanger]] (1993)                               	
* [[Lois and Clark]] (1993)
* [[The Client (1994 film)|The Client]] (1994)
* [[Clear and Present Danger (film)|Clear and Present Danger]] (1994)
* [[Sgt. Bilko]] (1996)
* [[Con Air]] (1997)
* [[Contact (1997 American film)|Contact]] (1997)                                    	
* True Vengeance (1997)                      	
* [[Turbulence (1997 film)|Turbulence]] (1997)
* [[Wag the Dog]] (1997)                           	
* [[Air Force One (film)|Air Force One]] (1997)                          	
* [[Iron Eagle II]] (1998)
* [[Armageddon (1998 film)|Armageddon]] (1998)
* [[Behind Enemy Lines (2001 film)|Behind Enemy Lines]] (2001)
* [[Rat Race (film)|Rat Race]] (2001)
* [[I Spy (film)|I Spy]] (2002)
* [[S.W.A.T. (film)|S.W.A.T.]] (2003)
* Hero (2004)
* Miracles (2004)                                   	
* [[Stealth (film)|Stealth]] (2005)                                      	
* [[The Island (2005 film)|The Island]] (2005)
* [[One Six Right]] (2005)                                          	
* [[Amazing Grace (2006 film)|Amazing Grace]] (2006)                                  	
* [[Transformers (film)|Transformers]] (2007)
&lt;/div&gt;

== Notes ==
{{Reflist|3}}

== References ==
{{refbegin|35em}}
* {{cite journal|last=Hyland|first=Alexa|title=Air-Born|journal=Los Angeles Business Journal|date=October 25, 2010|volume=32}}
* {{cite web|title=Aviation Pioneers|url=http://www.wingsoverkansas.com/profiles/article.asp?id=52|work=Wings Over Kansas|accessdate=22 January 2010}}
* {{cite web|title=Clay Lacy|url=https://www.imdb.com/name/nm0479916/|work=IMDB|accessdate=10 May 2011}}
* {{cite web|title=Clay Lacy Receives Aviation Awards|url=http://www.aeroclubsocal.org/News/claylacy.html|work=Aero Club News of Southern California|accessdate=23 November 2010}}
* {{cite news|last=Adelson|first=Andrea|title=Flying Goes Hollywood with Valley Pilot's Help|newspaper=Daily News of Los Angeles}}
* {{cite journal|last=Haughland|first=Vern|title=Jack Conroy's Fish Story|journal=Airline Pilot|year=1979}}
* {{cite book|last=Freeze|first=Di|title=Living Legends of Aviation|year=2008|publisher=Centennial Journal Publishing of Colorada|location=Centennial}}
* {{cite book|last=Geere|first=Stacy T.|title=Lucky Me: The Life and Flights of Veteran Aviator Clay Lacy|year=2010|publisher=The Donning Company Publishers|location=Van Nuys|isbn=978-1-57864-635-7}}
* {{cite journal|last=McLaren|first=Grant|title=Setting World Records: A Far-Ranging Conversation with Clay Lacy at Mach .80|journal=Professional Pilot|year=1995}}
* {{cite journal|last=Kessler|first=Judy|title=The UNICEF Express: 65 Cities in 5 Days with An Impulsive Danny Kaye|journal=People Weekly|year=1975}}
{{refend}}

== External links ==
* [http://www.nationalaviation.org/lacy-clay/ Clay Lacy National Aviation HOF biography ]
* {{IMDb name|0479916}}
* [http://www.moviepilots.com/members/lacy.html Lacy on MoviePilots.com]
* [https://www.claylacy.com/ Clay Lacy Aviation]
* [https://www.flickr.com/photos/50393882@N00/9780379042 Lacy's 1970 Championship Mustang at Reno, 2013]
* [http://airportjournals.com/clay-lacy-the-planes-ive-flown-the-people-ive-known-part-1/ Lacy biography from ''Airport Journals'' part 1] and [http://airportjournals.com/clay-lacy-the-planes-ive-flown-the-people-ive-known-part-2/ part 2]

{{Authority control}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Lacy, Clay}}
[[Category:1932 births]]
[[Category:Living people]]
[[Category:American aviation businesspeople]]
[[Category:Aviators from Kansas]]
[[Category:American aviation record holders]]
[[Category:Commercial aviators]]</text>
      <sha1>0ko02mfinsyinec6586ekpi2df2kus0</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
