<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10.xsd" version="0.10" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <dbname>enwiki</dbname>
    <base>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.32.0-wmf.16</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="118" case="first-letter">Draft</namespace>
      <namespace key="119" case="first-letter">Draft talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2300" case="first-letter">Gadget</namespace>
      <namespace key="2301" case="first-letter">Gadget talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2302" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition</namespace>
      <namespace key="2303" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Francis Chichester</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>520676</id>
    <revision>
      <id>854463525</id>
      <parentid>851071235</parentid>
      <timestamp>2018-08-11T15:09:27Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>JLSm69</username>
        <id>33636524</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor/>
      <comment>/* Family */</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="17193">{{Use dmy dates|date=October 2013}}
{{Use British English|date=October 2013}}
[[File:Sir Francis Chichester portrait.jpg|thumb|Sir Francis Chichester]]
'''Sir Francis Charles Chichester''' [[Knight Commander of the Order of the British Empire|KBE]] (17 September 1901 – 26 August 1972) was a pioneering aviator and solo sailor.

He was knighted by [[Elizabeth II of the United Kingdom|Queen Elizabeth II]] for becoming the first person to sail [[single-handed sailing|single-handed]] around the world by the [[clipper route]] and the fastest [[circumnavigation|circumnavigator]], in nine months and one day overall in 1966–67.

==Biography==

===Early life===
[[File:Old Rectory Shirwell 2017.jpg|thumb|right|The former Rectory in [[Shirwell]], birthplace of Francis Chichester photographed in 2017]]
Chichester was born in the rectory at [[Shirwell]] near [[Barnstaple]] in Devon, England, the son of a [[Church of England]] clergyman, Charles Chichester, himself the seventh son of [[Chichester baronets|Sir Arthur Chichester, 8th Baronet]].&lt;ref&gt;Leslie, Anita. ''Francis Chichester: A Biography''.  New York, Walker &amp; Co. 1975&lt;/ref&gt; His mother was Emily Annie, daughter of Samuel Page. At the age of six he was sent as a [[boarding school|boarder]] to The Old Ride Preparatory School for boys, then attended [[Marlborough College]] during [[World War I]]. At the age of eighteen Chichester emigrated to New Zealand where in ten years he built up a prosperous business in forestry, mining and property development, only to suffer severe losses in the [[Great Depression]].

===Aviator===
After returning to England in 1929 to visit his family, Chichester took flying lessons at [[Brooklands]], Surrey, and qualified as a pilot. He then took delivery of a [[de Havilland Gipsy Moth]] aircraft, which he intended to fly to New Zealand, hoping to break [[Bert Hinkler]]'s record solo flight back to Australia on the way. While mechanical problems meant that the record eluded him, he completed the trip in 41 days. The aircraft was then shipped to New Zealand. Finding that he was unable to carry enough fuel to cross the [[Tasman Sea]] directly, Chichester had his Gipsy Moth fitted with floats borrowed from the [[New Zealand Permanent Air Force]], and went on to make the first solo flight across the Tasman Sea from East to West (New Zealand to Australia). He was the first to land an aircraft at [[Norfolk Island]] and [[Lord Howe Island]].  Again, the trip was delayed: after his aircraft was severely damaged at Lord Howe, he had to rebuild it himself with the help of islanders.

Though the concept of "off-course navigation" (steering to one side so you know which way the error is) is probably as old as navigation, Chichester was the first to use it in a methodical manner in an aircraft.  His only method of fixing his position was to take sun sights with a [[sextant]]. As a solo pilot, this was a difficult thing to do in a moving aircraft, as he needed to fly the aircraft at the same time.  After the sun sight was taken, he had to make calculations by long-hand. As all this could be unreliable, Chichester needed an alternative. When he reached a point at which the sun was at a calculated altitude above the horizon, the pilot then made a 90-degree turn to the left (or right as calculated) and then flew along this line until the destination was reached. Since he did not know in advance when he would arrive at a line of position passing through his destination, he calculated a table or graph of the Sun's altitude and [[azimuth]] at his destination for a range of times bracketing his ETA. The advantage of this method was that the effects of drift were reduced to errors in distance travelled, usually much smaller.  Since Chichester arrived at Lord Howe Island in the afternoon, the Sun was to his north-west when he made his turn.  Some hours before making his turn, close to local noon when the Sun was to his north, Chichester made two observations with his sextant to check his dead-reckoning course.&lt;ref name=PositionLineSlideRules&gt;{{cite web|last=van Riet|first=Ronald|title=Position Line Slide Rules|url=http://www.rechenschieber.org/PositionLineSlideRules.pdf|accessdate=3 May 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The general principle was, when the Sun is to the right or left of one's course one can check the course but not distance to the destination.  When the Sun is ahead or behind one's course, the distance to one's destination can be checked but not one's course.  Chichester planned his final approach to follow a line of position directly to his destination. This technique allowed him to find tiny islands in the Pacific. He was awarded the inaugural Guild of Air Pilots and Air Navigators Johnston Memorial Trophy for this trip.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.gapan.org/about-the-guild/trophies-and-awards/award-winners/the-johnston-memorial-trophy/|title=The Johnston Memorial Trophy|accessdate=25 January 2014|deadurl=yes|archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20140201171738/http://www.gapan.org/about-the-guild/trophies-and-awards/award-winners/the-johnston-memorial-trophy/|archivedate=1 February 2014|df=dmy-all}}&lt;/ref&gt; Chichester then decided to circumnavigate the world solo; he made it to Japan but at [[Katsuura, Chiba|Katsuura]], Chiba he collided with an overhead cable, sustaining serious injuries.

===Second World War cartography===
Unable to join the [[Royal Air Force]] at the outbreak of the [[Second World War]] due to age and eyesight,&lt;ref&gt;The Lonely Sea and the Sky&lt;/ref&gt; he was not granted a commission until 14 March 1941 when he joined the [[Royal Air Force Volunteer Reserve]] for the duration of hostilities. His civil occupation was listed as Air Navigation Specialist. His first posting was to the Air Ministry in the Navigation section of the Directorate of Air Member Training, where he served until August 1942. In July 1943 he was sent to the [[Empire Central Flying School]] where he instructed in navigation until released in September 1945.&lt;ref&gt;Air Historical Branch (RAF)&lt;/ref&gt; He wrote the navigation manual that allowed the pilots of single-handed fighter aircraft to navigate across Europe and back using kneeboard navigation similar to that which he had used in the Pacific.

At the end of the war, he stayed in the United Kingdom.  He purchased 15,000 surplus Air Ministry maps, initially pasting them onto boards and making [[jigsaw puzzle]]s out of them, and later founded his own successful map-making company.

===Yachtsman===
In 1958, Chichester was diagnosed with terminal lung cancer. (This might have been a misdiagnosis; David Lewis, a London doctor, who competed against Chichester in the first solo trans-Atlantic race, reviewed his case and called Chichester's abnormality a "lung abscess".&lt;ref&gt;Lewis, David. The Ship Would Not Travel Due West. London: St Martin's Press, 1962.&lt;/ref&gt;) His wife Sheila put him on a strict vegetarian diet (now considered to be a [[macrobiotic]] diet) and his cancer went into remission. Chichester then turned to long-distance [[yacht]]ing.

In 1960, he entered and won the first [[single-handed sailing|single-handed]] [[Single-Handed Trans-Atlantic Race|transatlantic yacht race]], which had been founded by [[Herbert Hasler|'Blondie' Hasler]], in the yacht ''Gipsy Moth III''. He came second in the second race four years later.

On 27 August 1966 Chichester sailed his ketch ''[[Gipsy Moth IV]]'' from [[Plymouth]] in the United Kingdom and returned there after 226 days of sailing on 28 May 1967, having [[circumnavigation|circumnavigated]] the globe, with one stop (in Sydney). By doing so, he became the first person to achieve a true [[Around the world sailing record|circumnavigation of the world]] solo from West to East via the [[great Capes]]. The voyage was also a race against the clock, as Chichester wanted to beat the typical times achieved by the fastest fully crewed [[clipper ship]]s during the heyday of commercial sail in the 19th century.

{{efn|The first recorded solo circumnavigation of the globe was achieved by '''[[Joshua Slocum]]''' in 1898 but it took him three years with numerous stops – Slocum also took up the harder challenge of sailing east to west, against the prevailing wind). Also, The Argentinian '''[[Vito Dumas]]''' is said to have circumnavigated in 1942-1943. '''[[Alec Rose|Sir Alec Rose]]''' completed a circumnavigation in 1967-1968.  In 1968–1969 '''[[Robin Knox-Johnston]]''' completed the '''first [[single-handed sailing|single-handed]] non-stop circumnavigation'''.}}

===Honours and later life===
[[File:Francis Chichester memorial Shirwell.jpg|thumb|140px|right|Memorial to Francis Chichester in St Peter's church, Shirwell]]
[[File:Francis Chichester Grave 2017.jpg|thumb|140px|right|The grave of Francis Chichester in the churchyard of [[Church of St Peter, Shirwell|St Peter's Church]] in [[Shirwell]], [[Devon]]]]
In July 1967, a few weeks after his solo circumnavigation, Chichester was knighted, being appointed a [[Knight Commander of the Order of the British Empire]] for "individual achievement and sustained endeavour in the navigation and seamanship of small craft".&lt;ref name="kbe-award" /&gt; For the ceremony, the Queen used the sword used by her predecessor [[Elizabeth I of England|Queen Elizabeth I]] to knight the adventurer [[Francis Drake|Sir Francis Drake]], the first Englishman with his crew to complete a circumnavigation. ''Gipsy Moth IV'' was preserved alongside the ''[[Cutty Sark]]'' at [[Greenwich]].

Chichester was also honoured in 1967 by a newly issued 1/9d (one [[shilling]] and nine pence) postage stamp, which showed him aboard ''Gipsy Moth IV''.  This went against an unwritten tradition of the [[General Post Office]], because Chichester was neither a member of the royal family nor dead when the stamp was issued.

In 1968, when [[Donald Crowhurst]] was trying to win the [[Sunday Times Golden Globe Race]], a single-handed round-the-world event, it was Chichester who dismissed Crowhurst's wildly exaggerated reports of his own progress, which had fooled many enthusiastic supporters.

In 1970, Chichester attempted to sail 4,000 miles in twenty days, in ''Gipsy Moth V'', but failed by one day.

Francis Chichester died of cancer in [[Plymouth]], Devon, on 26 August 1972, and was buried in the church of his ancestors, [[Church of St Peter, Shirwell|St Peter's Church]] in [[Shirwell]], near [[Barnstaple]]. His widow died in 1989 and is buried with him.

==Family==
{{unreferenced section|date=April 2016}}
Sir Francis Chichester had two sons, George and Giles. His younger son, [[Giles Chichester]], was for many years a British politician, and Conservative Member of the [[European Parliament]] for South West England and [[Gibraltar]].

==''Gipsy Moth IV's'' restoration==
{{unreferenced section|date=April 2016}}
By the early 2000s, the condition of ''Gipsy Moth IV'', even though it continued to rest in a Greenwich dry dock hoist, had seriously deteriorated.  Admirers of the vessel knew that she required a complete restoration if her life was to be extended.  A campaign was launched in 2003 by Paul Gelder, editor of ''Yachting Monthly'' magazine, to sail the yacht around the world a second time in observance of the 40th anniversary of Chichester's epic voyage (and coincidentally the 100th birthday of the magazine).

In November 2004 she was lifted out of Greenwich dry dock (which some had called the yacht's "grave") after being sold to the UK Sailing Academy in [[Cowes]], Isle of Wight, for a token £1 and a [[gin and tonic]], said to be Chichester's favourite tipple. The UKSA, ''Yachting Monthly'' and the Maritime Trust were the three major project partners in the bold campaign to save the yacht.  She was taken by road back to [[Camper &amp; Nicholson]], her original builders in [[Gosport]].

On 20 June 2005 ''Gipsy Moth IV'' was relaunched after a £400,000 refit with money raised by donations from the public, and equipment and services given by the British marine industry.  In September 2005 she embarked on a 21-month educational round-the-world voyage with the Blue Water Round the World Rally, via the trade wind route and the Panama and Suez Canals (not the Capes as had been followed in its first circumnavigation). In spring 2006, she ran aground on an atoll in the South Pacific.  An extensive restoration in Auckland was required to repair the yacht, which was successfully refloated in June 2006. After being accompanied into [[Plymouth]] by a flotilla of boats, ''Gipsy Moth IV'' docked at West Hoe Pier on 28 May 2007, as she had done exactly 40 years earlier, to complete her journey round the world.

The yacht's restoration and the second circumnavigation are described in Paul Gelder's 2007 book, ''Gipsy Moth IV: A Legend Sails Again''.

==Other posthumous honours==
[[File:9 St James's Place, London, September 2016 01.jpg|thumb|9 [[St James's Place]], London, September 2016]]

The English rock group [[Dire Straits]] pay tribute to the achievements of Sir Francis in their album track entitled ''Single Handed Sailor'', which is track No.8 (of 9) of their 1979 album, ''[[Communiqué (Dire Straits album)|Communiqué]]''.{{citation needed|date=April 2016}}

[[Norfolk Island]] issued a stamp, in 1981, commemorating the first landing of an aircraft on the Island, Chichester's Gipsy Moth ''Mme Elijah'', at Cascade Bay on 28 March 1931. Another stamp (14 cents) was issued by Norfolk Island at a later date showing Chichester's seaplane.{{citation needed|date=April 2016}}

A memorial plaque to Chichester was unveiled at the family home at 9 [[St James's Place]], SW1 in September 1993.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.westminster.gov.uk/services/leisureandculture/greenplaques |title=Archived copy |accessdate=2012-08-05 |deadurl=yes |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20120716210428/http://www.westminster.gov.uk/services/leisureandculture/greenplaques/ |archivedate=16 July 2012 |df=dmy-all }} memorial plaque&lt;/ref&gt;

==Bibliography==
* Observer's Books Nos 3–5 with sub-titles of ''Solo to Sydney (1932)'', ''Seaplane Solo'' (1933) and ''Ride the Wind'' (1936). These books cover the England – Sydney flight, the New Zealand – Australia flight, and Sydney – Japan flight respc.
* ''Astro-Navigation'' Parts I, II, III and IV(1940)
* ''Dead Reckoning Navigation'' (with co-authors of WJD Allan and William Alexander) – Observer's Book &lt;ref&gt;From ''The Spotter's Handbook, first published by George Allen (London) in 1941&lt;/ref&gt;
* ''Maps, Charts and Navigation'' (with the same co-authors of Allen and Alexander – Observer's Book).
* ''Planisphere of Air Navigation Stars'' – Observer's Book
* ''The Spotter's Handbook'' WWII aviation identification.&lt;ref&gt;First published by George Allen and Unwin London in 1940&lt;/ref&gt;
* ''Pinpoint the Bomber'' Game to teach map reading.
* ''The Star Compass''
* ''The Pocket Plansiphere''
* ''Night and Fire Spotting'' (1941)
* ''Star Recognition'' (1943). Identification of major stars for navigation with one labelled and one unlabelled star chart.
* ''Solo To Sydney'' (1930) &amp; (1982). Flying from England to Sydney, Australia.
* ''Ride On The Wind'' (1936) &amp; (1967) Flying from Sydney to Japan
* ''The Sun Compass''&lt;ref&gt;Detail from George Allen publication of ''Alone Across the Atlantic'' (1961)&lt;/ref&gt;
* ''Alone Across the Atlantic'' (1961) &lt;ref&gt;First published by George Allen and Unwin London and in numerous reprints&lt;/ref&gt; Sailing over the Atlantic.
* ''Atlantic Adventure'' (1962) More Atlantic Sailing
* ''Alone Over the Tasman Sea'' (1945, 1966) originally published as "Seaplane Solo" (1933) Flying from New Zealand to Australia via Norfolk and Lord Howe Islands
* ''The Lonely Sea and the Sky'' (1964) Autobiography
* ''Along The Clipper Way'' (1966 &amp; 1967) (anthology of sailing stories)
* ''Gipsy Moth Circles the World'' (1967). England – Sydney – England solo sailing voyage.
* ''How to Keep Fit'' (1969) Fitness
* ''The Romantic Challenge'' (1971) An attempt on a sailing record.

==References==
{{Reflist|refs=
&lt;ref name="kbe-award"&gt;{{London Gazette|issue=44241 |date=3 February 1967 |page=1299 }}&lt;/ref&gt;
}}

==Notes==
{{notelist}}

==External links==
{{commonscat|Francis Chichester}}
* [http://news.bbc.co.uk/onthisday/hi/dates/stories/may/28/newsid_2495000/2495799.stm BBC story from 1967]
* [http://www.gipsymoth.org/ "Gipsy Moth IV" website]
* [http://theopencritic.com/?p=11 Gipsy Moth Circles the World] at The Open Critic

{{Authority control}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Chichester, Francis}}
[[Category:1901 births]]
[[Category:1972 deaths]]
[[Category:Knights Commander of the Order of the British Empire]]
[[Category:People in sports awarded knighthoods]]
[[Category:People educated at Marlborough College]]
[[Category:English male sailors (sport)]]
[[Category:English emigrants to New Zealand]]
[[Category:People from Barnstaple]]
[[Category:People connected with Plymouth]]
[[Category:New Zealand male sailors (sport)]]
[[Category:Single-handed circumnavigating sailors]]
[[Category:Circumnavigators of the globe]]
[[Category:Deaths from lung cancer]]
[[Category:Maritime writers]]
[[Category:Deaths from cancer in England]]
[[Category:Chichester family|Francis]]</text>
      <sha1>j5sgn4nczegupveuda8s080qj2pqt5c</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
