<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10.xsd" version="0.10" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <dbname>enwiki</dbname>
    <base>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.32.0-wmf.16</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="118" case="first-letter">Draft</namespace>
      <namespace key="119" case="first-letter">Draft talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2300" case="first-letter">Gadget</namespace>
      <namespace key="2301" case="first-letter">Gadget talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2302" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition</namespace>
      <namespace key="2303" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Frank Luke</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>184659</id>
    <revision>
      <id>853307138</id>
      <parentid>850933408</parentid>
      <timestamp>2018-08-03T20:29:55Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Pminx</username>
        <id>4422923</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>/* Other aces */</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="17537">&lt;!-- This article is a part of [[Wikipedia:WikiProject Aircraft]] and [[Wikipedia:WikiProject Biography/Military]]. --&gt;
{{Infobox military person
|name= Frank Luke, Jr.
| image_size        = 250
|birth_date= {{Birth date|1897|5|19}}
|death_date= {{Death date and age|1918|9|29|1897|5|19}}
|birth_place= [[Phoenix, Arizona|Phoenix]], [[Arizona Territory]]
|death_place= [[Murvaux]], [[France]]
|placeofburial=
|placeofburial_label= Place of burial
|image=Frank Luke cph.3a45244.jpg
|caption=[[File:cmoh army.jpg|90px]]&lt;br&gt;Medal of Honor recipient Frank Luke, Jr.
|nickname= "Arizona Balloon Buster"
| allegiance    = {{flag|United States|23px}}
| branch        = [[Air Service, United States Army]]
|serviceyears= 1917–1918
|rank= [[Second Lieutenant#United States|Second Lieutenant]] (posthumously promoted to First Lieutenant)
|commands=
|unit=
| battles       = [[File:World War I Victory Medal ribbon.svg|50px]]&amp;nbsp;[[World War I]]
* [[Meuse-Argonne Offensive]]
|awards= [[Medal of Honor]]&lt;br/&gt;[[Distinguished Service Cross (United States)|Distinguished Service Cross]] (2)&lt;br/&gt;[[War Merit Cross (Italy)|Croce al Merito di Guerra]] (Italian)
|laterwork=
}}

'''Frank Luke Jr.''' (May 19, 1897&amp;nbsp;– September 29, 1918) was an American [[fighter ace]], ranking second among [[United States Army Air Service|U.S. Army Air Service]] pilots after Captain [[Eddie Rickenbacker]] in number of aerial victories during [[World War I]] (Rickenbacker was credited with 26 victories, while Luke's official score was 18). Frank Luke was the first airman to receive the [[Medal of Honor]].&lt;ref name="arm" /&gt; [[Luke Air Force Base]], Arizona, a U.S. Air Force pilot training installation since World War II, is named in his honor.

==Biography==
Luke was born May 19, 1897, in [[Phoenix, Arizona]], after his family emigrated from Germany to America in 1874 and settled there. Frank was his family's fifth child, and had eight other brothers and sisters. He grew up excelling in sports, working in copper mines, and participating in bare-knuckle boxing matches. Following America's entry into World War I in April 1917, Frank enlisted in the [[Aviation Section, U.S. Signal Corps]] on September 25, 1917, and received pilot training in Texas and California. After being commissioned a [[Second Lieutenant#United States|Second Lieutenant]] in March 1918, he deployed to France for further training, and in July was assigned to the [[27th Fighter Squadron|27th Aero Squadron]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://afhra.maxwell.af.mil/rso/squadrons_flights_pages/0027fs.html 27th Fighter Squadron&lt;!-- bot-generated title --&gt;] {{webarchive|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20070313012658/http://afhra.maxwell.af.mil/rso/squadrons_flights_pages/0027fs.html |date=2007-03-13 }} at afhra.maxwell.af.mil&lt;/ref&gt;  Although Luke was still a second lieutenant at the time of his death, Stephen Skinner's book ''The Stand'' notes that he later received a posthumous promotion to first lieutenant.

Because of his arrogance and occasional tendencies to fly alone and disobey orders, Luke was disliked by some of his peers and superiors.  But the 27th was under standing orders to destroy German [[observation balloon]]s.  Because of this, Luke, along with his close friend Lt. [[Joseph Frank Wehner]], continually volunteered to attack these important targets although they were heavily defended by anti-aircraft guns on the ground.  The two pilots began a remarkable string of victories together, with Luke attacking the balloons and Wehner flying protective cover.  Wehner was killed in action on September 18, 1918, in a dogfight with [[Fokker D.VII]]s which were attacking Luke. Luke then shot down two of these D.VIIs and two balloons and a Halberstadt; the last "credit" enabled Luke to thereby achieve his 13th official kill—a Halberstadt Ctype observation plane of Flieger Abteilung 36.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.theaerodrome.com/forum/people/44756-lukes-13th-credit.html#post477402&lt;/ref&gt;

[[File:Frank Luke.gif|250px|right|thumb|Luke with his 13th official kill September 18, 1918]]

Between September 12 and September 29, Luke was credited with shooting down 14 German balloons and four airplanes:&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.theaerodrome.com/aces/usa/luke1.php Frank Luke - The Aerodrome - Aces and Aircraft of World War I&lt;!-- bot-generated title --&gt;] at www.theaerodrome.com&lt;/ref&gt; Luke achieved these 18 victories during just 10 sorties in eight days, a feat unsurpassed by any pilot in World War&amp;nbsp;I.&lt;ref name="arm" /&gt;

==Death—September 29, 1918==
[[File:frankluke.jpg|thumb|right|Lt. Frank Luke, Jr. with his [[SPAD S.XIII]] on September 19, 1918.]]
[[File:Phoenix-Frank Luke Jr. SPAD XIII-Sky Harbor Airport-1.JPG|250px|thumb|A [[SPAD XIII]] painted to represent the one flown by Frank Luke, Jr. The plane is approximately 80% original parts from several aircraft. It is one of five surviving today and is on display in Terminal 3 of [[Phoenix, Arizona|Phoenix's]] [[Phoenix Sky Harbor International Airport|Sky Harbor Airport]].]]

Luke's final flight took place during the first phase of the [[Meuse-Argonne Offensive]]. On September 28, after achieving his 14th and 15th victories, he landed his [[SPAD XIII]] at the French aerodrome at [[Cicognes]] where he spent the night, claiming engine trouble.&lt;ref name="smith-strickland"&gt;{{cite web|last=Smith-Strickland |first=Kiona |title=The Arizona Dragonslayer |url=http://www.damninteresting.com/the-arizona-dragonslayer/ |publisher=www.damninteresting.com|accessdate=9 September 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt; When he returned to the 1st Pursuit Group's base at [[Rembercourt-Sommaisne|Rembercourt]] the next day, he was confronted by Captain Alfred A. Grant, his squadron's commanding officer (C.O.). Despite being under threat of arrest by Grant for being [[Desertion#Absence without leave|AWOL]], Luke took off without authorization and flew to a forward airbase at [[Verdun]], where his sympathetic group commander, Major Hartney, canceled the arrest order and gave Luke tacit approval to continue his balloon hunting.&lt;ref name="smith-strickland" /&gt; That evening Luke flew to the front to attack three balloons in the vicinity of [[Dun-sur-Meuse]], six miles behind the German lines. He first dropped a message to a nearby U.S. balloon company, alerting them to observe his imminent attacks.  Luke shot down the enemy balloons, but was then severely wounded by a single [[machine gun]] bullet fired from a hilltop above him, a mile east of the last balloon site he had attacked.&lt;ref name="arm" /&gt; Luke landed in a field just west of the small village of [[Murvaux]]—after strafing a group of German soldiers on the ground—near the Ruisseau de Bradon, a stream leading to the Meuse River.  Although weakened by his wound, he made his way toward the stream, intending to reach the cover of its adjacent underbrush, but finally collapsed some 200 meters from his airplane. Approached by German infantry, Luke drew his [[Colt Model 1911]] pistol and fired a few rounds at his attackers before dying. Reports that a day later his body was found with an empty gun and a bullet hole in his chest, with seven dead Germans in front of him were proven erroneous.&lt;ref name="arm" /&gt;  According to author Skinner, the fatal bullet, fired from the hilltop machine gun position, had entered near Luke's right shoulder, passed through his body, and exited from his left side.

On September 30 the Germans buried Luke in the Murvaux cemetery, from where his body was retrieved two months later by American forces.  His final resting place is the [[Meuse-Argonne American Cemetery and Memorial]], located east of the village of [[Romagne-sous-Montfaucon]].

After the US Army obtained sworn testimony from French and American sources, Luke was awarded a [[Posthumous recognition|posthumous]] [[Medal of Honor]].  The presentation was made to Frank Luke, Sr., in Phoenix in May 1919. The family later donated the medal to the National Museum of the United States Air Force near Dayton, Ohio.  The museum's small exhibit honoring Lt. Frank Luke also contains his flying goggles, the gunsight from his last SPAD, documents written by Luke, and other personal items.  The museum's Early Years Gallery displays a fully restored SPAD XIII of the type flown by Luke.

Eddie Rickenbacker said of Luke: "He was the most daring aviator and greatest fighter pilot of the entire war. His life is one of the brightest glories of our Air Service. He went on a rampage and shot down fourteen enemy aircraft, including ten balloons, in eight days. No other ace, even the dreaded [[Red Baron|Richthofen]], had ever come close to that."&lt;ref name="arm" /&gt;

==Other aces==
Luke is often cited as the second-ranking American ace of World War I, but that statement ignores certain American pilots who flew with other Allied air services. Luke was, however, second only to Rickenbacker among pilots serving only with the AEF. (It is noteworthy that Luke's time on the front was comparatively quite short, and 17 of Luke's 18 victories were officially recorded as destroyed, versus only 11 of Rickenbacker's 26.)  Americans flying with Britain's Royal Flying Corps (Royal Air Force from April 1918) who exceeded Luke's score were [[Frederick W. Gillet]] (20 claims, all destroyed); [[Harold Albert Kullberg]], DFC, Lt. 1 Sqn RFC (19 confirmed) and [[Wilfred Beaver]] (19 claims, 12 destroyed).  Tied with Luke at 18 was [[William C. Lambert]] (18 claims).&lt;ref name=Miltarytimes/&gt;

==Honors and awards==

===Medal of Honor citation===
Rank and Organization: Second Lieutenant, 27th Aero Squadron, 1st Pursuit Group. Place and Date: Near Murvaux, France, September 29, 1918. Entered Service At: Phoenix, Ariz. Born:  May 19, 1897, Phoenix, Ariz. G. O. No.: 59, W.D., 1919.

'''Citation:'''

&lt;blockquote&gt;After having previously destroyed a number of enemy aircraft within 17&amp;nbsp;days he voluntarily started on a patrol after German observation balloons. Though pursued by 8 German planes which were protecting the enemy balloon line, he unhesitatingly attacked and shot down in flames 3 German balloons, being himself under heavy fire from ground batteries and the hostile planes. Severely wounded, he descended to within 50 meters of the ground, and flying at this low altitude near the town of Murvaux opened fire upon enemy troops, killing 6 and wounding as many more. Forced to make a landing and surrounded on all sides by the enemy, who called upon him to surrender, he drew his automatic pistol and defended himself gallantly until he fell dead from a wound in the chest.&lt;ref name=Miltarytimes&gt;{{Cite web
|accessdate=2009-08-07
|url=http://www.militarytimes.com/citations-medals-awards/recipient.php?recipientid=896
|title=Hall of Valor
|work= Frank Luke
|publisher=Military Times}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

The citation contained errors attributable to confused accounts from French witnesses to Luke's final flight, and to a staff officer's re-write of the original write-up, which emphasized the numerous high-risk missions he flew between September 12 and 29.&lt;ref name="arm"&gt;{{cite journal| last = Correll| first = John T.| year = 2009| title = The Legend of Frank Luke| journal = AIR FORCE Magazine | volume = 92| issue = August| pages = 48–51 | url =http://www.airforce-magazine.com/MagazineArchive/Pages/2009/August%202009/0809luke.aspx| accessdate =6 August 2009 }}&lt;/ref&gt;  Reports that he was intercepted by German fighters, strafed enemy troops before his forced landing; and was "surrounded on all sides" were literal mis-interpretations of French testimony and became part of the mythology that grew up around the event.&lt;ref name="arm" /&gt;
[[File:Frank_Luke_statue,_Phoenix_AZ.jpg|thumb|250px|right|Luke statue, Phoenix, Arizona, Roger Noble Burnham, sculptor, 1930]]
===First Distinguished Service Cross===
'''Citation:'''
&lt;blockquote&gt;The President of the United States of America, authorized by Act of Congress, July 9, 1918, takes pride in presenting the Distinguished Service Cross (Posthumously) to Second Lieutenant (Air Service) Frank Luke, Jr., United States Army Air Service, for extraordinary heroism in action while serving with 27th Aero Squadron, 1st Pursuit Group, U.S. Army Air Service, A.E.F., near St. Mihiel, France, September 12 to 15, 1918. Lieutenant Luke, by skill, determination, and bravery, and in the face of heavy enemy fire, successfully destroyed eight enemy observation balloons in four days.&lt;ref name=Miltarytimes/&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

===Second Distinguished Service Cross===
'''Citation:'''
&lt;blockquote&gt;The President of the United States of America, authorized by Act of Congress, July 9, 1918, takes pride in presenting a Bronze Oak Leaf Cluster in lieu of a Second Award of the Distinguished Service Cross (Posthumously) to Second Lieutenant (Air Service) Frank Luke, Jr., United States Army Air Service, for extraordinary heroism in action while serving with 27th Aero Squadron, 1st Pursuit Group, U.S. Army Air Service, A.E.F., near Etain, France, 18 September 1918. Immediately after destroying two enemy observation balloons, Lieutenant Luke was attacked by a large formation of German planes, Fokker type. He turned to attack two, which were directly behind him, and shot them down. Sighting an enemy biplane, although his gasoline was nearly gone, he attacked and destroyed this machine also.&lt;ref name=Miltarytimes/&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

===Other honors===
* [[Luke Air Force Base]], located west of Phoenix, Arizona, was named after Luke.
* [http://ww1mproject.org/items/show/1250 Memorial Statue] on the grounds of the State Capitol in Phoenix, Arizona.
* Memorial to Frank Luke and other members of the Phoenix Union High School Class of 1918, in front of the old Phoenix Union High School Building, Phoenix, Arizona.
*From 1919 to 1932, [[Ford Island|Luke Field]], [[Territory of Hawaii]], was named after Luke.
* [[Lukeville, Arizona]], on the U.S. border is named after Luke.
*Frank Luke was named the Class Exemplar of the [[United States Air Force Academy]]'s class of 2010.
*In the 2006 movie [[Flyboys (film)|Flyboys]], [[James Franco]]'s leading character Blaine Rawlings is inspired by Frank Luke.
*Frank Luke Street near [[Addison Airport]] in [[Addison, Texas]] is named after Luke.

==See also==
{{Portal|United States Air Force|Military of the United States|World War I|Biography}}
* [[List of Medal of Honor recipients for World War I]]
* [[List of World War I flying aces from the United States]]

==References==
{{Reflist}}
{{Refbegin}}
{{Refend}}

==Bibliography==
;General
* {{Cite book
 |url=http://www.thestandfrankluke.com/
 |title=The Stand: The Final Flight of Lt. Frank Luke, Jr.
 |author=Stephen Skinner
 |publisher=Schiffer Military History Books
 |accessdate=2007-03-08}}
* {{Cite web
 |url=http://www.theaerodrome.com/aces/usa/luke1.html
 |title=Frank Luke
 |work=Aces and Aircraft of World War I
 |publisher=The Aerodrome
 |accessdate=2006-03-14}}
* {{Cite web
 |url=http://www.frankluke.com
 |title=The Frank Luke Jr. Documentary
 |author=King, Tim
 |accessdate=2006-07-16}}
* {{Cite web
 |url=http://www.af.mil/news/story.asp?storyID=123006460
 |title=Lieutenant Frank Luke Jr.
 |work=Air Force Link
 |publisher= [[United States Air Force]]
 |accessdate=2006-07-16}}
* {{Cite web
 |url         = http://www.airman.af.mil/heritage/heritage_3.htm
 |title       = Medal of Honor recipients
 |work        = Airman Airforce Heritage
 |publisher   = [[United States Air Force]]
 |accessdate  = 2006-07-16
 |deadurl     = yes
 |archiveurl  = https://web.archive.org/web/20060714024758/http://www.airman.af.mil/heritage/heritage_3.htm
 |archivedate = 2006-07-14
 |df          = 
}}
*  Pardoe, Blaine. ''Terror of The Autumn Skies: The True Story oF Frank Luke, America's Rogue Ace of World War I'', New York, 2008
* {{Cite book
 |url=https://www.amazon.com/Above-Beyond-Incredible-Arizonas-Flying/dp/1507727275
 |title=Above and Beyond: The Incredible Story of Frank Luke Jr., Arizona's Medal of Honor Flying Ace of the First World War
 |author=Lloyd, Keith Warren
 |publisher=CreateSpace Publishing
 |accessdate=2015-01-31}}

==External links==
* {{Cite web |accessdate=November 30, 2013 |url=https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=GlcccNq_-cs |title=WW1 American Aces Interviews/Documentary 1989: Ace's High}}
* {{Cite web |accessdate=October 5, 2010 |url=http://www.acepilots.com/wwi/us_luke.html |title=Frank Luke at Acepilots.com}}
* {{Cite web |accessdate=October 5, 2010 |url=http://www.usaww1.com |title=July 14, 2008 - 90th anniversary Commemoration of Frank Luke and 1st Pursuit Group in France}}
* {{Cite web |accessdate=October 5, 2010 |url=http://www.indysquadron.com/thestandfrankluke/index.html |title=Indy Squadron |deadurl=yes |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20100804021935/http://www.indysquadron.com/thestandfrankluke/index.html |archivedate=August 4, 2010 |df= }}
*{{Find a Grave|9233|Frank Luke, Jr|work=Claim to Fame: Medal of Honor recipients}}

{{Authority control}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Luke, Frank, Jr.}}
[[Category:1897 births]]
[[Category:1918 deaths]]
[[Category:People from Phoenix, Arizona]]
[[Category:American World War I flying aces]]
[[Category:United States Army Medal of Honor recipients]]
[[Category:United States Army officers]]
[[Category:American people of German descent]]
[[Category:American military personnel killed in World War I]]
[[Category:Burials at Meuse-Argonne American Cemetery]]
[[Category:Recipients of the Distinguished Service Cross (United States)]]
[[Category:Recipients of the War Merit Cross (Italy)]]
[[Category:World War I recipients of the Medal of Honor]]</text>
      <sha1>2vu0rbj8iqh82anh8pw11xojm6gnhpa</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
