<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10.xsd" version="0.10" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <dbname>enwiki</dbname>
    <base>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.32.0-wmf.16</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="118" case="first-letter">Draft</namespace>
      <namespace key="119" case="first-letter">Draft talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2300" case="first-letter">Gadget</namespace>
      <namespace key="2301" case="first-letter">Gadget talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2302" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition</namespace>
      <namespace key="2303" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Glenn Curtiss</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>290046</id>
    <revision>
      <id>855620014</id>
      <parentid>855012897</parentid>
      <timestamp>2018-08-19T17:01:21Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Yestertempest</username>
        <id>33589252</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>added category</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="33395">{{For|the basketball player|Glenn M. Curtis}}
&lt;!-- This article is a part of [[Wikipedia:WikiProject Aircraft]]. Please see [[Wikipedia:WikiProject Aircraft/page content]] for recommended layout. --&gt;{{Infobox person
| name        = Glenn Curtiss
| image       = Glenn Curtiss - 1909 (cropped).jpg
| image_size  =
| caption     = Glenn Curtiss ''circa'' 1909
| birth_name  = Glenn Hammond Curtiss
| birth_date  = May 21, 1878
| birth_place = [[Hammondsport, New York]]
| death_date  = {{death date and age|1930|07|23|1878|05|21|mf=y}}
| death_place = [[Buffalo, New York]]
| occupation  = [[Aviator]] &lt;br&gt; Company director
| known for   = Cycle racing &lt;br&gt; Motorcycle racing &lt;br&gt; Air racing &lt;br&gt; [[Naval aviation]]&lt;br&gt; [[Flying boats]] &lt;br&gt; [[Transatlantic flight]]
| spouse      = Lena Pearl Neff (March 7, 1898 – until his death)
| children    = 2
}}
'''Glenn Hammond Curtiss''' (May 21, 1878 – July 23, 1930) was an American [[aviation]] and [[motorcycling]] pioneer, and a founder of the U.S. aircraft industry. He began his career as a bicycle racer and builder before moving on to motorcycles. As early as 1904, he began to manufacture engines for airships. In 1908, Curtiss joined the [[Aerial Experiment Association]], a pioneering research group, founded by [[Alexander Graham Bell]] at [[Beinn Bhreagh|Beinn Bhreagh, Nova Scotia]], to build flying machines.

Curtiss made the first officially witnessed flight in North America, won a race at the world's first international air meet in France, and made the first long-distance flight in the United States. His contributions in designing and building aircraft led to the formation of the [[Curtiss Aeroplane and Motor Company]], now part of [[Curtiss-Wright Corporation]]. His company built aircraft for the U.S. Army and Navy, and, during the years leading up to World War I, his experiments with seaplanes led to advances in naval aviation. Curtiss civil and military aircraft were predominant in the interwar and World War II eras.
{{TOC limit|limit=2}}

==Birth and early career==
Curtiss was born in 1878 in [[Hammondsport, New York]], to Frank Richmond Curtiss and Lua Andrews. Although his formal education extended only to [[eighth grade]], his early interest in mechanics and inventions was evident at his first job at the Eastman Dry Plate and Film Company (later [[Eastman Kodak Company]]) in [[Rochester, New York]].&lt;ref name= "Roseberry p.10"&gt;Roseberry 1972, p. 10.&lt;/ref&gt; He invented a stencil machine adopted at the plant and later built a rudimentary camera to study photography.&lt;ref name= "Roseberry p.10"/&gt;

==Marriage and family==
On March 7, 1898, Curtiss married Lena Pearl Neff (1879–1951), daughter of Guy L. Neff and Jenny M. Potter, in Hammondsport, New York. They had two children: 
Carlton N. Curtiss (1901–1902) and
Glenn Hammond Curtiss (1912–1969)

==Bicycles and motorcycles==
[[File:Glenn Curtiss on his V-8 motorcycle, Ormond Beach, Florida 1907.jpg|thumb|Glenn Curtiss on his [[Curtiss V-8 motorcycle|V-8 motorcycle]] in 1907]]
Curtiss began his career as a [[Western Union]] [[bicycle messenger]], a [[bicycle]] racer, and bicycle-shop owner. In 1901, he developed an interest in motorcycles when internal-combustion engines became more available. In 1902, Curtiss began manufacturing motorcycles with his own single-cylinder engines. His first motorcycle's [[carburetor]] was adapted from a tomato soup can containing a gauze screen to pull the gasoline up by [[capillary action]].&lt;ref&gt;Post, August. [https://books.google.com/books?id=OnoAAAAAYAAJ&amp;pg=PA13&amp;dq=tomato+glenn+curtiss&amp;hl=en&amp;ei=CMlFTKHnEIjksQPMj83cAg&amp;sa=X&amp;oi=book_result&amp;ct=result&amp;resnum=7&amp;ved=0CEsQ6AEwBg#v=onepage&amp;q=tomato%20curtiss&amp;f=false "The Evolution of a Flying-Man"], ''The Century: A Popular Quarterly'', Volume 81, 1911, pp. 13–14. Retrieved: July 20, 2010.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Curtiss, Glenn Hammond and August Post. [https://books.google.com/books?id=X_sJAAAAIAAJ&amp;pg=PA16&amp;dq=tomato&amp;hl=en&amp;ei=CMlFTKHnEIjksQPMj83cAg&amp;sa=X&amp;oi=book_result&amp;ct=result&amp;resnum=2&amp;ved=0CDIQ6AEwAQ#v=onepage&amp;q=tomato&amp;f=false ''The Curtiss Aviation Book.''] New York: Frederick A. Stokes Company, 1912 (reprint). {{ISBN|0-559-64105-2}}. Retrieved: July 20, 2010.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[https://books.google.com/books?id=pycDAAAAMBAJ&amp;pg=PA130 "Glenn Curtiss."] ''[[Popular Science]]'', March 1927, p. 130. ISSN 0161-7370.&lt;/ref&gt; In 1903, he set a [[motorcycle land speed record]] at {{convert|64|mph|km/h}} for one mile (1.6&amp;nbsp;km). When E.H. Corson of the Hendee Mfg Co (manufacturers of [[Indian (motorcycle)|Indian motorcycles]]) visited Hammondsport in July 1904, he was amazed that the entire Curtiss motorcycle enterprise was located in the back room of the modest "shop". Corson's motorcycles had just been trounced the week before by "Hell Rider" Curtiss in an endurance race from New York to [[Cambridge, Maryland]].&lt;ref&gt;Harvey 2005, p. 254.&lt;/ref&gt;

On January 21, 1906,&lt;ref&gt;Scientific American, Volume 96, Number 06, February 1906&lt;/ref&gt; Curtiss set an unofficial world record of {{convert|136.36|mph|km/h}}, on a {{convert|40|hp|kW}} {{convert|269|cuin|cc|abbr=on}} [[Curtiss V-8 motorcycle|V-8-powered motorcycle]] of his own design and construction in [[Ormond Beach, Florida]]. The air-cooled [[F-head]] engine was intended for use in aircraft.&lt;ref&gt;House 2003, p. 40.&lt;/ref&gt; He remained "the fastest man in the world", the title the newspapers gave him, until 1911,&lt;ref name="Roseberry p.57"&gt;Roseberry 1972, p. 57.&lt;/ref&gt; and his motorcycle record was not broken until 1930. This motorcycle is now in the [[Smithsonian Institution]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.nasm.si.edu/imageDetail.cfm?imageID=1553 "Curtiss V-8 Motorcycle."] {{webarchive|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20100906140855/http://www.nasm.si.edu/imagedetail.cfm?imageID=1553 |date=2010-09-06 }} ''Smithsonian Air and Space Museum Collections.'' Retrieved: February 24, 2011.&lt;/ref&gt; Curtiss's success at racing strengthened his reputation as a leading maker of high-performance motorcycles and engines.&lt;ref&gt;Hatch 2007, p. 36.&lt;/ref&gt;

[[File:Curtiss Motorcycle at San Francisco Motorcycle Club.jpg|thumb|Curtiss Motorcycle at San Francisco Motorcycle Club in 2018]]

==Aviation pioneer==

===Curtiss, motor expert===
In 1904, Curtiss became a supplier of engines for the California "aeronaut" [[Thomas Scott Baldwin|Tom Baldwin]]. In that same year, Baldwin's ''California Arrow'', powered by a Curtiss 9 HP V-twin motorcycle engine, became the first successful [[dirigible]] in America.&lt;ref name="Roseberry p.41"&gt;Roseberry 1972, p. 41.&lt;/ref&gt;

In 1907, [[Alexander Graham Bell]] invited Curtiss to develop a suitable engine for heavier-than-air flight experimentation. Bell regarded Curtiss as "the greatest motor expert in the country"&lt;ref name="Roseberry p.71"&gt;Roseberry 1972, p. 71.&lt;/ref&gt; and invited Curtiss to join his [[Aerial Experiment Association]] (AEA).

===AEA aircraft experiments===
[[File:Curtiss june bug.jpg|thumb|The ''June Bug'' on its prize-winning historic flight with Curtiss at the controls]]
Between 1908 and 1910, the AEA produced four aircraft, each one an improvement over the last. Curtiss primarily designed the AEA's third aircraft, Aerodrome #3, the famous ''[[AEA June Bug|June Bug]],'' and became its test pilot, undertaking most of the proving flights. On July 4, 1908, he flew {{convert|5080|ft|m|abbr=on}} to win the [[Scientific American]] Trophy and its $2,500 prize.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.centennialofflight.net/essay/Explorers_Record_Setters_and_Daredevils/Curtiss/EX3.htm "Glenn H. Curtiss."] ''centennialofflight.net'', 2003. Retrieved: July 20, 2009.&lt;/ref&gt; This was considered to be the first pre-announced public flight of a heavier-than-air flying machine in America.  On June 8, 1911 Curtiss received U.S. Pilot's License #1 from the [[Aero Club of America]], because the first batch of licenses were issued in alphabetical order; Wilbur Wright received license #5.  The flight of the ''June Bug'' propelled Curtiss and aviation firmly into public awareness.  At the culmination of the Aerial Experiment Association's experiments, Curtiss offered to purchase the rights to Aerodrome #3, essentially using it as the basis of his "[[Curtiss No. 1]], the first of his production series of pusher aircraft.&lt;ref&gt;Casey 1981, p. 38.&lt;/ref&gt;

===The pre-war years===

====Aviation competitions====
During the 1909–1910 period, Curtiss employed a number of demonstration pilots, including [[Eugene Burton Ely|Eugene Ely]], [[Charles K. Hamilton]], [[Augustus Post]], and [[Hugh Robinson (aviator)|Hugh Robinson]]. Aerial competitions and demonstration flights across North America helped to introduce aviation to a curious public; Curtiss took full advantage of these occasions to promote his products.&lt;ref&gt;Casey 1981, pp. 65–67.&lt;/ref&gt; This was a busy period for Glenn Curtiss.

[[File:Curtiss_France.jpg|thumb|right|upright|Souvenir [[postcard]] of the ''Grande Semaine d'Aviation'', 1909]]
In August 1909, Curtiss took part in the ''[[Grande Semaine d'Aviation]]'' aviation meeting at [[Reims]], [[France]], organized by the [[Aéro-Club de France]]. The [[Wright Brothers|Wrights]], who were selling their machines to customers in Germany at the time, decided not to compete in person. Two Wright aircraft (modified with a landing gear) were at the meet, but they did not win any events.  Flying his [[Curtiss No. 2|No. 2 biplane]], Curtiss won the overall speed event, the [[Gordon Bennett Trophy (aeroplanes)|Gordon Bennett Cup]], completing the 20-km (12.5-mile) course in just under 16&amp;nbsp;minutes at a speed of {{convert|46.5|mph|km/h|abbr=on}}, six seconds faster than runner-up [[Louis Blériot]]. {{#tag:ref|Curtiss was awarded French pilot's license No. 2 as a tribute to his Gordon Bennett Cup victory.&lt;ref&gt;Roseberry 1972, p. 320.&lt;/ref&gt; Blériot held No. 1 and Leon Delagrange No. 3, as the first 16 certificates of the Aero Club de France were retrospectively numbered on 4 December 1909 in alphabetical order.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.flightglobal.com/pdfarchive/view/1952/1952%20-%200057.html "Forty-eight Years Back; Some Notable Aviation Anniversaries: Recollections of the Early Certificate-holders."] ''Flight,''  4 January 1952.&lt;/ref&gt;|group=N}}

On May 29, 1910, Curtiss flew from Albany to New York City to make the first long-distance flight between two major cities in the U.S. For this {{convert|137|mi|km|adj=on}} flight, which he completed in just under four hours including two stops to refuel, he won a $10,000 prize offered by publisher [[Joseph Pulitzer]] and was awarded permanent possession of the ''Scientific American ''trophy.

In June 1910, Curtiss provided a simulated bombing demonstration to naval officers at Hammondsport. Two months later, Lt. Jacob E. Fickel demonstrated the feasibility of shooting at targets on the ground from an aircraft with Curtiss serving as pilot. One month later, in September, he trained [[Blanche Stuart Scott]], who was possibly the first American woman pilot. The fictional character [[Tom Swift]], who first appeared in 1910 in ''[[Tom Swift and His Motor Cycle]]'' and ''[[Tom Swift and His Airship]]'', has been said to have been based on Glenn Curtiss.&lt;ref name= "Dizer p.35"&gt;Dizer 1982, p. 35.&lt;/ref&gt; The Tom Swift books are set in a small town on a lake in upstate New York.&lt;ref&gt;Karenko, J. P. [http://www.tomswift.info/homepage/mcycle.html "Tom Swift and his Motorcycle."] ''tomswift.info'', August 1, 2006. Retrieved: September 8, 2009.&lt;/ref&gt;

===Naval aviation===
On November 14, 1910, Curtiss demonstration pilot [[Eugene Ely]] took off from a temporary platform mounted on the forward deck of the cruiser [[USS Birmingham (CL-2)|USS ''Birmingham'']]. His successful takeoff and ensuing flight to shore marked the beginning of a relationship between Curtiss and the Navy that remained significant for decades. At the end of 1910, Curtiss established a winter encampment at San Diego to teach flying to Army and Naval personnel. Here, he trained Lt. [[Theodore Ellyson]], who became U.S. Naval Aviator #1, and three Army officers, 1st Lt. [[Paul W. Beck]], 2nd Lt. [[George E. M. Kelly]], and 2nd Lt. John C. Walker, Jr., in the first military aviation school. ([[Chikuhei Nakajima]], founder of [[Nakajima Aircraft Company]], was a 1912 graduate.) The original site of this winter encampment is now part of [[Naval Air Station North Island]] and is referred to by the Navy as "The Birthplace of Naval Aviation".

Through the course of that winter, Curtiss was able to develop a float (pontoon) design that enabled him to take off and land on water. On January 26, 1911, he flew the first [[seaplane]] from the water in the United States.&lt;ref&gt;Roseberry 1972, p. 314.&lt;/ref&gt; Demonstrations of this advanced design were of great interest to the Navy, but more significant, as far as the Navy was concerned, was Eugene Ely successfully landing his Curtiss pusher (the same aircraft used to take off from the ''Birmingham'') on a makeshift platform mounted on the rear deck of the battleship [[USS Pennsylvania (ACR-4)|USS ''Pennsylvania'']]. This was the first [[Arresting gear|arrester-cable]] landing on a ship and the precursor of modern-day carrier operations. On January 28, 1911, Ellyson took off in a Curtiss “grass cutter” to become the first Naval aviator.
[[File:Aero and Hydro cover 14 March 1914.jpg|thumb|upright|"FIRM BELIEVERS IN TRANS-ATLANTIC AVIATION", Porte and Curtiss on the cover of ''Aero and Hydro'', 14 March 1914]]
Curtiss custom built floats and adapted them onto a [[Curtiss Model D|Model D]] so it could take off and land on water to prove the concept. On February 24, 1911, Curtiss made his first amphibious demonstration at North Island by taking off and alighting on both land and water. Back in Hammondsport, six months later in July 1911, Curtiss sold the U.S. Navy their first aircraft, the A-1 ''Triad''. The A-1, which was primarily a seaplane, was equipped with retractable wheels, also making it the first amphibious aircraft. Curtiss trained the Navy's first pilots and built their first aircraft. For this, he is considered in the USA to be "The Father of Naval Aviation". The Triad was immediately recognized as so obviously useful, it was purchased by the U.S. Navy, Russia, Japan, Germany, and Britain. Curtiss won the [[Collier Trophy]] for designing this aircraft.&lt;ref name="The Curtiss Company"&gt;[http://www.centennialofflight.net/essay/Aerospace/Curtiss/Aero2.htm "The Curtiss Company."] ''US Centennial of Flight Commemoration,'' 2003.  Retrieved: January 28, 2011.&lt;/ref&gt;

Around this time, Curtiss met retired British naval officer [[John Cyril Porte]], who was looking for a partner to produce an aircraft with him to win the ''[[Daily Mail]]'' prize for the first [[transatlantic crossing]]. In 1912, Curtiss produced the two-seat ''[[Curtiss Model F|Flying Fish]]'', a larger craft that became classified as a [[flying boat]] because the hull sat in the water; it featured an innovative notch (known as a "step") in the hull that Porte recommended for breaking clear of the water at [[takeoff]]. Curtiss correctly surmised that this configuration was more suited to building a larger long-distance craft that could operate from water, and was also more stable when operating from a choppy surface. Porte and Curtiss produced the [[Curtiss Model H|''America'']] in 1914, a larger flying boat with two engines, for the transatlantic crossing.

==World War I and later==

===World War I===
With the start of [[World War I]], Porte returned to service in the [[Royal Navy]], which subsequently purchased several models of the ''America'', now called the H-4, from Curtiss. Porte licensed and further developed the designs, constructing a range of [[Seaplane Experimental Station|Felixstowe]] long-range patrol aircraft, and from his experience passed along improvements to the hull to Curtiss. The later British designs were sold to the U.S. forces, or built by Curtiss as the [[Felixstowe F5L|F5L]]. The Curtiss factory also built a total of 68 "Large Americas", which evolved into the [[Curtiss Model H|H-12]], the only American-designed and -built aircraft to see combat in World War I.
[[File:Flying jenny cropped.jpg|thumb|A Curtiss JN-4 (Jenny) on a training flight during World War I]]
As 1916 approached, the United States was feared to be drawn into the conflict. The Army's [[Aviation Section, U.S. Signal Corps]] ordered the development of a simple, easy-to-fly-and-maintain, two-seat trainer. Curtiss created the [[JN-4]] "Jenny" for the Army, and the N-9 seaplane version for the Navy. They were some of the most famous products of the Curtiss company, and thousands were sold to the militaries of the United States, Canada, and Britain. Civilian and military aircraft demand boomed, and the company grew to employ 18,000 workers in Buffalo and 3,000 workers in Hammondsport.

In 1917, the U.S. Navy commissioned Curtiss to design a long-range, four-engined flying boat large enough to hold a crew of five, which became known as the [[Curtiss NC]]. The four NC flying boats attempted a transatlantic crossing in 1919, and the [[NC-4]] successfully crossed. It is now on permanent display in the National Museum of Naval Aviation in Pensacola, Florida.

===Patent dispute===
{{See also|Wright brothers patent war}}
A patent lawsuit by the Wright brothers against Curtiss in 1909 continued until it was resolved during World War I. Since the last Wright aircraft, the Wright Model L, was a single prototype of a "scouting" aircraft, made in 1916, the [[Government of the United States|U.S. government]], desperately short of combat aircraft, pressured both firms to resolve the dispute. In 1917, the U.S. government offered a large and profitable contract to Curtiss to build aircraft for the U.S. Army.

===Post-World War I===
Peace brought cancellation of wartime contracts. In September 1920, the Curtiss Aeroplane and Motor Company underwent a financial reorganization. Glenn Curtiss cashed out his stock in the company for $32 million and retired to Florida.&lt;ref&gt;Rosenberry 1972, p. 429.&lt;/ref&gt; He continued on as a director of the company, but served only as an adviser on design. [[Clement Melville Keys|Clement M. Keys]] gained control of the company, which later became the nucleus of a large group of aviation companies.&lt;ref&gt;Studer 1937, p. 352.&lt;/ref&gt;

===Later years===
Curtiss and his family moved to Florida in the 1920s, where he founded 18 corporations, served on civic commissions, and donated extensive land and water rights. He co-developed the city of [[Hialeah, Florida|Hialeah]] with James Bright and developed the cities of [[Opa-locka, Florida|Opa-locka]] and [[Miami Springs, Florida|Miami Springs]], where he built a family home, known variously as the [[Glenn Curtiss House|Miami Springs Villas House, Dar-Err-Aha, MSTR No. 2, or Glenn Curtiss House]].&lt;ref name="Life"&gt;[http://www.aviation-history.com/early/curtiss.htm "The Life and Times of Glenn Hammond Curtiss."] ''aviation-history.com''. Retrieved: July 20, 2010.&lt;/ref&gt; The Glenn Curtiss House, after years of disrepair and frequent vandalism, is being refurbished to serve as a museum in his honor.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.nps.gov/history/nr/travel/aviation/gle.htm "The Glenn Curtiss House."] ''Aviation: From Sand Dunes to Sonic Booms: A National Register of Historic Places Travel Itinerary.'' via ''nps.gov''. Retrieved: July 20, 2010.&lt;/ref&gt;

His frequent hunting trips into the Florida [[Everglades]] led to a final invention, the Adams Motor "Bungalo", a forerunner of the modern [[recreational vehicle]] trailer (named after his business partner and half-brother, G. Carl Adams). Shortly before his death, he designed a tailless aircraft with a V-shaped wing and tricycle landing gear that he hoped could be sold in the price range of a family car.&lt;ref&gt;[https://books.google.com/books?id=9ycDAAAAMBAJ&amp;pg=PA55&amp;dq=Popular+Science+motor+gun+boat&amp;hl=en&amp;ei=HTLuTPyyFsOOnwe36dH2Cg&amp;sa=X&amp;oi=book_result&amp;ct=result&amp;resnum=7&amp;ved=0CEUQ6AEwBg#v=onepage&amp;q=Popular%20Science%20motor%20gun%20boat&amp;f=true "V-Shaped Plane Has Low Landing Speed."] ''Popular Science,'' March 1931.&lt;/ref&gt;

The [[Wright Aeronautical]] Corporation, a successor to the original Wright Company, ultimately merged with the [[Curtiss Aeroplane and Motor Company]] on July 5, 1929, forming the [[Curtiss-Wright]] company, shortly before Curtiss's death.&lt;ref name="The Curtiss Company"/&gt;

==Death==
Traveling to Rochester to contest a lawsuit brought by former business partner [[Augustus Moore Herring|August Herring]], Curtiss suffered an attack of [[appendicitis]] in court. He died on July 23, 1930, in [[Buffalo, New York]],&lt;ref name="Life"/&gt; of complications from an [[appendectomy]]. His funeral service was held at St. James Episcopal Church in his home town, Hammondsport,  with interment in the family plot at Pleasant Valley Cemetery in Hammondsport.

==Awards and honors==
By an act of Congress on March 1, 1933, Curtiss was posthumously awarded the [[Distinguished Flying Cross (United States)|Distinguished Flying Cross]], which now resides in the Smithsonian. Curtiss was inducted into the [[National Aviation Hall of Fame]] in 1964, the [[International Aerospace Hall of Fame]] in 1965&lt;ref&gt;Sprekelmeyer, Linda, editor. ''These We Honor: The International Aerospace Hall of Fame''. Donning Co. Publishers, 2006. {{ISBN|978-1-57864-397-4}}.&lt;/ref&gt;, the [[Motorsports Hall of Fame of America]] in 1990, the [[Motorcycle Hall of Fame]] in 1998,&lt;ref&gt;{{mhof|153}}&lt;/ref&gt; and the [[National Inventors Hall of Fame]] in 2003. The Smithsonian's [[National Air and Space Museum]] has a collection of Curtiss's original documents&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.nasm.si.edu/research/arch/findaids/pdf/Glenn_H_Curtiss_Collection_Finding_Aid.pdf "Glenn H. Curtiss Collection."] ''National Air and Space Museum – Documents.'' Retrieved: April 23, 2011.&lt;/ref&gt; as well as a collection of airplanes, motorcycles and motors.&lt;ref&gt;[http://blog.nasm.si.edu/aviation/saving-jenny/ "Glenn H. Curtiss Collection."] {{webarchive|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20140203214453/http://blog.nasm.si.edu/aviation/saving-jenny/ |date=2014-02-03 }} ''National Air and Space Museum.'' Retrieved: January 28, 2014.&lt;/ref&gt;  [[LaGuardia Airport]] was originally called Glenn H. Curtiss Airport when it began operation in 1929.

The [[Glenn H. Curtiss Museum]] in Hammondsport is dedicated to Curtiss's life and work.

==Timeline==
{{prose|date=May 2018}}
{{div col|colwidth=30em}}
*1878 Birth in Hammondsport, New York
*1898 Marriage
*1900 Manufactures Hercules bicycles
*1901 Motorcycle designer and racer
*1903 American motorcycle champion
*1903 Unofficial one-mile [[motorcycle land speed record]] {{convert|64|mph|km/h|abbr=on}} on Hercules V8 at [[Yonkers, New York]]&lt;ref&gt;House 2003, pp. 31–32.&lt;/ref&gt;
*1904 [[Thomas Scott Baldwin]] mounts Curtiss motorcycle engine on a hydrogen-filled dirigible
*1904 Set 10-mile world speed record
*1904 Invented handlebar throttle control;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.nationalaviation.org/curtiss-glenn/ "Glenn Curtiss."] ''nationalaviation.org.'' Retrieved: May 30, 2011.&lt;/ref&gt; handlebar throttle control also credited to the 1867–1869 [[Roper steam velocipede]]&lt;ref&gt;Johnson, Paul F. [http://americanhistory.si.edu/onthemove/collection/object_271.html ''Roper Steam Velocipede.''] ''National Museum of American History, [[Smithsonian Institution]]''. Retrieved: May 30, 2011.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Girdler, Allan. "First Fired, First Forgotten." ''[[Cycle World]]'' ([[Hachette Filipacchi Media U.S.]]), Volume 37, Issue 2, February 1998, pp. 62–70. ISSN 0011-4286.&lt;/ref&gt; 
*1905 Created G.H. Curtiss Manufacturing Company, Inc.
*1906 Curtiss writes the [[Wright brothers]] offering them an aeronautical motor
*1907 Curtiss joins [[Alexander Graham Bell]] in experimenting in aircraft
*1907 Set world [[motorcycle land speed record]] of {{convert|77.6|mi/h|km/h|1|abbr=on}}&lt;ref name=deCet2002&gt;de Cet 2003, p. 116.&lt;/ref&gt;
*1907 Set world [[motorcycle land speed record]] at {{convert|136.36|mi/h|km/h|2|abbr=on}} in his V8 motorcycle in [[Ormond Beach, Florida]]&lt;ref name=deCet2002/&gt;
*1908 First Army dirigible flight with Curtiss as flight engineer
*1908 One of several claimants for the first flight of a powered aircraft controlled by [[aileron]]s (manned glider flights with ailerons having been accomplished in 1904, unmanned flights even earlier)&lt;ref name="Parkin"&gt;Parkin, John H. [https://books.google.com/books/about/Bell_and_Baldwin.html?id=6ZBTAAAAMAAJ ''Bell and Baldwin: Their Development of Aerodromes and Hydrodromes at Baddeck, Nova Scotia''], Toronto: [[University of Toronto Press]], 1964, pg. 65.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="Ransom"&gt;Ransom, Sylvia and Jeff, James. {{webarchive |url=https://web.archive.org/web/20110801000000*/http://schools.bibb.k12.ga.us/166120913744293/lib/166120913744293/_files/Ch_1-4_CR.ppt |date=1 August 2011 |title=World Power }} Bibb County, Georgia, U.S.: [[Bibb County School District]]. April 2002, pp. 106-107.&lt;/ref&gt;
*1908 Lead designer and pilot of "[[AEA June Bug|June Bug]]" on July 4
*1909 Sale of Curtiss's "Golden Flyer" to the New York Aeronautic Society for $5,000.00 USD, marks the first sale of any aircraft in the U.S., triggers Wright Brothers lawsuits.
*1909 Won first international air speed record with {{convert|46.5|mi/h|km/h|1|abbr=on}} in [[Rheims]], [[France]]
*1909 First U.S. licensed aircraft manufacturer.
*1909 Established first flying school in United States and exhibition company
*1910 Long distance flying record of {{convert|150|mi|km}} from [[Albany, New York]] to [[New York City]]
*1910 First simulated bombing runs from an aircraft at Lake Keuka
*1910 First firearm use from aircraft, piloted by Curtiss
*1910 First radio communication with aircraft in flight in a Curtiss biplane
*1910 Curtiss moved to California and set up a shop and flight school at the [[Los Angeles Motordrome]], using the facility for sea plane experiments
*1910 Trained [[Blanche Stuart Scott]], the first American female pilot
*1910 First successful takeoff from a United States Navy ship ([[Eugene Burton Ely]], using Curtiss Plane)
*1911 First landing on a ship (Eugene Burton Ely, using Curtiss Plane) (2&amp;nbsp;Months later)
*1911 The Curtiss School of Aviation, established at [[Rockwell Field]] in February
[[File:First pilot's license.JPG|thumb|Glenn H. Curtiss's pilot license]]
*1911 Pilot license #1 issued for his ''June Bug'' flight
*1911 Ailerons patented
*1911 Developed first successful pontoon aircraft in US
*1911 [[seaplane|Hydroplane]] A-1 Triad purchased by US. Navy (US Navy's first aircraft)
*1911 Developed first retractable landing gear on his hydroaeroplane
*1911 His first aircraft sold to U.S. Army on April 27
*1911 Created first military flying school
*1912 Developed and flew the first flying boat on Lake Keuka
*1912 First [[Aircraft catapult|ship catapult]] launching on October 12 (Lt. Ellyson)&lt;ref&gt;Studer 1937, p. 258.&lt;/ref&gt;
*1912 Created the first flying school in Florida at Miami Beach
[[File:1913 Langley Medal awarded to Glenn Hammond Curtiss.jpg|thumb|right|The 1913 [[Langley Gold Medal|Langley Medal]] awarded to Curtiss]]
*1914 Curtiss made a few short flights in the [[Langley Aerodrome]], as part of an unsuccessful attempt to bypass the Wright Brothers' patent on aircraft 
*1915 Start production run of [[Curtiss Jenny|"Jennys"]] and may other models including flying boats
*1915 Curtiss started the [[Atlantic Coast Aeronautical Station]] on a 20-acre tract east of Newport News (VA) Boat Harbor in the Fall of 1915 with Captain [[Thomas Scott Baldwin]] as head. 
*1917 Opens "Experimental Airplane Factory" in Garden City, Long Island
*1919 Curtiss NC-4 flying boat crosses the Atlantic
*1919 Commenced private aircraft production with the [[Curtiss Oriole|Oriole]]
*1921 Developed [[Hialeah, Florida]], including Hialeah Park Race Track
*1921 Donated his World War I training field to the Navy
*1922 Opened [[Hialeah Park Race Track]] with his business partner James H. Bright
*1923 Developed [[Miami Springs, Florida]] and created a flying school and airport
[[File:Glenn curtiss.jpg|thumb|right|Tombstone]]
*1923 (circa) Created first airboats
*1925 Builds his [[Curtiss mansion|Miami Springs mansion]]
*1926 Developed [[Opa-locka, Florida]] and airport facility
*1928 Created the Curtiss Aerocar Company in Opa-locka, Florida.&lt;ref name= "House p.213"&gt;House 2003, p. 213.&lt;/ref&gt;
*1928 Curtiss towed an Aerocar from [[Miami]] to [[New York City]] in 39&amp;nbsp;hours
*1930 Death in Buffalo, New York
*1930 Buried in Pleasant Valley Cemetery in Hammondsport, New York
*1964 Inducted in the [[National Aviation Hall of Fame]]
*1990 Inducted in the [[Motorsports Hall of Fame of America]] in the air-racing category
{{div col end}}

==See also==
*[[Rodman Wanamaker]]
*[[Charles M. Olmsted]]
*[[American Trans-Oceanic Company]]
*[[Curtiss Model T]]
*[[Curtiss Autoplane]]
*[[Schneider Trophy]]
*[[Curtiss &amp; Bright]]
*[[Opa-locka Company]]
*[[Opa-locka Airport]]

==References==

===Notes===
{{reflist|group=N}}

===Citations===
{{Reflist|30em}}

===Bibliography===
{{refbegin}}
* [http://www.time.com/time/magazine/article/0,9171,719293,00.html "At Dayton".] ''[[Time (magazine)]]'', October 13, 1924.
* Casey, Louis S. ''Curtiss: The Hammondsport Era, 1907–1915''. New York: Crown Publishers, 1981. {{ISBN|978-0-517-54565-2}}.
* Curtiss, Glenn and Augustus Post. ''The Curtiss Aviation Book.'' New York: Frederick A. Stokes, 1912.
* de Cet, Mirco. [https://books.google.com/books?id=wNzyIcw2vxoC&amp;pg=PA116 ''The Illustrated Directory of Motorcycles''.] St. Paul: Minnesota: MotorBooks/MBI Publishing Company, 2002. {{ISBN|978-0-7603-1417-3}}.
* Dizer, John T. ''Tom Swift &amp; Company.'' Jefferson, North Carolina: McFarland Publishing, 1982. {{ISBN|0-89950-024-2}}.
* FitzGerald-Bush, Frank S. ''A Dream of Araby: Glenn Curtiss and the Founding of Opa-locka''. Opa-locka, Florida: South Florida Archaeological Museum, 1976.
* Harvey, Steve. ''It Started with a Steamboat: An American Saga''. Bloomington, Indiana: AuthorHouse, 2005. {{ISBN|978-1-4208-4943-1}}.
* [[Alden R. Hatch|Hatch, Alden]]. ''Glenn Curtiss: Pioneer of Aviation.'' Guilford, Connecticut: The Lyons Press, 2007. {{ISBN|978-1-59921-145-9}}.
* House, Kirk W. ''Hell-Rider to King of the Air.'' Warrendale, Pennsylvania: SAE International, 2003. {{ISBN|0-7680-0802-6}}.
* Mitchell, Charles R. and Kirk W. House. ''Glenn H. Curtiss: Aviation Pioneer.''  Charleston, South Carolina: Arcadia Publishing, 2001.  {{ISBN|978-0-7385-0519-0}}.
* Roseberry, C.R. ''Glenn Curtiss: Pioneer of Flight''. Garden City, New York: Doubleday &amp; Company, 1972. {{ISBN|0-8156-0264-2}}.
* Shulman, Seth. ''Unlocking the Sky: Glenn Hammond Curtiss and the Race to Invent the Airplane''. New York: [[Harper Collins]], 2002. {{ISBN|0-06-019633-5}}.
* [http://www.time.com/time/magazine/article/0,9171,716840,00.html "Speed Limit."] ''[[Time (magazine)]]'', October 29, 1923.
* Studer, Clara. ''Sky Storming Yankee: The Life of Glenn Curtiss''. New York: Stackpole Sons, 1937.
* Trimble, William F. ''Hero of the Air: Glenn Curtiss and the Birth of Naval Aviation.'' Annapolis, Maryland: Naval Institute Press, 2010. {{ISBN|978-1-59114-879-1}}.
{{Refend}}

== External links ==
{{Commons category|Glenn Curtiss}}
{{wikisource}}
* [http://invention.psychology.msstate.edu/i/Curtiss/CurtissAviation.html The Curtiss Aviation Book by Glenn Curtiss and Augustus Post]
* [http://www.britishpathe.com/video/launching-of-america/query/Curtiss+America Wanamaker's transatlantic ''America'' flying boat] Film of the assembly and naming of [[Curtiss Model H|''America'']], 22 June 1914
* [http://www.centennialofflight.net/essay/Explorers_Record_Setters_and_Daredevils/Curtiss/EX3.htm U.S. Government Centennial of Flight – Glenn Curtiss]
* {{Find a Grave|9264}}
* [http://www.glennhcurtissmuseum.org/ Glenn Curtiss Museum in Hammondsport, NY]
* [http://www.nationalaviation.org/curtiss-glenn/ National Aviation Hall of Fame: Glenn Curtiss] Retrieved May 26, 2011
* {{worldcat id|id=lccn-n50-18722}}

{{s-start}}
{{s-ach}}
{{s-bef|before=[[William Allen White]]}}
{{s-ttl|title=[[List of People on the Cover of Time Magazine: 1920s|Cover of Time Magazine]]
| years = 13 October 1924}}
{{s-aft|after=[[Patrick Hastings]]}}
{{s-end}}
&lt;!-- awarded before name changed to Collier Trophy --&gt;
{{Authority control}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Curtiss, Glenn}}
[[Category:1878 births]]
[[Category:1930 deaths]]
[[Category:Aircraft designers]]
[[Category:Alexander Graham Bell]]
[[Category:American aerospace engineers]]
[[Category:American aviation record holders]]
[[Category:American male cyclists]]
[[Category:American inventors]]
[[Category:American motorcycle designers]]
[[Category:Aviation history of the United States]]
[[Category:Aviation pioneers]]
[[Category:Aviators from New York (state)]]
[[Category:Bicycle messengers]]
[[Category:Collier Trophy recipients]]
[[Category:Curtiss-Wright Company| ]]
[[Category:Deaths from appendicitis]]
[[Category:International Motorsports Hall of Fame inductees]]
[[Category:Members of the Early Birds of Aviation]]
[[Category:Motorcycle Hall of Fame inductees]]
[[Category:Motorcycle land speed record people]]
[[Category:Motorsports Hall of Fame of America inductees]]
[[Category:National Aviation Hall of Fame inductees]]
[[Category:National Inventors Hall of Fame inductees]]
[[Category:People from Hammondsport, New York]]
[[Category:Articles containing timelines]]</text>
      <sha1>oz2jwaspxf0rap47xdlfk8972iq1t6y</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
