<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10.xsd" version="0.10" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <dbname>enwiki</dbname>
    <base>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.32.0-wmf.16</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="118" case="first-letter">Draft</namespace>
      <namespace key="119" case="first-letter">Draft talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2300" case="first-letter">Gadget</namespace>
      <namespace key="2301" case="first-letter">Gadget talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2302" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition</namespace>
      <namespace key="2303" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Hazel Ying Lee</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>4372481</id>
    <revision>
      <id>848597499</id>
      <parentid>843377152</parentid>
      <timestamp>2018-07-03T00:15:28Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Snori</username>
        <id>545864</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>/* Death */ pp</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="17754">{{Infobox person
| name               = Hazel Ying Lee
| image              = File:WASP Hazel Ying Lee (cropped).JPG
| image_upright =
| alt                = 
| caption            = Hazel Ying Lee
| native_name        = {{zh|c=李月英|p=Lǐ Yuèyīng}}
| native_name_lang   = 
| pronunciation      = 
| birth_name         =  &lt;!-- only use if different from name above --&gt;
| birth_date         ={{Birth date|1912|08|24}}
| birth_place        = [[Portland, Oregon|Portland]], [[Oregon]], U.S.
| baptised           =  &lt;!-- will not display if birth_date is entered --&gt;
| death_date         =  {{Death date and age|1944|11|25|1912|08|24}} 
| death_place        = [[Great Falls, Montana]], U.S.
| death_cause        = Airplane accident
| burial_place       = [[River View Cemetery (Portland, Oregon)|River View Cemetery]], Portland, Oregon
| burial_coordinates =  {{coord|45.465|N|122.673|W|type:landmark||display=inline}}
| monuments          = 
| residence          = 
| nationality        = 
| other_names        = 
| citizenship        = 
| education          = 
| alma_mater         = 
| occupation         = Pilot
| years_active       = 
| era                = World War II
| employer           = 
| organization       = Women Airforce Service Pilots
| home_town          = 
| height             =  &lt;!-- "X cm", "X m"  or "X ft Y in" plus optional reference (conversions are automatic) --&gt;
| weight             =  &lt;!-- "X kg", "X lb" or "X st Y lb" plus optional reference (conversions are automatic) --&gt;
| spouse             =Louie Yim-qun
| mother             =Ssiu Lan Wong
| father             =Yuet Lee
| relatives          = 
| family             = 
| footnotes          = 
}}

'''Hazel Ying Lee''' ({{zh|c=李月英|p=Lǐ Yuèyīng}}; August 24, 1912 – November 25, 1944) was a [[Chinese-American]] pilot who flew for the [[Women Airforce Service Pilots]] (WASP) during [[World War II]].&lt;ref name="afbio"&gt;{{cite web|title=Hazel Ying Lee: Showcased Asian-American involvement in war effort|url=http://www.af.mil/News/ArticleDisplay/tabid/223/Article/109612/hazel-ying-lee-showcased-asian-american-involvement-in-war-effort.aspx|publisher=Air Force ISR Agency|date=March 6, 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Early life==
Lee was born in [[Portland, Oregon]]. Her parents were Yuet Lee and Ssiu Lan Wong from [[Taishan, Guangdong]]. Her father was a merchant. Her mother devoted her energy to raising eight children and helping with the family business. Despite the widespread anti-Chinese bias of her time, Lee led a full and active life. Lee swam, played [[Team handball|handball]], loved to play cards and, in her teenage years, learned how to drive.&lt;ref name="Flaccus"&gt;{{cite news|last1=Flaccus|first1=Gillian|title=Chinese American WASP Losing Her Anonymity|url=http://articles.latimes.com/2003/may/11/news/adna-pilot11|accessdate=30 January 2018|work=Los Angeles Times|date=11 May 2003}}&lt;/ref&gt; Following graduation from [[high school]] in 1929, Lee found a job as an [[elevator]] operator at Liebes Department Store in downtown Portland. It was one of the few jobs that a Chinese-American woman could hold during this time.&lt;ref name="Heishman"/&gt;&lt;ref name="Merry"/&gt;

In 1932, Lee took her first airplane ride with a friend at an air show.&lt;ref name="Documentary"/&gt; At a time when less than 1% of pilots in the U.S. were women, Lee joined the Chinese Flying Club of Portland and took flying lessons with famed aviator Al Greenwood.&lt;ref name="Unander"&gt;{{cite journal|last1=Unander|first1=Lee Sig|title=Sky's the Limit|journal=1859 Oregon's Magazine|date=November 10, 2016|url=https://1859oregonmagazine.com/think-oregon/art-culture/hazel-lee/|accessdate=30 January 2018}}&lt;/ref&gt; Despite opposition from her mother, Lee "had to fly."&lt;ref name="Flaccus"/&gt; In discussing Lee's love of flying her sister Frances said,  "It was the thought of doing something she loved. Lee enjoyed the danger and doing something that was new to Chinese girls."
In October 1932 Lee became one of the first Chinese-American women to earn a pilot's license.&lt;ref name="Unander"/&gt; In speaking of Lee and the handful of other Chinese-American women pilots of that time, author [[Judy Yung]] has written "Although few in number, these first Chinese American aviators, in their attempt to participate in a daring sport, broke the stereotype of the passive Chinese women and demonstrated the ability of Chinese American women to compete in a male dominated field." While in Portland, Lee met her future husband "Clifford" [[Louie Yim-qun]].

===Time in China===
In response to [[Japanese invasion of Manchuria|Japanese invasion of China]] in 1933, Lee journeyed to China with the goal of joining the Chinese Air Force.&lt;ref name="NBC"&gt;{{cite news|last1=Gandhi|first1=Lakshmi|title=Remembering Hazel Lee, the first Chinese-American female military pilot|url=https://www.nbcnews.com/news/asian-america/remembering-hazel-lee-first-chinese-american-female-military-pilot-n745851|accessdate=29 January 2018|publisher=NBC News|date=May 25, 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt; Despite the need for pilots the [[Republic of China Air Force]] would not accept a woman pilot.&lt;ref name="Oregon"&gt;{{cite web|title=Hazel Ying Lee (1912-1944)|url=https://oregonencyclopedia.org/articles/lee_hazel_ying/#.Wm5Eha6nGos|website=oregonencyclopedia.org|accessdate=28 January 2018|language=en}}&lt;/ref&gt; Frustrated, Lee instead settled in [[Guangzhou|Canton]] and spent the next few years flying for a private airline. At the time Lee was one of a very small number of women pilots in China.&lt;ref name="ww2db"&gt;{{cite web|url=http://ww2db.com/person_bio.php?person_id=627|title=Hazel Lee : World War II Database|accessdate=July 1, 2014}}&lt;/ref&gt; In 1937, Japan [[Second Sino-Japanese War|invaded China]]. Lee remained in the country despite the war and was in Canton when hundreds of civilians were killed in Japanese air attacks.&lt;ref name="Canton Bombings"&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.combinedfleet.com/Canton_t.htm|title=The Campaign to Seize Canton (Guangzhou) - 1937 - 1938|accessdate=October 6, 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt; Friends speak of Lee's calm while bombs fell all around and remember Lee's effort to find shelter for friends, neighbors and family. Thanks to Lee, all survived the bombing attacks. Following another unsuccessful effort to join the Chinese Air Force, Lee escaped to [[Hong Kong]] and returned to the [[United States]] in 1938.&lt;ref name="Documentary"/&gt; In [[New York City]], Lee worked for the Chinese government as a buyer of war materials for besieged China.&lt;ref name="ww2db"/&gt;

==WASP career==
[[File:Hazel Ying Lee, one of the first two Chinese Americans in the Women Air Force Service Pilots.jpg|thumb|rigt|200px|Hazel Ying Lee, 1932]]

After the Japanese attack on [[Pearl Harbor]], America was drawn into [[World War II]]. As the war claimed the time and lives of American pilots, it became clear that there were not enough male pilots to sustain the war effort at home. With the ambivalent support of Army Air Force Commander [[Henry H. Arnold|Henry "Hap" Arnold]], the [[Women Airforce Service Pilots]] or "WASP," was created in 1943, under the command of famed aviator [[Jacqueline Cochran]].

Experienced women pilots, like Lee, were eager to join the WASP, and responded to interview requests by Cochran. Members of the WASP reported to Avenger Field, in [[Sweetwater, Texas]] for an arduous six-month training program. Lee was accepted into the 4th class, 43 W 4.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Women Airforce Service Pilots: Hazel Ah Ying Lee|url=http://www.twu.edu/library/wasp/wasppdf/Lee.pdf|publisher=Texas Women's University}}&lt;/ref&gt; Hazel Ying Lee was the first Chinese-American woman to fly for the United States military.&lt;ref name="NBC"/&gt; During Hazel's training it was reported that she fell from the aircraft she was riding in when the instructor made an unexpected [[Aerobatic maneuver|loop]]. Her seat belt wasn't fastened correctly, at the time, and she saved herself by using her [[parachute]]. Hazel landed in a field and walked back to the base dragging the parachute behind her.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last1=Simons|first1=Lisa M. B.|title=The U.S. WASP: Trailblazing Women Pilots of World War II|date=2017|publisher=Capstone|isbn=9781515779377|page=4|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=a1smDwAAQBAJ&amp;printsec=frontcover&amp;source=gbs_atb#v=onepage&amp;q&amp;f=false|accessdate=3 February 2018|language=en}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Although flying under military command the women pilots of the WASP were classified as civilians and were paid through the civil service.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|title=Girl Pilots|journal=Life Magazine|date=19 July 1943|issue=July 19, 1943|pages=73–80|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=MVAEAAAAMBAJ&amp;printsec=frontcover&amp;source=gbs_ge_summary_r&amp;cad=0#v=onepage&amp;q&amp;f=false|publisher=Time Inc|language=en}}&lt;/ref&gt; No military benefits were offered and if a WASP member was died in the line of duty no military funerals were allowed.&lt;ref name="Dromgoole"&gt;{{cite book|last1=Dromgoole|first1=Glenn|title=West Texas Stories|date=2016|publisher=ACU Press|isbn=9780891126744|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=3RczDQAAQBAJ&amp;pg=PT65&amp;lpg=PT65&amp;dq=WASP+family+member+accepts+award&amp;source=bl&amp;ots=9Lt5aM0oP_&amp;sig=18y5pIGw9_QLywaSOQIlS7uz4WM&amp;hl=en&amp;sa=X&amp;ved=0ahUKEwj7uPirgvjYAhWGuFMKHUDABCQQ6AEIQDAH#v=onepage&amp;q=WASP%20family%20member%20accepts%20award&amp;f=false|accessdate=28 January 2018|language=en}}&lt;/ref&gt; The WASPs were often assigned the least desirable missions, such as winter trips in open cockpit airplanes.&lt;ref name="Heishman"&gt;{{cite news|last1=Heishman|first1=Allison|title="Fighting for Democracy": Hazel Ying Lee - National Constitution Center|url=https://constitutioncenter.org/blog/fighting-for-democracy-hazel-ying-lee|accessdate=30 January 2018|publisher=National Constitution Center|date=October 14, 2011|language=en}}&lt;/ref&gt; Commanding officers were reluctant to give women any flying deliveries. It took an order from the head of the [[Air Transport Command (United States Air Force)|Air Transport Command]] to improve the situation.

Upon graduation, Lee was assigned to the third Ferrying Group at [[Romulus, Michigan]].&lt;ref name="Merry"&gt;{{cite book|last1=Merry|first1=Lois K.|title=Women Military Pilots of World War II: A History with Biographies of American, British, Russian and German Aviators|date=2010|publisher=McFarland|isbn=9780786457687|pages=176–179|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=oBIi6ezWZ0IC&amp;pg=PA176&amp;lpg=PA176&amp;dq=hazel+lee+ying&amp;source=bl&amp;ots=UX5V0AZtlV&amp;sig=Zf8rF8FoFU4BFBnRuySm-iCXKtw&amp;hl=en&amp;sa=X&amp;ved=0ahUKEwieq8bQl4PZAhVB4oMKHQKaBys4FBDoAQhHMAY#v=onepage&amp;q=hazel%20lee%20ying&amp;f=false|accessdate=31 January 2018|language=en}}&lt;/ref&gt; Their assignment was critical to the war effort. They delivered aircraft, being manufactured in large numbers in converted automobile factories, to points of embarkation, where they would then be shipped to the European and Pacific war fronts. In a letter to her sister, Lee described Romulus as "a 7-day workweek, with little time off."&lt;ref name="Flaccus"/&gt; When asked to describe Lee's attitude, a fellow member of the WASP summed it up in Lee's own words, "I'll take and deliver anything." Lee was described by her fellow pilots as "calm and fearless" even during forced landings. One emergency landing took place at a wheat field in [[Kansas]]. A farmer, armed with a pitchfork, chased Lee around her plane as he was shouting to his neighbors that the Japanese had invaded Kansas. Evading his attack Lee told the farmer who she was and demanded he stop which he did.&lt;ref name="afbio"/&gt; Lee was a favorite her fellow pilots known for a great sense of humor and being mischievous.&lt;ref name="Documentary"&gt;{{cite news|title=Documentary honors Chinese-American woman who flew U.S. fighter planes|url=http://billingsgazette.com/news/local/documentary-honors-chinese-american-woman-who-flew-u-s-fighter/article_1d7e3309-f4e1-5798-99d4-5feb7f5bda46.html|accessdate=29 January 2018|work=The Billings Gazette|publisher=Associated Press|date=May 10, 2003|language=en}}&lt;/ref&gt; Lee used her lipstick to inscribe Chinese characters on the tail of her plane and the planes of her fellow pilots.&lt;ref name="afbio"/&gt;&lt;ref name="Unander"/&gt; One lucky fellow who happened to be a bit on the chubby side, had his plane dubbed (unknown to him) "Fat Ass."
[[File:Image-Hazel Ying Lee.jpg|thumb|right|Hazel Ying Lee reviews her performance after a session in a Link trainer]]
Lee was in demand when a mission was RON (Remaining Overnight). In a big city or in a small country town, she could always find a Chinese restaurant, supervise the menu, and often cook the food herself. She was a great cook. Fellow WASP pilot Sylvia Dahmes Clayton observed that "Hazel provided me with an opportunity to learn about a different culture at a time when I did not know anything else. She expanded my world and my outlook on life."&lt;ref name="Heishman"/&gt; In September 1944, Lee was sent to Pursuit School at [[Brownsville, Texas]] for intensive training.&lt;ref name="Oregon"/&gt; She was part of Class 44-18 Flight B and went on to be among the 134 women pilots who flew "Pursuit," that is faster, high powered fighters such as the [[P-63 Kingcobra]], [[P-51 Mustang]] and [[P-39 Airacobra]] with Lee's favorite being the Mustang.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Hazel Ying Lee|url=https://www.wai.org/pioneers/2011/hazel-ying-lee|website=Women in Aviation International|accessdate=31 January 2018|language=en}}&lt;/ref&gt; Lee and the others were the first women to pilot fighter aircraft for the United States military.

===Death===
On November 10, 1944 Lee received orders to go to the [[Bell Aircraft]] factory at [[Niagara Falls, New York]] where she was to fly a P-63 Kingcobra aircraft to [[Great Falls, Montana]]. During the War Lee and the other Pursuit pilots delivered over 5,000 fighters to Great Falls which was a link in supplying Soviet allies with planes under the [[Lend-Lease]] program.&lt;ref name="Merry"/&gt; From there male pilots flew the fighters on to Alaska where Soviet pilots waited to fly the planes to their home bases. Bad weather delayed the mission at [[Fargo, North Dakota]] and on [[Thanksgiving]] morning the weather cleared allowing Lee to leave Fargo.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|last1=Venugopal|first1=Anjana|title=Badass Ladies of China: Hazel Ying Lee|publisher=The World of Chinese|url=http://www.theworldofchinese.com/2016/04/badass-ladies-hazel-ying-lee/|accessdate=31 January 2018|work=www.theworldofchinese.com|date=April 14, 2016|language=en}}&lt;/ref&gt; A little after 2 p.m. Lee was cleared to land in Great Falls with a large number of P-63's approached the airport at the same time. There was confusion on the part of the control tower and Lee's plane and another P-63 collided. The aircraft were engulfed in flames and Lee was pulled from the burning wreckage of her airplane with her flight jacket still smoldering.&lt;ref name="Merry"/&gt; 

Two days later, on November 25, 1944, Lee died from the burns she received in the accident. Only three days after learning of Lee's death the Lee family received another telegram informing them that Lee's brother Victor, who was serving with the U.S. Tank Corps, had been killed in combat in France.&lt;ref name="Oregon"/&gt; As they prepared to bury Hazel and Victor, the family picked out a burial site in a [[Portland, Oregon]] cemetery.&lt;ref name="burial"&gt;{{cite web|title=Hazel Ying Lee: Fighting for Gender Equality|url=http://www.ncdemocracy.org/sites/www.ncdemocracy.org/files/docs/FFD_EducGuide_10_Hazel_0.pdf|publisher=National Center for the Preservation of Democracy}}&lt;/ref&gt; The cemetery refused to allow the family to bury Hazel and Victor in the chosen spot, citing cemetery policy that did not allow Asians to be buried "in the White section."&lt;ref name="Documentary"/&gt; After a lengthy battle, the Lee family prevailed. Lee was laid to rest in a non-military funeral, and buried alongside her brother, on a sloping hill in [[River View Cemetery (Portland, Oregon)|River View Cemetery]],&lt;ref name="burial"/&gt; overlooking the [[Willamette River]].

For over three decades, members of the WASP and their supporters attempted to secure military status for the women pilots.&lt;ref name="Collins"/&gt; In March 1977, following United States Congressional approval of Public Law 95-202, the efforts of the Women Airforce Service pilots were finally recognized and military status was finally granted.&lt;ref name="Collins"&gt;{{cite news|last1=Collins|first1=Shannon|title=WASP Pursued Love of Flying, Fought for Women Vets’ Recognition|url=https://www.defense.gov/News/Article/Article/689318/wasp-pursued-love-of-flying-fought-for-women-vets-recognition/|accessdate=28 January 2018|publisher=U.S. Department of Defense|date=March 9, 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt; Thirty-eight pilots of the WASP died while in service to their country during the difficult years of World War II and Lee was the last to die during the program. In 2004 Hazel Ying Lee was inducted into Oregon's Aviation Hall Of Honor.&lt;ref name="Unander"/&gt;

==References==
{{Reflist|2}}

==External links==
*[http://www.hazelyinglee.com/ A Brief Flight... Hazel Ying Lee and the women who flew pursuit]
*[http://wingsacrossamerica.us/wasp/ WASP on the WEB]

{{Authority control}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Lee, Hazel Ying}}
[[Category:American military personnel of Chinese descent]]
[[Category:American women in World War II]]
[[Category:Military personnel from Portland, Oregon]]
[[Category:Chinese people of World War II]]
[[Category:American people of Chinese descent]]
[[Category:Female aviators]]
[[Category:Aviators killed in aviation accidents or incidents in the United States]]
[[Category:1912 births]]
[[Category:1944 deaths]]
[[Category:Accidental deaths in Montana]]
[[Category:Women Airforce Service Pilots]]
[[Category:American military personnel killed in World War II]]
[[Category:American female aviators]]</text>
      <sha1>i28s4ubrbgn49i9i0by43wwy4rd2kj1</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
