<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10.xsd" version="0.10" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <dbname>enwiki</dbname>
    <base>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.32.0-wmf.16</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="118" case="first-letter">Draft</namespace>
      <namespace key="119" case="first-letter">Draft talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2300" case="first-letter">Gadget</namespace>
      <namespace key="2301" case="first-letter">Gadget talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2302" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition</namespace>
      <namespace key="2303" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Jeff Dunham</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>4699275</id>
    <revision>
      <id>855957347</id>
      <parentid>855829255</parentid>
      <timestamp>2018-08-21T23:55:20Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>CalliopeMuse</username>
        <id>33865157</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor/>
      <comment>/* 2009–present */ typo</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="55035">{{distinguish|Jeff Denham}}
{{Use dmy dates|date=January 2016}}
{{pp-semi-blp|small=yes}}
{{Infobox comedian
| name              = Jeff Dunham
| image             = Jeff Dunham and Achmed.JPG
| imagesize         =
| caption           = Dunham with his puppet "Achmed the Dead Terrorist"
| birth_name        = Jeffrey Dunham
| birth_date        = {{Birth date and age|mf=yes|1962|4|18}}
| birth_place       = [[Dallas, Texas]], U.S.
| medium            = Stand-up&lt;br /&gt;Film&lt;br /&gt;Television
| genre             = [[Ventriloquism]], [[observational comedy]], [[black comedy]], [[prop comedy]]
| subject           =
| active            = 1976–present
| spouse            = {{unbulleted list|{{marriage|Paige Brown|1994|2008|reason=div.}}||{{marriage|Audrey Murdick|2012|}}}}
| children          = 5
| notable_work      = ''[[Jeff Dunham: Arguing with Myself]]''&lt;br /&gt;''[[Jeff Dunham: Spark of Insanity]]''&lt;br /&gt;''[[Jeff Dunham's Very Special Christmas Special]]''&lt;br /&gt;''[[The Jeff Dunham Show]]''&lt;br /&gt;''Jeff Dunham: Controlled Chaos''&lt;br /&gt;''Jeff Dunham: Minding the Monsters''
| signature         =
| website           = {{URL|jeffdunham.com}}
}}

'''Jeffrey''' "'''Jeff'''" '''Dunham''' (born April 18, 1962) is an American [[ventriloquist]] and [[comedian]] who has also appeared on numerous television shows, including ''[[Late Show with David Letterman]]'', ''[[Comedy Central Presents]]'', ''[[The Tonight Show]]'' and ''[[Sonny With a Chance]]''. He has six specials that run on [[Comedy Central]]: ''[[Jeff Dunham: Arguing with Myself]]'', ''[[Jeff Dunham: Spark of Insanity]]'', ''[[Jeff Dunham's Very Special Christmas Special]]'', ''[[Jeff Dunham: Controlled Chaos]]'', ''[[Jeff Dunham: Minding the Monsters]]'', and ''[[Jeff Dunham: All Over the Map]]''. Dunham also starred in ''[[The Jeff Dunham Show]]'', a series on the network in 2009.&lt;ref name=NewYorkTimes&gt;{{cite news|url=https://www.nytimes.com/2009/11/01/magazine/01ventriloquist-t.html|title=Comedy for Dummies|publisher=[[The New York Times]]|date=October 29, 2009|first=Jon|last=Mooallem}}&lt;/ref&gt;

His style has been described as "a dressed-down, more digestible version of [[Don Rickles]] with [[Dissociative identity disorder|multiple personality disorder]]". Describing his characters, [[Time magazine]] said, "All of them are politically incorrect, gratuitously insulting and ill tempered."&lt;ref name=Time&gt;Luscombe, Belinda. [http://www.time.com/time/magazine/article/0,9171,1901490,00.html "The Puppet Master"]. ''[[Time magazine|Time]]'' magazine. June 8, 2009&lt;/ref&gt; Dunham has been credited with reviving ventriloquism,&lt;ref&gt;Braxton, Greg. [http://articles.latimes.com/2009/nov/04/entertainment/et-dunham4 "Jeff Dunham throws his voice into stardom"], ''[[The Los Angeles Times]]'', November 4, 2009.&lt;/ref&gt; and doing more to promote the art form than anyone since [[Edgar Bergen]].&lt;ref name=NewYorkTimes/&gt;

Dunham has been called "America's favorite comedian" by [[Slate.com]], and according to the concert industry publication ''Pollstar'', he is the top-grossing standup act in [[North America]], and is among the most successful acts in Europe as well. As of November 2009, he has sold over four million DVDs, an additional $7 million in merchandise sales,&lt;ref name=TomMorris&gt;Morris, Tom. [http://www.huffingtonpost.com/tom-morris/success-for-dummies_b_350592.html "Success for Dummies"], ''[[The Huffington Post]]''. November 9, 2009.&lt;/ref&gt; and received more than 350 million hits on [[YouTube]] as of October 2009 (his introduction of Achmed the Dead Terrorist in ''Spark of Insanity'' was ranked as the ninth most watched YouTube video at the time).&lt;ref name=NewYorkTimes/&gt; ''A Very Special Christmas Special'' was the most-watched telecast in Comedy Central history, with its DVD selling over 400,000 in its first two weeks.&lt;ref name=MultiPlatform&gt;[http://www.comedycentral.com/press/press_releases/2009/032309_cc-signs-jeff-dunham.jhtml "Jeff Dunham and Friends have found a Home at Comedy Central signing a Multi-Platform Deal to Encompass all Areas of Entertainment" [[Comedy Central]]; March 23, 2009].&lt;/ref&gt; ''[[Forbes|Forbes.com]]'' ranked Dunham as the third highest-paid comedian in the United States behind [[Jerry Seinfeld]] and [[Chris Rock]],&lt;ref name=TomMorris/&gt; and reported that he was one of the highest-earning comics from June 2008 to June 2009, earning approximately $30 million during that period.&lt;ref name="Forbes"&gt;{{cite news|url=https://www.forbes.com/2009/07/13/top-earning-comedians-business-entertainment-top-earning-comedians.html|title=The Top-Earning Comedians|last=Rose|first=Lacey|date=13 July 2009 |publisher=[[Forbes]]|accessdate=22 January 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt; Dunham also does occasional acting roles. He achieved the [[Guinness Book of World Records]] record for "Most tickets sold for a stand-up comedy tour" for his ''Spark of Insanity'' tour, performing in 386 venues worldwide.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news|url=http://www.guinnessworldrecords.com/world-records/most-tickets-sold-for-a-stand-up-comedy-tour|title=Most tickets sold for a stand-up comedy tour|work=Guinness World Records|access-date=2017-03-23|language=en-GB}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news|url=http://www.billboard.com/articles/business/6494723/kevin-hart-biggest-comedy-tour-ever-what-now|title=Kevin Hart Is On Track for the Biggest Comedy Tour of All Time|work=Billboard|access-date=2017-03-23}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Early life==
Dunham was born in [[Dallas, Texas]] on April 18, 1962.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Jeff Dunham Biography|url=http://www.biography.com/people/jeff-dunham-20682855|publisher=[[Biography.com]]|accessdate=December 23, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=OfficialBio&gt;The biography page on [http://www.jeffdunham.com/#/bio Dunham's official site] established his year of birth when it was accessed on April 17, 2009, but had been removed by November 28, 2009. [https://web.archive.org/web/20071011000433/http://www.jeffdunham.com/ Archive of 2007 version of official site].&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=BirthOfADummy&gt;{{cite episode|title=Jeff Dunham: Birth of a Dummy|series=[[Biography (TV series)|Biography]]|network=[[The Biography Channel]]|date=November 22, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; When he was three months old, he was adopted by real estate appraiser Howard Dunham, and his homemaker wife Joyce, who raised him in a devoutly [[Presbyterian]] household&lt;ref name=BirthOfADummy/&gt; in an affluent Dallas neighborhood, as an only child.&lt;ref name=FastLiving&gt;{{cite web |url=https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=PCepNGDZ5vs&amp;NR=1 |title=Clip of Dunham from an episode of the CMT TV series ''Fast Living'' |accessdate=4 May 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt;

He began [[ventriloquism]] in 1970 at age eight, when his parents gave him a [[Mortimer Snerd]] dummy for Christmas, and an accompanying how-to album.&lt;ref name=OfficialBio/&gt; The next day he checked out a how-to book on ventriloquism from the library,&lt;ref name=NewYorkTimes/&gt;&lt;ref name=BirthOfADummy/&gt; and explained in 2011 that he still had it, remarking that he was "a thief in the third grade". By the fourth grade, Dunham decided he not only wanted to be a professional ventriloquist, but the best one ever.&lt;ref name=BirthOfADummy/&gt; Dunham began practicing for hours in front of a mirror, studying the routines of [[Edgar Bergen]], and the how-to record ''Jimmy Nelson's Instant Ventriloquism'',&lt;ref name=NewYorkTimes/&gt; finding ventriloquism to be a learned skill, similar to juggling, that anyone with a normal speaking voice can acquire.&lt;ref name=Rotorway&gt;[http://www.kitplanes.com/magazine/rotorcraft/204-1.phtml Jeff Dunham. "Building a Rotorway 162F Part 1 of 8: How I got into this."] {{Webarchive|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20090309035533/http://www.kitplanes.com/magazine/rotorcraft/204-1.phtml |date=9 March 2009 }} ''KITPLANES Magazine'', March 1997.&lt;/ref&gt; Dunham has explained that, as an only child, he enjoyed being alone, likening his solitude to a "warm blanket" with which he could explore his own thoughts and ideas, which prepared him for the solitude of living alone when he later moved to Los Angeles as a struggling comedian.&lt;ref name=BirthOfADummy/&gt;

When Dunham was in the sixth grade, he began attending the Vent Haven ConVENTion in [[Fort Mitchell, Kentucky]], an annual international meeting of ventriloquists that includes competitions, where he met [[Jimmy Nelson (ventriloquist)|Jimmy Nelson]] in person. Dunham has missed only one ConVENTion since then, in 1977. The organizers of the ConVENTion eventually declared Dunham a "retired champion", ineligible from entering any more competitions, as other attendees were too intimidated to compete against him. The Vent Haven Museum devotes a section to Dunham, alongside [[Señor Wences]] and Dunham's idol, [[Edgar Bergen]].&lt;ref name=NewYorkTimes/&gt;

==Career==
===Beginnings===
Dunham began performing for audiences as a teenager,&lt;ref name=OfficialBio/&gt; in various venues such as school, church, and during his job at [[Six Flags]]. By his middle school years, he began to perform for banquets attended by local celebrities such as [[Dallas Cowboys]] quarterback [[Roger Staubach]], having developed his style of lampooning those he performed for, using the puppets to say things too risque for him to say without them.&lt;ref name=NewYorkTimes/&gt; Dunham's television debut came in 1976 when the still prepubescent performer caught the attention of Dallas reporters like [[Bill O'Reilly (political commentator)|Bill O'Reilly]], who interviewed Dunham for a local news story.&lt;ref name=BirthOfADummy/&gt; Dunham later did commercials for [[Datsun]] dealerships in Dallas and [[Tyler, Texas|Tyler]] while still in high school.&lt;ref name=NewYorkTimes/&gt;&lt;ref name=BirthOfADummy/&gt; While emceeing a high school talent show, he dealt with a heckler, and won over the rest of the audience.&lt;ref name=BirthOfADummy/&gt; During this period he became so associated with his craft that he and one of his dummies "cowrote" a column in the school paper, and he would pose with his dummies for yearbooks&lt;ref name=NewYorkTimes/&gt; as an inexpensive way to acquire professional photos of his act for promotional purposes.&lt;ref name=AllByMySelves&gt;{{cite book|last=Dunham|first=Jeff|title=All By My Selves: Walter, Peanut, Achmed and Me|publisher=Dutton Adult|date=November 2010|isbn=0-525-95141-5}}&lt;/ref&gt; He was voted Most Likely to Succeed, and in 1980, after he graduated from high school, Dunham gave himself a career goal of obtaining, within ten years, an appearance on ''[[The Tonight Show Starring Johnny Carson]]'', which was seen as the "holy grail" for comedians.&lt;ref name=BirthOfADummy/&gt;

That year Dunham began attending [[Baylor University]], hoping to graduate with a degree in communications, while performing around campus.&lt;ref name=BirthOfADummy/&gt; He would also fly around the country on weekends,&lt;ref name=NewYorkTimes/&gt; doing up to 100 private shows a year,&lt;ref name=BirthOfADummy/&gt; entertaining corporate customers such as [[General Electric]], whose CEO, [[Jack Welch]], he mocked during his routine.&lt;ref name=NewYorkTimes/&gt; By his junior year in college (1983–84), Dunham was making $70,000 a year, and as word spread of his act, he landed featured spots opening for [[Bob Hope]] and [[George Burns]], though he still perceived his act as raw, as he did not have any knowledge of standup comedy beyond his [[Bill Cosby]] albums.&lt;ref name=BirthOfADummy/&gt;

He caught a break in 1985 when he was asked to join the [[Broadway show]] ''[[Sugar Babies (musical)|Sugar Babies]]'' with [[Mickey Rooney]] and [[Ann Miller]], replacing an outgoing variety act. For the naive and devoutly-raised Dunham, Broadway was a new world filled with beautiful showgirls and crusty stagehands, and his first taste of entertainment industry egos came when Rooney called Dunham into his dressing room, and told him he was there for one reason alone: so that Rooney could change his costumes.&lt;ref name=BirthOfADummy/&gt; He performed at the [[Westbury Music Fair]] on [[Long Island]]. These early experiences, in which he used characters like José Jalapeño on a Stick, taught him the value of modifying his act regionally, as the jalapeño jokes that worked well in Texas were not as well received by audiences in Long Island. After graduating from Baylor University in 1986,&lt;ref name=Rotorway/&gt; he continued honing his act in comedy clubs in the Southwest with new characters such as Peanut and José Jalapeño, but struggled against the perception he relates from fellow comedians that he was not a true comedian because he relied on props.

His experience at [[Catch a Rising Star (comedy clubs)|Catch a Rising Star]] in New York City served as a bitter confirmation of where ventriloquists stood in the comedic food chain, as the emcee at that club gave Dunham little respect. According to Dunham, after he arrived at the club in the evening and informed the emcee that he was a ventriloquist, the emcee reacted with derision, telling Dunham that he would be given a late time slot, and after that time slot came and passed, kept postponing Dunham's stage time until Dunham left the club.&lt;ref name=BirthOfADummy/&gt;

By the end of 1988, Dunham felt his career went as far as it could go in Texas, and he moved to [[Los Angeles, California]],&lt;ref name=OfficialBio/&gt;&lt;ref name=BirthOfADummy/&gt; never having, as he has commented, "a real job",&lt;ref name=ComCenBio/&gt; much to the concern of his parents, who assumed he would relegate his act to local venues such as church groups. When he first arrived in Los Angeles, the comedy in his act bombed. Dunham attributes this initial reaction to his underdeveloped comedy, explaining that while the characters' personalities were developed at that point, his jokes were not. In addition to this, the comedy world was not welcoming to ventriloquists, and his manager, Judi Brown-Marmel, did not use the word "ventriloquist" when finding bookings for him, choosing to present him as a comedy duo. After Dunham became friends with Mike Lacey, owner of [[The Comedy &amp; Magic Club]] in [[Hermosa Beach]], Lacey gave Dunham a steady slot at the club, where Dunham sharpened his act by observing the techniques of comedians like [[Jerry Seinfeld]], and taking the advice of colleague [[Bill Engvall]], moving away from his [[Motion Picture Association of America film rating system#Ratings|G-Rated]] material toward edgier, more adult themes.&lt;ref name=BirthOfADummy/&gt;

===''The Tonight Show''===
At the end of 1988, Dunham was told by James McCawley, a talent booker for ''The Tonight Show Starring Johnny Carson'', that Dunham would be given a spot on the coveted program. Though the 26-year-old Dunham was elated that his 10-year goal was arriving two years early, McCawley later cancelled Dunham's appearance after attending, with [[Roseanne Barr]], a public performance of Dunham's the day before Dunham's scheduled ''Tonight Show'' taping. McCawley informed Dunham on the day of the scheduled taping that he had been wrong in his initial assessment of Dunham, whom he now said was not ready for ''The Tonight Show''. Dunham continued to tighten his act in Los Angeles clubs, performing the same six-minute segment with Peanut a total of nine times for McCawley over the next few months. Finally at the Ice-House in [[Pasadena, California|Pasadena]] in April 1990, after Dunham did the same segment, McCawley informed Dunham that he would finally get his ''Tonight Show'' appearance. Dunham and Peanut appeared on ''The Tonight Show Starring Johnny Carson'' on April 6, 1990, alongside guests [[Bob Hope]] and [[B.B. King]].&lt;ref name=BirthOfADummy/&gt; Following his bit, he was invited to sit on [[Johnny Carson]]'s couch, a mark of approval on Carson's show.&lt;ref name=BirthOfADummy/&gt; Upon sitting down next to Carson's desk, Dunham pulled out Walter, who told Carson sidekick [[Ed McMahon]], [[American Family Publishers|"Stop sending me all your damn mail."]] At the time, Dunham saw his ''Tonight Show'' appearance as his big break, but was frustrated at his parents' initial disapproval over Walter's use of the words "hell" and "damn",&lt;ref name=BirthOfADummy/&gt; and he would toil in obscurity for another twelve years, continuing his stand up at venues such as [[The Improv]] chain, and appearing in small roles on TV.&lt;ref name=TomMorris/&gt; One of these was a 1996 episode of ''[[Ellen (TV series)|Ellen]]'', in which he appeared with Walter.&lt;ref name=NewYorkTimes/&gt; Dunham also appeared with Walter in a TV commercial for [[The Hertz Corporation|Hertz]].&lt;ref&gt;[https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=thsS58Yoz6o&amp;feature=related Video of the Jeff Dunham's [[Hertz]] commercial].&lt;/ref&gt; Dunham would appear on ''The Tonight Show'' a total of four times, as well as similar TV venues such as ''[[Hot Country Nights]]'', appearing in one segment with [[Reba McEntire]]. This exposure helped make Dunham a large theater headliner, a rare accomplishment for a ventriloquist, but by the mid-1990s, his television appearances had dwindled, and with them, so did his stage audiences.&lt;ref name=BirthOfADummy/&gt;

Dunham moved back to clubs, more than 200 appearances a year. To maintain a connection with his fan base, he would use question cards that he had audiences fill out for his performances to build a database, which was tailor-made for the burgeoning [[World Wide Web]]. Though he was voted Funniest Male Standup at the [[American Comedy Awards]] in 1998, his club work kept him away from his wife and daughters between two and three weeks each month, which put a strain on his marriage, and made paying bills for his expanded family difficult. By 2002, Dunham was hoping to obtain more TV work to raise his profile and ease his standup schedule. Such exposure was elusive until a successful appearance on ''[[The Best Damn Sports Show Period]]'', where Dunham and Walter made jokes at the expense of co-hosts [[Tom Arnold (actor)|Tom Arnold]], [[Michael Irvin]], [[John Salley]] and [[John Kruk]], generating laughter from them, and giving Dunham much-needed exposure. In 2003, Dunham was the frontrunner to replace [[Jimmy Kimmel]] on ''[[Fox NFL Sunday]]'', but hosts [[Howie Long]] and [[Terry Bradshaw]] were not amenable to the idea of being upstaged by a puppet, and, as Dunham tells it, did not provide a welcoming atmosphere to Dunham, nor allow him to speak much during his appearance.&lt;ref name=BirthOfADummy/&gt;

===First Comedy Central specials===
On July 18, 2003, Dunham appeared on ''[[Comedy Central Presents]]'', his first solo appearance on [[Comedy Central]]. During his half hour piece, he showcased José Jalapeño on a Stick, Walter, an early version of Melvin the Superhero Guy and Peanut, whom Dunham had begun to merchandise into a line of dolls. The appearance was successful, but Comedy Central resisted giving Dunham more airtime, feeling that he was not a good fit for them.&lt;ref name=NewYorkTimes/&gt; By 2005 Dunham decided to gamble on financing his own comedy DVD, ''[[Jeff Dunham: Arguing with Myself]]'', which was taped in [[Santa Ana, California]].&lt;ref name=BirthOfADummy/&gt; Dunham's manager, Judi Brown-Marmel, lobbied the network to air it, pointing to Dunham's drawing power and merchandising profits, and arguing that the network needed more diverse content. Surprised by the high ratings of the first [[Blue Collar Comics]] concert movie that same year, the network began to reconsider its brand. In late 2006, Comedy Central aired ''Arguing with Myself'', drawing two million viewers when it aired,&lt;ref name=NewYorkTimes/&gt; and selling two million DVDs.&lt;ref name=BirthOfADummy/&gt;

In 2007, Dunham appeared as The Amazing Ken with José Jalapeño on a Stick in the [[Larry the Cable Guy]] feature film ''[[Delta Farce]]''.
His second special, ''[[Jeff Dunham: Spark of Insanity]]'', was taped at the [[Warner Theatre (Washington, D.C.)|Warner Theater]] in [[Washington, D.C.]] that same year. It served not only to cement Dunham's stardom, but to introduce his most controversial character, Achmed the Dead Terrorist, which became a viral Internet sensation. A clip of Achmed from ''Insanity'' attracted over 140 million hits on [[YouTube]],&lt;ref name=BirthOfADummy/&gt; making it the ninth most watched clip on that website as of October 2009.&lt;ref name=NewYorkTimes/&gt;

By 2008, Dunham's characters had crossed language barriers, with his specials dubbed for audiences in various countries such as France, and Dunham attracting requests for performances in South Africa, Australia, Norway, Denmark, China, and the Middle East.&lt;ref name=BirthOfADummy/&gt; ''[[Jeff Dunham's Very Special Christmas Special]]'' was taped at the [[Pabst Theater]] in [[Milwaukee, Wisconsin]] that same year, and premiered on Comedy Central on November 16, 2008, watched by 6.6 million people.&lt;ref name=NewYorkTimes/&gt; It became available on DVD and [[Blu-ray Disc|Blu-ray]] on November 18, 2008.&lt;ref&gt;[https://www.amazon.com/dp/B001DWNUIS ''Jeff Dunham's Very Special Christmas Special'']. Amazon.com; retrieved January 8, 2012.&lt;/ref&gt; The special's premiere was the highest rated telecast in Comedy Central's history.&lt;ref name=Time/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.variety.com/article/VR1117996088.html?categoryid=14&amp;cs=1|title=Dunham's 'Christmas' sleighs ratings|date=18 November 2008|author=Daniel Frankel|work=[[Variety (magazine)|Variety]]}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In September 2008, his career reached new heights as he began performing in arenas filled with tens of thousands of people. Dunham was somewhat wary of such large venues, but adapted by adjusting the timing of his often rapid exchanges with the puppets so that audience members farthest from the stage could have time to react.&lt;ref name=BirthOfADummy/&gt;

In addition to his comedy specials, Dunham also released his first music album, ''[[Don't Come Home for Christmas]]'', on November 4, 2008.&lt;ref&gt;[https://www.amazon.com/dp/B001DXD57S ''Don't Come Home for Christmas'']. Amazon.com; retrieved November 23, 2011.&lt;/ref&gt; It contains original Christmas songs as well as a parody of "[[Jingle Bells]]" by Achmed entitled "Jingle Bombs". All the songs, with the exception of "Jingle Bombs", were written and accompanied by [[Brian Haner]], who joined Dunham's act as "Guitar Guy". His first onscreen appearance was in ''Jeff Dunham's Very Special Christmas Special''.{{citation needed|date=May 2014}}

===2009–present===
[[File:Jeff Dunham performing in July 2014.jpg|thumbnail|right|Dunham performing in 2014]]
In March 2009, Dunham signed a multi-platform deal with Comedy Central. It included a fourth stand-up special to air in 2010, DVDs, a consumer products partnership, a 60-city tour beginning in September 2010, and an order for a television series called ''[[The Jeff Dunham Show]]'' that premiered on October 22, 2009.&lt;ref name=MultiPlatform/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.comedycentral.com/shows/jeff_dunham/index.jhtml ''The Jeff Dunham Show'' at Comedy Central].&lt;/ref&gt; Despite having the most-watched premiere in Comedy Central history, and higher average ratings than other shows on that network initially, the show was canceled after only one season, amid poor reviews, dwindling ratings and higher production costs than other Comedy Central shows.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.thrfeed.com/2009/12/comedy-central-no-plans-to-renew-jeff-dunham.html|title=Comedy Central: 'No plans' to renew Jeff Dunham|author=Nellie Andreeva|date=29 December 2009 |publisher=''The Live Feed'' blog |deadurl=yes |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20100101061739/http://www.thrfeed.com/2009/12/comedy-central-no-plans-to-renew-jeff-dunham.html |archivedate=1 January 2010 |accessdate=22 January 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="Huffington Post"&gt;{{cite news|last=Shae|first=Danny|title="Jeff Dunham Show" CANCELED By Comedy Central|url=http://www.huffingtonpost.com/2009/12/29/jeff-dunham-show-canceled_n_406408.html|work=Huffington Post|accessdate=25 February 2012|date=29 December 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Dunham appeared in a guest role with Bubba J on NBC's sitcom ''[[30 Rock]]'', playing a ventriloquist named Rick Wayne and his dummy Pumpkin from [[Stone Mountain, Georgia]].&lt;ref&gt;Brown, Lane. [http://nymag.com/daily/entertainment/2009/10/jeff_dunham_saves_30_rock.html "No Dunham Bump for 30 Rock Ratings"]. ''[[New York Magazine]]''. October 20, 2009.&lt;/ref&gt; In November 2009 Dunham also appeared with Walter in "Hart to Hart", an episode of the [[Disney Channel]] series ''[[Sonny With a Chance]]'', as two security guards. He appeared in the 2010 [[Steve Carell]]/[[Paul Rudd]] comedy, ''[[Dinner for Schmucks]]'', as Lewis, with a new puppet named Diane.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.dinnerforschmucks.com/ ''Dinner for Schmucks''] {{webarchive |url=https://web.archive.org/web/20100409001345/http://www.dinnerforschmucks.com/ |date=9 April 2010 }} official site; accessed May 4, 2013.&lt;/ref&gt;

His fourth special, ''Jeff Dunham: Controlled Chaos'', premiered on September 25, 2011, on Comedy Central. His fifth special, ''Minding the Monsters'', which was taped in Savannah, premiered on Comedy Central on October 7, 2012.&lt;ref&gt;Harr, Dan (July 31, 2012). [http://www.musicnewsnashville.com/new-jeff-dunham-special-minding-the-monsters-coming-in-october "New Jeff Dunham Special 'Minding The Monsters' Coming in October"]. Music News Nashville.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Dunham, Jeff. ''Minding the Monsters''. Comedy Central. October 7, 2012.&lt;/ref&gt; His sixth special, ''All Over the Map'', which was taped in various international cities, premiered on Comedy Central on November 16, 2014.

On March 28, 2014, [[Country Music Television]] premiered ''Achmed Saves America'', an animated film starring Achmed the Dead Terrorist.&lt;ref name=Zap2it&gt;Bibel, Sara  [http://tvbythenumbers.zap2it.com/2014/03/19/jeff-dunhams-achmed-saves-america-to-premier-friday-march-28-on-cmt/246119 "Jeff Dunham's 'Achmed Saves America' to Premier Friday, March 28 on CMT"], TVbytheNumbers.Zap2it.com, March 19, 2014; accessed May 4, 2014.&lt;/ref&gt;

Dunham's seventh special, ''Unhinged in Hollywood'', premiered on September 17, 2015. Rather than premiering on Comedy Central, the special instead aired on [[NBC]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|last1=Holmes|first1=Manny|title=Jeff Dunham Books Primetime Special for NBC|url=https://variety.com/2015/tv/news/jeff-dunham-books-primetime-special-for-nbc-1201536953/|website=Variety|publisher=Variety|accessdate=11 July 2015|date=9 July 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Critical praise and controversy==
In January 2008, Dunham was voted by fans the Top Comic in [[Comedy Central]]'s "Stand-Up Showdown". He is the only person ever to win the "Ventriloquist of the Year" Award twice, was nominated "Comedian of the Year" by the [[The Nashville Network|TNN]] Music City News Country Awards,&lt;ref name=ComCenBio&gt;{{Cite web |url=http://www.comedycentral.com/comedians/browse/d/jeff_dunham.jhtml |title=Archived copy |access-date=2 February 2008 |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20080314104803/http://www.comedycentral.com/comedians/browse/d/jeff_dunham.jhtml |archive-date=14 March 2008 |dead-url=bot: unknown |df=dmy-all}}&lt;/ref&gt; and has drawn praise from the ''[[Dallas Morning News]]'' for his technique and timing.&lt;ref name=ComCenBio/&gt; Critics, such as Randee Dawn of ''[[The Hollywood Reporter]]'', accused Dunham's characters of being racist caricatures, sexist, and homophobic.&lt;ref name=TomMorris/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |author=Dawn, Randee |date=20 October 2009 |url=http://www.hollywoodreporter.com/review/jeff-dunham-show-tv-review-93691 |title=The Jeff Dunham Show |work=[[The Hollywood Reporter]]|accessdate=22 January 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In 2008, a TV commercial for a ringtone which featured Dunham's character Achmed the Dead Terrorist (see Characters below) was banned by the [[South Africa]]n [[Advertising Standards Authority (South Africa)|Advertising Standards Authority]] after a complaint was filed by a citizen stating that the ad was offensive to [[Muslims]], and portrayed all Muslims as terrorists. Dunham responded that "Achmed makes it clear in my act that he is not Muslim." However, the ASA noted that the name Achmed was of Arab origin and was one of the names of [[Muhammad]]. Dunham responded, ''"I've skewered whites, blacks, Hispanics, Christians, Jews, Muslims, gays, straights, rednecks, addicts, the elderly, and my wife. As a standup comic, it is my job to make the majority of people laugh, and I believe that comedy is the last true form of free speech ... I'm considering renaming Achmed 'Bill'"'', he added.&lt;ref name=FoxNews&gt;Miller, Joshua Rhett. [http://www.foxnews.com/story/0,2933,431866,00.html "Comedian Defends 'Achmed the Dead Terrorist' Puppet Routine Against South African Ban"]. [[Fox News]]. October 2, 2008&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://news.iafrica.com/sa/1194100.htm "Dead terrorist ad banned"]. iafrica.com. October 6, 2008&lt;/ref&gt; Dunham has conceded that he does exhibit particular sensitivity to the "conservative country crowd," or those characterized by "basic Christian values", as they are one of his largest constituencies, and part of his upbringing.&lt;ref name=NewYorkTimes/&gt;

Dunham was heckled and criticized for mocking TV critics during a July 2009 press tour to promote his then-upcoming Comedy Central TV series, ''[[The Jeff Dunham Show]]'', as well as Comedy Central programming chief Lauren Correo.&lt;ref name=NewYorkTimes/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;de Moraes, Lisa. [https://www.washingtonpost.com/wp-dyn/content/article/2009/07/29/AR2009072903534.html "How to Woo the TV Critics? With Insults"], ''[[The Washington Post]]''. July 30, 2009; accessed May 4, 2014.&lt;/ref&gt; In October 2009 ''The Jeff Dunham Show'' enjoyed good initial ratings, but was not well liked by critics,&lt;ref&gt;Dietz, Jason (May 3, 2010). [http://www.metacritic.com/feature/best-and-worst-tv-shows-2009-2010-season "2009–10 TV Scorecard: The Best and Worst Shows and Networks"]. [[Metacritic]].&lt;/ref&gt; some of whom either questioned the wisdom of translating his act into a series, or cited Dunham, his previous specials, or ventriloquism itself as reasons for disliking the show.&lt;ref&gt;McLaren, Richard. [http://articles.boston.com/2009-10-22/ae/29265641_1_achmed-dunham-show-dummies "‘Dunham Show’ laughs are strictly for dummies"] {{Webarchive|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20110629003701/http://articles.boston.com/2009-10-22/ae/29265641_1_achmed-dunham-show-dummies |date=29 June 2011 }}. ''[[The Boston Globe]]''. October 22, 2009&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="chisun"&gt;Wiser, Paige. [http://blogs.suntimes.com/tv/2009/10/tv_review_comedy_centrals_the.html "TV Review: Comedy Central's 'The Jeff Dunham Show'"]. ''[[Chicago Sun-Times]]''. October 22, 2009&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Stuever, Hank. [https://www.washingtonpost.com/wp-dyn/content/article/2009/10/21/AR2009102103668.html "Jeff Dunham's laugh-free zone"]. ''The Washington Post''. October 22, 2009&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Lowry, Brian. [http://www.variety.com/review/VE1117941417.html?categoryid=32&amp;cs=1&amp;nid=4749 "The Jeff Dunham Show"]. ''[[Variety (magazine)|Daily Variety]]''. October 20, 2009&lt;/ref&gt;

J.P. Williams, the producer of the [[Blue Collar Comedy Tour]], has opined that Dunham's act is not funny on its own merits, and that his material gets a greater reaction because of the puppet characters than it would otherwise garner by itself.&lt;ref name=NewYorkTimes/&gt; Blue Collar veteran Bill Engvall, a friend of Dunham's, insists otherwise, saying that Dunham is inherently funny with or without the puppets.&lt;ref name=BirthOfADummy/&gt;

In a 2014 show in Malaysia, the government requested that he not use or name Achmed in his show. Due to the restriction, but to avoid disappointing fans, Achmed was renamed to be "Jacques Merde, the Dead French Terrorist" (Jacques Merde meaning "Jack S&amp;#104;&amp;#105;t").&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |url= https://sg.entertainment.yahoo.com/blogs/singapore-showbiz/jeff-dunham-and--achmed-the-dead-terrorist--joke-about-chewing-gum-in-first-singapore-show-102046216.html |title= Jeff Dunham and 'Achmed the Dead Terrorist' joke about chewing gum in first Singapore show |author= Nurul Azliah |work= Singapore Showbiz |publisher= Yahoo! Entertainment |date= 22 May 2014 |access-date= 25 September 2015 |archive-url= https://web.archive.org/web/20150925143950/https://sg.entertainment.yahoo.com/blogs/singapore-showbiz/jeff-dunham-and--achmed-the-dead-terrorist--joke-about-chewing-gum-in-first-singapore-show-102046216.html |archive-date= 25 September 2015 |dead-url= yes |df= dmy-all }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |url= http://thecomicscomic.com/2014/05/27/jeff-dunham-puts-new-words-in-achmed-the-dead-terrorists-mouth-for-malaysian-audience-on-world-tour/ |title= Censored: Jeff Dunham puts new words in Achmed The Dead Terrorist's mouth for Malaysian audience on world tour |publisher= The Comic's Comic |author= Sean L. McCarthy |date= 2014 }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |url= http://lasvegassun.com/vegasdeluxe/2014/jun/18/q-after-30-years-road-jeff-dunham-ready-residency-/ |title= Q+A: After 30 years on the road, Jeff Dunham is ready for a run at Planet Hollywood |author= Robin Leach |date= 18 June 2014 |publisher= Las Vegas Sun |accessdate=22 January 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Books==
In 2003, BRASMA Publications released ''Dear Walter'', a collection of questions asked of Dunham's fictional curmudgeon at live performances, authored by Dunham and Walter Cummings.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |last=Dunham |first=Jeff |isbn=0970132301 |title=Dear Walter}}&lt;/ref&gt; His autobiography, ''All By My Selves: Walter, Peanut, Achmed and Me'', was published by Dutton in November 2010.&lt;ref name=AllByMySelves/&gt;

==Characters==

===Walter===
{{distinguish|Walter (Muppet)}}
[[File:Walter (Jeff Dunham Character, 2007).jpg|thumb|Dunham with Walter, in a shot from a 2007 performance]]

Walter is a retired, grumpy old man with arms always crossed in discontent. Dunham was inspired to create Walter when he watched [[Bette Davis]]'s final appearance on ''The Tonight Show Starring Johnny Carson'', giving her honest, unfiltered candor to Walter, and patterning Walter's frown on Dunham's own.&lt;ref name=BirthOfADummy/&gt; He has a brash, negative and often sarcastic view on today's world. He is a [[Vietnam War]] veteran and a former welder, and "doesn't give a damn" about anyone, especially his own wife and certain audience members. Walter appeared in all four [[Comedy Central]] specials. He's been married for several decades. When Dunham asks him if he remembers the happiest moment of his life after Walter tells him he has been married for forty-six years, Walter responds, "Forty-''seven'' years ago!" Dunham created the Walter puppet himself, including both the initial sculpture and the silicone mold, though he eventually began using professional effects companies for the latter stages with his subsequent puppets.&lt;ref name=SparkDVD&gt;This is mentioned in an extra on the ''Spark of Insanity'' DVD.&lt;/ref&gt;

In ''Relative Disaster'' it's revealed that Walter might be Jeff's biological father.

===Peanut===
Peanut is a hyperactive,&lt;ref name=NewYorkTimes/&gt; purple-skinned "woozle"&lt;ref&gt;{{cite av media|url=https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=fWThRmRW6GE|title=YouTube|publisher=}}&lt;/ref&gt; with white fur covering most of his body, a tuft of green hair on the top of his head, and one sneaker on his left foot. Dunham explains in ''Arguing with Myself'' that Peanut is from a small [[Micronesia]]n island, and that they met in Florida. Peanut's humor is not based on a particular motif or stereotype, as those of the other characters, and he has been described as "the bad kid".&lt;ref name=Time/&gt; He often makes fun of Dunham, and torments and mocks José Jalapeño on a Stick. Touching upon his unusual appearance and personality, he asks Dunham in ''Arguing with Myself'', after Dunham denies ever having done drugs, "Then how the hell did you come up with ''me''?"

===José Jalapeño on a Stick===
José is a talking [[jalapeño]] pepper on a stick who wears a small [[sombrero]]. José, who speaks with a thick Spanish accent, is typically paired with Peanut, who often makes fun of José, uses appeals to [[Latino]] stereotypes when doing so, and makes fun of his being on a stick.&lt;ref name="puppets"/&gt; Although José was not Dunham's first puppet, it was the first that Dunham made himself.&lt;ref&gt;This is mentioned in the DVD Commentary of ''Arguing with Myself''.&lt;/ref&gt;

Dunham has not used José in any specials since "Minding the Monsters", although he was referenced by Walter in ''Relative Disaster''.

===Bubba J===
Bubba J is a beer-drinking [[redneck]] that Dunham describes in ''Arguing with Myself'' and ''A Very Special Christmas Special'' as "[[white trash]] [[trailer park]]", and whom Dunham uses for humor centered on such stereotypes. To this end, he frequently does jokes involving Bubba J's love of drinking beer and [[NASCAR]], and his low intelligence. Touching upon such stereotypes, Bubba mentions in ''Arguing with Myself'' that he met his wife at a family reunion, and remembers seeing her with a [[corn dog]] in one hand, a beer in another, and leaning against a [[ferris wheel]], "making it tilt".&lt;ref name="puppets"/&gt; Although he does not appear onstage, Bubba has a prominent role as the backstage security guard in ''Controlled Chaos''.

===Sweet Daddy Dee===
Dunham introduces Sweet Daddy Dee in ''[[Jeff Dunham: Arguing with Myself|Arguing with Myself]]'' as his "new manager". He calls himself a "pimp", which he says stands for "Player In the Management Profession." According to Sweet Daddy, because he is a pimp, that makes Jeff the "[[Prostitution|ho]]". When Dunham objects, Daddy Dee points out that Dunham makes people laugh and feel good for a living. When Dunham agrees that this is the case, Daddy Dee says, "You a ho." When Dunham asks what he would say if he told him that he was a comedian only because he enjoyed it, Daddy Dee responds, "You a ''dumb'' ho."&lt;ref name="puppets"&gt;{{cite web|title=Jeff Dunham and his puppets|publisher=UnikNotions|url=http://uniknotions.com/fullarticle.php?articlenum=100|accessdate=4 May 2014|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20160203010854/http://uniknotions.com/fullarticle.php?articlenum=100|archive-date=3 February 2016|dead-url=yes|df=dmy-all}}&lt;/ref&gt; Much unlike Bubba J, he hates NASCAR. Sweet Daddy's headstone is featured in the beginning of the special ''Minding the Monsters''. As revealed in the DVD release, this signifies that he will no longer be used; however, he has reappeared in some videos on Jeff's YouTube channel, he was also referenced in ''Relative Disaster''.{{citation needed|date=May 2014}}

===Melvin the Superhero Guy===
Melvin wears a blue superhero costume, and is used to poke fun at [[superhero]]es. When asked about his superhuman powers, he indicates that he has [[X-ray vision]], adding, "I love looking at boobies!" He appears to have no other powers, however: When Dunham asks how far he can fly, he responds, "How far can you throw me?", and when asked if he can stop a bullet like [[Superman]], he responds, "Yeah. Once". Dunham portrays Melvin as unimpressed with other superheroes: When told Superman can leap tall buildings in a single bound, Melvin dismisses him as a "showoff," arguing that he can simply walk around them, observes that [[Aquaman]] has the same powers as [[SpongeBob SquarePants (character)|SpongeBob SquarePants]], asserts that the [[Flash (comics)|Flash]]'s [[speedster (comics)|super speed]] is derived from [[methamphetamine]], that the [[Hulk (comics)|Hulk]]'s vaunted ability to get stronger as he gets angrier merely mirrors "every white trash guy on ''[[Cops (TV series)|COPS]]''," and makes [[innuendo]] about the [[Ephebophilia|questionable relationship]] between [[Batman]] and the underage [[Robin (comics)|Robin]]. Melvin's first onscreen appearance was in the July 2003 ''[[Comedy Central Presents]]'' episode, in which he had small, black, beady eyes. By his next appearance, in ''Spark of Insanity'', he had been modified to have large, blue, [[strabismus|crossed eyes]]. He has an enormous nose, which he claims is his symbol, and whose similarity in shape to that of a penis is alluded to in the act. Dunham sculpted the current version of Melvin's head himself, and hired an effects company called Renegade Effects Groups to create the rubber mold and complete the puppet, before then installing the mechanics himself.&lt;ref name=SparkDVD/&gt; Melvin's headstone is featured in the beginning of the special ''Minding the Monsters''. As revealed in the DVD release, this signifies that he will no longer be used. {{citation needed|date=May 2014}}

===Achmed the Dead Terrorist===
Achmed is the skeletal corpse of an incompetent [[suicide bomber]], whom Dunham uses to satirize the contemporary issue of [[terrorism]]. He is known for yelling, "Silence! I keel you!" to Dunham and people laughing in the audience. Achmed first appeared in ''Spark of Insanity'', and has since appeared in every Dunham special since then. In ''Spark of Insanity'' the audience learns several things about Achmed. When Dunham says that Achmed must be dead because he's a skeleton, Achmed responds, "[[Monty Python and the Holy Grail|It's a flesh wound]]." When Dunham inquires as to how he died, Achmed explains his incompetence with explosives, while also casting aspersions on Dunham's sexual prowess by saying that they both suffer from "[[Premature ejaculation|premature detonation]]". Although he frequently mentions working for [[Osama Bin Laden]], Achmed denies being a Muslim and says "Look at my ass! It says '[[Made in China]]'!" He says he is afraid of Walter, partially because he's "one mean son of a bitch" and finds Walter's flatulence to be more potent than Saddam Hussein's [[Halabja poison gas attack|mustard gas]]. In [[Jeff Dunham's Very Special Christmas Special|''Very Special Christmas Special'']], he sings a song called "Jingle Bombs".

By June 2009, the sketch in which Dunham introduced Achmed has amassed nearly 200 million views.&lt;ref name=Time/&gt;&lt;ref name=Purcell&gt;"Achmed the dead terrorist and humor in popular geopolitics" by Darren Purcell, Melissa Scott Brown and Mahmut Gokmen, ''GeoJournal'', January 31, 2009.&lt;/ref&gt; The large, round, articulated eyes of puppets such as Achmed and Achmed Junior are constructed by the same effects artist who created the dinosaur eyes for the ''[[Jurassic Park (film)|Jurassic Park]]'' films.&lt;ref name=BirthOfADummy/&gt; The character's popularity lead to a starring role in ''Achmed Saves America'', an animated film that premiered on Country Music Television in March 2014. In the film, which depicts the mishap that led to the character's skeletonization, Achmed himself is in an American town called Americaville, which he plots to blow up, before developing an affinity for American culture.&lt;ref name=Zap2it/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.achmedsavesamerica.com ACHMED SAVES AMERICA – Official Trailer], AchmedSavesAmerica.com; retrieved March 20, 2014.&lt;/ref&gt;

===Little Jeff===
Little Jeff is a miniature version of Dunham himself, usually dressed in the same clothes Dunham wears during each show. He appeared in ''Jeff Dunham: Controlled Chaos'' as a puppet that Peanut used when trying to do ventriloquism like Dunham. Peanut named the doll "Little Ugly Ass-Jeff", and uses him to insult Dunham. In ''Unhinged in Hollywood'', Dunham himself puppeteers him, and gives him different voice than he did in his past performances.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.jeffdunham.com/characters/little-jeff/|title=Little Jeff - Jeff Dunham|publisher=}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Diane===
Diane first appeared with Dunham in the 2010 film ''[[Dinner for Schmucks]]'' as "Debbie", his character's "wife". She made her stand-up debut in Dunham's Identity Crisis Tour 2010.&lt;ref&gt;[http://campaigns.eaudiencemarketing.com/emails/AhI17386Ykrr Jeff Dunham's Identity Crisis Tour]; accessed 28 September 2010.&lt;/ref&gt;

===Achmed Junior===
Achmed Junior is the estranged son of Achmed. He was designed by ''[[Mad (magazine)|Mad]]'' magazine illustrator [[Tom Richmond (illustrator)|Tom Richmond]].&lt;ref name=BirthOfADummy/&gt; He first appeared during the Identity Crisis Tour 2010, and made his first onscreen appearance in Dunham's fourth special, ''Jeff Dunham: Controlled Chaos''. Like his father, Achmed Junior is the victim of a bomb, which resulted in the destruction of the half of his face and body. He speaks with a British accent because he was raised in Britain after the accident. Much to his father's consternation, he expresses an attraction to Dunham's male stage hand, Marnell, who constantly came on stage because Achmed kept losing balance on the stand and eventually Marnell brought duct tape. He does not wish to be a suicide bomber.&lt;ref&gt;Dunham, Jeff (). [https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=IL357BrwK7c ''Jeff Dunham: Controlled Chaos'']. [[YouTube]] (2011), 7:43 to 8:09.&lt;/ref&gt;

===Seamus===
Seamus is Dunham's newest adopted addition to his family. He is an Irish infant, but is already well-versed in drinking. He is introduced in the Netflix special ''Relative Disaster''.

===Others===
Other characters that Dunham has voiced include a miniature puppet of Peanut's, and an unseen [[Mezcal worm|worm inside a bottle of tequila]], both of which he has used, for example, in his appearance on [[A&amp;E Television Networks|A&amp;E]]'s ''An Evening at [[The Improv]]''.&lt;ref&gt;[https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=lDsjr7O6_T0&amp;feature=related Video of Dunham]. [[A&amp;E Television Networks|A&amp;E]]'s ''An Evening at [[The Improv]]''.&lt;/ref&gt;

==Personal life==
Dunham met his first wife, Paige Brown, at the Comedy Corner in [[West Palm Beach, Florida]]. They began dating in December 1992. In May 1994, Dunham married Brown and adopted her one-and-a-half-year-old daughter, Bree. Their daughters Ashlyn and Kenna were born in 1995 and 1997, respectively. Dunham's time away while performing proved a strain on the marriage,&lt;ref name=BirthOfADummy/&gt; and in November 2008, he filed for divorce.&lt;ref name=NewYorkTimes/&gt;&lt;ref name=Time/&gt;&lt;ref name=BirthOfADummy/&gt;&lt;ref name=AllByMySelves/&gt; By mid-2009, Dunham was in a relationship with fellow Texan Audrey Murdick, a certified nutritionist, personal trainer, and competition bodybuilder,&lt;ref name=BirthOfADummy/&gt;&lt;ref name=AllByMySelves/&gt; and on December 25, 2011 they became engaged.&lt;ref&gt;Dunham, Jeff (December 27, 2011). [https://twitter.com/jeffdunham/status/151758321945280512 "Hey everyone! On Christmas Day,@AudreyMurdick &amp; I got engaged!"], [[Twitter]]; accessed May 4, 2014.&lt;/ref&gt; On October 12, 2012, the couple married.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|author=Dunham, Jeff|url=https://twitter.com/jeffdunham/status/257173671502827520|title=TA DAAAA! @audreymurdick and I are now married and I'm the luckiest guy on the planet! #jedreywedding2012 Off to honeymoon!|publisher=Twitter|date=October 13, 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt; On May 14, 2015, Dunham announced, via Facebook, that he and Audrey were expecting twin boys.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.facebook.com/JeffDunham/photos/a.10150112173813827.293840.8303218826/10153298257928827/?type=1|title=Jeff Dunham - Timeline Photos - Facebook|publisher=}}&lt;/ref&gt; In October, she gave birth to James Jeffrey and Jack Steven.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://celebritybabies.people.com/2015/10/13/jeff-dunham-welcomes-twin-sons-jack-steven-and-james-jeffrey/|title=Jeff Dunham Welcomes Sons Jack Steven and James Jeffrey – Moms &amp; Babies – Celebrity Babies and Kids - Moms &amp; Babies - People.com|work=PEOPLE.com}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In addition to building the dummies he uses in his act, Dunham also restores antique ones as a hobby, such as The Umpire, a {{convert|6|ft|m|adj=mid|-tall}} mechanized dummy built in 1941 to work the plate at a girls' [[softball]] game, which went unused and packed away for 50 years before Dunham acquired it in early 2008.&lt;ref name=NewYorkTimes/&gt;

Dunham has harbored a love of [[helicopter]]s since childhood and is fond of building and flying his own [[kit helicopters]] from [[Rotorway]] helicopter kits. At the time he finished writing his autobiography in June 2010, he was beginning to build his fourth kit.&lt;ref name=BirthOfADummy/&gt;&lt;ref name=FastLiving/&gt;&lt;ref name=AllByMySelves/&gt; He is an aficionado of [[muscle car]]s and [[Apple, Inc.]] products.&lt;ref name=AllByMySelves/&gt;

According to the July 16, 2012, TV documentary, ''[[The Batmobile]]'', Dunham owns a replica of the Batmobile that was used in the Tim Burton film ''[[Batman (1989 film)|Batman]]''.&lt;ref&gt;Rushworth, Heather (July 13, 2012). [http://www.execdigital.com/entertainment/comedian-jeff-dunham-interview-he-owns-a-batmobile "Comedian Jeff Dunham Interview: He Owns a Batmobile?!"] {{Webarchive|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20130130210903/http://www.execdigital.com/entertainment/comedian-jeff-dunham-interview-he-owns-a-batmobile |date=30 January 2013 }}. Exec Digital; accessed May 4, 2014.&lt;/ref&gt;

==Tours==
{{BLP unsourced section|date=January 2015}}
{| class="wikitable"
!Tour
!Dates
&lt;sup&gt;(non-inclusive)&lt;/sup&gt;
!Countries
&lt;sup&gt;(in order of first show)&lt;/sup&gt;
!Notes
|-
|Spark of Insanity
|Sept. 8, 2007 –&lt;br /&gt; Jan. 9, 2010
|United States, Canada, England, Sweden, Denmark, Finland, Norway, Australia
|
|-
|Identity Crysis
|Jan. 9, 2010 –&lt;br /&gt; Sept. 24, 2011
|United States, Canada, Netherlands, Ireland, England, Scotland, South Africa, Switzerland, Belgium, Norway, Sweden, France
|
|-
|Controlled Chaos
|Oct. 6, 2011 –&lt;br /&gt; Sept. 30, 2012
|United States, Canada, Scotland, England, Germany, Belgium, Northern Ireland, Ireland, South Africa, Australia, New Zealand
|
|-
|Disorderly Conduct
|Nov. 1, 2012 –&lt;br /&gt;Sept. 28, 2014
|Canada, United States, Denmark, Belgium, Netherlands, Iceland, Sweden, Norway, Ireland, England, Scotland, United Arab Emirates, Israel, South Africa, Australia, Malaysia, Singapore
|
|-
|Not Playing With a Full Deck
|{{nowrap|Nov. 28, 2014–}}
|United States
|All shows at Planet Hollywood Resort &amp; Casino, Las Vegas, Nevada.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news|url=http://www.latimes.com/travel/lasvegas/lasvegasnow/la-tr-lvn-las-vegas-shows-jeff-dunham-20150323-story.html|title=Jeff Dunham extends his Las Vegas residency four more months|date=2015-03-24|work=Los Angeles Times|access-date=2017-09-25|language=en-US|issn=0458-3035}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news|url=https://lasvegassun.com/vegasdeluxe/2014/nov/28/jeff-dunham-brings-not-playing-full-deck-planet-ho/|title=Q+A: Jeff Dunham brings 'Not Playing With a Full Deck' to Planet Hollywood|date=2014-11-28|work=LasVegasSun.com|access-date=2017-09-25}}&lt;/ref&gt;
|-
|Perfectly Unbalanced
|Unknown –&lt;br /&gt; Sept. 13, 2017
|United States, Canada
|Exact date for when tour started is unknown. He received a star on the Hollywood Walk of Fame during this tour.&lt;ref name="Billboard"&gt;{{Cite news|url=http://www.billboard.com/articles/business/7965835/jeff-dunham-tour-dates|title=Famed Ventriloquist Jeff Dunham Announces 60-City Passively Aggressive Tour: Exclusive|work=Billboard|access-date=2017-09-25}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news|url=https://variety.com/2017/scene/features/walk-of-fame-honoree-jeff-dunham-1202564694/|title=Walk of Fame Honoree Jeff Dunham Opens Up About His Constant Reinvention|last=Blair|first=Iain|date=2017-09-21|work=Variety|access-date=2017-09-25|language=en-US}}&lt;/ref&gt;
|-
|Passively Aggressive
|{{nowrap|Sept. 28, 2017 –}}&lt;br /&gt; May 5, 2018
|United States, Canada
|&lt;ref name="Billboard"/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news|url=https://www.usatoday.com/story/entertainment/events/things-to-do/2017/09/19/jeff-dunham-tour-louisville/681052001/|title=Jeff Dunham brings his 'Passively Aggressive' tour to Yum Center|work=USA TODAY|access-date=2017-09-25|language=en}}&lt;/ref&gt;
|}

==Filmography==
{| class="wikitable sortable"
|- style="background:#b0c4de; text-align:center;"
! Year
! Title
! Role
!class="unsortable" |Notes
|-
| 1991
| ''[[Hot Country Nights]]''
| Himself
| One episode
|-
| 1996
| ''[[Ellen (TV series)|Ellen]]''
| Starky the Ventriloquist
| Episode: "When the Vow Breaks: Part 1" (with Walter as Gus)
|-
| 2002
| ''[[Any Day Now (TV series)|Any Day Now]]''
| Ventriloquist
| Episode: "Truth Hurts"
|-
| 2002
| ''[[She Spies]]''
| Elvis Presley ventriloquist
| Episode: "Ice Man"
|-
| 2003
| ''[[Comedy Central Presents]]''
| Himself
| Also writer
|-
| 2003
| ''[[One on One (TV series)|One on One]]''
| Benny / Kenny
| Episode: "I Know What You Did Last Thursday"
|-
| 2005
| ''[[Blue Collar TV]]''
| Ventriloquist
| Episode: "Stupidity"
|-
| 2006
| ''[[Jeff Dunham: Arguing with Myself]]''
| Himself
| TV special; also writer and executive producer
|-
| 2007
| ''[[Delta Farce]]''
| Amazing Ken
| First feature-length movie
|-
| 2007
| ''[[Jeff Dunham: Spark of Insanity]]''
| Himself
| TV special; also writer and executive producer
|-
| 2008
| ''[[History of the Joke]]''
| Himself
| TV documentary
|-
| 2008
| ''[[Jeff Dunham's Very Special Christmas Special]]''
| Himself
| TV special; also writer, executive producer and songwriter
|-
| 2009
| ''[[30 Rock]]''
| Rick Wayne
| Episode: "Stone Mountain" (with Bubba J. as Pumpkin)
|-
| 2009
| ''[[The Jeff Dunham Show]]''
| Himself
| 7 episodes; also writer and executive producer
|-
| 2009
| ''[[Sonny with a Chance]]''
| Jeff
| Episode: "Hart to Hart" (with Walter)
|-
| 2009
| ''I'm No Dummy''
| Himself
| [[Documentary film]]
|-
| 2010
| ''[[Dinner for Schmucks]]''
| Lewis the Ventriloquist
|
|-
| 2011
| ''[[Jeff Dunham: Controlled Chaos]]''
| Himself
| TV special; also writer and executive producer
|-
| 2012
| ''The Batmobile''
| Himself
| TV documentary
|-
| 2012
| ''[[Jeff Dunham: Minding the Monsters]]''
| Himself
| TV special; also writer and executive producer
|-
| 2012
| ''[[Big Top Scooby-Doo!]]''
| Schmatko, Conductor (voice)
| Video
|-
| 2013
| ''[[From Up on Poppy Hill]]''&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news|url=http://www.variety.com/article/VR1118060314?refCatId=13|title='Poppy Hill' sets high-profile voices|last=McNary|first=Dave|newspaper=[[Variety (magazine)|Variety]]|publisher=Reed Business Information|date=October 5, 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;
| Gen (voice)
| English version
|-
| 2014
| ''[[The Nut Job]]''
| Mole (voice)
| 
|-
| 2014
| ''[[Jeff Dunham: All Over the Map]]''
| Himself
| TV special; also writer, executive producer and co-editor
|-
| 2014
| ''Achmed Saves America''
| Achmed / Bubba J. / Himself
| Video; creator, executive producer and original character designer
|-
| 2016
| ''[[Hell's Kitchen (U.S. TV series)|Hell's Kitchen]]''
| Himself
| Episode: "9 Chefs Compete"(with Walter)
|-
| 2017
| ''[[Smurfs: The Lost Village]]''
| [[Farmer Smurf]] (voice)
|
|-
| 2017
| ''[[The Nut Job 2: Nutty by Nature]]''
| Mole (voice)
| 
|-
| 2017
| ''[[Mune: Guardian of the Moon]]''
| Phospho (voice)
| 
|-
| 2017
| ''Jeff Dunham: Relative Disaster''
| Himself
| [[Netflix]] special
|}

==References==
{{Reflist|2}}

==External links==
{{Commons category}}
{{Wikiquote}}
* {{official website}}
* [http://www.cc.com/comedians/jeff-dunham Jeff Dunham] at [[Comedy Central]]
* {{IMDb name|0242278|Jeff Dunham}}

{{Authority control}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Dunham, Jeff}}
[[Category:1962 births]]
[[Category:20th-century American comedians]]
[[Category:21st-century American comedians]]
[[Category:American adoptees]]
[[Category:American male voice actors]]
[[Category:American Presbyterians]]
[[Category:American puppeteers]]
[[Category:American stand-up comedians]]
[[Category:Baylor University alumni]]
[[Category:Living people]]
[[Category:Male actors from Dallas]]
[[Category:Ventriloquists]]
[[Category:Puppet designers]]</text>
      <sha1>1bstpae5bh2ythasij2g82qv8z397yj</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
