<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10.xsd" version="0.10" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <dbname>enwiki</dbname>
    <base>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.32.0-wmf.16</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="118" case="first-letter">Draft</namespace>
      <namespace key="119" case="first-letter">Draft talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2300" case="first-letter">Gadget</namespace>
      <namespace key="2301" case="first-letter">Gadget talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2302" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition</namespace>
      <namespace key="2303" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Léon Lemartin</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>29486639</id>
    <revision>
      <id>845939454</id>
      <parentid>838603023</parentid>
      <timestamp>2018-06-15T05:11:30Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Jon Kolbert</username>
        <id>29727696</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor/>
      <comment>Updating URL format for [[The New York Times]] archives</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="18040">{{Use dmy dates|date=August 2013}}
{{Infobox person
|name    = Léon Lemartin
|image    = Léon Lemartin.jpg
|caption   = Léon Lemartin
|birth_date = {{birth date|1883|10|20|df=y}}
|birth_place = [[Dunes, Tarn-et-Garonne]]
|death_date = {{death date and age|1911|6|18|1883|10|20|df=y}}
|death_place = [[Vincennes]], Paris, France
|other_names =
|known_for  = The world's first Test pilot,&lt;ref&gt;[http://patrimoine.gadz.org/gadz/lemartin.htm Léon Lemartin (Ai. 1899)]&lt;/ref&gt; by contract with [[Louis Blériot]] in the year 1910, record breaking pioneer [[aviator]] who carried seven, eight, eleven passengers
|occupation = Aircraft engineer and pilot
|nationality = French
}}

'''Théodore Clovis Edmond Lemartin''', known as '''Léon Lemartin''' (20 October 1883 [[Dunes, Tarn-et-Garonne]] – 18 June 1911, [[Vincennes]])&lt;ref name="Dunes"&gt;[http://mairie.dunes.pagesperso-orange.fr/histoire.htm History of Dunes –  Lemartin]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="Patri"/&gt; was a pioneer [[aviator]] who set a world record on 3 February 1911 at [[Pau, Pyrénées-Atlantiques|Pau, France]] when he carried seven&lt;ref name="Hartford"&gt;{{cite news |coauthors= |title=Takes Seven Persons Up in Monoplane. French Aviator Breaks World's Record| url=https://pqasb.pqarchiver.com/courant/access/763924142.html?dids=763924142:763924142&amp;FMT=CITE&amp;FMTS=CITE:AI&amp;type=historic&amp;date=Feb+03,+1911&amp;author=&amp;pub=Hartford+Courant&amp;desc=TAKES+SEVEN+PERSONS+UP+IN+MONOPLANE&amp;pqatl=google |quote= |work=[[Hartford Courant]] |date=3 February 1911 |accessdate=2010-11-04 }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="Chicago"&gt;{{cite book |coauthors= |title=The Chicago daily news almanac |year=1911 |publisher= |page= |quote= M. Le Martin, at Pau, France, carries seven passengers in a monoplane in a ...  | url=https://books.google.com/books?id=Q24aAQAAIAAJ&amp;pg=PA364&amp;lpg=PA364&amp;dq=Le+Martin+aviator&amp;source=bl&amp;ots=CI9nOky1xB&amp;sig=4JMZi_YetiLpUQU1hWtplh8A7p0&amp;hl=en&amp;ei=cVnUTIaoGIKdlgfRq9DHBA&amp;sa=X&amp;oi=book_result&amp;ct=result&amp;resnum=6&amp;ved=0CCgQ6AEwBQ#v=onepage&amp;q=Le%20Martin%20aviator&amp;f=false |isbn= }}&lt;/ref&gt; passengers in a [[Blériot XIII]] ''Aerobus''. He then took eight, eleven and thirteen passengers aloft the following month.&lt;ref name="Avia xiii"&gt;[http://www.aviafrance.com/aviafrance1.php?ID=10206&amp;ID_CONSTRUCTEUR=212&amp;ANNEE=0&amp;ID_MISSION=0&amp;MOTCLEF= AviaFrance – Profile of the Bleriot XIII]&lt;/ref&gt;

The son of a blacksmith, in 1902 he became a graduate ''[[Gadzarts|Gadz'Art]]'', an engineer of 'Arts and Crafts' of the [[École Nationale Supérieure d'Arts et Métiers]] (ENSAM) – a prestigious university ([[grande ecole]]) specialising in engineering.&lt;ref name="Patri"/&gt;&lt;ref name="La Marseil"/&gt; His aeronautic career included working with [[Gabriel Voisin]], the [[Gnome et Rhône|Seguin brothers]], [[Henri Farman]], [[Ernest Archdeacon]] and [[Louis Blériot]]. He was present when Blériot made the historic first crossing of the [[English channel]] in 1909.&lt;ref name="Patri"/&gt;&lt;ref name="OlivierD"/&gt; On 4 October 1910 he was awarded [[List of pilots awarded an Aviator's Certificate by the Aéro-Club de France in 1910|Aviator's Certificate number 249]] by the [[Aéro-Club de France]].

On 24 May 1911, three weeks before his death, he reportedly surpassed the world speed record although it was never officially recognized. He achieved {{convert|128.418|km/h|mph|abbr=on}} over the {{convert|33|km|mi}} flight between [[Etampes]] and [[Toury]] in a Blériot using his own enhancements to the [[Gnome Omega]] {{convert|50|hp|abbr=on}} motor.&lt;ref name="Patri"/&gt;

He died in a crash on 18 June 1911 during the Paris–London–Paris leg of ''Le Circuit Européen'' (Tour of Europe) air race. He was still within sight of the reportedly 'up to 1 million' spectators at the take-off in [[Vincennes]].&lt;ref name="NYT June 19, 1911"&gt;{{cite news |coauthors= |title=Three Men Die in Paris Flight. Five Also Hurt at Start of Big Circuit Race to London and Back. |url=https://timesmachine.nytimes.com/timesmachine/1911/06/19/104827149.pdf |quote=Two prominent aviators were killed and several injured in the first stage of the European Circuit aeroplane race from Paris to London and back, which started to-day from the aviation field at Vincennes, with stops at various places going and returning, while another competitor was killed near Chateau-Thierry. |newspaper=[[New York Times]] |date=19 June 1911 |accessdate=2010-11-04 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Early life==
Lemartin was born in the [[Communes of France|commune]] of [[Dunes, Tarn-et-Garonne|Dunes]] in the [[Departments of France|Department]] of [[Tarn-et-Garonne]] in south west France.&lt;ref name="Dunes"/&gt;&lt;ref name="Patri"/&gt; From the moment of his birth he was known as Léon, but his forenames (Théodore, Clovis, Edmond) honoured both his father and both of his grandfathers. When he graduated in 1902 and required authorisations to work he discovered a mistake on his birth certificate, that his family name of 'Le Martin' had been written 'Lemartin', but he decided that it was easier to adopt the 'new' spelling.&lt;ref name="Patri"/&gt;

His father Edmond was a [[blacksmith]] and [[farrier]] (Fr. Maréchal-ferrant), and a member of the '[[Compagnons du Tour de France]]' (a French community of craftsmen and artisans). He was also the inventor of several 'furnaces maréchal', some of which were patented. Edmond believed strongly in both science and technology so Léon spent many hours working in the forge learning practical skills.&lt;ref name="Patri"/&gt;

Once Lemartin achieved his 'school certificate' he was enrolled at the 'Ecole Pratique' d'[[Agen]]'. He was a gifted and serious student who advanced quickly so that in October 1899, when he was just sixteen, he left his native [[:fr:Brulhois|Brulhois]] area and travelled almost {{convert|500|km|mi}} to enroll at the 'Institute of Arts et Métiers' in [[Aix-en-Provence]] where he became a ''[[Gadzarts|Gadz'Art]]'', the nickname given to the students and alumni of the [[École Nationale Supérieure d'Arts et Métiers]] (ENSAM), a prestigious university (''[[grande ecole]]'') specialising in engineering. At the age of nineteen, in 1902, he became a qualified ''Gadz'Art'', an engineer of 'Arts and Crafts' (''Ingénieur des Arts et Métiers'') and moved to Paris.&lt;ref name="Patri"&gt;[http://patrimoine.gadz.org/gadz/lemartin.htm Patrimoine (Heritage) – Grandes figures of gadzarts – Profiles of alumni – Léon Lemartin by Jean-Louis Eytier with contributions from Jacques Dalmon, the only grandson of Lemartin.]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="La Marseil"&gt;[http://www.lamarseillaise.fr/economie/ces-gadz-arts-aixois-entr-s-dans-la-l-gende.html La Marseillaise, Ces « Gadz’Arts » Aixois Entres dans la Legende. 19-07-2010 – Graduates of ''Ingénieur des Arts et Métiers'' at Aix-en-Provence]&lt;/ref&gt;

In December 1902 Lemartin met aviation enthusiast Louise Soriano, who had divorced the [[Charles de Lambert (aviator)|Comte Charles de Lambert]] and married [[:es:Ricardo Soriano|Ricardo Soriano von Hermansdorff Sholtz]], Marquis de Ivanrey. Lemartin and Louise worked together during their joint airship project and subsequently married, upon which he adopted her daughter Jane (or Jeanne&lt;ref&gt;[[:fr:Léon Lemartin|French article -Léon Lemartin]]&lt;/ref&gt;) de Lambert from her first marriage.&lt;ref name="Patri"/&gt; Louise died in December 1907 and is buried in Dunes. Lemartin then married Madeleine, née Baas, and they had three children: Louise, Simone and Léone. Jane de Lambert also grew up in the family. After his death, Madeleine married his brother Albert and had two more children, Maurice and Roger.&lt;ref name="Patri"/&gt;

==Airship project==
Lemartin had an early interest in ballooning and, learning from [[Alberto Santos-Dumont]], he began to build an airship in collaboration with the Spanish aristocrat, financier, engineer, inventor and adventurer Ricardo Soriano von Hermansdorff Sholtz. The project failed due to a fire, so Lemartin applied to the 'L'École Duvignau', but without success.&lt;ref name="Patri"/&gt;

==Gnome years==

[[File:Gnome Omega OW.jpg|thumb|right|Gnome 7 Omega at the [[Shuttleworth Collection]]. Brown staining caused by burnt [[castor oil]]]]

[[File:Gnome Omega RAFM.jpg|thumb|left|Gnome 7 Omega on display at the [[Royal Air Force Museum London]]]]

In the early 1900s, Lemartin started work at the automobile manufacturer [[Charron (automobile)|Charron]], based in [[Puteaux]] Paris. He later moved to [[E.N.V.]] He later worked for [[Gabriel Voisin]] on the structure of his early experimental glider which was towed into the air from the river Seine, flying {{convert|600|m|ft}}, in 1905.

Lemartin was apparently not convinced by the Voisin approach and agreed with [[Louis Bleriot]] that the engine was key to achieving powered heavier-than-air flight in a monoplane. Thus, he joined [[Gnome et Rhône|Société Des Moteurs Gnome]] (the Gnome motor company founded by [[Louis Seguin|Louis]] and [[Laurent Seguin]] in 1905) where he worked on their 7-cylinder [[Gnome Omega]] [[rotary engine]] project, and became a key developer of the basic idea. The Omega set a benchmark with its delivery of 50&amp;nbsp;hp (37&amp;nbsp;kW) from {{convert|75|kg|lb}}. He also had a special role in the company whereby he was seconded to directly support the aviators who were using the Omega.

At Gnome, he worked with [[Jules Védrines]], another young engineer who went on to win the special consolation prize in the 1911 ''[[Daily Mail]]'' [[Daily Mail aviation prizes|Round-Britain Air race]] and the overall prize in the [[1911 Paris to Madrid air race]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://transpressnz.blogspot.com/2011/01/century-ago-paris-to-madrid-air-race-of.html Paris-Madrid Air race – 1911]&lt;/ref&gt;

One of the notable events of the [[Grande Semaine d'Aviation]] held at Reims in August 1909 was the public debut of the Gnome rotary engine, and Gnome-engined aircraft won first and third places in the distance prize.[[Henri Farman]]'s winning flight of ({{convert|180|km|mi}}) was made with a Gnome engine which had been installed immediately before the flight, his previous engine having proved unreliable. He used the same aircraft to win the passenger carrying prize.

&lt;!--As senior customer engineer at Gnome, Lemartin worked on the engines for [[Alfred Leblanc]]'s [[Blériot XI]] aircraft at major air-meetings such as Reims, Nice, and Bordeaux.--&gt;

==Blériot years==
On 20 August 1910, Lemartin signed a contract to join [[Louis Bleriot]]'s flying school to train as a pilot and work as an engineer. By this contract, he becomes the first ever official Test Pilot in the world. He qualified six weeks later on 4 October. His registration number was 249, and he was assigned to Bleriot's schools at [[Étampes]] and [[Pau, Pyrénées-Atlantiques|Pau]]. His contract entitled him to 400 francs per month (about €1,100 in 2006), 30 francs per flight (~€80), and 32,500 francs (~€87,000) to his widow in case of death.&lt;ref name="Patri"/&gt; On 4 October 1910 he was awarded [[List of pilots awarded an Aviator's Certificate by the Aéro-Club de France in 1910|Aviator's Certificate number 249]] by the [[Aéro-Club de France]].

On 3 February 1911, at Pau, he broke the world record by carrying seven passengers in a [[Blériot XIII]], surpassing [[Roger Sommer]]'s previous record of six.&lt;ref name="Hartford"/&gt;&lt;ref name="Chicago"/&gt; During March 1911, he went on to increase the record to eight, then eleven, and finally thirteen passengers,&lt;ref name="Avia xiii"/&gt; and including the aviators [[Jeanne Herveu]] (founder of the first flying school for women.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.earlyaviators.com/eherveux.htm Jeanne Herveux]&lt;/ref&gt;), and [[Paul Wyss]], a [[Switzerland|Swiss]] pilot who was training at the Bleriot school in Pau at the time.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.pionnair-ge.com/spip1/spip.php?article72 Pionnair, Les pionniers de l’aéronautique à Genève, Paul Wyss : pilote indépendant des premiers meetings aériens Genevois.]&lt;/ref&gt;).

{{quote|Despite its weight, my monoplane lifted into the air perfectly. I had a very clear vision and next to me the passengers were installed under the wings, like the Imperial Parisian omnibus, watching the hills roll by ... and I'm happy to be their pilot.|Léon Lemartin|''[[The Independent]]'', February 1910.}}

On 24 May 1911, three weeks before his death, he reportedly surpassed the world speed record, although it was never officially authorised. He achieved {{convert|128.418|km/h|abbr=on}} between [[Etampes]] and [[Toury]] in a Blériot using "his own" enhanced model of the Gnome {{convert|50|hp|abbr=on}} motor.&lt;ref name="Patri"/&gt; (The official record of {{convert|125|km/h|mph|abbr=on}} was set by Leblanc on 12 June during qualifying for the ''[[Gordon Bennett Trophy (aeroplanes)|Gordon Bennett Trophy]]''.)&lt;ref name="Patri"/&gt;

On 1 June 1911, he signed a new contract with Louis Bleriot, becoming a member of the race team to compete at major events and receive one third of any prizes won. The total prize money for the event was 450,000 francs&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.flightglobal.com/pdfarchive/view/1911/1911%20-%200163.html The Circuit of Europe]  ''[[Flight International|Flight]]'' 25 February 1911&lt;/ref&gt; (about €1,200,000 in 2006), made up of a number of separate prizes for the various stages of the race.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.flightglobal.com/pdfarchive/view/1911/1911%20-%200554.html The Circuit of Europe]''[[Flight International|Flight]]'' 24 June 1911&lt;/ref&gt;

==Death and commemoration==
[[File:Léon Lemartin (1911).jpg|thumb|Lemartin in 1911]]

Lemartin died in a crash on 18 June 1911 during the first leg of ''Le Circuit Européen'' (Tour of Europe) air race. He was still within sight of the reportedly 'up to 1 million' spectators at the take-off in [[Vincennes]].

The '' Circuit Européen'' (Tour of Europe) was his first competition. The night before his departure from Vincennes, he was working on the machines of his teammates [[Gustav Hamel]] and Lieutenant [[Jean Louis Conneau]] (flying under the name André Beaumont) who went on to win both ''Le Circuit Européen'' and ''Paris-Rome''. Thus the next morning, 18 June, Lemartin was tired.&lt;ref name="NYT June 19, 1911"/&gt;
That morning, the weather was not good and Roland Garros, who was the first to start, had to scratch. He advised Lemartin against flying because ''"les ailes souples ne vont pas tenir!"'' ("the wings are too flexible and will not hold"), but Lemartin wanted to achieve his dream of racing before a million spectators.

According to the ''[[New York Times]]'' of 19 June 1911:
&lt;blockquote&gt; The wind was rising at the start of the contest, and Le Martin, who was one of the most experienced aviators in France, rocked about a good deal as his machine left the ground and swept across the field. His aeroplane had reached the woods, a quarter of a mile beyond the barriers, when it was observed to pitch swiftly downward and into the trees. Le Martin was using a biplane, ''[sic]'' which was broken badly as it fell at the foot of an oak tree. A corner of the motor struck Le Martin's head, crushing his skull, and his right leg was also broken in two places. The aviator was barely alive when he was taken away by Red Cross surgeons, whose stations surrounded the field. The crowds removed their hats as the wounded aviator was carried past, or as word passed among the people that he was dead. Le Martin was alive when he reached the hospital, but expired a few minutes afterwards.&lt;ref name="NYT June 19, 1911"/&gt; &lt;/blockquote&gt;

Soon after the crash, Madame Bleriot arrived at the site. [[Ernest Monis]] the [[Prime Minister of France]], who was a spectator, sent his doctor, but Lemartin died on arrival at the hospital ''Saint-Antoine'' in Vincennes.&lt;ref name="NYT June 19, 1911"/&gt; Coincidentally, two other pilots in the race were killed in separate accidents on the same day.

Despite his brief career, Lemartin is considered one of the pioneers of French aviation. He was the 59th aviation pioneer to die.&lt;ref name="OlivierD"&gt;[http://www.universud.fr/Images/Lemartin-BDC%20-%20copie.pdf ''Léon Lemartin, Chef-Pilote de la Maison Blériot'' by Jacques and Olivier Dalmon, Published 2009, Universud, L’Etoile B1, Marseille]&lt;/ref&gt;

Lemartin is buried at Dunes (Tarn-et-Garonne), where both a street and the airport (Piste Théodore Léon Lemartin) bear his name.{{coord|44.108840|0.773500|}}&lt;ref name="OlivierD"/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.aerosteles.net/fiche.php?code=dunes-lemartin&amp;type=ps&amp;lang=en Piste Théodore Léon Lemartin at Dunes airport]&lt;/ref&gt;

His widow Madeleine, who received an insurance allocation of 32,500 francs, continued to raise his three children, Louise, Simone and Léone, plus Jane de Lambert.&lt;ref&gt;[http://cdg.pagesperso-orange.fr/CDG15012009.html CDG 1911 Airshow essay]&lt;/ref&gt; Madeleine subsequently married Léon's brother Albert and they had two more children, Maurice and Roger.&lt;ref name="Patri"/&gt;

Lemartin's only grandson, Jacques Dalmon, wrote his grandfather's biography in 1994 (''Lemartin, pilote-aviateur''). He also published a new revision in 2009 in co-operation with Lemartin's great grandson, Olivier Dalmon (''Léon Lemartin, Chef-Pilote de la Maison Blériot'').&lt;ref name="OlivierD"/&gt;

==See also==
*[[List of fatalities from aviation accidents]]

==References==
{{Reflist|2}}

=== Other sources ===
*Jacques Dalmon, ''Lemartin, pilote-aviateur '', Universud Editeur , 1994.
*Jacques &amp; Olivier Dalmon, '' Lemartin, Chef-Pilote de la Maison Blériot '', Universud Editeur, 2009.
*Presse Parisienne, Française et Internationale 1910–1911 : [[L'Illustration]], Le Matin, L'Excelsior, l'Indépendant, [[La Vie au Grand Air]]...

{{Aviators killed in early aviation accidents}}
{{Authority control}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Lemartin, Leon}}
[[Category:1883 births]]
[[Category:1911 deaths]]
[[Category:French aviators]]
[[Category:Aviation history of France]]
[[Category:Aviation pioneers]]
[[Category:Members of the Early Birds of Aviation]]
[[Category:French aerospace engineers]]
[[Category:Victims of aviation accidents or incidents in France]]
[[Category:Accidental deaths in France]]
[[Category:French aviation record holders]]</text>
      <sha1>d8iha8cz605tjgnmqepefx2ota3cndi</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
