<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10.xsd" version="0.10" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <dbname>enwiki</dbname>
    <base>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.32.0-wmf.16</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="118" case="first-letter">Draft</namespace>
      <namespace key="119" case="first-letter">Draft talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2300" case="first-letter">Gadget</namespace>
      <namespace key="2301" case="first-letter">Gadget talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2302" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition</namespace>
      <namespace key="2303" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Prince Bernhard of Lippe-Biesterfeld</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>22396008</id>
    <revision>
      <id>855984111</id>
      <parentid>854985163</parentid>
      <timestamp>2018-08-22T04:30:08Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <ip>203.145.94.119</ip>
      </contributor>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="63999">{{more citations needed|date=June 2017}}
{{For|his father|Prince Bernhard of Lippe (1872–1934)}}
{{Infobox royalty|consort=yes
| name         = Prince Bernhard
| image        = Bernhard of Lippe-Biesterfeld 1976.jpg
| alt          = Bernhard of the Netherlands
| caption      = Prince Bernhard wearing his trademark [[carnation]], 1976
| succession   = [[List of Dutch consorts|Prince consort of the Netherlands]]
| moretext     = 
| reign        = 6 September 1948 – {{nowr|30 April 1980}}
| predecessor  = [[Henry of Mecklenburg-Schwerin]]
| successor    = [[Claus van Amsberg]]
| spouse       = {{ubl|[[Queen Juliana]]|{{marriage|1937|2004|reason=died}}}}
| issue        = {{ubl|[[Queen Beatrix]]
                      |[[Princess Irene of the Netherlands|Princess Irene]]
                      |[[Princess Margriet]]
                      |[[Princess Christina of the Netherlands|Princess Christina]]}}
| issue-link   = #Marriage and children
| issue-pipe   = among others…
| full name    = Bernhard Leopold Frederik Everhard Julius Coert Karel Godfried Pieter
| house        = [[House of Lippe|Lippe]]
| father       = [[Prince Bernhard of Lippe (1872–1934)|Prince Bernhard of Lippe]]
| mother       = [[Armgard von Cramm]]
| birth_date   = {{dob|dy=y|1911|06|29}}
| birth_place  = [[Jena]], [[Grand Duchy of Saxe-Weimar-Eisenach|Saxe-Weimar-Eisenach]]
| death_date   = {{dob|dy=y|2004|12|01|1911|06|29}}
| death_place  = [[University Medical Center Utrecht]], [[Utrecht]], Netherlands
| burial_date  = 11 December 2004
| burial_place = [[Nieuwe Kerk (Delft)|Nieuwe Kerk]], [[Delft]], Netherlands
| occupation   = [[Officer (armed forces)|Military officer]], [[aviator]], [[Conservation movement|conservationist]], [[Board of directors|nonprofit director]]
| signature    = Bernhard of Lippe-Biesterfeld Signature.jpg
| religion     = {{ubl|[[Church of Lippe]] (until 1937)|[[Dutch Reformed Church]]}}
}}

'''Prince Bernhard of Lippe-Biesterfeld''' (later '''Prince Bernhard of the Netherlands'''; [[German language|German]]: ''Bernhard Friedrich Eberhard Leopold Julius Kurt Carl Gottfried Peter Graf von Biesterfeld''; 29 June 1911 – 1 December 2004) was a German-born prince who was the [[prince consort|consort]] of [[Juliana of the Netherlands|Queen Juliana of the Netherlands]]; they were the parents of four children, including the former Queen of the Netherlands, [[Beatrix of the Netherlands|Princess Beatrix]].

He belonged to the princely [[House of Lippe]] and was a nephew of the [[Principality of Lippe]]'s last sovereign [[Leopold IV, Prince of Lippe|Leopold IV]]. From birth he held the title Count of Biesterfeld; his uncle raised him to princely rank with the [[style (manner of address)|style]] of [[Serene Highness]] in 1916. He studied law and worked as an executive secretary at the [[Paris]] office of [[IG Farben]]. In 1937 he married Princess Juliana of the Netherlands, and was immediately given the title Prince of the Netherlands with the style of [[Royal Highness]]. Upon his wife's accession to the throne he became the prince consort of the Netherlands in 1948.

Although his private life was rather controversial, he was still generally regarded as a charming and popular figure by the majority of the Dutch for his performance as a combat pilot and his activities as a liaison officer and personal aide to the Queen during [[World War II]] and for his work during post-war reconstruction. During World War II he was part of the London-based Allied war planning councils and saw active service as a [[Wing Commander (rank)|Wing Commander]] ([[RAF]]) flying both fighter and bomber planes into combat. He was a Dutch [[General officer|general]] and Supreme Commander of the Dutch Armed forces, involved in negotiating the terms of surrender of the German Army in the Netherlands. For proven bravery, leadership and loyalty during his wartime efforts he was appointed a Commander of the [[Military William Order]], the Netherlands' oldest and highest honour. After the war he was also made Honorary [[Air Marshal]] of the [[Royal Air Force]] by Queen [[Elizabeth II]] of the United Kingdom. In 1969, Bernhard was awarded the Grand Cross (Special Class) of the [[Order of Merit of the Federal Republic of Germany]].

Bernhard helped found the [[World Wildlife Fund]] (later renamed [[World Wide Fund for Nature]]), becoming its first President in 1961, and in 1970 establishing the WWF's [[financial endowment]] "[[The 1001: A Nature Trust]]". In 1954, he was a co-founder of the international [[Bilderberg Group]], which has met annually since then to discuss corporate globalization and other issues concerning Europe and North America. He was forced to step down from both groups after being involved in the [[Lockheed bribery scandals|Lockheed Bribery Scandal]].

== Early life ==
Bernhard was born Bernhard Leopold Friedrich Eberhard Julius Kurt Karl Gottfried Peter, Count of Biesterfeld in [[Jena]], [[Saxe-Weimar-Eisenach]], [[German Empire]] on 29 June 1911, the elder son of [[Prince Bernhard of Lippe (1872–1934)|Prince Bernhard of Lippe]] and his wife, [[Armgard von Cramm]]. He was a grandson of [[Ernest, Count of Lippe-Biesterfeld]], who was [[regent]] of the [[Principality of Lippe]] until 1904. He was also a nephew of the principality's last sovereign [[Leopold IV, Prince of Lippe]].

Because his parents marriage did not properly conform with the marriage laws of the House of Lippe, it was initially deemed [[morganatic marriage|morganatic]], so Bernhard was only granted the title of "Count of Biesterfeld" at birth. He and his brother could only succeed to the Lippian throne if the entire reigning House became extinct. In 1916, his uncle Leopold IV as reigning Prince raised Bernhard and his mother to Prince and Princess of Lippe-Biesterfeld, thereby retroactively according his parents' marriage dynastic status. The suffix Biesterfeld was revived to mark the beginning of a new [[cadet line]] of the [[House of Lippe]].&lt;ref&gt;Jean-Fred Tourtchine, 'Généalogie et état présent des familles princières de Lippe-Biesterfeld (princes souverains de Lippe) et de Lippe-Weissenfeld', in: ''L'ordre de la noblesse. Familles d'Europe enregistrées in ordine nobilitatis en 1983-1984. Volume sixième 1983-194''. [Paris, 1985], p. CCLVXXXVI.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Zijl, Annejet van der, ''Bernhard, een verborgen geschiedenis'' pp 45 en 87"p 45 ...bood Leopold aan Armgard de oude graventitel van de Biesterfelders toe te kennen – zij het met het laagadellijke 'von' in plaats van het hoogadellijke 'zur'. Deze nieuwe Biesterfelderlijn zou wel meetellen in de erfopvolging, maar in lijn moeten aansluiten achter de overige zijtakken." "p 87 ....kende hij in dit ene en hoogst uitzonderlijke geval ..... alsnog de prinselijke titel 'zur Lippe-Biesterfeld' toe ... en zijn familielijn maakte een flinke sprong vooruit in de erfopvolging."&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Prinses Armgard verkreeg in 1909 voor haar en haar nakomelingen de titel Gravin (Graaf) van Biesterfeld en in 1916 bij decreet van de laatste regerende vorst van Lippe. Leopold IV die van Prinses (Prins) van Lippe-Biesterfeld. Hierdoor werd de nieuwe Biesterfeldse linie gesticht, die in de rij van hen die tot troonopvolging in Lippe gerechtigd zijn, vóór die van het Lippe-Weissenfeldse vorstelijk huis gaan ''Gedenkalbum uitgegeven bij het koperen huwelijksfeest van het Koninklijk echtpaar door de NV drukkerij De Spaarnestad Haarlem voor de abonnees van haar periodieken, 1949 p. 12.''&lt;/ref&gt;

After [[World War I]], Bernhard's family lost their German [[Principality]] and the [[revenue]] that had accompanied it. But the family was still reasonably well-off and Bernhard spent his early years at Castle Reckenwalde, the family's new [[estate (house)|estate]] in [[East Brandenburg]] thirty kilometers east of the River [[Oder]], (now the village of [[Wojnowo, Lubusz Voivodeship]] in [[Poland]]), near the city of Züllichau ([[Sulechów]]). He received his early education at home. When he was twelve, he was sent to [[boarding school|board]] at the [[gymnasium (school)|''Gymnasium'']] in Züllichau and several years later to board at a Gymnasium in [[Berlin]], from which he [[graduation|graduated]] in 1929.

Bernhard suffered from poor health as a boy. Doctors predicted that he would not live very long. This prediction might have been the key to Bernhard's reckless driving and the risks that he took in the Second World War and thereafter. The prince wrecked several cars and planes in his lifetime.

Bernhard studied [[law]] at the [[University of Lausanne]], [[Switzerland]] and in Berlin, where he acquired a taste for fast [[automobile|car]]s, [[horse riding]], and big-game [[hunting]] [[safari]]s. He was nearly killed in a [[boat]]ing accident and an [[airplane]] crash, and he suffered a broken neck and crushed ribs in a 160&amp;nbsp;km/h (100 [[miles per hour|mph]]) [[car crash]] in 1938.

While at university, Bernhard joined the [[Nazi Party]]. He also enrolled in the [[Sturmabteilung]] (SA), which he left in December 1934 when he graduated and went to work for [[IG Farben]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|last=Waterfield|first=Bruno|title=Dutch Prince Bernhard 'was member of Nazi party'|url=https://www.telegraph.co.uk/news/worldnews/europe/netherlands/7377402/Dutch-Prince-Bernhard-was-member-of-Nazi-party.html|accessdate=13 June 2011|newspaper=The Telegraph|date=5 March 2010|location=London}}&lt;/ref&gt; The Prince later denied that he had belonged to SA, to the [[Reiter-SS]] (SS Cavalry Corps), and to the [[National Socialist Motor Corps|NSKK]], but these are well-documented memberships. Nevertheless, while he was not a fierce champion of democracy, the Prince was never known to hold any [[Political radicalism|radical]] political views or express any [[racism|racist]] sentiments, even though he admitted that he briefly had sympathised with Adolf Hitler's regime.&lt;ref&gt;[https://www.telegraph.co.uk/news/worldnews/europe/netherlands/7377402/Dutch-Prince-Bernhard-was-member-of-Nazi-party.html Dutch Prince Bernhard 'was member of Nazi party' --The Telegraph]&lt;/ref&gt; 

The Prince eventually went to work for the German chemical giant IG Farben, then the world's fourth-largest company (which survives today as [[BASF]], [[Agfa-Gevaert|AGFA]], and [[Bayer]]). He lodged with the exiled Russian nobleman Count Pavel Kotzbue and his wife the American-born [[Allene Tew]]. After training, Bernhard became [[secretary]] to the [[board of directors]] at the [[Paris]] office in 1935.

== Marriage and children==
[[File:Engagement Juliana Bernhard.jpg|thumb|left|220px|Princess Juliana and Prince Bernhard celebrate their engagement in [[Amsterdam]] on 8 September 1936.]]
[[File:JulianaBernhard1937.jpg|thumb|left|220px|Princess Juliana and Prince Bernhard 1937 wedding]]
Bernhard met then-Princess Juliana at the [[1936 Winter Olympics]] at [[Garmisch-Partenkirchen]]. Juliana's mother, [[Wilhelmina of the Netherlands|Queen Wilhelmina]], had spent most of the 1930s looking for a suitable husband for Juliana.  As a [[Protestant]] of royal rank (the [[Lippe]]s were a sovereign house in the German Empire), Bernhard was acceptable for the devoutly religious Wilhelmina. Wilhelmina left nothing to chance, and had her lawyers draft a very detailed [[prenuptial agreement]] that specified exactly what Bernhard could and could not do. The couple's engagement was announced on 8 September 1936, and they were married at [[The Hague]] on 7 January 1937. Earlier, Bernhard had been granted Dutch citizenship, and changed the spelling of his names from German to Dutch. Previously styled as Serene Highness, he became a Royal Highness by Dutch Law. His appropriateness as consort of the future Queen would later become a matter of some public debate.

Prince Bernhard was father of six children, four of them with Queen Juliana. The eldest daughter is [[Beatrix of the Netherlands|Princess Beatrix]], former Queen of the Netherlands, (1938). His other daughters with Juliana are [[Princess Irene of the Netherlands|Irene]] (1939), [[Princess Margriet of the Netherlands|Margriet]] (1943) and [[Princess Christina of the Netherlands|Christina]] (1947).

[[File:Princess Juliana and family 1942.jpg|thumb|right|220px|Princess Juliana and Prince Bernhard with their oldest daughters [[Beatrix of the Netherlands|Princess Beatrix]] and [[Princess Irene of the Netherlands|Princess Irene]] in [[Ottawa]] on 4 May 1942.]]
[[File:Prince Bernhard 1942.jpg|thumb|right|220px|Prince Bernhard in [[Ottawa]] on 6 May 1942.]]

He had two illegitimate daughters. The first is Alicia von Bielefeld (born 21 June 1952), whose mother has not been identified. She is a [[landscape architect]] and lives in the [[United States]]. Prince Bernhard's sixth daughter, Alexia Grinda (a.k.a. Alexia Lejeune or Alexia Grinda-Lejeune, born in [[Paris]] on 10 July 1967), is his child by the French [[socialite]] and [[fashion model]] Hélène Grinda.&lt;ref&gt;Hélène Grinda: born in 1944, wife of Stanislas, 6e Baron Lejeune (1945–1998), son of Edgard-Louis, 5e Baron Lejeune (born 1915), and wife Claude de Bonardi du Mesnil (1914–1967), by whom she has a son Cyril, 7e Baron Lejeune, born 1972, and daughter of Jean-Paul Grinda (1900–1975) and wife Françoise Blason&lt;/ref&gt; Although rumours about these two children had already spread, it was made official after his death. In December 2008, Dutch historian Cees Fasseur claimed that former British Conservative Cabinet Minister [[Jonathan Aitken]] was the result of a wartime affair between Prince Bernhard and Aitken's mother, previously [[Penelope, Lady Aitken|Penelope Maffey]].&lt;ref name=theweek&gt;{{cite web|title=Jonathan Aitken is of 'royal blood'|url=http://www.theweek.co.uk/people/40659/jonathan-aitken-%E2%80%98royal-blood%E2%80%99|website=theweek.co.uk|publisher=[[Michael Wolfe]]|accessdate=21 November 2014}}&lt;/ref&gt;

== Attitudes to Nazi Germany ==
Prince Bernhard was a member of the "Reiter-SS", a mounted unit of the [[Schutzstaffel|SS]] and joined the [[Nazi party]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.uni-muenster.de/NiederlandeNet/nl-wissen/monarchie/personen/bernhard.html|title=NiederlandeNet – Monarchie - Personen A-Z -  Prinz Bernhard|author=Westfälische Wilhelms-Universität Münster, NiederlandeNet|date=23 March 2011|publisher=}}&lt;/ref&gt; He later also joined the [[National Socialist Motor Corps]].

Various members of his family and friends were aligned with the Nazis prior to the Second World War, a number of whom attended the royal wedding. Protocol demanded that the prospective Prince-Consort be invited to an audience with his head of state, who at the time was Adolf Hitler. Hitler himself gives an account of the conversation he had with Bernhard in his ''Tischgespräche'' (''Table Conversations''). ''Table Conversations'' was a collection of monologues, remarks, and speeches Hitler gave during lunch or dinner to those invited to the table by him. Bernhard himself called Hitler a tyrant in a public speech on the [[BBC]] on 25 June 1940 after France fell to Germany.{{Citation needed|date=June 2011}}

The Prince's brother, Prince Aschwin of Lippe-Biesterfeld, was an officer in the German Army. Although the secret services on both sides were interested in this peculiar pair of brothers, no improper contacts or leaks of information were ever discovered. The Prince proved himself to be a loyal Dutch citizen and officer. He cut off relations with those members of his family who were enthusiastic Nazis. As a sign of his "Dutchness" he spoke only [[Dutch language|Dutch]] when negotiating the surrender of German forces in the Netherlands. The Prince was known to be very fond of smart uniforms and medals. He made a point of wearing his medals in the English court style, even though members of the Dutch armed forces wear their medals in the Prussian style.{{Citation needed|date=July 2010}}

The Prince's mother was no admirer of the Nazis and got into trouble for refusing to hoist the [[swastika]] flag on her country seat at Reckenwalde.{{Citation needed|date=May 2015}}

[[File:The British Army in North-west Europe 1944-45 BU766.jpg|thumb|right|220px|General [[Brian Horrocks]], Field Marshal [[Bernard Montgomery, 1st Viscount Montgomery of Alamein|Bernard Montgomery]] and Prince Bernhard before [[Operation Market Garden]] on 8 September 1944.]]
[[File:Juliana, Truman.jpg|thumb|right|220px|Queen Juliana and Prince Bernhard with President of the United States [[Harry S. Truman]] and First Lady [[Bess Truman]] at [[Ronald Reagan Washington National Airport|Washington National Airport]] on 2 April 1952.]]

==Second World War==
Prince Bernhard began to make himself popular in the eyes of the Dutch people at the outset of the [[World War II|Second World War]]. During the German invasion of the Netherlands, the Prince, carrying a machine gun, organised the palace guards into a combat group and shot at German warplanes. The Royal family fled the Netherlands and took refuge in [[England]]. In disagreement with Queen Wilhelmina's decision to leave the Kingdom, the young Prince Consort, aged 28, is said at first to have refused to go and to have wanted to oppose the Nazi occupation from within the country. However, in the end he agreed to join his wife and become head of the Royal Military Mission based in London. Once safely there, his wife Princess Juliana and their children went on to [[Canada]], where they remained until the end of the war.

In England, Prince Bernhard asked to work in British [[Intelligence (information gathering)|Intelligence]] but the War [[Admiralty]], and later [[Dwight Eisenhower|General Eisenhower's]] Allied Command offices, did not trust him sufficiently to allow him access to sensitive intelligence information. However, on the recommendation of Bernhard's friend and admirer [[George VI of the United Kingdom|King George VI]], who was also of German aristocratic descent through his mother [[Mary of Teck]] and his great-grandfather [[Prince Albert of Saxe-Coburg and Gotha|Prince Albert]], and after being personally screened by intelligence officer [[Ian Fleming]] at the behest of [[Winston Churchill|Churchill]], he was later given work to do in the [[Allies of World War II|Allied]] War Planning Councils.

&lt;blockquote&gt;''"For Bernhard, the Prince of the Netherlands, the war was a frustrating business. Born a German, he had married Queen Wilhelmina's only child, Princess Juliana, and in due time made a conscious and meaningful transition of loyalties to his new homeland. Because of this, and in view of the doubts his background initially evoked among some Britons, he longed more than anyone for a chance to get at Holland's aggressors."'' [[Erik Hazelhoff Roelfzema]] aka [[Soldier of Orange]], decorated war hero.&lt;ref&gt;Hazelhoff, Erik ''[[Soldier of Orange]]'' (The Holland Heritage Society, New York, 1980) {{ISBN|0-943010-00-4}} P.190&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

On 25 June 1940, three days after France fell to the German war machine, Bernhard spoke on the Overseas Service of the BBC, calling Hitler a German tyrant and expressing his confidence that Great Britain would defeat the [[Third Reich]].

In 1940, Flight Lieutenant Murray Payne gave the Prince instruction in flying a [[Supermarine Spitfire|Spitfire]]. The Prince made 1,000 flight-hours in a Spitfire with the RAF's [[No. 322 (Dutch) Squadron RAF]], wrecking two planes during landings. He remained an active pilot throughout his life and flew his last airplane 53 years later, with his grandson and heir to the throne, who inherited his passion for flying.

In 1941, Prince Bernhard was given the honorary rank of [[Wing Commander (rank)|wing commander]] in the [[Royal Air Force]]. As "Wing Commander Gibbs (RAF)", Prince Bernhard flew over occupied Europe, attacking [[V-1 (flying bomb)|V-1]] launch pads in a [[B-24 Liberator]], bombing [[Pisa]] and engaging submarines over the Atlantic in a [[B-25 Mitchell]] and conducting reconnaissance over enemy-held territory in an [[L-5 Grasshopper]]. Prince Bernhard was awarded the Dutch [[Airman's Cross]] for his "ability and perseverance" (Dutch: "bekwaamheid en volharding").&lt;ref&gt;Source: Interview with the Prince, 1993, Henny Meyer, published in "Het Vliegerskruis" (1997)&lt;/ref&gt; In 1941 he also received a promotion to [[Honorary Air Commodore]].&lt;ref name="Memoriam"&gt;[https://web.archive.org/web/20150919040047/http://www.koninklijkhuis.nl/encyclopedie/wie-is-wie/in-memoriam/bernhard-prins-der-nederlanden-(1911-2004)/ In memoriam: Bernhard Prins der Nederlanden (1911-2004)], ''koninklijkhuis''&lt;/ref&gt;

He also helped organised the Dutch resistance movement and acted as personal secretary for Queen Wilhelmina.

Queen Wilhelmina erased the style "honorary" (the exact words were "[[à la suite]]") in the decree promoting Bernhard to General. In this unconstitutional manner, she gave this Royal Prince a status that was never intended by either Parliament or her Ministers. The Minister of Defence did not choose to correct the Monarch and the Prince took an active and important role in the Dutch Armed forces.

By 1944, Prince Bernhard became Commander of the Dutch Armed Forces. After the liberation of the Netherlands, he returned with his family and became active in the negotiations for the German surrender. He was present during the [[Armistice]] negotiations and German surrender at [[Hotel de Wereld]] ("''The World Hotel''"), [[Wageningen]] in The Netherlands on 5 May 1945, where he avoided speaking German.&lt;ref&gt;[http://cgi.omroep.nl/cgi-bin/streams?/tv/vpro/GE/sb.hoteldewereld.asf?title=HOTEL DE WERELD – herdenking en interview met Prins Bernhard 35 jaar na de bevrijding]. Video footage of 1980 commemoration of the German capitulation at "Hotel de Wereld" in Wageningen, opening speech by the Prime Minister, and interview with Prince Bernhard. (Dutch)&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://cgi.omroep.nl/cgi-bin/streams?/tv/vpro/GE/bb.capitulatiebesprekingen.asf?title=CAPITULATIEBESPREKINGEN TE WAGENINGEN Historic video footage (black and white, no audio)].&lt;/ref&gt;
The Prince was a genuine war hero in the eyes of most of the Dutch and even kept cordial relations with the Communists who fought against the Nazis. In the post-war years he earned respect for his work in helping to reinvigorate the economy of the Netherlands.

[[File:Aankomst van Prins Bernhard op Schiphol vanuit Zuid Amerika , Prins Bernhard tij, Bestanddeelnr 910-7969.jpg|thumb|left|220px|Prince Bernhard at [[Amsterdam Airport Schiphol]] on 4 November 1959.]]
[[File:Bloemendefile voor koningin Juliana op Paleis Soestdijk , koppen van Prinses Bea, Bestanddeelnr 911-2041.jpg|thumb|left|220px|Queen Juliana and Prince Bernhard at [[Soestdijk Palace]] on 30 April 1960.]]
[[File:Prince-Bernhard-Shah of Persia-Queen Farah-1970.jpg|thumb|right|220px|Prince Bernhard with Shah of Iran [[Mohammad Reza Pahlavi]] and Queen [[Farah Pahlavi]] in [[Tehran]] on 1 February 1970.]]
[[File:Den Haag; v.l.n.r. Prins Bernhard, President Soeharto, mevrouw Soeharto, koningin Juliana.jpg|thumb|right|220px|Prince Bernhard and Queen Juliana with President of Indonesia [[Suharto]] and First Lady [[Siti Hartinah]] at [[Soestdijk Palace]] during a state visit on 3 September 1970.]]
[[File:Prince Bernhard and Mobutu Sese Seko 1973.jpg|thumb|right|220px|Prince Bernhard and President of Zaire [[Mobutu Sese Seko]] in [[Kinshasa]] 12 August 1973.]]
[[File:Dalai Lama en Prins Bernhard (1973).jpg|thumb|right|220px|Prince Bernhard and the [[14th Dalai Lama]] at [[Soestdijk Palace]] 9 October 1973.]]
[[File:SFA004000743.jpg|thumb|right|220px|Queen Juliana and Prince Bernhard returning from [[Porto Ercole]], [[Italy]] due to developments in the Lockheed scandal on 26 August 1976.]]

== Postwar roles ==
After the War, the position of Inspector General was created for the Prince.

He was made a member of the boards of supervisors of [[Fokker]] Aircraft and [[KLM|KLM Royal Dutch Airlines]], and within a few years he had been invited to serve as an adviser or non-executive director of numerous corporations and institutions. There have been claims about KLM helping Nazis to leave Germany for Argentina on KLM flights while Bernhard was on its board.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news| url=http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/europe/6635677.stm | work=BBC News | title=KLM accused of helping Nazis flee | date=8 May 2007}}&lt;/ref&gt; After a 1952 trip with Queen Juliana to the [[United States]], Prince Bernhard was heralded by the media as a business ambassador ''extraordinaire'' for the Netherlands.&lt;ref&gt;[http://cgi.omroep.nl/cgi-bin/streams?/ibg/sn215009-bb.wmv?title=KONINKLIJK BEZOEK AAN DE VERENIGDE STATEN]. Historic video footage of the Royal visit to the USA.&lt;/ref&gt;

With his global contacts, Bernhard in May 1954, was a key figure in organising a meeting at the Bilderberg Hotel in the Netherlands for the business elite and intellectuals of the Western World to discuss the economic problems in the face of what they characterized as the growing threat from [[Communism]]. This first meeting was successful, and it became an annual gathering known as the [[Bilderberg Group]]. The idea for the [[European Union]], first proposed by [[Robert Schuman]] on 9 May 1950, was encouraged at Bilderberg.

Prince Bernhard was a very outspoken person who often flouted protocol by remarking upon subjects about which he felt deeply. Almost until his last day he called for more recognition for the Polish veterans of the Second World War who had figured greatly in the liberation of the Netherlands, but only after his death did the Dutch Government decide to publicly recognize the important role of the Polish Army in the liberation:{{Citation needed|date=June 2009}} on 31 May 2006, at the Binnenhof in The Hague, [[Queen Beatrix]] conferred the [[Military William Order]], the highest Dutch military decoration, on the [[Polish 1st Independent Parachute Brigade]].

== Friendships and International connections ==
Prince Bernhard was seen as a jet-setting and charismatic ambassador for the Dutch during post-war reconstruction.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/europe/4060449.stm|title=Netherlands' Prince Bernhard dies|date=2 December 2004|work=BBC News|accessdate=3 May 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.terradaily.com/2004/041201205040.eqgwyyfr.html|title=Outspoken Dutch Prince Bernhard always in the public eye|date=1 December 2004|work=TerraDaily|accessdate=3 May 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt; Because of his connections Prince Bernhard reportedly maintained friendships with several high-profiled international figures, some of this verified friendships included: [[Nelson Mandela]],&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.peaceparks.nl/images/pictures/ocetznchjrfrirjw4d6c923410409.jpg|title=Peace Parks Foundation|date=1997|work=Peace Parks|accessdate=3 May 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.telegraaf.nl/buitenland/article21437093.ece/binary/i/11.jpg|title=Leven Mandela in foto's|date=5 December 2013|work=Telegraaf|accessdate=3 May 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.earthtouchnews.com/conservation/human-impact/an-earth-touch-tribute-to-former-president-nelson-mandela|title=AN EARTH TOUCH TRIBUTE TO FORMER PRESIDENT NELSON MANDELA|date=6 December 2013|work=EarthTouch|accessdate=3 May 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.nd.nl/nieuws/buitenland/prins-bernhard-en-mandela-openen-wildpark.90819.lynkx|title=Prins Bernhard en Mandela openen wildpark|date=29 August 2003|work=NederlandsDagblad|accessdate=3 May 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[David Rockefeller]],&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.telegraph.co.uk/news/politics/7804197/The-Bilderberg-Group-fact-and-fantasy.html|title=The Bilderberg Group: fact and fantasy|date=4 Jun 2010|work=The Daily Telegraph|accessdate=3 May 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=eYIvYH0q8_E|title=Opening Words at 1st ever Bilderberg meeting|date=29 May 1954|work=YouTube|accessdate=3 May 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.npogeschiedenis.nl/nieuws/2013/juni/Bilderberg-geschiedenis-conferentie-bernhard.html|title=Het geheim van de Bilderberg-conferenties|date=6 June 2013|work=NPO|accessdate=3 May 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[Mohammad Reza Pahlavi]],&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://nos.nl/artikel/2079325-tweelingzus-laatste-sjah-van-iran-overleden.html|title=Tweelingzus laatste sjah van Iran overleden|date=8 January 2016|work=NOS|accessdate=3 May 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://gpdhome.typepad.com/nieuwsberichten/2012/05/reza-pahlavi-te-gast-in-den-haag.html|title=Reza Pahlavi te gast in Den Haag|date=30 May 2012|work=Royalblog.nl|accessdate=3 May 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[Ian Fleming]],&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.theaustralian.com.au/arts/books/stephen-dandocollins-wwii-dutch-airlift-manna-from-heaven/news-story/2bde05f411cdeb3bcddc0eb6427e162a|title=Stephen Dando-Collins: WWII Dutch airlift manna from heaven|date=23 May 2015|work=The Australian|accessdate=6 May 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.nrc.nl/handelsblad/2008/02/02/prins-bernhard-ontmoet-ian-fleming-11486197|title=PRINS BERNHARD ONTMOET IAN FLEMING|date=2 February 2008|work=NRC Handelsblad|accessdate=6 May 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.rnw.org/archive/james-bond-was-dutch|title=James Bond was Dutch|date=4 April 2012|work=RNW Media Handelsblad|accessdate=6 May 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[Walter Bedell Smith]]&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.groene.nl/artikel/het-correggio-mysterie|title=Het Correggio-mysterie|date=10 January 2004|work=Groene Amsterdamer|accessdate=11 June 2018}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://politiek.tpo.nl/2013/11/25/prins-bernhard-nog-flink-kan-gaan-spoken/|title=Hoe prins Bernhard nog flink kan gaan spoken|date=25 November 2013|work=ThePost|accessdate=11 June 2018}}&lt;/ref&gt;

== Scandals and insinuations ==
=== The ''Hofmans'' Affair ===
In the middle of the 1950s, Prince Bernhard was involved in what some considered a personal vendetta against [[Greet Hofmans]], a [[faith healer]] and layer-on of hands. For nine years she was a friend and adviser of Queen Juliana, often residing at Palace Soestdijk. Originally, Hofmans was introduced to Queen Juliana on the initiative of Prince Bernhard in 1948 to treat the eye sickness of Princess Marijke Christina. This illness arose because Juliana was infected with [[rubella]] during pregnancy. Hofmans developed a great influence on the Queen, encouraging pacifist ideas. In the period of the [[Cold War]] this caused a crisis in the Royal Household. Reputedly it reached the point where it threatened the marriage of Juliana and Bernhard.

Outside the Netherlands, a great deal was written about the Hofmans affair. On 13 June 1956, an article appeared in the German magazine ''[[Der Spiegel]]'' with the title "''Zwischen Königin und [[Rasputin]]''" – "between the Queen and her Rasputin", which painted a less-than-flattering picture of Hofmans. Later, Bernhard admitted that he personally provided the information for the article. It is thought that by doing this he hoped to have Hofmans removed from the court. The Prime Minister, [[Willem Drees]], had to act and appointed a committee of "three wise men" (elder statesmen) to advise the royal couple. The Prince got what he wanted; Hofmans was banished, and various friends and supporters of the Queen in the Royal Household had to give up their office.

In 2008 the report of the "three wise men" has been made public and forms part of the book ''Juliana &amp; Bernhard'' by historian Fasseur, who was also granted access to the private royal archive by the Queen. Bernhard was reprimanded for leaking confidential information to the international press, but although both Juliana and Princess Wilhelmina (the former Queen) mention their fear of a "German putsch" (i.e. Juliana's abdication followed by Bernhard's rule on behalf of their adolescent oldest daughter and successor to the throne) Juliana was forced to break all relations with Hofmans.

The book attempts to rehabilitate Bernhard, describing how the Prince only resorted to bringing in the international press after repeated, desperate and often dramatic pleading with his wife to distance herself from the Hofmans clan. Fasseur said: "Bernard was obviously a free spirited chap, who independently went about his business. But he was still very much a family man. I got the feeling he was the only one that was seeing things were getting completely out of hand and tried to salvage the situation as much as he could."&lt;ref&gt;{{nl icon}} [http://www.volkskrant.nl/binnenland/article1090514.ece/Brief_Bernhard_aan_Juliana Interview (Dutch) with historian Fasseur]. Volkskrant.nl. 12 November 2008&lt;/ref&gt;

The royal family did not edit the book, nor did they have a preview before its printing. But after reading it they endorsed its accounts of the developments that led to Hofmans's dismissal.

=== The Lockheed scandal ===
Scandal rocked the Royal Family in 1976 when it was revealed that Prince Bernhard had accepted a US$1.1 million [[bribe]] from U.S. aircraft manufacturer [[Lockheed Corporation]] to influence the Dutch Government's purchase of [[F-104 Starfighter|fighter aircraft]]. At the time he had served on more than 300 corporate boards and committees worldwide and had been praised in the Netherlands for his efforts to promote the economic well-being of the country. [[Prime Minister of the Netherlands]] [[Joop den Uyl]] ordered an inquiry into the [[Lockheed bribery scandal|Lockheed affair]], while Prince Bernhard refused to answer reporters' questions, stating: "I am above such things".&lt;ref&gt;Browne, Anthony (4 December 2004) [http://www.timesonline.co.uk/article/0,,3-1387624,00.html From beyond the grave, Prince finally admits taking $1m bribe]. Timesonline.co.uk. Retrieved on 23 April 2014.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="Telegraph"&gt;{{cite news|url=https://www.telegraph.co.uk/news/obituaries/1478171/HRH-Prince-Bernhard-of-the-Netherlands.html|title=HRH Prince Bernhard of the Netherlands|date=4 December 2004|work=[[The Daily Telegraph]]|accessdate=4 February 2018}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The Dutch and international press headlined the stories for months, providing records of Prince Bernhard's Reiter SS membership and details of his numerous extramarital affairs, including the purchase of a luxurious [[Paris]] apartment for his [[Mistress (lover)|mistress]] [[Hélène Grinda]], with whom he had an [[illegitimate]] daughter, Alexia. (Bernhard also had a second illegitimate daughter, Alicia, in the US.)

On 26 August 1976, a toned-down, but nonetheless devastating, report on Prince Bernhard's activities was released to a shocked Dutch public. The Prince's own letter of 1974, to Lockheed Corporation, demanding "commissions" be paid to him on Dutch Government aircraft purchases was very damaging evidence of improper conduct by the Inspector-General of the Dutch Armed Forces. Criminal charges were not pressed by the Government out of respect for [[Queen Juliana]], whose later abdication was tacitly understood to be directly related to her husband's conduct.&lt;ref name="Telegraph"/&gt;

Prince Bernhard resigned as Inspector-General of the Dutch Armed Forces. This meant that he was no longer officially allowed to wear a uniform in public,&lt;ref name="Telegraph"/&gt; but it did not stop him from attending the 1979 funeral of [[Louis Mountbatten, 1st Earl Mountbatten of Burma|Lord Mountbatten]] in [[London]] in full military dress.

Prime Minister [[Joop den Uyl]] made a statement in Parliament and told the delegates that the Prince would also resign from his various high-profile positions in businesses, charities, and other institutions. The Dutch [[Netherlands States-General|States-General]] voted against criminal prosecution. Prince Bernhard turned over the Presidency of the international [[World Wildlife Fund]] to [[Prince Philip, Duke of Edinburgh]].&lt;ref name="Telegraph"/&gt;

=== Project Lock ===
[[File:Princes Juliana and Prince Bernhard 1980.jpg|thumb|left|220px|Princess Juliana and Prince Bernhard at [[Soestdijk Palace]] on 31 May 1980.]]
[[File:Bloemengala Rijnsburg 1982 - Prins Bernhard, Koningin Juliana + Anita Meyer 932-4145.jpg|thumb|left|220px|Prince Bernhard and Princess Juliana during a benefit for the [[World Wide Fund for Nature]] in [[Rijnsburg]] on 19 November 1982.]]

In 1988, Prince Bernhard and Princess Juliana sold two paintings from their personal collection to raise money for the [[World Wide Fund for Nature|World Wildlife Fund]]. The paintings sold for [[Pound sterling|GBP]]700,000, which was deposited in a Swiss WWF bank account. In 1989, however, [[Charles de Haes]], Director-General of the WWF, transferred GBP500,000 back to Bernhard, for what De Haes called a private project. In 1991, newspapers reported what this private project was: Prince Bernhard had hired KAS International, owned by [[Special Air Service]] founder [[David Stirling|Sir David Stirling]], to use [[mercenary|mercenaries]] – mostly British – to fight [[poaching|poachers]] in [[nature reserve]]s.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=https://www.independent.co.uk/news/world/pretoria-inquiry-confirms-secret-battle-for-the-rhino-1324553.html|title=Pretoria inquiry confirms secret battle for the rhino|work=The Independent|date=18 January 1996|location=London}}&lt;/ref&gt; The [[paramilitary]] group infiltrated organisations profiting from illegal trade in [[ivory]] in order to arrest them.

This [[Project Lock]] seemed to have backfired enormously, however. Bernhard's private army had not only infiltrated in the illegal trade, they were also participating in it. To make things worse, [[Ireland|Irish]] reporter Kevin Dowling discovered that the South African Army was also involved in the trade, hinting at connections between the Bernhard's troops and the WWF and the struggle for maintaining [[Apartheid]]. Moreover, he claimed members of the South African-run counterinsurgency unit [[Koevoet]] ([[Afrikaans]] and [[Dutch language|Dutch]] for "crowbar") had been trained under Project Lock.

In 1995, [[Nelson Mandela]] called upon the [[Kumleben Commission]] to investigate, among other things, the role of the WWF in apartheid-South Africa. In the report that followed, it was suggested that mercenaries from Project Lock had planned assassinations of [[African National Congress|ANC]] members and that mercenaries had been running training camps in the wildlife reserves, training fighters from the anti-communist groups [[UNITA]] and [[Renamo]]. Although Prince Bernhard was never accused of any crime in this context, the Project Lock scandal dealt another damaging blow to the Prince's reputation.

=== Other controversies ===
Yet more controversy came on 30 October 2002, when he paid the fines of two [[Albert Heijn]] supermarket staff members, who were convicted of assaulting a shoplifter after they detained him.

In an interview published after his death, on 14 December 2004, Prince Bernhard admitted that he had accepted more than one million dollars (US) in bribes from Lockheed. He acknowledged it was a mistake and claimed that all of the money went to the WWF. He said: "I have accepted that the word Lockheed will be carved on my tombstone."&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.timesonline.co.uk/tol/news/world/article398546.ece |title=Dead prince admits Dutch bribery scandal |accessdate=2007-07-12 |deadurl=bot: unknown |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20110523173052/http://www.timesonline.co.uk/tol/news/world/article398546.ece |archivedate=23 May 2011 |df=dmy-all }}. Timesonline.co.uk. 3 December 2004.&lt;/ref&gt; He also admitted to having fathered two illegitimate daughters in the years following his marriage.&lt;ref&gt;{{nl icon}} [http://www.volkskrant.nl/binnenland/article1090365.ece/ARCHIEF_-_De_prins_is_dood%2C_de_prins_spreekt ARCHIEF – De prins is dood, de prins spreekt – Binnenland – VK]. Volkskrant.nl (14 December 2004). Retrieved on 23 April 2014.&lt;/ref&gt;

In February 2008, [[Joop den Uyl]]'s biography claimed that the official report investigating the Lockheed bribe scandal also presented proof that the Prince had accepted money from yet another aerospace firm: [[Northrop Corporation|Northrop]]. The former Prime Minister claimed he had not made the information public to protect the Dutch monarchy.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.nos.nl/nos/artikelen/2008/02/art000001C8741816873E2D.html |title=Archived copy |accessdate=2008-02-21 |deadurl=bot: unknown |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20090415023053/http://www.nos.nl/nos/artikelen/2008/02/art000001C8741816873E2D.html |archivedate=15 April 2009 |df=dmy-all }}.&lt;/ref&gt;

The 2009 publication ''HRH: High Stakes at the Court of His Royal Highness'' by historian Harry Veenendaal and journalist Jort Kelder alleges that the Prince in 1950 attempted to oust the young government of the newly founded [[Republic of Indonesia]] and place himself to lead the Islands as Viceroy similar to Lord Mountbatten's role in British India. This was particularly contentious as in 1949 the Netherlands had already officially recognised its former colony as an independent nation.&lt;ref&gt;{{nl icon}} [http://www.volkskrant.nl/binnenland/article1321864.ece/Bernhard_genoemd_als_onderkoning_Indonesie Dutch newspaper article about the book release]. Volkskrant.nl (16 January 2010). Retrieved on 23 April 2014.&lt;/ref&gt;

== Death ==
In 1994 the Prince had a colon tumor removed and suffered severe complications due to [[Acute respiratory distress syndrome|respiratory distress]]. In December, his daughter Queen Beatrix rushed to the hospital straight after landing from a trip to Africa. By Christmas the prospect of death had faded and spring the next year he recovered enough to go home. His health problems continued in 1998 when he had a prostate swelling and in 1999 when he suffered difficulties breathing and talking. He did, however, attend the wedding of his grandson, straight after having prostate surgery.
In 2000, his life was endangered again when he suffered neurological complications and continued breathing problems. Two days after intensive medical (and media) attention the Royal Press Office issued a statement the Prince was reading newspapers again.

[[File:Prins Bernhard 1999 Sander Lamme.jpg|thumb|Prince Bernhard wearing his trademark carnation in [[Amsterdam]] on 6 July 1999.]]
[[File:Prins Bernhard decorates K.A. van der Hucht 7731699 500 500 6UWC.jpg|thumb|Prince Bernhard in [[Amsterdam]] on 20 June 2003.]]
[[File:Begrafenis bernhard.jpg|thumb|left|The state funeral of Prince Bernhard in [[Delft]] on 11 December 2004.]]
[[File:Bernard begrafenis.jpg|thumb|left|The state funeral of Prince Bernhard in [[Delft]] on 11 December 2004.]]

Over the following years Bernhard continued to shine at the military parades on the national liberation day celebrating the defeat of Nazi Germany. Only when his wife Juliana died in March 2004 did the deeply upset Prince become exceedingly fragile. Up to the last moment it remained uncertain if he could attend the Royal funeral, which he eventually managed to attend. He said his final farewells to his war comrades on Liberation Day in May and in November that same year he was diagnosed with untreatable cancer.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.nu.nl/algemeen/450300/bernhard-kleurrijk-en-onstuimig-video.html ANP (National Press Association of the Netherlands) news coverage summary]. Nu.nl. Retrieved on 23 April 2014.&lt;/ref&gt;

Prince Bernhard died of [[cancer]] at the age of 93 at [[University Medical Center Utrecht]] in [[Utrecht (city)|Utrecht]] on 1 December 2004; until his death he suffered from malignant [[lung]] and [[intestine|intestinal]] [[tumor]]s. On 11 December 2004, he was interred with a lavish state funeral at the [[Nieuwe Kerk (Delft)|Nieuwe Kerk]], [[Delft]]. Bernhard's funeral was different from those of Prince [[Claus von Amsberg|Claus]] and Queen [[Juliana of the Netherlands|Juliana]] in that Bernhard's coffin was transported on the undercarriage of a [[cannon]] instead of in the traditional carriage used when the coffins of Prince Claus and Queen Juliana were transported to Delft. Together with the playing of many military marches and the forming of guards of honour by [[Second World War]] [[veteran]]s this gave the funeral procession a military character as the late Prince, a Second World War veteran, had wished. As a final tribute to his former military role in the [[Royal Netherlands Air Force]], three modern [[F-16]] jet fighters and a World War II [[Supermarine Spitfire|Spitfire]] plane performed a low flypast during the funeral in a classic [[missing man formation]].

== In popular culture ==
In the years after Bernhard died his life story still fascinates many and is the inspiration for literature, theatre, television and even comic books.&lt;ref&gt;[http://lambiek.net/artists/v/varekamp.htm Erik Varekamp on Comiclopedia]
* [[Erik Varekamp|Varekamp, E.]] en Peet, M. (2004), ''Agent Orange, De jonge jaren van Prins Bernhard''. Amsterdam: Uitgeverij Van Praag. {{ISBN|904903201X}}
* Varekamp, E. en Peet, M. (2005), ''Het grote Prins Bernhard aankleedboek''. Amsterdam: Uitgeverij Van Praag. {{ISBN|9049032036}}
* Varekamp, E. en Peet, M. (2006), ''Agent Orange, Het huwelijk van Prins Bernhard''. Amsterdam: Uitgeverij Van Praag. {{ISBN|978-9049032043}}
* Varekamp, E. en Peet, M. (2008), ''Agent Orange, De oorlogsjaren van Prins Bernhard I''. Amsterdam: Uitgeverij Van Praag. {{ISBN|9789049032074}}
* Varekamp, E. en Peet, M. (2010), ''Agent Orange, De oorlogsjaren van Prins Bernhard II, De stadhoudersbrief''. Amsterdam: Uitgeverij Van Praag. {{ISBN|9789049032098}}
* Varekamp, E. en Peet, M. (2012), ''Agent Orange, De oorlogsjaren van Prins Bernhard III, De affaire Kingkong''. Amsterdam: Uitgeverij Van Praag. {{ISBN|9789049032128}}&lt;/ref&gt; In 2010 fact and fiction of the life of Bernhard was portrayed in a Dutch television series. In a biographical dissertation by Dutch journalist and historian Annejet van der Zijl published in March 2010, Bernhard was called "a failure" in the history of the Dutch Royal Family and a "creature of his own myths".&lt;ref&gt;"[http://www.nrc.nl/international/article2500347.ece/Queens_father_a_creature_of_his_own_myths Queen's father a creature of his own myths]"&lt;/ref&gt;

==Titles, styles and honours==

===Titles===
*'''29 June 1911 – 1916:''' Count Bernhard of [[Lippe-Biesterfeld]]
*'''1916 – 7 January 1937:''' ''His Serene Highness'' Prince Bernhard of Lippe-Biesterfeld
*'''7 January 1937 – 6 September 1948:''' ''His Royal Highness'' Prince Bernhard of the Netherlands&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.angelfire.com/ne2/wetgeving/nederlands/besluitverleningtitelbernhard.html Decree about the titles and names of Prince Bernhard after his marriage with Princess Juliana] – Website with Legislation concerning the Royal House of the Netherlands (''[[Dutch language|Dutch]]'')&lt;/ref&gt;
*'''6 September 1948 – 30 April 1980:''' ''His Royal Highness'' The Prince of the Netherlands&lt;ref name="titels"&gt;{{cite web| url=https://www.koninklijkhuis.nl/onderwerpen/titels-aanspreektitels-en-beschermheerschappen/inhoud/koninklijke-familie | title=Titels leden Koninklijke Familie|publisher=The Royal House| accessdate=26 May 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt;
*'''30 April 1980 – 1 December 2004:''' ''His Royal Highness'' Prince Bernhard of the Netherlands

[[File:Coat of Arms of Bernhard of Lippe-Biesterfeld.svg|thumb|Coat of arms of Prince Bernhard of Lippe-Biesterfeld]]

===Honours===

====National honours====
* {{flag|Netherlands}}: Honorary Knight Commander of the [[Military William Order]]&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|title=Staatsalmanak voor het Koninkrijk der Nederlanden|date=2004|publisher=Sdu Uitgevers|location=The Hague|isbn=90-121-0543-9|pages=A2-A3|language=Dutch}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* {{flag|Netherlands}}: Knight Grand Cross of the [[Order of the Netherlands Lion]]
* {{flag|Netherlands}}: Knight Grand Cross of the [[Order of Orange-Nassau]]
* {{flag|Netherlands}}: Grand Master Knight Commander of the [[Order of the Golden Ark|Order of the Golden Ark, 1st Class]]
* {{flag|Netherlands}}: Knight Commander of the [[Order of Saint John (Bailiwick of Brandenburg)|Order of St. John in the Netherlands]]
* {{flag|Netherlands}}: Recipient of the [[Airman's Cross]]
* {{flag|Netherlands}}: Recipient of the [[Decorations and medals of the Netherlands|Queen Juliana Inauguration Medal]]

====Foreign honours====
* {{flag|Argentina}}: Grand Cross of the [[Order of the Liberator General San Martín]]
* {{flag|Austria}}: Grand Star [[Decoration for Services to the Republic of Austria|Decoration for Services to the Republic of Austria, Gold]]&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | url = http://www.parlament.gv.at/PAKT/VHG/XXIV/AB/AB_10542/imfname_251156.pdf | title = Reply to a parliamentary question about the Decoration of Honour | language = German | page=111 |trans-title=| format = PDF | accessdate = November 2012 }}&lt;/ref&gt;
* {{flag|Belgium}}: Knight Grand Cordon of the [[Order of Leopold (Belgium)|Order of Leopold]]
* {{flag|Belgium}}: Recipient of the [[Croix de guerre (Belgium)|War Cross Medal 1939–1945]]
* {{flag|Brazil}}: Grand Cross of the [[Order of the Southern Cross]]
* {{flag|Cameroon}}: Grand Cross of the [[Order of Valour]]
* {{flag|Czech Republic}}: Grand Cross of the [[Order of the White Lion]]
* {{flag|Czechoslovakia}}: Recipient of the [[Czechoslovak War Cross 1939–1945]]
* {{flag|Chile}}: Grand Cross of the [[Order of Merit (Chile)|Order of Merit]]
* {{flag|Colombia}}: Grand Cross of the [[Order of Boyaca|Order of Boyaca, Special Class]]
* {{flag|Denmark}}: Knight Grand Cross of the [[Order of the Elephant]]
* {{flag|Dominican Republic}}: Grand Cross of the [[Order of Merit of Duarte, Sánchez and Mella|Order of Merit of Duarte, Sánchez and Mella, Silver]]
* {{flag|Ecuador}}: Grand Cross of the [[Order of Abdon Calderón]]
* {{flagicon|Ethiopia|1897}} [[Solomonic dynasty|Ethiopian Imperial Family]]: Knight Grand Cordon with Collar of the [[Order of the Queen of Sheba]]
* {{flag|Finland}}: Grand Cross of the [[Order of the White Rose of Finland]]
* {{flag|France}}: Grand Cross of the [[Legion of Honour]]
* {{flag|France}}: Commander of the [[Ordre des Palmes Académiques|Order of Academic Palms, 1st Class]]
* {{flag|France}}: Recipient of the [[Aeronautical Medal]]
* {{flag|Germany}}: Grand Cross of the [[Order of Merit of the Federal Republic of Germany|Order of Merit of the Federal Republic of Germany, Special Issue]]
* Greece
** {{flagicon|Kingdom of Greece}} [[Greek Royal Family]]: Knight Grand Cross of the [[Order of George I]]
** {{flag|Greece}}: Recipient of the [[War Cross (Greece)|1940 War Cross Medal]]
* {{flag|Honduras}}: Grand Cross of the Order of Santa Rosa and of Civilisation
* {{flag|Indonesia}}: Adipurna Grand Cross of the [[Orders, decorations, and medals of Indonesia|Order of the star of Mahaputera]]
* {{flagicon|Iran|1964}} [[Pahlavi Dynasty|Iranian Imperial Family]]: Knight Grand Cordon of the [[Order of the Lion and the Sun]]
* {{flagicon|Iran|1964}} [[Pahlavi Dynasty|Iranian Imperial Family]]: Recipient of the [[2,500 year celebration of the Persian Empire|Commemorative Medal of the 2,500 year Celebration of the Persian Empire]]&lt;ref&gt;[http://badraie.com/guests.htm Badraie] {{webarchive|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20040302191209/http://badraie.com/guests.htm |date=2 March 2004 }}. Badraie. Retrieved on 23 April 2014.&lt;/ref&gt;
* {{flag|Italy}}: Grand Cross of the [[Order of Merit of the Italian Republic]]
** {{flag|Sovereign Military Order of Malta}}: Bailiff Knight Grand Cross of [[Medals, awards and orders of the Sovereign Military Order of Malta#Sovereign Military Hospitalier Order of Saint John of Jerusalem, of Rhodes and of Malta|Honour and Devotion of the Sovereign Military Order of Malta, 3rd First Class]]
* {{flag|Ivory Coast}}: Grand Cross of the [[National Order of the Ivory Coast]]
* {{flag|Japan}}: Knight Grand Cordon of the [[Order of the Rising Sun]]
* {{flag|Liberia}}: Grand Cross of the [[Order of the Pioneers of Liberia]]
* {{flag|Luxembourg}}: Knight Grand Cross of the [[Order of the Gold Lion of the House of Nassau]]
* {{flag|Luxembourg}}: Recipient of the [[Luxembourg War Cross|War Cross Medal 1939-1945]]
* {{flag|Mexico}}: Grand Cross of the [[Order of the Aztec Eagle|Order of the Aztec Eagle, Special Class]]
* {{flagicon|Kingdom of Nepal}} [[Kingdom of Nepal|Nepal]]: Member Grand Cross of the [[Order of Ojaswi Rajanya]]
* {{flag|Nicaragua}}: Grand Cross of the Order of Rubén Darío, Special Class
* {{flag|Norway}}: Knight Grand Cross of the [[Order of St. Olav]]
* {{flag|Panama}}: Grand Cross of the [[Order of Manuel Amador Guerrero]]
* {{flag|Paraguay}}: Grand Cross of the National Order of Merit, Special Class
* {{flag|Peru}}: Grand Cross of the [[Order of the Sun of Peru]]
* {{flag|Poland}}: Grand Cross of the [[Virtuti Militari|Order of Military Virtue]]
* {{flag|Senegal}}: Grand Cross of the [[Orders, decorations, and medals of Senegal|National Order of Merit]]
* {{flag|Spain}}: Knight Grand Cross of the [[Order of Charles III]]
* {{flag|Suriname}}: Grand Cross of the [[Honorary Order of the Yellow Star]]
* {{flag|Sweden}}: Knight Grand Cross of the [[Order of the Seraphim]]
* {{flag|Thailand}}: Knight Grand Cordon with Chain of the [[Order of the Royal House of Chakri]]
* {{flag|Tunisia}}: Grand Cross of the Order of Independence]
* {{flag|United Kingdom}}: Honorary Knight Grand Cross of the [[Order of the Bath]]
* {{flag|United Kingdom}}: Recipient of the [[France and Germany Star]]
* {{flag|United Kingdom}}: Recipient of the [[Defence Medal (United Kingdom)|Defence Medal]]
* {{flag|United Kingdom}}: Recipient of the [[King George VI Coronation Medal]]
* {{flag|United Kingdom}}: Recipient of the [[Queen Elizabeth II Coronation Medal]]
* {{flag|United States}}: Officer of the [[Legion of Merit]]
* {{flag|Venezuela}}: Grand Cross of the [[Order of the Liberator]]
* {{flag|Yugoslavia}}: Grand Cross of the [[Order of the Yugoslav Star]]

==Military ranks==

===Military ranks of the Armed forces of the Netherlands===
{{Col-begin}}
{{Col-3}}
{| class="wikitable"
|+
! [[Royal Netherlands Army]] !! Date
|-
||[[File:Nl-landmacht-kapitein ritmeester.svg|80px]] [[Captain (armed forces)|Captain]]||3 December 1936
|-
||[[File:Nl-landmacht-generaal majoor.svg|80px]] [[Major general]]||25 May 1942
|-
||[[File:Nl-landmacht-luitenant generaal.svg|80px]] [[Lieutenant general]]||15 December 1943
|-
||[[File:Nl-landmacht-generaal.svg|80px]] [[Four-star rank|General]]||3 September 1944
|}
{{Col-3}}
{| class="wikitable"
|+
! [[Royal Netherlands East Indies Army]] !! Date
|-
||[[File:Nl-landmacht-kapitein ritmeester.svg|80px]] [[Captain (armed forces)|Captain]]||23 August 1940
|-
||[[File:Nl-landmacht-luitenant generaal.svg|80px]] [[Lieutenant general]]||15 December 1943
|-
||[[File:Nl-landmacht-generaal.svg|80px]] [[Four-star rank|General]]||3 September 1944
|}
{{Col-3}}
{| class="wikitable"
|+
! [[Royal Netherlands Navy]] !! Date
|-
||[[File:Nl-marine-vloot-luitenant ter zee der 1e klasse.svg|80px]] [[Lieutenant commander]]||3 December 1936
|-
||[[File:Nl-marine-vloot-kapitein ter zee.svg|80px]] [[Captain (naval)|Captain]]||23 August 1940
|-
||[[File:Nl-marine-vloot-schout schout bij nacht.svg|80px]] [[Rear admiral]]||25 May 1942
|-
||[[File:Nl-marine-vloot-vice-admiraal.svg|80px]] [[Vice admiral]]||15 December 1943
|-
||[[File:Nl-marine-vloot-luitenant admiraal.svg|80px]] [[Lieutenant admiral]]||3 September 1944
|}
{{Col-end}}
{| class="wikitable"
|+
! [[Royal Netherlands Air Force]] !! Date
|-
||[[File:Nl-luchtmacht-generaal.svg|80px]] [[Four-star rank|General]]||27 March 1953
|}

===Honorary Military ranks of Foreign Armed forces===
{{Col-begin}}
{{Col-2}}
{| class="wikitable"
|+
! [[Royal Air Force]] !! Date
|-
||[[File:UK-Air-OF6.svg|80px]] [[Air commodore]]||4 April 1941
|-
||[[File:UK-Air-OF8.svg|80px]] [[Air marshal]]||15 September 1964 &lt;ref&gt;{{London Gazette|issue=43434 |date=11 September 1964 |page=7765 |supp=y }}&lt;/ref&gt;
|-
|}
{{Col-2}}
{| class="wikitable"
|+
! [[Royal New Zealand Air Force]] !! Date
|-
||[[File:UK-Air-OF6.svg|80px]] [[Air commodore]]||19 August 1946
|-
|}
{{Col-end}}

== Ancestry ==
{{ahnentafel
|collapsed=yes |align=center
|boxstyle_1=background-color: #fcc;
|boxstyle_2=background-color: #fb9;
|boxstyle_3=background-color: #ffc;
|boxstyle_4=background-color: #bfc;
|boxstyle_5=background-color: #9fe;
|1= 1. '''Prince Bernhard of Lippe-Biesterfeld'''
|2= 2. [[Prince Bernhard of Lippe-Biesterfeld (1872–1934)|Prince Bernhard of Lippe-Biesterfeld]]
|3= 3. [[Armgard of Sierstorpff-Cramm]]
|4= 4. [[Ernest II, Count of Lippe-Biesterfeld]]
|5= 5. Countess [[Karoline of Wartensleben]]
|6= 6. [[Baron Aschwin of Sierstorpff-Cramm]]
|7= 7. [[Baroness Hedwig of Sierstorpff-Driburg]]
|8= 8. [[Julius, Count of Lippe-Biesterfeld]]
|9= 9. Countess Adelheid Clotilde of Castell-Castell
|10= 10. Count Leopold Otto of Wartensleben
|11= 11. Mathilde Halbach
|12= 12. Wolfgang Adolf of Cramm
|13= 13. Hedwig of Cramm
|14= 14. Count Ernst Moritz of Sierstorpff-Driburg
|15= 15. Baroness Karoline von Vincke
|16= 16. Ernst I, Count of Lippe-Biesterfeld
|17= 17. Modeste Christiane von Unruh
|18= 18. Friedrich, Count of Castell-Castell
|19= 19. Princess Emilie of Hohenlohe-Langenburg
|20= 20. Count Cäsar Alexander of Wartensleben
|21= 21. Friederike von Gfug, Heiress of Osniszczewo
|22= 22. [[Arnold Halbach]]
|23= 23. Johanna Mathilde Bohlen
|24= 24. Friedrich Carl August of Cramm
|25= 25. Charlotte Sophie von Uetterodt
|26= 26. Philipp Lebrecht von Cramm
|27= 27. Philippine Wilhelmine von Griesheim
|28= 28. Count Kaspar Heinrich of Sierstorpff-Driburg
|29= 29. Friederike Charlotte von Vincke
|30= 30. Baron Friedrich Ludwig von Vincke
|31= 31. Baroness Eleonore Louise of Syberg zum Busch
}}

== References ==
{{Reflist|35em}}

== External links ==
{{Commons category|Bernhard of Lippe-Biesterfeld}}
* [http://www.koninklijkhuis.nl/english/Special_pages/Bernhard/Prince_Bernhard/Biography Official Biography (Summary) Official Dutch Royal Website]{{dead link|date=September 2017 |bot=InternetArchiveBot |fix-attempted=yes }}
* [http://www.cybermotorcycle.com/gallery/corgi/Corgi_Prince_Bernhard.htm Prince Bernhard takes delivery of his second [[Corgi Motorcycle Co Ltd.|Corgi]]]
* {{Official website|http://www.koninklijkhuis.nl/english/index.jsp|Dutch Royal House official website}}
* [http://www.panda.org The World Wildlife Fund website]
* [https://web.archive.org/web/20111019034224/http://www.koninklijkhuis.nl/Speciale_webpagina_s/Bernhard/Prins_Bernhard.html Official memorial]
* [http://www.go2war2.nl/artikel/1072 Article about Prince Bernhard during World War II on Go2War2 (Dutch)]
* [http://www.mars-mercurius.nl The Mars en Mercurius website]
* [http://cgi.omroep.nl/cgi-bin/streams?/ibg/sn040003-sb.wmv?title= '''Historic video footage Montgomery visit 1945.''']
* [http://cgi.omroep.nl/cgi-bin/streams?/ibg/sn036006-sb.wmv?title= '''Historic video footage Churchill visit 1946.''']
* [http://cgi.omroep.nl/cgi-bin/streams?/ibg/sn207021-bb.wmv?title= '''Historic video footage Eisenhower visit 1951.''']
* {{PM20|FID=pe/001587}}

{{s-start}}
{{S-hou|[[House of Lippe]]|29 June|1911|1 December|2004}}
{{S-roy|nl}}
|-
{{s-vac|last=[[Duke Henry of Mecklenburg-Schwerin]]}}
{{s-ttl|title=[[List of Dutch consorts|Prince Consort of the Netherlands]]|years=1948–1980}}
{{s-aft|after=[[Prince Claus of the Netherlands|Claus von Amsberg]]}}
{{s-npo}}
|-
{{s-non|rows=2|reason=First}}
{{s-ttl|title=[[Chairmen]] of the [[Bilderberg Group]]|years=1954–1976}}
{{s-aft|after=[[Walter Scheel]]}}
|-
{{s-ttl|title=[[World Wide Fund for Nature#Presidents|President of the World Wide Fund for Nature]]|years=1961–1977}}
{{s-aft|after=[[John Hugo Loudon]]}}
|-
{{s-mil}}
|-
{{s-vac|last=[[Henri Winkelman]]}}
{{s-ttl|title=[[Commander-in-chief]] of the [[Armed forces of the Netherlands]]|years=1944–1945}}
{{s-vac|next=[[Henk Kruls]]|as=[[Chief of Defence (Netherlands)|Chief of the Netherlands Defence Staff]]}}
|-
{{s-non|rows=4|reason=First}}
{{s-ttl|title=[[Inspector General]] of the [[Royal Netherlands Army]]|years=1945–1970}}
{{s-non|rows=3|reason=Last&lt;br&gt;'''Became Inspector General of&lt;br&gt;the Armed forces of the Netherlands}}
|-
{{s-ttl|title=[[Inspector General]] of the [[Royal Netherlands Navy]]|years=1946–1970}}
|-
{{s-ttl|title=[[Inspector General]] of the [[Royal Netherlands Air Force]]|years=1953–1970}}
|-
{{s-ttl|title=[[Inspector General]] of the [[Armed forces of the Netherlands]]|years=1970–1976}}
{{s-aft|after=[[Witius Henrik de Savornin Lohman]]}}
{{end}}
{{Dutch consorts}}
{{WWFN}}

{{Use dmy dates|date=April 2014}}

{{Authority control}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Bernhard of Lippe-Biesterfeld}}
[[Category:1911 births]]
[[Category:2004 deaths]]
[[Category:20th-century Calvinist and Reformed Christians]]
[[Category:20th-century Protestants]]
[[Category:21st-century Protestants]]
[[Category:Aide-de-camp to the Monarch of the Netherlands]]
[[Category:Animal rights activists]]
[[Category:Burials in the Royal Crypt at Nieuwe Kerk, Delft]]
[[Category:Chairmen of the Steering Committee of the Bilderberg Group]]
[[Category:Commanders-in-chief of the Armed Forces of the Netherlands]]
[[Category:Converts to Calvinism from Lutheranism]]
[[Category:Counts of Lippe]]
[[Category:Counts of Lippe-Biesterfeld]]
[[Category:Deaths from cancer]]
[[Category:Deaths from cancer in the Netherlands]]
[[Category:Deaths from lung cancer]]
[[Category:Deaths from stomach cancer]]
[[Category:Dutch activists]]
[[Category:Dutch conservationists]]
[[Category:Dutch lobbyists]]
[[Category:Dutch members of the Dutch Reformed Church]]
[[Category:Dutch nonprofit directors]]
[[Category:Dutch nonprofit executives]]
[[Category:Dutch people of World War II]]
[[Category:Dutch royal consorts]]
[[Category:Engelandvaarders]]
[[Category:German Calvinist and Reformed Christians]]
[[Category:German Lutherans]]
[[Category:German princes]]
[[Category:German royalty]]
[[Category:Grand Crosses Special Class of the Order of Merit of the Federal Republic of Germany]]
[[Category:Honorary air commodores]]
[[Category:House of Lippe]]
[[Category:House of Orange-Nassau]]
[[Category:Humboldt University of Berlin alumni]]
[[Category:Inspectors general]]
[[Category:Knights Commander of the Military Order of William]]
[[Category:Knights Grand Cross of the Order of Orange-Nassau]]
[[Category:Knights of the Order of the Netherlands Lion]]
[[Category:Knights of the Order of Saint John in the Netherlands]]
[[Category:Members of the Council of State (Netherlands)]]
[[Category:Members of the Steering Committee of the Bilderberg Group]]
[[Category:National Socialist Motor Corps members]]
[[Category:Nobility of Lippe]]
[[Category:People associated with the Lockheed bribery scandals]]
[[Category:People from Jena]]
[[Category:People from Saxe-Weimar-Eisenach]]
[[Category:People from Thuringia]]
[[Category:Princes of Lippe]]
[[Category:Princes of Lippe-Biesterfeld]]
[[Category:Protestant Church Christians from the Netherlands]]
[[Category:Recipients of the Airman's Cross]]
[[Category:Recipients of the Order of Orange-Nassau]]
[[Category:Royal Air Force air marshals]]
[[Category:Royal Air Force personnel of World War II]]
[[Category:Royal Australian Air Force officers]]
[[Category:Royal Netherlands Air Force generals]]
[[Category:Royal Netherlands Air Force officers]]
[[Category:Royal Netherlands Air Force personnel of World War II]]
[[Category:Royal Netherlands Air Force pilots]]
[[Category:Royal Netherlands Army generals]]
[[Category:Royal Netherlands Army officers]]
[[Category:Royal Netherlands Army personnel of World War II]]
[[Category:Royal Netherlands East Indies Army generals]]
[[Category:Royal Netherlands East Indies Army officers]]
[[Category:Royal Netherlands East Indies Army personnel of World War II]]
[[Category:Royal Netherlands Navy admirals]]
[[Category:Royal Netherlands Navy officers]]
[[Category:Royal Netherlands Navy personnel of World War II]]
[[Category:University of Lausanne alumni]]
[[Category:World Wide Fund for Nature]]
[[Category:Nansen Refugee Award winners]]
[[Category:Recipients of the Order of the White Lion]]
[[Category:Recipients of the Czechoslovak War Cross]]</text>
      <sha1>drednudyenp4p18i4fgcactyvcng1lh</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
