<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10.xsd" version="0.10" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <dbname>enwiki</dbname>
    <base>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.32.0-wmf.16</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="118" case="first-letter">Draft</namespace>
      <namespace key="119" case="first-letter">Draft talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2300" case="first-letter">Gadget</namespace>
      <namespace key="2301" case="first-letter">Gadget talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2302" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition</namespace>
      <namespace key="2303" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Raymonde de Laroche</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>913019</id>
    <revision>
      <id>842169642</id>
      <parentid>838381572</parentid>
      <timestamp>2018-05-20T18:18:59Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <ip>86.2.65.41</ip>
      </contributor>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="8815">{{Use dmy dates|date=March 2011}}
{{Infobox person
| name   = Raymonde de Laroche
| image     = Raymonde_de_LaRoche_Head.jpg
| caption  = Raymonde de Laroche in August 1909
| birth_date  = {{birth date|1882|8|22|df=y}}
| birth_place = Paris, France
| death_date  = {{death date and age|1919|7|18|1882|8|22|df=y}}
| death_place = Le Crotoy airfield, France
| occupation     = [[Aviator]]
}}

'''Raymonde de Laroche''' (22 August 1882 – 18 July 1919), born '''Elise Raymonde Deroche''', was a [[French people|French]] pilot and the first woman in the world to receive an [[Pilot licensing and certification|aeroplane pilot's licence]].

==Early life==
Born on 22 August 1882 in Paris, Raymonde Deroche was the daughter of a plumber. She had a fondness for sports as a child, as well as for motorcycles and automobiles when she was older. As a young woman she became an actress and used the stage name "Raymonde de Laroche". Inspired by [[Wilbur Wright]]'s 1908 demonstrations of powered flight in [[Paris]] and being personally acquainted with several aviators, including artist-turned-aviator [[Léon Delagrange]], who was reputed to be the father of her son André, de Laroche determined to take up flying for herself.&lt;ref name="Lebow2003"/&gt;{{rp|9–10}}

==Achievements in aviation==
[[File:Mme. la Baronne de Laroche, aviatrice, au poste de direction d'un biplan Voisin (c. 1910).jpg|left|thumb|Raymonde de Laroche in her Voisin aeroplane in 1909]]
In October 1909, de Laroche appealed to her friend, aviator and aeroplane builder [[Charles Voisin]], to instruct her in how to fly. On 22 October 1909, de Laroche went to the Voisin brothers' base of operations at Chalons, {{convert|90|mi|km}} east of Paris. Voisin's aircraft could seat only one person, so she operated the plane by herself while he stood on the ground and gave instructions. After she mastered taxiing around the airfield, she lifted off and flew {{convert|300|yd}}.&lt;ref name="Lebow2003"/&gt;{{rp|11–13}} De Laroche's flight is often cited as the first by a woman in a powered heavier-than-air craft; there is evidence that two other women, P. Van Pottelsberghe and [[Thérèse Peltier]], had flown the previous year with [[Henri Farman]] and Delagrange respectively as passengers but not as pilots.&lt;ref name=Peltier&gt;[http://www.earlyaviators.com/epeltier.htm Early Aviators – Peltier Biography]&lt;/ref&gt;

Decades later, aviation journalist Harry Harper wrote that until de Laroche made her celebrated flight on the Voisin, she had only flown once, for a short hop, as a passenger; when she first took the controls, Charles Voisin expressly forbade her to attempt a flight; and after taxiing twice across the airfield, she took off, flying "ten or fifteen feet high" and handling the controls with "cool, quick precision".&lt;ref&gt;''Air Trails'', July 1953. "The Brave Baroness – First Licensed Ladybird" by Harry Harper.&lt;/ref&gt;

Although [[Gabriel Voisin]] wrote, "... my brother [was] entirely under her thumb",&lt;ref&gt;Voisin, G.: ''Mes 10000 Cerfs-Volants''. Editions Table Ronde, 1960. {{ISBN|2-7103-2012-6}}.&lt;/ref&gt; the story of de Laroche as a headstrong woman making the flight after scant preparation and against Voisin's orders almost certainly romanticises what actually took place. ''Flight'' magazine, a week after the flight, reported: "For some time the Baroness has been taking lessons from M. Chateau, the Voisin instructor, at Chalons, and on Friday of last week she was able to take the wheel for the first time. This initial voyage into the air was only a very short one, and ''terra firma'' was regained after {{convert|300|yd}}."&lt;ref name=Flight&gt;[http://www.flightglobal.com/pdfarchive/view/1909/1909%20-%200693.html ''Flight'', page 695, 30 October 1909.]&lt;/ref&gt; ''Flight'' was also responsible for bestowing the title "Baroness" upon de Laroche, as she was not of [[nobility|noble]] birth.&lt;ref name="Lebow2003"/&gt;{{rp|9}} ''Flight'' added that on the following day she circled the flying field twice, "the turnings being made with consummate ease. During this flight of about four miles (6&amp;nbsp;km) there was a strong gusty wind blowing, but after the first two turnings the Baroness said that it did not bother her, as she had the machine completely under control."&lt;ref name=Flight/&gt;

On 8 March 1910,&lt;ref name="Lebow2003"&gt;{{Cite book|author=Eileen F. Lebow|title=Before Amelia: Women Pilots in the Early Days of Aviation|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=KsSz9JsBk_IC&amp;pg=PA14|accessdate=7 March 2011|date=7 April 2003|publisher=Brassey's|isbn=978-1-57488-532-3}}&lt;/ref&gt;{{rp|14}} de Laroche became the first woman in the world to receive a pilot licence when the Aero-Club of France issued her licence #36 of the ''[[Fédération Aéronautique Internationale]]'' (International Aeronautics Federation or F.A.I.).

[[File:Raymonde de Laroche in her Voisin biplane, Reims air show - 191007.jpg|thumb|Raymonde de Laroche in flight in her Voisin biplane at the [[Grande Semaine d'Aviation de la Champagne]] Reims airshow in 1910]]

De Laroche participated in aviation meetings at [[Heliopolis (Cairo Suburb)|Heliopolis]] in Egypt as well as [[Saint Petersburg]], [[Budapest]] and [[Rouen]]. During the show in St. Petersburg, she was personally congratulated by Tsar [[Nicholas II of Russia|Nicholas II]]. There, she was presented once again as "Baroness" de Laroche. Thereafter, the title became commonly used.&lt;ref name="Lebow2003"/&gt;{{rp|16}}

In July 1910, de Laroche was participating in the week-long airshow at [[Reims]] in France. On 8 July, her aeroplane crashed, and she suffered such severe injuries that her recovery was in doubt, but two years later, she was fit again and had returned to flying. On 26 September 1912, she and Charles Voisin were involved in a car crash. Voisin was killed, and she was severely injured.&lt;ref name=CharlesVoisin&gt;[http://www.earlyaviators.com/evoisin.htm Early Aviators – Charles Voisin Biography]&lt;/ref&gt;

On 25 November 1913 de Laroche won the Aero-Club of France's [[Coupe Femina|Femina Cup]] for a non-stop long-distance flight of over 4 hours duration.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|title=Mme de Laroche gagne la Coup Femina|language=fr|date=Dec 10, 1913|journal=La Revue aérienne| url=http://gallica.bnf.fr/ark:/12148/bpt6k6555030g/f13.item.r=coupe%20femina |page=669|access-date=Nov 29, 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt;

During World War I, as flying was considered too dangerous for women, she served as a military driver, chauffeuring officers from the rear zones to the front under fire.&lt;ref name="Lebow2003"/&gt;{{rp|20}}

In June 1919 de Laroche set two women's altitude records,&lt;ref name=Lienhard&gt;[http://www.uh.edu/engines/epi1813.htm University of Houson, "Engines of our Ingenuity, No. 1813: Raymonde de Laroche", undated article by John H. Lienhard], retrieved on 27 March 2008.&lt;/ref&gt; one at {{convert|15700|ft|m}}; and also the women's distance record, at {{convert|201|mi|km}}.&lt;ref name="Lebow2003"/&gt;{{rp|21}}

==Death and legacy==
On 18 July 1919 de Laroche, who was a talented engineer, went to the airfield at Le Crotoy as part of her plan to become the first professional woman test pilot. She co-piloted an experimental aircraft (whether she flew this  is not known); on its landing approach the aeroplane went into a dive and crashed, killing both de Laroche and the co-pilot.

There is a statue of de Laroche at [[Le Bourget Airport]] in France.

From 6 March to 12 March 2010, to celebrate the Centennial of Licensed Women Pilots, women pilots from eight countries on three continents used 20 types of aircraft to establish a new world record: 225 girls and women introduced to piloting by a woman pilot in one week.

[[Women Of Aviation Worldwide Week]] is held annually during the week including 8 March, which marks the anniversary of Raymonde de Laroche's pilot licence and International Women’s Day, and aims to foster diversity in aviation by celebrating women’s history, raising awareness of aviation’s opportunities among girls and women, and shaping the future by introducing girls and women to aviation through industry-wide collaboration.

==References==
{{Reflist}}

==External links==
{{Commons}}
*[http://www.nasm.si.edu/research/aero/women_aviators/raymonde_delaroche.htm The Smithsonian web page about de la Roche]
*[http://www.earlyaviators.com/edelaroc.htm Early Aviators – De Laroche Biography]

{{Authority control}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Laroche, Raymonde de}}
[[Category:1882 births]]
[[Category:1919 deaths]]
[[Category:Aviation pioneers]]
[[Category:Female aviators]]
[[Category:Aviators killed in aviation accidents or incidents in France]]
[[Category:French aviators]]
[[Category:French baronesses]]
[[Category:Burials at Père Lachaise Cemetery]]
[[Category:French female aviators]]
[[Category:Women aviation record holders]]
[[Category:French aviation record holders]]</text>
      <sha1>3wdsq926zzqm0xjwn0wf447p3yoe8rf</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
