<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10.xsd" version="0.10" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <dbname>enwiki</dbname>
    <base>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.32.0-wmf.16</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="118" case="first-letter">Draft</namespace>
      <namespace key="119" case="first-letter">Draft talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2300" case="first-letter">Gadget</namespace>
      <namespace key="2301" case="first-letter">Gadget talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2302" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition</namespace>
      <namespace key="2303" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Robert Campbell Reeve</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>15129600</id>
    <revision>
      <id>852984946</id>
      <parentid>852038094</parentid>
      <timestamp>2018-08-01T17:25:02Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Recensore256</username>
        <id>34313057</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>/* The war years */ Added and cited HoF induction</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="27030">{{Infobox person
|name          = Robert Campbell Reeve
|image         = Robert Campbell Reeve.jpg
|image_size    = 250px
|alt           = 
|caption       = Bob Reeve
|birth_name    = Robert Campbell Reeve
|birth_date    = {{Birth date|1902|03|27}}
|birth_place   = [[Waunakee, Wisconsin]]
|death_date    = {{Death date and age|1980|08|25|1902|03|27}}
|death_place   = 
|body_discovered = 
|death_cause   = 
|resting_place = 
|resting_place_coordinates = &lt;!-- {{coord|LAT|LONG|display=inline,title}} --&gt;
|residence     = 
|nationality   = American
|ethnicity     = 
|citizenship   = 
|other_names   = 
|known_for     = Founding [[Reeve Aleutian Airways]]
|education     = 
|alma_mater    = 
|employer      = 
|occupation    = Pilot, Airline owner
|years_active  = 
|home_town     = 
|salary        = 
|networth      = 
|height        = 
|weight        = 
|title         = 
|term          = 
|predecessor   = 
|successor     = 
|party         = [[Republican Party (United States)|Republican]]
|opponents     = 
|boards        = 
|religion      = 
|spouse        = Janice ("Tilly") {{Not a typo|Morisette}}
|partner       = 
|children      = Richard, Roberta, Janice, David, Whitham
|parents       = Hubert and Mae Reeve
|relations     = [[Donald Sheldon]] (son-in-law)
|callsign      = 
|awards        = 
|signature     = 
|website       = 
|footnotes     = 
|box_width     = 
}}

'''Robert Campbell "Bob" Reeve''' (March 27, 1902 – August 25, 1980) was the founder of [[Reeve Aleutian Airways]].

==Childhood==
Reeve was born in [[Waunakee, Wisconsin|Waunakee]], [[Wisconsin]], on March 27, 1902. He was one of twins, his brother was Richard. Their parents were Hubert and Mae Reeve. Mae died in 1904, and their father remarried, leaving the boys to fend for themselves. Bob and Richard went their separate ways early in life. Reeve was fascinated by [[aviation]] from an early age, and studied all he could on the subject. He enlisted in the [[US Army]] aged 15 in 1917. Discharged from the Army at the end of the war, Reeve had reached the rank of sergeant. He wanted to re-enlist, but his father was against this so Reeve returned to school, but dropped out after a few months and went to [[San Francisco]]. From there he got passage as an ordinary seaman to [[Shanghai]], where he took a job in the Chinese Maritime Customs Service, serving on the [[Yangtze]] and Taku rivers. In 1921, Reeve was working in [[Vladivostok]], [[USSR]], but returned home as a result of his father's pleading.&lt;ref name=Fly&gt;{{cite book | first = Stan| last = Cohen| year = 1988| title = Flying Beats Work: The Story of Reeve Aleutian Airways| chapter = Chapter 1| publisher = Pictorial Histories Publishing Company| location = Missoula, Montana| isbn = 0-933126-98-0}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=Hall&gt;[https://www.wisconsinaviationhalloffame.org/inductees/reeve.htm Hall of Fame Inductee: Robert C. Reeve]. Wisconsin Aviation Hall of Fame.&lt;/ref&gt;

Reeve finished high school, and then entered the [[University of Wisconsin–Madison]] in 1922, his brother already being there. A picture of the aviator [[Carl Ben Eielson]] was on the wall at the fraternity house, this inspired Reeve, George Gardner, Monk MacKinnon and Ora McMurray to skip classes to spend time at Madison airfield, where Cash Chamberlain had a [[Curtiss Jenny]]. Six months short of graduation, all four were expelled from the university. This pushed them further into aviation, with Gardner and MacKinnon becoming President and Vice-President respectively of [[Northwest Airlines]].&lt;ref name=Fly/&gt;

==Barnstorming days==
Reeve headed to [[Florida]], then to [[Beaumont, Texas]] where he joined a pair of [[Barnstorming|barnstormers]]—"Hazard" and "Maverick". In exchange for two months' work at the airfield, Reeve got three hours flying instruction (which was called five) and [[First solo flight|soloed]]. When the [[United States government role in civil aviation|Air Commerce Act of 1926]] came into force, he got one of the first [[Aircraft Maintenance Technician|Engine and Aircraft Mechanic's License]]s and his [[Pilot certification in the United States|Commercial Pilot's License]]. Reeve joined the [[United States Army Aviation Branch|Army Air Corps]] at [[March Field]], but was discharged after a short time.&lt;ref name=Fly/&gt;

==South America==
[[File:Ford Trimotor.jpg|thumb|Ford Trimotor.]]
[[File:Lockheed Vega 5b Smithsonian.jpg|thumb|Lockheed Vega 5B]]
By the late 1920s, barnstorming wasn't a viable way to make a living. [[Pan Am]] teamed up with [[W. R. Grace and Company]] to bid for an [[airmail]] contract in [[South America]]. The new airline, [[Pan American-Grace Airways]] (Panagra) flew weekly airmail from the US to [[Lima]], [[Peru]] via the [[Panama Canal Zone|Canal Zone]]. A [[Ford Trimotor]] was purchased and Reeve trained with the [[Ford Motor Company]] on these aircraft, delivering the first to Lima in August 1929. Panagra offered Reeve the chance to fly Airmail Route 9 from Lima to [[Santiago, Chile]], at this time the longest aviation route in the world at {{convert|1900|mi|km}}. In 1930 the route was extended to [[Montevideo]], [[Uruguay]]. It was during this time that Reeve learned about bush flying, developing techniques to avoid coastal fog, which would later serve him in [[Alaska]], and mountain flying skills. He established a speed record between Santiago and Lima, covering the 1,900 miles in 20 hours. In January 1932, he crashed a [[Lockheed Vega]] of Panagra at Santiago, and quit before he was fired.&lt;ref name=Fly2&gt;{{cite book | first = Stan| last = Cohen| year = 1988| title = Flying Beats Work The Story of Reeve Aleutian Airways| chapter = Chapter 2| publisher = Pictorial Histories Publishing Company| location = Missoula, Montana| isbn = 0-933126-98-0}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Alaska==
Reeve's move to [[Alaska]] came as the result of unrelated incidents. He had met a [[Klondike Gold Rush|Klondike]] prospector, [[Bill Gates (frontiersman)|"Swiftwater Bill" Gates]], in [[Chile]], who had told him of the Gold Rush thirty years earlier. He had also talked to Eddie Craig, a mining engineer at the [[Kennecott, Alaska|Kennicott Copper Mine]] in Alaska in the early 1900s. These stories, and the idea that there was new country to conquer pulled Reeve north. He returned home to Wisconsin, where he suffered a slight attack of [[polio]], which affected one of his legs slightly.&lt;ref name=Fly2/&gt;

Reeve [[Stowaway|stowed away]] on a [[steamship]], arriving in Alaska with $2 in his pocket, and [[Valdez, Alaska]] with 20¢. At [[Valdez Airport|Valdez airfield]], Owen Meals had a wrecked [[Alexander Aircraft Company|Eaglerock]] aircraft with a [[Wright J-5]] engine that had been a spare for [[Sir Hubert Wilkins]] when he made his flight across the [[North Pole]] to [[Spitsbergen]].&lt;ref name=Fly3&gt;{{cite book | first = Stan| last = Cohen| year = 1988|title = Flying Beats Work: The Story of Reeve Aleutian Airways| chapter = Chapter 3| publisher = Pictorial Histories Publishing Company| location = Missoula, Montana| isbn = 0-933126-98-0}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Reeve worked for a month at $1 an hour repairing the plane, and then leased the plane from Meals at $10 an hour. Having created a landing strip, Reeve was in business. His first charter was to Middleton Island, where the beach looked fine to land on, but the aircraft sank up to its wheels in the soft sand. An old block and tackle was found and used to rescue the aircraft from the incoming tide. Reeve managed to take off, and attempted to fly back to Valdez, but was forced to land at [[Seward, Alaska|Seward]] owing to a storm. When he eventually got back to Valdez his tanks were almost empty, and he hadn't earned a cent. Reeve said this trip was worth $1,000 in experience. Reeve quickly learnt that the bush pilot's biggest worry was paying for gas, which could be $0.25 a gallon in one place, and $1.50 in another.&lt;ref name=Fly3/&gt;

That winter, Reeve was hired to fly supplies to [[Chisana]] at 20¢/lb, his base for this was at Christochina, where a small airstrip had been created with high obstacles each end of the runway. Oil in the aircraft engines had to be drained each night, and warmed up on a stove each morning before being returned to the engine, as it was so cold that the oil would freeze. Reeve made a $2,000 profit on the Chisana route and had heard of a [[Fairchild 51]] for sale in [[Fairbanks]]. This was the type of aircraft he had used in the [[Andes]]. He bought it for $3,500, with $1,500 down and the balance within two years.&lt;ref name=Fly3/&gt;

==Reputation earned==
Reeve's first trip in the Fairchild was to fly Mr and Mrs Ole Hay and their two children, aged 4 and 4 months, to [[Nome, Alaska|Nome]]. Just out of [[McGrath, Alaska|McGrath]], they ran into dense [[fog|ice-fog]], a complete [[Whiteout (weather)|white out]], so Reeve landed on the frozen Kateel River and the made camp. After 25 hours, conditions had improved sufficiently for them to continue as far as [[Shaktoolik]]. It took three days to get to Nome, and another ten days before he could leave for Valdez, picking up a medical emergency in Shaktoolik on the way. Again Reeve had to land because of the weather, this time landing on the [[Skwentna River]]. Reeve flew the patient to Seward the next day, and when he eventually returned to Valdez, Reeve found that stories of his outward trip were in the newspapers. He was officially initiated into the ranks of the Heroic Bush Pilots.&lt;ref name=Fly3/&gt;

==Tilly==
In March 1933, Reeve took an order into Chisana. On the way back to Valdez his engine quit and he made a forced landing by [[Mount Wrangell]]. He and his passenger used [[snowshoes]] to walk the {{convert|20|mi|km}} to the Nabesna Mine, where owner Carl Whitham assisted them. They returned to Valdez for help, got the spare parts to repair the engine and flew back to the plane, where the three men repaired the engine, using a tree to hoist it clear of the aircraft.&lt;ref name=Fly3/&gt;

During the [[Great Depression]], there was constant talk of reopening the [[gold]] mines. One of the biggest was the Big Four Mine on the Brevier Glacier, only {{convert|30|mi|km}} from Valdez, but at and elevation of {{convert|6000|ft|m}}. Clarence Poy of San Francisco said he would buy the mine if Reeve flew his supplies and men in. Reeve took the current owner, Jack Cook to the mine to inspect it. The landing spot turned out not to be as good as had been claimed, but although the aircraft was partially buried in soft snow, no damage was done. Reeve later marked out a landing strip with flags and lamp black.&lt;ref name=Fly3/&gt;

Reeve's success with supplying the Big Four Mine let to further contracts with other mines; the Mayfield, Little Giant and Ramsay Rutherford. During this time, Reeve learned more about assessing suitability of landing sites from the air, and developed the technique of dropping supplies by air. Miners being so keen on getting their supplies that they would pay for another load if supplies were damaged when dropped. In 1934, the price of gold almost doubled under the [[New Deal]] [[Gold Reserve Act]] and Valdez boomed. In the summer of 1934, Reeve's exploits, including landing on mudflats (having manufactured skis from stainless steel to fit to his aircraft) regularly reached the papers. He received some fan letters, including one from Miss Janice {{Not a typo|Morisette}}, who asked if he needed an extra hand. Janice lived about 30 miles from Reeve's hometown. They corresponded for a few months and Janice flew to Valdez in June 1935. Reeve left on a prospecting trip to [[Canada]], but his curiosity got the better of him and he returned within a month. When he first saw her she reminded him of "[[Tillie the Toiler|Tilly the Toiler]]" and thus the nickname stuck.&lt;ref name=Fly3/&gt;

[[File:Fairchild 71B ExCC.jpg|thumb|Fairchild 71.]]
Reeve tried his hand at mining, and joined with prospector Andy Thompson to prospect the Ruff &amp; Tuff Mine. He went to Canada in 1936 to try placer mining to finance the Ruff &amp; Tuff. The mining didn't pay, so Reeve returned to Valdez flying supplies. He earned enough money to buy basic equipment for the Ruff &amp; Tuff and later he and Thompson sold the mine, with Reeve getting the contract to supply it. Tilly had returned to San Francisco in the meantime, but she returned in April 1936. Reeve decided that despite his sporadic income, he would marry Tilly and so they were married in Fairbanks. Reeve bought another plane, a [[Fairchild 71]] to celebrate.&lt;ref name=Fly3/&gt;

==Expedition==
Reeve made several modifications to his plane, which he tried to keep from the local inspector. When questioned about these, his answers resulted in official approval from the inspector for the modifications.&lt;ref name=Fly3/&gt;

Reeve received a letter from [[Bradford Washburn]] in January 1937 asking if he could fly a party of climbers to the glacier at the base of [[Mount Lucania]] in Canada. Reeve agreed to undertake the task. In April, the bulk of the supplies were flown in. When he flew Washburn and [[Robert Bates (mountaineer)|Robert Bates]] to the site, the weather had turned unseasonably warm and the plane sank up to its belly in slush. It was over a week before Reeve could take off, after the temperature had dropped sufficiently for a crust of ice to form over the slush. The trip was described by Reeve as the "most hazardous" of his career, but he had set a new world record of {{convert|8750|ft|m}} for the highest landing on skis, more than {{convert|1800|ft|m}} higher than any in either the [[Arctic]] or [[Antarctic]].&lt;ref name=Fly3/&gt;

The day after the Washburn trip, the engine of the Fairchild 51 quit. Reeve spent eight months repairing the [[Wright Whirlwind]] engine, but never put it back in the aircraft. He was now back to only one. Reeve made his last glacier landing in 1938, when he flew Brad Washburn to the [[Mount Marcus Baker|Mount Marcus Glacier]]. His brother Richard was killed in a plane crash in 1938 and in the spring of 1939 a storm overturned the Fairchild 71. He spent all summer repairing it, only for the hangar to burn down with the aircraft inside. Reeve bought another Fairchild 71 and spent a further month repairing it. At this time, the [[Civil Aeronautics Administration (United States)|CAA]] came in to regulate flying in Alaska. Pilots were assigned routes under a "[[grandfather rights]]" scheme based on the territory they had served for four months prior to August 22, 1938. Reeve was given a small area around [[Copper River (Alaska)|Copper River]]. The work available wouldn't support a growing family (at this time they had two children, Richard and Roberta) so they left Valdez in January 1941 for Fairbanks.&lt;ref name=Fly3/&gt;

==The war years==
Reeve arrived in Fairbanks and had to borrow $65 to pay his first month's rent. [[Noel Wien]] gave Reeve his first charter, and a lifelong friendship was formed. In April 1941, Reeve was one of a few pilots in Alaska without a certified route, and was hired by the CAA to survey the many new airfields planned to be built as part of [[Hap Arnold]]'s master plan for Alaska's defense. While the Army and Navy concentrated on building bases at Anchorage and in the [[Aleutian Islands]], the CAA was responsible for constructing the airfields in the interior.&lt;ref name=Fly4&gt;{{cite book | first = Stan| last = Cohen| year = 1988| title = Flying Beats Work: The Story of Reeve Aleutian Airways| chapter = Chapter 4| publisher = Pictorial Histories Publishing Company| location = Missoula, Montana| isbn = 0-933126-98-0}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The first to be built was the airfield at Northway, {{convert|100|mi|km}} east of Fairbanks. The contractors were the [[Morrison-Knudsen]] company (M-K). Supplies were trucked via the [[Richardson Highway]] and a summer trail to the Nasbena Mines, 60 miles from the airfield site, and then flown by Reeve to [[Northway, Alaska|Northway]], where an [[airstrip]] had been hacked out of the woods. Some items had to be cut into two or three pieces and re-welded at the destination as they were too big or heavy for the Fairchild.&lt;ref name=Fly4/&gt;

Although Reeve was working from dawn to dusk, he couldn't keep up with demand for supplies at Northway, and a backlog built up at Nabesna. M-K ordered a [[Boeing 80]]A and Reeve was sent to [[Seattle]] to collect it. It took five weeks to modify the plane, and when he returned with it to Northway, found a {{convert|3000|ft|m}} runway at what was now Reeve Field. The 80A was designed to haul {{convert|4000|lb|kg}} but Reeve soon found he could haul {{convert|7000|lb|kg}} in it. Reeve was again flying from dawn to dusk, sometimes on only two engines.&lt;ref name=Fly4/&gt;

With the money earned from the CAA contract, Reeve ordered three more aircraft. He bought another Boeing 80A, a [[Hamilton H-47|Hamilton Metalplane]] and another Fairchild 71. The army wanted him to survey a route for a [[railroad]] from [[Prince George, BC]], to Nome. Reeve took the surveyors along the route but on the homeward trip the aircraft—a Fairchild—broke through the ice on the [[Kluane Lake]]. The aircraft was abandoned but the mission successfully completed. The pass was named Reeve Pass, it is located between Francis Lake and the Salmon River. The Fairchild was left at [[Burwash Landing]], and Reeve hired a pilot to fly the Hamilton from Washington to Alaska. The plane crashed in Washington, killing the pilot and Reeve was broke again, not having enough money even to buy the fuel to fly the Boeing to Alaska. He managed to borrow money from the Pacific National Bank despite them having a rule never to lend to bush pilots.&lt;ref name=Fly4/&gt;

[[File:Fairchild FC-2W ExCC.jpg|thumb|Fairchild FC-2W-2.]]
Reeve flew back to [[Juneau]] unannounced, and was almost shot down because he didn't identify himself. He returned to working for the CAA, now earning $80 an hour with fuel supplied flying supplies, materials and workers to the new airfields being constructed at [[Big Delta]], [[Tanacross, Alaska|Tanacross]], [[Galena, Alaska|Galena]], Moses Point and Nome, doing all the flying and maintenance himself and regularly working 15-hour days. In November 1942 Reeve signed a contract with the [[Alaska Communications System]] (ACS) and moved his family to [[Anchorage]]. The contract with ACS involved flying all over Alaska, the Aleutians and western Canada. On July 5, 1943, Reeve was flying radar equipment and four technicians from Cold Bay to [[Amchitka]] when he ran into zero-zero visibility conditions. During 1942 Reeve purchased a Fairchild FC-2W-2. A forced landing was made 20 miles east of Cold Bay. Reeve managed to salvage his radio, but the uninsured plane was written off. The delay in the delivery of the radar parts allowed the [[Japan]]ese to evacuate [[Kiska]] undetected, which may have saved American lives, as when US forces landed on Kiska they found it deserted. Previously the [[Aleutian Islands Campaign|Battle of Attu]] had cost 500 lives.&lt;ref name=Fly4/&gt;&lt;ref name=Fleet&gt;[https://www.webcitation.org/query?url=http://www.geocities.com/alaskanheritage/REEVEFLEET.html&amp;date=2009-10-25+12:16:21 geocities] Reeve fleet list.&lt;/ref&gt;

Reeve's thoughts turned to post-war activities. He knew he would need bigger, faster planes and thought his best hope would be to pick an area that no-one else wanted. Reeve bought a hardware store on Fourth Avenue, Anchorage. An old friend, Carl Whitham came to Anchorage, and they formed a partnership to develop some of Whitham's old prospects. Whitham died of cancer in the spring and Reeve's prospecting days were over.&lt;ref name=Fly4/&gt;

In 1946, Reeve formed ''Reeve Aleutian Airways'' and was its president until his death in 1980. He allowed his pilots license to lapse in 1948 after he caught himself missing an item on a checklist. Reeve was invited to run for territorial governor of Alaska in 1952, but decided against this due to a conflict of interests. Reeve received an honorary Doctor of Science degree at the [[University of Alaska]] in 1963. Reeve was named "Alaskan of the Year" in 1972 and inducted into the [[National Aviation Hall of Fame]] in 1975. He was made honorary Mayor of [[Shemya]] in 1978. He died on August 25, 1980, and in that year was inducted into the International Aerospace Hall of Fame. The Alaska Aviation Heritage Museum inducted Reeve into the Alaska Aviation Pioneer Hall of Fame on February 25, 2005. The Bob Reeve High School in Adak, Alaska was named after him.&lt;ref name=Hall/&gt;&lt;ref name=Fly5&gt;{{cite book | first = Stan| last = Cohen| year = 1988| title = Flying Beats Work: The Story of Reeve Aleutian Airways| chapter = Epilogue| publisher = Pictorial Histories Publishing Company| location = Missoula, Montana| isbn = 0-933126-98-0}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=Fame&gt;[http://www.alaskajournal.com/stories/022005/hom_20050220002.shtml Alaska Journal of Commerce] Story {{webarchive |url=https://web.archive.org/web/20050313234430/http://www.alaskajournal.com/stories/022005/hom_20050220002.shtml |date=March 13, 2005 }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=Fame2&gt;[http://www.afa.org/magazine/hall_of_fame/ Airforce Magazine] {{webarchive |url=https://web.archive.org/web/20071218080317/http://www.afa.org/magazine/hall_of_fame/ |date=December 18, 2007 }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=Fame3&gt;[http://www.allstar.fiu.edu/aero/reeve.htm Allstar] International Aerospace HoF entry.&lt;/ref&gt;

In 1980, Reeve was inducted into the [[International Air &amp; Space Hall of Fame]] at the [[San Diego Air &amp; Space Museum]].&lt;ref&gt;Sprekelmeyer, Linda, editor. ''These We Honor: The International Aerospace Hall of Fame''. Donning Co. Publishers, 2006. [[International Standard Book Number|ISBN]] [[Special:BookSources/978-1-57864-397-4|978-1-57864-397-4]].&lt;/ref&gt;

==Personal life==
Bob and Tilly Reeve had five children: Richard, Roberta, Janice, David, and Whitham. Richard would become President of ''Reeve Aleutian'' upon the death of his father, Janice remained as a Vice President of the airline, Roberta married famed bush pilot [[Donald Sheldon|Don Sheldon]], Whitham formed his own engineering business, and David became Senior Vice President of Midwest Airlines and President/CEO of Skyway Airlines in Milwaukee, WI.

==Aircraft==
Reeve's aircraft included:

===Boeing 80A===
* '''NC224M''' c/n 1082. Ex [[Boeing Air Transport]] (United Air Lines). Rebuilt as an 80A-1 in 1930. To Monterey Peninsula Airways in 1939, then via Charles H Babb to the Morrison-Knudsen Construction Company. Accident on March 21, 1943, at Anchorage, repaired with parts from NC229M. Given to Reeve in 1946, sat outside Reeve's hangar until 1960 when hauled to the Anchorage landfill. Rescued before being buried and passed to Boeing Management Association. Aircraft and spares flown to McChord Air Base near Seattle and stored. Eventually restored by Pacific Northwest Aviation Historical Foundation at Auburn and displayed at the [[Museum of Flight]], Seattle. It is the sole surviving Boeing 80.&lt;ref name=Fly4/&gt;&lt;ref name=Leeuw&gt;[http://www.ruudleeuw.com/spl-olddays.htm Ruud Leeuw] Photo of restored aircraft.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=Coates&gt;[http://www.edcoatescollection.com/ac3/Airline/Reeve%20Airways%20Boeing%2080A.html Ed Coates] Photo&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=Reg4&gt;[http://www.aerofiles.com/regs-m.html Aerofiles] Registration details.&lt;/ref&gt;
* '''NC229M''' c/n 1087. Parts from this aircraft were used to repair NC224M after that aircraft had been involved in an accident on March 21, 1943, at Anchorage.&lt;ref name=Fly4/&gt;&lt;ref name=Reg4/&gt;
* '''NC793K''' c/n 1081. Purchased 1942, written off near Cold Bay, Alaska July 5, 1943.&lt;ref name=Coates/&gt;&lt;ref name=Geo&gt;[https://www.webcitation.org/query?url=http://www.geocities.com/alaskanheritage/REEVEFLEET.html&amp;date=2009-10-25+12:16:21 geocities]&lt;/ref&gt;

===Hamilton Metalplane===
Reeve purchased a Hamilton Metalplane, but it crashed on the delivery flight.&lt;ref name=Air&gt;[http://www.airliners.net/open.file?id=0617819&amp;WxsIERv=Unzvygba%20Zrgnycynar%20U47&amp;Wm=0&amp;WdsYXMg=Abegujrfg%20Nveyvarf&amp;QtODMg=Fbhgu%20Fg%20Cnhy%20Zhavpvcny%20%96%20Syrzvat%20Svryq%20%28FTF%29&amp;ERDLTkt=HFN%20-%20Zvaarfbgn&amp;ktODMp=Whar%2022%2C%202004&amp;BP=1&amp;WNEb25u=Enycu%20Z.%20Crggrefra&amp;xsIERvdWdsY=AP879U&amp;MgTUQtODMgKE=Uvqqra%20njnl%20va%20n%20unatne%20V%20sbhaq%20guvf%20trz%20bs%20na%20nvecynar.%20Abegujrfg%20Nveyvarf%20syrj%20gurz%20va%20gur%201920%27f%2F30%27f.&amp;YXMgTUQtODMgKERD=2332&amp;NEb25uZWxs=2004-07-10%2000%3A00%3A00&amp;ODJ9dvCE=&amp;O89Dcjdg=65&amp;static=yes&amp;width=1024&amp;height=717&amp;sok=JURER%20%20%28nvepensg%20%3D%20%27Unzvygba%20Zrgnycynar%20U47%27%29%20%20BEQRE%20OL%20cubgb_vq%20QRFP&amp;photo_nr=1&amp;prev_id=&amp;next_id=0617818 Airliners.net] Photo of a similar aircraft.&lt;/ref&gt;

===Lockheed Vega 5B===
* '''N9424''' Reeve flew a Lockheed Vega when with Panagra in South America. An accident at Santiago led to his resignation and move to Alaska. He is pictured in front of N9424 in ''Flying Beats Work''.&lt;ref name=Fly2/&gt;

===Fairchild 51===
* '''NC5364''' c/n 102.&lt;ref name=Reg3&gt;[http://www.aerofiles.com/regs-5000.html Aerofiles] Registration details.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=Alaska&gt;[http://vilda.alaska.edu/cdm4/item_viewer.php?CISOROOT=/cdmg13&amp;CISOPTR=1186&amp;REC=20 Alaska.edu] Photograph of aircraft.&lt;/ref&gt;

===Fairchild 71===
* '''NC119H''' c/n 675. Ex Marine Airways. Bought in the winter if 1939/40 to replace NC9745.&lt;ref name=Thou&gt;[http://1000aircraftphotos.com/Contributions/Opland/4440.htm 1000 Aircraft photos] Picture of NC119H.&lt;/ref&gt;
* '''NC9745''' c/n 611. This was the aircraft that was blown over, then destroyed in a hangar fire when repairs were nearly complete.&lt;ref name=Thou/&gt;&lt;ref name=Reg2&gt;[http://www.aerofiles.com/regs-9000.html Aerofiles] Registration details.&lt;/ref&gt;

===Fairchild FC-2W-2===
* '''NC7034''' c/n 136. Ex Utah Oil Refining Company. Bought by Reeve in 1941/42, the frame of the [[fuselage]] is currently on display at the Alaska Aviation Heritage Museum.&lt;ref name=Thou2&gt;[http://1000aircraftphotos.com/Contributions/Opland/6968.htm 1000 Aircraft photos] Color photo of aircraft.&lt;/ref&gt;

===Ford Tri-motor===
* '''NC8416''' c/n 54.&lt;ref name=Reg&gt;[http://www.aerofiles.com/regs-8000.html Aerofiles] Registration details.&lt;/ref&gt;

==References==
{{reflist}}

==Further reading==
* Romulo, Beth Day. ''Glacier pilot: The Story of Bob Reeve and the flyers who Pushed Back Alaska's Air Frontiers''.

{{Aviation in Wisconsin}}
{{Authority control}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Reeve, Robert Campbell}}
[[Category:1902 births]]
[[Category:1980 deaths]]
[[Category:Alaska Republicans]]
[[Category:Aviation accidents and incidents in Alaska]]
[[Category:History of aviation]]
[[Category:Aviation pioneers]]
[[Category:Aviators from Alaska]]
[[Category:Aviators from Wisconsin]]
[[Category:Bush pilots]]
[[Category:Businesspeople from Anchorage, Alaska]]
[[Category:Businesspeople in aviation]]
[[Category:National Aviation Hall of Fame inductees]]
[[Category:People from Dane County, Wisconsin]]
[[Category:Businesspeople from Milwaukee]]
[[Category:People from Valdez, Alaska]]
[[Category:University of Wisconsin–Madison alumni]]
[[Category:20th-century American businesspeople]]
[[Category:American aviation record holders]]</text>
      <sha1>qag3kct9afynbm54sq2v9rnav0s9nh6</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
