<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10.xsd" version="0.10" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <dbname>enwiki</dbname>
    <base>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.32.0-wmf.16</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="118" case="first-letter">Draft</namespace>
      <namespace key="119" case="first-letter">Draft talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2300" case="first-letter">Gadget</namespace>
      <namespace key="2301" case="first-letter">Gadget talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2302" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition</namespace>
      <namespace key="2303" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>W. E. Johns</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>341912</id>
    <revision>
      <id>851011518</id>
      <parentid>846894391</parentid>
      <timestamp>2018-07-19T13:26:46Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <ip>114.77.48.55</ip>
      </contributor>
      <comment>/* Early life */Added content</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="17039">{{for|the American operatic tenor|William Johns}}
{{Use dmy dates|date=April 2012}}
{{Infobox writer &lt;!-- for more information see [[:Template:Infobox writer/doc]] --&gt;
| name = William Earl Johns
| image =
| pseudonym = Captain W. E. Johns
| birth_date = {{Birth date|1893|2|5|df=yes}}
| birth_place = [[Bengeo]], [[Hertford]], United Kingdom
| death_date = {{death date and age|1968|6|21|1893|2|5|df=y}}
| death_place = [[London Borough of Richmond upon Thames]], United Kingdom
| subject = Aviation
| occupation = Aviator, author, editor
| nationality = [[United Kingdom|British]]
| genre = [[Adventure fiction]], [[War fiction]], [[Science Fiction]]
| notableworks =
| spouse=Maude Penelope Hunt (m. 1914)
| partner=Doris May Leigh
| children=William Earl Carmichael Johns (1916–1954)&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.popularflying.com/Covers/19/ |title=POPULAR FLYING MAGAZINE – ISSUE 1 (0F 88) |website=Popularflying.com |date= |accessdate=2016-11-19}}&lt;/ref&gt;
| period=1922–68
}}

'''William Earl Johns''' (5 February 1893{{spaced ndash}}21 June 1968) was an English First World War [[Aviator|pilot]], and writer of adventure stories, usually written under the [[pen name]] '''Captain W. E. Johns'''. He was the creator of the fictional air-adventurer ''[[Biggles]]''.

==Early life==
Johns was born in [[Bengeo]], [[Hertford]], England, the son of Richard Eastman Johns, a fabric tailor, and Elizabeth Johns ([[Married and maiden names|née]] Earl), the daughter of a master butcher. A younger brother, Russell Ernest Johns, was born on 24 October 1895. Johns' early ambition was to be a soldier, and he was a crack shot with a rifle. From January 1905, he attended [[Richard Hale School|Hertford Grammar School]].&lt;ref name=johns&gt;{{cite web | url=http://www.wejohns.com/Biography/Biography1/ | title=A Brief Biography of Captain W. E. Johns  Part One | website=Wejohns.com | accessdate=17 October 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt; He also attended evening classes at the local art school.

Johns was not a natural scholar. He included some of his experiences at this school in his book ''Biggles Goes to School'' (1951). In the summer of 1907 he was [[Apprenticeship|apprenticed]] to a county municipal [[Surveying|surveyor]] for four years and in 1912 was appointed as a sanitary inspector in [[Swaffham]] in [[Norfolk]]. Soon afterwards, his father died of [[tuberculosis]] at the age of 47. On 6 October 1914 Johns married Maude Penelope Hunt (1882–1961), the daughter of the Rev. John Hunt, vicar of [[Little Dunham]], Norfolk.&lt;ref name=johns/&gt; Their only son, William Earl Carmichael Johns, was born in March 1916.

==Military career and the First World War ==
In 1913, while living in [[Swaffham]], and working as a sanitary inspector, Johns enlisted in the [[Territorial Army (United Kingdom)|Territorial Army]] as a [[Trooper (rank)|trooper]] in the [[Norfolk Yeomanry|King's Own Royal Regiment (Norfolk Yeomanry)]].  The regiment was mobilised in August 1914 and was sent overseas in September 1915, embarking on [[RMS Olympic|RMS ''Olympic'']].  The Norfolk Yeomanry fought (as infantry) at [[Battle of Gallipoli|Gallipoli]] until December when they were withdrawn to [[Egypt]].  In September 1916 Johns transferred to the [[Machine Gun Corps]]. While serving on the [[Macedonian front (World War I)|Macedonian front]] in [[Greece]] he was hospitalised with [[malaria]].  After recovering, he was commissioned into the [[Royal Flying Corps]] (RFC) in September 1917 as a temporary [[second lieutenant]]&lt;ref name="LG 19 October 1917"&gt;{{London Gazette |issue=30347 |date=19 October 1917 |page=10886 }}&lt;/ref&gt;  and posted back to England for flight training.

Johns undertook his initial flying training at the short-lived airfield at [[Coley Park]] in [[Reading, Berkshire|Reading]], flying the [[Farman MF.11|Farman MF.11 Shorthorn]] aircraft. He was then posted to No.25 Flying Training School at [[Thetford]] in Norfolk, closer to where his wife Maude and son Jack were living.&lt;ref name=cpabac&gt;{{cite web | title = The Coley Park Aerodrome and CWS Jam Works | url = http://www.users.on.net/~kevros/coleypark/oc_aerocws.htm | publisher = Coley Park &amp; Beyond (Kevin Rosier)|website=Users.on.net | accessdate =15 February 2008}}&lt;/ref&gt;
 
On 1 April 1918, Johns was appointed flying instructor at [[Marske-by-the-Sea]] in [[Cleveland, England|Cleveland]]. The aircraft of the time were very unreliable and he wrote off three planes in three days through engine failure – crashing into the sea, then the sand, and then through a fellow officer's back door. Later, he was caught in fog over the [[Tees]], missed [[Hartlepool]] and narrowly escaped flying into a cliff. Shooting one's own propeller off with a forward-mounted machine-gun with malfunctioning [[synchronization gear|synchronisation]] was a fairly common accident, and it happened to Johns twice. The Commanding Officer at Marske was a Major Champion, known as 'Gimlet', a name used later by Johns for the hero of a series of stories. During this time Johns's probationary commission was confirmed&lt;ref&gt;{{London Gazette |issue=30887 |date=6 September 1918 |page=10551}}&lt;/ref&gt; and he served as a flying instructor until August 1918 when he transferred to the [[Western Front (World War I)|Western Front]].

He performed six weeks of active duty as a bomber pilot with [[No. 55 Squadron RAF]], close to the average in the latter part of the war.&lt;ref&gt;H.A.Jones. ''War in the Air''. Naval and Military Press; New edition (8 Oct 2002)&lt;/ref&gt; This squadron was part of the [[Independent Air Force]], a section of the Royal Air Force that had been formed for the purpose of bombing strategic targets deep inside Germany.

On 16 September 1918 he was piloting one of six [[De Havilland DH4]]s on their way to bomb [[Mannheim]] when his aircraft was hit by anti-aircraft fire and he was forced to drop out of formation. He jettisoned his single {{convert|250|lb|kg|adj=on}} bomb and turned for home, but was attacked by a number of [[Fokker D.VII]] fighters. During a lengthy but one-sided battle, Johns' observer and rear-gunner, Second Lieutenant Alfred Edward Amey, was badly wounded and the aircraft shot down. The victory was credited to [[Georg Weiner]], the commander of [[Jagdstaffel 3]].&lt;ref name="Hart" /&gt; Johns and Amey were taken prisoner by German troops: Johns received a leg wound during the battle and was slightly injured in the crash, but Amey died of his injuries later that day.&lt;ref name="Hart"&gt;{{cite book | title=Aces Falling: War Above The Trenches, 1918 | publisher=W&amp;N | author=Hart, Peter | year=2007 | page=278 | isbn=0297846531}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="auction"&gt;{{cite web | url=http://www.invaluable.com/auction-lot/medals-royal-flying-corps-biggles-observer-s-casu-1-c-h46sfkylnv | title=Bosleys 2005, Lot 556 | website=Invaluable.com | accessdate=16 October 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt; Johns was a prisoner of war until the end of the war (November 1918).&lt;ref group="Note"&gt;Amey's medals were sold at auction in the United Kingdom in 2005, in a lot that included a letter to his family from Johns, describing the circumstances of his death ''(see: Bosleys 2005, Lot 556)''. In the preface of ''Biggles Pioneer Air Fighter'' (1954), Jones noted that this had been Amey's very first sortie, and he hadn't even had time to unpack his things after arriving at the squadron's base.&lt;/ref&gt;

After the war, Johns remained in the [[Royal Air Force]], apparently with the substantive rank of [[Pilot Officer]].&lt;ref group="Note"&gt;It was common for officers continuing in the service after the war to take a lower rank than that held during the conflict, but it does seem highly unlikely he had ever held the rank of "Captain" in the RFC (equivalent to [[Flight Lieutenant]] in the RAF), even on an "acting" basis.&lt;/ref&gt; His promotion to the rank of [[Flying Officer]] was [[gazetted]] on 23 November 1920.&lt;ref name="LG 30 November 1920"&gt;{{London Gazette |issue=32145 |date=30 November 1920 |page=11823 }}&lt;/ref&gt; Johns worked in central London as a recruiting officer&lt;ref name=johns2&gt;{{cite web | url=http://www.wejohns.com/Biography/Biography2/ | title=A Brief Biography of Captain W. E. Johns  Part Two | website=Wejohns.com | accessdate=17 October 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt; and rejected [[T. E. Lawrence]] (of Arabia) as an RAF recruit for obviously giving a false name, but was later ordered to accept him.&lt;ref&gt;Biography of Johns, ''[[Oxford Dictionary of National Biography]]''&lt;/ref&gt;

By 1923, Johns had left his wife. His RAF commission had been extended a further four years and he had moved to [[Birmingham]], again working as a recruitment officer. In Birmingham  he met Doris 'Dol' May Leigh&lt;ref name=johns2 /&gt; (1900–1969), daughter of Alfred Broughton Leigh. They later moved to [[Newcastle upon Tyne]] when Johns was posted there. Although he never divorced Maude Hunt, Doris Leigh was known as 'Mrs Johns' until her death. Johns continued to pay for his wife and son's upkeep and for her nursing care (she suffered from acute arthritis).&lt;ref name=johns2 /&gt;

On 15 October 1927, he was transferred to the reserves.&lt;ref name="LG 11 October 1927"&gt;{{London Gazette |issue=33319 |date=11 October 1927 |page=6402 }}&lt;/ref&gt; Four years later, on 15 October 1931, he relinquished his commission.&lt;ref name="LG 22 December 1931"&gt;{{London Gazette |issue=33782 |date=22 December 1931 |page=8260 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Writing==
{{see also|List of works by W. E. Johns}}
&lt;!-- Commented out: [[File:Biggles of 266 cover.jpg|thumb|right|Cover of ''Biggles of 266'']] --&gt;
W. E. Johns was a prolific author and editor. In his 46-year writing career (1922–68) he penned over 160 books, including nearly one hundred Biggles books, more than sixty other novels and factual books, and scores of magazine articles and short stories.

His first novel, ''Mossyface'',&lt;ref group="Note"&gt;Mossy Face, was a name given by the Allies to [[Havrincourt|Havrincourt Wood]], it is mentioned in some of the Biggles stories and in some pilot's memoirs of the period.&lt;/ref&gt; was published in 1922 under the pen name "William Earle". After leaving the RAF, Johns became a newspaper air correspondent, as well as editing and illustrating books about flying. At the request of John Hamilton Ltd, he created the magazine ''Popular Flying'' which first appeared in March 1932. It was in the pages of ''Popular Flying'' that Biggles first appeared.

The first Biggles book, ''The Camels are Coming'',&lt;ref group="Note"&gt;The [[Sopwith Camel]] aeroplane, not the animal&lt;/ref&gt; was published in August 1932 and Johns would continue to write Biggles stories until his death in 1968. At first, the Biggles stories were credited to "William Earle", but later Johns adopted the more familiar "Capt. W. E. Johns". While his apparent final RAF rank of [[flying officer]] was equivalent to an army (or RFC) lieutenant, [[captain]] is commonly used for the commander of a vessel or aircraft.&lt;ref group="Note"&gt;Nonetheless, in a pen name Johns was entitled to any rank he might have chosen!&lt;/ref&gt;

Johns was also a regular contributor to ''[[Modern Boy]]'' magazine in the late 1930s as well as editing (and writing for) both ''Popular Flying'' and ''[[Flying (magazine)|Flying]]''. From the early 1930s Johns called for the training of more pilots, for if there were not enough when war came, "training would have to be rushed, and under-trained airmen would die in accidents or in combat against better trained German pilots."&lt;ref&gt;[https://www.independent.co.uk/voices/comment/biggles-flies-uncensored-more-whisky-less-jingoism-8944480.html Patrick Cockburn, "Biggles flies uncensored: more whisky, less jingoism." ''[[The Independent]]'', Sunday 17 November 2013] Retrieved 23 November 2013.&lt;/ref&gt;  He was removed as editor at the beginning of 1939, probably as a direct result of a scathing editorial, strongly opposed to the policy of [[Appeasement of Hitler|appeasement]] and highly critical of several [[Conservative Party (UK)#1920-1963|Conservative]] statesmen of the time.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.popularflying.com/Covers/81/ |title=POPULAR FLYING MAGAZINE – ISSUE 1 (0F 88) |website=Popularflying.com |date= |accessdate=2016-11-19}}&lt;/ref&gt; Cockburn, however, feels that the government was concerned about being so "expertly attacked" on the lack of trained pilots by the editor of the most widely read aviation magazines in the world, including readers "in the RAF or connected with flying."&lt;ref&gt;Cockburn 2013.&lt;/ref&gt;

Johns' opposition to appeasement is reflected in some of his books. For example, in ''The Black Peril'' (1935) the storyline revolves around German preparations for conquest. Even more advanced in his thinking, for that time, was the story ''Biggles Air Commodore'' (1937) which alludes to Japanese preparations for conquest of British colonies in the Far East.

Apart from "Biggles", his other multi-volume fiction series were:

* The 6-volume "Steeley" series (1936–1939), featuring former First World War pilot turned crime-fighter Deeley Montfort Delaroy (nicknamed "Steeley").
* The 11-volume "[[Worrals]]" series (1941–1950), detailing the exploits of plucky WAAF [[Flight Officer]] Joan "Worrals" Worralson (who was also the subject of three short stories); these were created at the request of the [[Air Ministry]] to inspire young women to join the [[Women's Auxiliary Air Force]].
* The 10-volume "Gimlet" series (1943–1954), whose hero is the dashing British [[commando]] [[Captain Lorrington "Gimlet" King]].
* A 10-volume science fiction series (1954–1963) that follows the interplanetary adventures of retired RAF Group Captain Timothy 'Tiger' Clinton, his son Rex, scientist Professor Lucius Brane (who invents a spaceship powered by [[cosmic rays]]) and Brane's resourceful butler Judkins.

Johns also wrote eight other books of juvenile fiction, twelve books of fiction for adults, and eight factual books, including several books on aviation, books on pirates and treasure hunting, and a book on gardening, ''The Passing Show''.

Unusually among children's writers of the time, from 1935 Johns employed a working-class character as an equal member of the Biggles team – "Ginger" Habblethwaite, later Hebblethwaite, the son of a Northumberland miner. However, readers never learn his real Christian name, and he proclaims himself a Yorkshireman once or twice.

==Death==
W. E. Johns died on 21 June 1968 in his 76th year. Shortly before his death he was writing the final Biggles story, entitled ''Biggles does some Homework'', which shows Biggles at last preparing to retire, and meeting his [[Multiracial|mixed-race]] replacement. The twelve chapters written were issued privately in 1997.&lt;ref name = Homework&gt;{{cite web | url = http://www.biggles.info/Details/97/ | title = Biggles does some homework – plot summary |website=Biggles.info| accessdate = 2010-02-03 | date = 2006-07-26 | last = Harris | first = R }}&lt;/ref&gt; 

Johns' body was cremated at the [[Kingston-upon-Thames]] Crematorium, on Bonner Hill.&lt;ref&gt;Entry for W.E Johns in [[Findagrave]]. https://www.findagrave.com/memorial/35221044&lt;/ref&gt;

==Personal life==
From 1953  Johns resided at Park House, Hampton Court Road, at [[Hampton Court]] in [[Middlesex]].&lt;ref&gt;'London mansion where the Biggles' children's books were written by Capt. W.E Johns goes on sale', 'Daily Mail', 19 October 2015. http://www.dailymail.co.uk/news/article-3279043/The-mansion-daring-adventures-Biggles-written-author-Captain-William-Earl-Johns-gone-sale-3-75-million.html&lt;/ref&gt;

==Biography==
''By Jove, Biggles!'', a biography of Johns, was published in 1981, written by [[Peter Berresford Ellis]] and Piers Williams. It was republished as ''Biggles! The Life Story of Capt. W. E. Johns'' (Veloce Publishing, 1993, {{ISBN|187410526X}}).

==Notes==
{{reflist|group=Note|colwidth=60em}}

==References==
{{Reflist|30em}}

==External links==
* [http://www.wejohns.com/ Website covering all W. E. Johns' books]
* [http://www.biggles.info/ The Biggles Information website]
* [http://bigglesforum.net/ Biggles Forum] Biggles Forum: Capt W. E. Johns reference and community
* [http://www.collectingbooksandmagazines.com/captain.html ''W. E. Johns and Biggles'' on the Collecting Books and Magazines website]
* [http://www.wejas.org.uk/ wejas.org.uk, Website celebrating W. E. Johns – the man and his work]
* [https://www.mirror.co.uk/news/uk-news/how-boys-hero-biggles-helped-6296218 "How boys' own hero Biggles helped train the RAF pilots who won the Battle of Britain"]

{{Authority control}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Johns, W. E.}}
[[Category:1893 births]]
[[Category:1968 deaths]]
[[Category:British Army personnel of World War I]]
[[Category:British World War I prisoners of war]]
[[Category:Norfolk Yeomanry soldiers]]
[[Category:Machine Gun Corps soldiers]]
[[Category:Royal Air Force officers]]
[[Category:Royal Air Force personnel of World War I]]
[[Category:Royal Flying Corps officers]]
[[Category:World War I prisoners of war held by Germany]]
[[Category:People from Hertford]]
[[Category:People educated at Hertford Grammar School]]
[[Category:Shot-down aviators]]</text>
      <sha1>bzzhk653tlj6n6xgi6dj0g2uvt9jsb4</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
