<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10.xsd" version="0.10" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <dbname>enwiki</dbname>
    <base>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.32.0-wmf.16</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="118" case="first-letter">Draft</namespace>
      <namespace key="119" case="first-letter">Draft talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2300" case="first-letter">Gadget</namespace>
      <namespace key="2301" case="first-letter">Gadget talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2302" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition</namespace>
      <namespace key="2303" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Wiley Post</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>562989</id>
    <revision>
      <id>855819817</id>
      <parentid>855819615</parentid>
      <timestamp>2018-08-21T02:11:14Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Binksternet</username>
        <id>4967956</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>Reverted 1 edit by [[Special:Contributions/78.250.199.214|78.250.199.214]] ([[User talk:78.250.199.214|talk]]): Rv... irrelevant here. ([[WP:TW|TW]])</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="21755">{{for|the airport|Wiley Post Airport}}
{{distinguish|Wally Post}}
&lt;!-- This article is a part of [[Wikipedia:WikiProject Aircraft]]. Please see [[Wikipedia:WikiProject Aircraft/page content]] for recommended layout. --&gt;{{Infobox person
|name=Wiley Post
|image=Wiley Post cph.3b33667.jpg
|image_size=
|caption=
|birth_date=Wiley Hardeman Post&lt;br&gt;{{birth date|1898|11|22|mf=y}}
|birth_place=[[Van Zandt County, Texas]], US
|death_date={{death date and age|1935|8|15|1898|11|22|mf=y}}
|death_place=[[Point Barrow]], [[Alaska]], US
|occupation=[[Aviator]]
|spouse=[[Mae Laine]] (m. June 27, 1927)
|parents=William Francis Post and Mae Quinlan Post
}}
[[File:NASM - Lockheed Vega - Winnie Mae.jpg|thumb|right|240px|"Winnie Mae" a [[Lockheed Vega]] aircraft of Wiley Post, when it was on display at the [[Steven F. Udvar-Hazy Center]]]]

'''Wiley Hardeman Post''' (November 22, 1898 &amp;ndash; August 15, 1935) was a famed American aviator during the [[Aviation between the World Wars|interwar period]], the first [[aviator|pilot]] to fly solo around the world. Also known for his work in high-altitude flying, Post helped develop one of the first [[pressure suit]]s and discovered the [[jet stream]]. On August 15, 1935, Post and American humorist [[Will Rogers]] were killed when Post's aircraft [[Rogers-Post Site|crashed on takeoff]] from a lagoon near [[Point Barrow]] in the [[Territory of Alaska]].

Post{{'}}s [[Lockheed Vega]] aircraft, the ''Winnie Mae'', was on display at the [[National Air and Space Museum]]'s [[Steven F. Udvar-Hazy Center]] from 2003 to 2011. It is now featured in the "Time and Navigation" gallery on the second floor of the [[National Air and Space Museum]] in Washington, D.C.

==Early life==
Post was born to cotton farmer parents, William Francis and Mae Quinlan Post. His family moved to Oklahoma when he was five. He was an indifferent student, but managed to complete the sixth grade. By 1920 his family settled on a farm near [[Maysville, Oklahoma]].&lt;ref name="EOHC-Post"&gt;Carlson. Erik D. [http://www.okhistory.org/publications/enc/entry.php?entry=PO023 "Post, Wiley Hardeman (1898 - 1935)."] ''Encyclopedia of Oklahoma History and Culture''. Retrieved: April 10, 2015.&lt;/ref&gt; {{efn|There is disagreement about Wiley Post's birthplace. Some sources say it was Grand Saline, Texas.&lt;ref&gt;Johnson, Bobby H. [http://www.tshaonline.org/handbook/online/articles/fpo27 "Post, Wiley Hardeman."] ''The Texas State Historical Association''. Retrieved: April 3, 2009.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="EOHC-Post"/&gt; others claim he was born in [[Corinth, Texas|Corinth]], [[Van Zandt County, Texas]].&lt;ref name="EOHC-Post"/&gt; An old edition of the ''World Book'' claims it was Grand Plain Texas. Even Maysville, Oklahoma has claimed the honor.&lt;ref name="Oklahoman"&gt;[http://newsok.com/article/2656579 "Festival Celebrates Wiley Post's Birthplace." ''Oklahoman''. June 10, 1999.] Accessed January 19, 2017.&lt;/ref&gt;}}

Young Wiley's first view of an aircraft in flight came in 1913 at the county fair in [[Lawton, Oklahoma]].  The plane was a Curtiss-Wright "[[Pusher configuration|Pusher type]]". The event so inspired him that he immediately enrolled in the [[Sweeney Automobile School|Sweeney Automobile and Aviation School]] in Kansas City. Seven months later, he returned to Oklahoma and went to work at the Chickasaw and Lawton Construction Company.&lt;ref name="EOHC-Post"/&gt;

During World War I Post wanted to become a pilot in the U.S. Army Air Service (USAS). Joining the training camp at the University of Oklahoma, he learned radio technology. Germany surrendered before he completed his training, the war ended, and he went to work as a "[[roughneck]]" in the Oklahoma oilfields. The work was unsteady and he turned briefly to armed robbery.  He was arrested in 1921 and sent to the [[Oklahoma State Reformatory]].    Serving more than a year in the Oklahoma State Reformatory, he was paroled in the summer of 1922.&lt;ref name="EOHC-Post"/&gt;

==Early flying career==
{{refimprove|section|date=July 2018}}&lt;!--this paragraph and first subsection have no citations--&gt;
Post's aviation career began at age 26 as a parachutist for a flying circus, ''Burrell Tibbs and His Texas Topnotch Fliers,'' and he became well known on the [[barnstorming]] circuit. On October 1, 1926, an oil field accident cost him his left eye, but he used the settlement money to buy his first aircraft. Around this time, he met fellow Oklahoman Will Rogers when he flew Rogers to a rodeo, and the two eventually became close friends. Post was the personal pilot of wealthy Oklahoma oilmen Powell Briscoe and F.C. Hall in 1930 when Hall bought a high-wing, single-engine Lockheed Vega, one of the most famous record-breaking aircraft of the early 1930s. The oilman nicknamed it the ''Winnie Mae'' after his daughter, and Post achieved his first national prominence in it by winning the National Air Race Derby, from Los Angeles to Chicago. The fuselage was inscribed, "Los Angeles to Chicago 9 hrs. 8 min. 2 sec. August 27, 1930." Adam Charles Williams finished second with a time of 9 hrs. 9 min. 4 sec.

===Around the world===
[[File:Bundesarchiv Bild 102-11928, Ozeanflieger Wiley Post und Harold Gatty.jpg|thumb|220px|left|Wiley Post with Harold Gatty in Germany, 1931]]

In 1930, [[Circumnavigation world record progression|the record]] for [[Circumnavigation|flying around the world]] was not held by a fixed-wing aircraft, but by the [[LZ 127 Graf Zeppelin|''Graf Zeppelin'']], piloted by [[Hugo Eckener]] in 1929 with a time of 21&amp;nbsp;days. On June 23, 1931, Post and his navigator, [[Harold Gatty]], left [[Roosevelt Field]] on [[Long Island, New York]], in the ''Winnie Mae'' with a flight plan that would take them around the world, stopping at [[Harbour Grace, Newfoundland and Labrador|Harbour Grace]], [[RAF Sealand|Flintshire]], [[Hanover]] twice, [[Berlin Tempelhof Airport|Berlin]], [[Khodynka Aerodrome|Moscow]], [[Novosibirsk]], [[Irkutsk]], [[Blagoveshchensk]], [[Khabarovsk]], [[Nome, Alaska|Nome]], where his propeller had to be repaired, [[Fairbanks, Alaska|Fairbanks]] where the propeller was replaced, [[Edmonton City Centre (Blatchford Field) Airport|Edmonton]], and [[Cleveland Hopkins International Airport|Cleveland]] before returning to Roosevelt Field. They arrived back on July 1, after traveling {{convert|15474|miles|km}} in the record time of 8&amp;nbsp;days and 15 hours and 51 minutes, in the first successful aerial circumnavigation by a single-engined monoplane. The reception they received rivaled [[Charles Lindbergh]]'s everywhere they went. They had lunch at the [[White House]] on July 6, rode in a [[ticker-tape parade]] the next day in New York City, and were honored at a banquet given by the Aeronautical Chamber of Commerce of America at the [[Hotel Astor]]. After the flight, Post acquired the ''Winnie Mae'' from F.C. Hall, and he and Gatty published an account of their journey titled, ''Around the World in Eight Days,'' with an introduction by Will Rogers.

===First solo pilot===
After the record-setting flight, Post wanted to open his own aeronautical school, but could not raise enough financial support because of doubts many had about his rural background and limited formal education. Motivated by his detractors, Post decided to attempt a solo flight around the world and to break his previous speed record. Over the next year, Post improved his aircraft by installing an [[autopilot]] device and a [[radio direction finder]] that were in their final stages of development by the [[Sperry Corporation|Sperry Gyroscope Company]] and the [[United States Army]]. In 1933, he repeated his flight around the world, this time using the auto-pilot and compass in place of his navigator and becoming the first to accomplish the feat alone. He departed from [[Floyd Bennett Field]] and continued on to Berlin where repairs were attempted to his autopilot, stopped at [[Kaliningrad Devau Airport|Königsberg]] to replace some forgotten maps, Moscow for more repairs to his autopilot, Novosibirsk, Irkutsk for final repairs to the autopilot, [[Skovorodino, Amur Oblast|Rukhlovo]], Khabarovsk, [[Flat, Alaska|Flat]] where his propeller had to be replaced, Fairbanks, Edmonton, and back to Floyd Bennett Field.  Fifty thousand people greeted him on his return on July 22 after 7&amp;nbsp;days, 18 hours, 49 minutes&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.firstflight.org/shrine/wiley_post.php "Wiley H. Post."] ''First Flight Society.'' Retrieved: December 6, 2012. - 21 hours less than his previous record, and he was given a second ticker-tape parade in New York.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Meunier, Claude. [http://www.soloflights.org/post_data_e.html "WILEY POST."] ''Solo flights around the world,'' October 15, 2007. Retrieved: December 6, 2012.&lt;/ref&gt;

==Pressure suit==
[[File:Wiley Post.jpg|thumb|upright|Wiley Post in his third pressure suit]]

In 1934, with financial support from [[Frank Phillips (oil industrialist)|Frank Phillips]] of the [[ConocoPhillips|Phillips Petroleum Company]], Post began exploring the limits of high-altitude long-distance flight. The Winnie Mae's cabin could not be pressurized, so he worked with Russell S. Colley of the [[BF Goodrich|B.F. Goodrich Company]] to develop what became the world's first practical [[pressure suit]]. Three pressure suits were fabricated for Wiley Post; only the final version proved successful. The first suit ruptured during a pressure test. The redesigned second suit used the same helmet as the first but when tested  was too tight and they were unable to remove it from Post, so they had to cut him out thus destroying the suit. The third suit was redesigned from the previous two.&lt;ref&gt;Young 2009, pp. 13–16.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Kozloski 1994, pp. 11–14.&lt;/ref&gt;

The body of the suit had three layers: long underwear, an inner black rubber air pressure bladder, and an outer layer made of rubberized parachute fabric. The outer layer was glued to a frame with arm and leg joints that allowed him to operate the flight controls and to walk to and from the aircraft. Attached to the frame were pigskin gloves, rubber boots, and an aluminum-and-plastic diver's helmet. The helmet had a removable faceplate that could be sealed at a height of 17,000&amp;nbsp;ft, and could accommodate [[earphones]] and a [[throat microphone]]. The helmet was cylinder-shaped with a circular window. In the first flight using the suit on September 5, 1934, Post reached an altitude of 40,000&amp;nbsp;ft above Chicago. Eventually flying as high as 50,000&amp;nbsp;ft, Post discovered the [[jet stream]] and made the first major practical advances in pressurized flight.&lt;ref name=Evo&gt;Mallan 1971, p. 31.&lt;/ref&gt; As of 2011 the suit is currently being restored.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.nasm.si.edu/imageDetail.cfm?imageID=1446 "Wiley Post suit in Rocketry and Space Flight."] ''National Air &amp; Space Museum'' via ''nasm.si.edu''. Retrieved: July 18, 2010.&lt;/ref&gt;

===Attempted high altitude non-stop transcontinental flights===
[[File:Wiley Post Transcontinental Flights 1935.jpg|thumb|left|Cover flown by Wiley Post on all four of his attempts to make the first high altitude non-stop transcontinental flight from Los Angeles to New York. February–June 1935]]

Between February 22 and June 15, 1935, Post made four unsuccessful attempts to complete the first high altitude non-stop flight from Los Angeles to New York, all of which failed for various mechanical reasons. The first attempt on February 22 ended just 57.5 miles north of Los Angeles at Muroc, CA (Now [[Edwards AFB]]). This was followed by attempts on March 15 (Cleveland, Ohio; 2,035 miles), April 14 (Lafayette, Indiana; 1,760 miles), and June 15 (Wichita, KS; 1,188 miles). As the attempts were also meant to be the "First Air Mail Stratosphere Flight" over U.S. Air Mail Route #2 (AM-2) from Los Angeles to New York, Post also carried a quantity of 'cacheted' [[Cover (philately)|cover]]s sponsored by [[Trans World Airlines|Transcontinental &amp; Western Air, Inc]] on all four flights. When Post was killed on August 15, 1935, thus ending the possibility of any more attempts to complete the AM-2 stratosphere flight, the covers were finally cancelled in Los Angeles on August 20, 1935, and forwarded to their addressees.

==Final flight and death==
[[File:Will Rogers and Wiley Post cph.3b05600.jpg|thumb|240px|Post with Will Rogers before their deaths, August 1935]]
In 1935 Post became interested in surveying a mail-and-passenger air route from the West Coast of the United States to Russia. Short on cash, he built a hybrid using parts salvaged from two different aircraft: the fuselage of an airworthy [[Lockheed Model 9 Orion|Lockheed Orion]] and the wings of a wrecked experimental [[Lockheed Explorer]]. The Explorer wing was six feet longer in span than the Orion's original wing, an advantage that extended the range of the hybrid aircraft. As the Explorer wing did not have retractable landing gear, it also lent itself to the fitting of [[floatplane|floats]] for landing in the lakes of [[Alaska]] and [[Siberia]]. [[Lockheed Corporation|Lockheed]] flatly refused to make the modifications Post requested on the grounds that the two designs were incompatible and potentially a dangerous mix, leaving him no alternative but to make the changes himself.&lt;ref name="Sterling 2001, p. 164"&gt;Sterling 2001, p. 164.&lt;/ref&gt;

Post's friend [[Will Rogers]] visited him often at the airport in [[Burbank, California]], while Pacific Airmotive Ltd. was modifying the aircraft,&lt;ref&gt;Sterling 2001, pp. 167–169.&lt;/ref&gt; and asked Post to fly him through Alaska in search of new material for his newspaper column. When the floats Post had ordered did not arrive at [[Seattle]] in time, he used a set that was designed for a larger type, making the already nose-heavy hybrid aircraft still more nose-heavy.&lt;ref&gt;Johnson and Mohler. [http://www.sil.si.edu/smithsoniancontributions/AnnalsofFlight/pdf_lo/SAOF-0008.pdf ''Wiley Post, His Winnie Mae, and the World's First Pressure Suit.'']  p. 112. Retrieved: 3 April 2009.&lt;/ref&gt; However, according to the research of [[Bryan Sterling]], the floats were the correct type for the aircraft.&lt;ref name="Sterling 2001, p. 164"/&gt;

After making a test flight in July, Post and Rogers left [[Lake Washington]], near [[Seattle]], in early August and made several stops in Alaska. While Post piloted the aircraft, Rogers wrote his columns on his typewriter. Before they left Fairbanks they signed and mailed a [[burgee|yacht club burgee]] belonging to the South Coast Corinthian Yacht Club. The signed burgee is on display at South Coast Corinthian Yacht Club in Marina del Rey, California. On August 15, they left [[Fairbanks]], Alaska, for [[Point Barrow]]. They were a few miles from there when they became uncertain of their position in bad weather and landed in a lagoon to ask for directions. On takeoff, the engine failed at low altitude, and the aircraft, uncontrollably nose-heavy at low speed, plunged into the lagoon, shearing off the right wing, and ended up inverted in the shallow part. Both men died instantly.&lt;ref&gt;Sterling 2001, p. 246.&lt;/ref&gt;
Post is buried in Memorial Park Cemetery (section 48), [[Oklahoma City, Oklahoma]].&lt;ref&gt;[https://www.findagrave.com/memorial/831 "Wiley Post."] ''Find A Grave''. Retrieved: April 10, 2015&lt;/ref&gt;

==Honors and tributes==
In 1936, the [[Smithsonian Institution]] acquired the ''Winnie Mae'' from Post's widow for $25,000. The United States Congress authorized the purchase on August 24, 1935, just nine days after Post's death in Alaska. Two monuments at the [[Rogers-Post Site|crash site]] commemorate the death of the two men and are listed on the [[National Register of Historic Places]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.cr.nps.gov/nr/travel/aviation/rps.htm "Rogers-Post Site."]  ''National Park Service''. Retrieved: April 3, 2009.&lt;/ref&gt; The nearby [[Wiley Post–Will Rogers Memorial Airport]] located in [[Barrow, Alaska]] bears their names.

[[Wiley Post Airport]], a large FAA designated [[reliever airport]] in Oklahoma City, is named after Post.  [[Will Rogers World Airport|Oklahoma City's major commercial airport]] is named after Will Rogers, so that both victims of the crash are honored by airports in [[Oklahoma City]].  The [[Will Rogers – Wiley Post Memorial Seaplane Base]] is a [[seaplane]] base located on Lake Washington, at the north end of the [[Renton Municipal Airport]] in [[Renton, Washington]].

Post received the [[Distinguished Flying Cross (USA)|Distinguished Flying Cross]] (1932), the Gold Medal of Belgium (1934), and the [[Harmon Trophy|International Harmon Trophy]] (1934). He was enshrined in the [[National Aviation Hall of Fame]] in 1969.&lt;ref&gt;[http://nationalaviation.blade6.donet.com/components/content_manager_v02/view_nahf/htdocs/menu_ps.asp?NodeID=-244570675&amp;group_ID=1134656385&amp;Parent_ID=-1 "Wiley Post: Dare Devil."] ''National Aviation Hall of Fame'' (NAHF), 2006. Retrieved: April 3, 2009.&lt;/ref&gt; Post was inducted into the First Flight Society's First Flight Shrine, located at the Wright Brothers National Memorial, on December 17, 1970.

In 1997, he was inducted into the [[International Air &amp; Space Hall of Fame]] at the [[San Diego Air &amp; Space Museum]].&lt;ref&gt;Sprekelmeyer, Linda, editor. ''These We Honor: The International Aerospace Hall of Fame''. Donning Co. Publishers, 2006. [[International Standard Book Number|ISBN]] [[Special:BookSources/978-1-57864-397-4|978-1-57864-397-4]].&lt;/ref&gt;

In 1979, the [[United States Postal Service]] honored Post with two [[airmail]] [[Postage stamp|stamps]].&lt;ref&gt;Horwitz, Ed. "Wiley Post remembered as aviation pioneer." ''Stamps'',  1995. {{ISSN|0038-9358}}.&lt;/ref&gt;

Post was inducted posthumously into the Oklahoma Hall of Fame in 2004.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.oklahomahof.com/Inductees.aspx "Wiley Post".] ''Oklahoma Hall of Fame: Haylord-P{ickens Museum''. Retrieved: April 10, 2015.&lt;/ref&gt;

The Wiley Post Commission, based in Oklahoma City, presents the annual Wiley Post Spirit Award to "an individual in general aviation who best exemplifies the innovative and pioneering spirit of Wiley Post."&lt;ref&gt;[http://generalaviationnews.com/2007/01/05/wiley-post-spirit-award-presented-to-international-aviator-for-first-time/ "Wiley Post Spirit Award presented to international aviator for the first time."] ''General Aviation News''. Retrieved: April 10, 2015.&lt;/ref&gt;

==Notes==
{{notelist}}

==References==
'''Citations'''
{{Reflist}}

'''Bibliography'''
{{Refbegin}}
* Johnson, Bobby H. [http://www.tshaonline.org/handbook/online/articles/fpo27 "Post, Wiley Hardeman."] ''The Texas State Historical Association''. Retrieved: April 3, 2009.
* Johnson, Bobby H. and R. Stanley Mohler. ''Wiley Post, His Winnie Mae, and the World's First Pressure Suit.'' Washington, DC: Smithsonian Institution, 1971. {{ISBN|978-0-8061-3768-1}}.
* Kozloski, Lillian D. [https://books.google.com/books?id=v5JOPgAACAAJ&amp;source=gbs_navlinks_s ''U.S. Space Gear: Outfitting The Astronaut.''] Washington, D.C.: Smithsonian Institution Press, 1994. {{ISBN|0-87474-459-8}}.
* [https://web.archive.org/web/20040419021613/http://www.nasm.si.edu/research/aero/aircraft/lockheed_5c.htm "Lockheed 5C Vega."]  ''Smithsonian National Air and Space Museum''. Retrieved: April 3, 2009.
* Mallan, Lloyd. [https://books.google.com/books?id=bLdTAAAAMAAJ&amp;q=Suiting+Up+For+Space&amp;dq=Suiting+Up+For+Space&amp;hl=en&amp;ei=33VDTKGGG4H-8AbFj43eDw&amp;sa=X&amp;oi=book_result&amp;ct=result&amp;resnum=1&amp;ved=0CDwQ6AEwAA ''Suiting Up For Space: The Evolution of the Space Suit.''] New York: The John Day Company, 1971.
* Onkst, David H. [https://web.archive.org/web/20121008043851/http://www.centennialofflight.gov/essay/Explorers_Record_Setters_and_Daredevils/Wiley_Post/EX27.htm " Wiley Post."] ''U.S. Centennial of Flight Commission''. Retrieved: 3 April 2009.
* Post, Wiley.''Around The World In Eight Days''. New York: Crown Book, reprint 1989. {{ISBN|0-517-57352-0}}.
*Sterling, Bryan and Frances. ''Forgotten Eagle: Wiley Post: America's Heroic Aviation Pioneer''. New York: Carroll &amp; Graf Publishers, 2001. {{ISBN|0-7867-0894-8}}.
* [http://www.century-of-flight.net/Aviation%20history/pathfinders/Wiley%20Post.htm "Wiley Post."]. ''Century of Flight''. Retrieved: April 3, 2009.
* [http://www.acepilots.com/post.html "Wiley Post and the Winnie Mae."] ''AcePilots.com'', 2003. Retrieved: April 3, 2009.
* Young, Amanda. [https://books.google.com/books?id=D-sxPQAACAAJ&amp;dq=Spacesuits&amp;cd=2 ''Spacesuits: The Smithsonian National Air and Space Museum Collection.'']  Brooklyn, NY: House Cultural Entertainment Inc., 2009. {{ISBN|978-1-57687-498-1}}.
{{Refend}}

==External links==
*[http://www.wileypost.org wileypost.org]
*[https://books.google.com/books?id=xd8DAAAAMBAJ&amp;pg=PA492&amp;dq=%22Popular+Mechanics%22+Jan+1935+floating&amp;hl=en&amp;ei=Wtc4TsGsDeSusAKXtpka&amp;sa=X&amp;oi=book_result&amp;ct=result&amp;resnum=10&amp;sqi=2&amp;ved=0CFUQ6AEwCQ#v=onepage&amp;q&amp;f=true "Wiley Post seeks New Record"] ''Popular Mechanics'', October 1934 pp.&amp;nbsp;492–494
*[http://rentonwa.gov/living/default.aspx?id=254 Renton Municipal Airport - Will Rogers-Wiley Post Seaplane Base].
*[http://www.americanairmailsociety.org/assets/images/C95.jpg C95 Wiley Post Stamp]
*[http://www.americanairmailsociety.org/assets/images/C96.jpg C96 Wiley Post Stamp]
{{refend}}

{{Authority control}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Post, Wiley}}
[[Category:1898 births]]
[[Category:1935 deaths]]
[[Category:People from Van Zandt County, Texas]]
[[Category:People from Maysville, Oklahoma]]
[[Category:Aviation pioneers]]
[[Category:Aviators from Texas]]
[[Category:Accidental deaths in Alaska]]
[[Category:Aviators killed in aviation accidents or incidents in the United States]]
[[Category:Harmon Trophy winners]]
[[Category:National Aviation Hall of Fame inductees]]
[[Category:Recipients of the Distinguished Flying Cross (United States)]]
[[Category:American aviation record holders]]</text>
      <sha1>gi8ep76ifivs3dgavwhdeer2sntdlw8</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
