<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10.xsd" version="0.10" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <dbname>enwiki</dbname>
    <base>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.32.0-wmf.16</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="118" case="first-letter">Draft</namespace>
      <namespace key="119" case="first-letter">Draft talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2300" case="first-letter">Gadget</namespace>
      <namespace key="2301" case="first-letter">Gadget talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2302" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition</namespace>
      <namespace key="2303" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Arthur Watts (illustrator)</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>18274146</id>
    <revision>
      <id>838794626</id>
      <parentid>833534448</parentid>
      <timestamp>2018-04-29T10:01:31Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>GHH111</username>
        <id>32987901</id>
      </contributor>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="10395">{{For|other people named Arthur Watts|Arthur Watts (disambiguation)}}
{{EngvarB|date=July 2017}}
{{Use dmy dates|date=July 2017}}
{{Infobox person
| name        =  Arthur Watts
| birth_date   = 28 April 1883
| birth_place    = [[Rochester, Kent]], England
| death_date   = 20 July 1935
| death_place = [[Pian San Giacomo]], [[Graubünden]], Switzerland
| othername   = 

| yearsactive = 
| spouse      = Phyllis Sachs (first), Margerie Dawson Scott (second) -1935 (his death)
| children  =  [[Margaret Furse|Alice Margaret]] &lt;br&gt; Marjorie Ann&lt;br&gt; Simon&lt;br&gt; Julyan
}}
'''Arthur George Watts''' [[Distinguished Service Order|DSO]] (1883–1935) was an illustrator and artist who was killed in an airplane crash in the Swiss Alps.

==Early life and education==
Watts was born in [[Rochester, Kent]] in 1883 the son of Joseph Watts, Deputy Surgeon-General in the [[Indian Medical Service]] [[Indian Army]] and his wife Alice. His father retired early and the family lived in [[Dulwich]] and [[South Norwood|Norwood]] in south-east London where the family usually employed a resident cook and housemaid, and a nurse while the children were young.&lt;ref&gt;England &amp; Wales Census, 1891 and 1900.&lt;/ref&gt;

Educated at [[Dulwich College]] Watts was a talented artist from an early age and inked funny drawings in the margins of his school books, at Crystal Palace Poster Academy he was awarded a silver medal for merit in 1901. From the age of 17 he was educated at the [[Slade School of Fine Art]] from where he went to the Free Arts Schools in [[Antwerp]] and then [[Paris]], [[Moscow]] and [[Madrid]]. He was reportedly one of the London arts schools crowd who holidayed regularly in St Ives, Cornwall during the Edwardian period.&lt;ref name=thetimes/&gt;
[[File:The Italian Navy in the Mediterranean, 1915-1918 Q19106.jpg|thumb|305px| A naval motor launch of World War I ]]

==Naval service==
Watts served in World War I in the [[Royal Naval Volunteer Reserve]] attaining the rank of [[Commander]] and receiving the [[Distinguished Service Order]] for his bravery in the [[Zeebrugge Raid]] in 1918.&lt;ref&gt;Bryant, Mark. ''World War I in Cartoons''. London: Grub Street Pub, 2006, page 9, {{ISBN|190494356X}}.&lt;/ref&gt;

He received a temporary commission as [[sub-lieutenant]] in the Royal Naval Volunteer Reserve in December 1914,&lt;ref&gt;{{London Gazette |issue=29021|page=11135|date=29 December 1914}}&lt;/ref&gt; and on 18 December 1915 he was promoted to temporary [[lieutenant]].&lt;ref&gt;{{London Gazette |nolink=y |issue=29475|page=1688|date=15 February 1915}}&lt;/ref&gt;
In command of motor launch ML.239 in April 1918 he played a distinguished part in the "combined operation" known as the Zeebrugge Raid, also participating in the operations at [[Ostend]] in May 1918 when [[HMS Vindictive|HMS ''Vindictive'']] was sunk to block the harbor entrance. Watts was awarded the Distinguished Service Order as an acting [[lieutenant-commander]] on 27 August 1918.&lt;ref&gt;{{London Gazette |nolink=y |issue=30870|page=10089|date=27 August 1918}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Career==
[[File:A man pulling a doctor down the path to his house to see his Wellcome V0011550.jpg|thumb|306px|''Punch'' magazine humour, 1930s]]
By 1904 he was providing humorous and other illustrations for papers such as the ''[[Tatler]]'', ''[[Bystander (magazine)|The Bystander]]'', ''[[Pearson's Magazine]]'' and ''[[London Opinion]]''.&lt;ref name=askart&gt;[http://www.askart.com/artist/Arthur_George_Watts/1135811/Arthur_George_Watts.aspx "Arthur Watts"]. (AskArt.com).&lt;/ref&gt; In 1911 Watts was living with his wife of one year and their baby daughter Margaret at 21A Regents Park Road in central London where he worked from a studio at home as a successful illustrator.&lt;ref&gt;England &amp; Wales Census, 1911.&lt;/ref&gt;

His first drawing for ''[[Punch (magazine)|Punch]]'', the English humour magazine, was published in 1912 and his work, particularly cartoons, continued to appear regularly until the time of his death having become a regular feature after 1921. He also did four drawings a week for ''[[Radio Times]]''; illustrated about a dozen books, including ''Diary of a Provincial Lady'' by [[E M Delafield]]; and designed travel posters for the railways and the [[London Underground]]. He edited and illustrated ''A Painter's Anthology''.

Many of Watts' cartoons highlighted the class distinctions that existed in the UK in the nineteen-twenties and thirties. They offered a social commentary and an acute observation of differences in accent, vocabulary, dress, drinking habits and even table manners. Some of his sharpest barbs were aimed at the "modern" art of the period, the nouveau riche, day trippers, social climbers and hen-pecked husbands. His contorted figures in paint, plaster and stone are clever caricatures of what he saw around him.&lt;ref name=askart/&gt;

==Family==
Watts married Phyllis Sachs, a fellow artist, in 1910. Their only child Alice Margaret became costume designer [[Margaret Furse]]. Phyllis died in 1922 and in 1925 he married Marjorie Dawson Scott (daughter of PEN Club founder [[Catherine Amy Dawson Scott]]&lt;ref&gt;[http://studymore.org.uk/ymew.htm#MarjorieWatts Marjorie Watts (tag)]. "Charlotte Mew Chronology" (http://studymore.org.uk/ymew.htm).&lt;/ref&gt;), by whom he had three children.&lt;ref name=thetimes&gt;Obituary. ''The Times''. 22 July 1935.&lt;/ref&gt;  The family lived in Holly-place, [[Hampstead]].&lt;ref&gt;Arthur George Watts. National Probate Registry. 1935.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{London Gazette |nolink=y |issue=34208|page=6516|date=15 October 1935}}&lt;/ref&gt; Their daughter Marjorie Ann Watts also became an illustrator, and a writer.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.camdenreview.com/node/987155&lt;/ref&gt; Their son Simon Watts (born 1930) emigrated to the United States and graduated from MIT with an engineering degree. He chose to pursue a career as a furniture maker and boat builder and is the author of several books on woodworking and boat building.

==Death in an air crash==
[[File:Douglas DC-2.jpg|thumb|305px|Douglas DC-2 in KLM service]]
Watts was killed at about 12:15 hours on Saturday, 20 July 1935 when travelling aboard [[KLM]] (Royal Dutch Airlines) [[Douglas DC-2]] (registration "PH-AKG") named "Gaai" on a scheduled flight from [[Milan]], Italy to [[Amsterdam]], Netherlands via [[Frankfurt am Main|Frankfurt]], Germany. The aircraft which had recently been delivered from the manufacturers took off from Milan at 11:36 hours. While flying at 5000m altitude it suffered with ice build up and had to descend to 3000m, at which altitude it was flying between mountains surrounded by clouds. Reportedly the crew may have entered the wrong mountain pass as they circled a valley in cloud and rain, possibly attempting to force land wheels-up when the aircraft stalled and crashed near the [[San Bernardino Pass]] near [[Pian San Giacomo]], killing all four crew and all nine passengers.&lt;ref&gt;[https://aviation-safety.net/database/record.php?id=19350720-0 "Crash on 20 July 1935"]. Aviation Safety Network (aviation-safety.net).&lt;/ref&gt;

Watts was hurrying home from Milan to be with his wife who had given birth to their third child four days earlier.&lt;ref name=thetimes/&gt;

''The Times of London'' on 22 July 1935 carried an article "Dutch Air Disaster: Liner's crash in Alps" which states that the accident occurred a short distance south of the San Bernardino Pass on the Pian San Giacomo a small plateau between high mountains at an altitude of 3,845 feet, about 2.5 miles from the village of Mesocco. The story reported that the aircraft was at loo low an altitude to fly over the mountains towards San Bernardino but found the southern end of the pass blocked by a mass of dark clouds. At that time it was believed to have either been struck by lightning or dragged down by an air current as it suddenly hit the ground from a height of 600 feet. Rescuers found everybody dead, except for a woman who died soon afterwards. When police attended they recovered a large amount of money and mail-bags. An investigation found that the storm in the area had been so violent that swollen rivers had swept away two bridges, the local power plant had been put out of action and that the weather had played a significant part in the accident. The dead were removed to a small chapel at San Giacomo to await instructions for their disposition.&lt;ref&gt;''The Times'', Dutch Air Disaster article - 22 July 1935&lt;/ref&gt;

== Selected works ==
'''Articles and essays'''
* ''Black and White Drawing - Solving Some of Its Problems.''
* "A Three-Legged Cruise" (''[[Yachting Monthly]]'', August to November 1913) - 4 parts
* "The Scented Trawler" (''Yachting Monthly'', 1917) - recounts a brief adventure at sea while on duty with the Auxlilary Patrol during World War I

'''Books illustrated'''
* ''A Painter's Anthology'' - Arthur Watts
* ''Diary of a Provincial Lady'' - [[E M Delafield]]
* ''The Provincial Lady in London'' - E M Delafield
* ''The Provincial Lady Goes Further'' - E M Delafield
* ''Poems of Impudence'' - Evoe ([[E V Knox]])
* ''So, This is Science'' - [[H F Ellis]]
* ''The Navy and Defense'' - [[Lord Chatfield]] (includes a single sketch which Watts provided for an event aboard [[HMS Repulse (1916)|HMS Repulse]] at which time he also produced this illustration for Punch)
* ''Peeps at Parnasus: A Delicious Survey, Half Parody, Half Caricature, of the Whole Pageant of English Verse-Malicious and Gay.'' - [[Olga Katzin]]
* ''The Tragedy of Mr. Punch: A Fantastic Play in Prologue and One Act'' - [[Russell Thorndike]] and [[Reinald Arkell]]
* ''The Horoscope. A Biographical Poem in Three Books With an Epilogue.'' - [[Horace Horsnell]]

== References ==
{{reflist |25em}}

== Further reading ==

* ''The Art of Arthur Watts''. Edited by Simon Watts. Ottawa: Lee Valley. 2003.

==External links==
{{portal |Cartoons}}
* www.arthurwatts.com (The Art of Arthur Watts) – former website maintained by the family of Arthur Watts
* {{LCAuth|no89007563|Arthur Watts|4|ue}}

{{Authority control}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Watts Arthur}}
[[Category:British illustrators]]
[[Category:British cartoonists]]
[[Category:1883 births]]
[[Category:1935 deaths]]
[[Category:Companions of the Distinguished Service Order]]
[[Category:Royal Navy officers of World War I]]
[[Category:Victims of aviation accidents or incidents in Switzerland]]
[[Category:Aviation accidents and incidents in 1935]]
[[Category:Victims of aviation accidents or incidents in 1935]]
[[Category:The New Yorker people]]</text>
      <sha1>hy6c4lpxxtsa9gycfzq01yjcgfgiymo</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
