<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10.xsd" version="0.10" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <dbname>enwiki</dbname>
    <base>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.32.0-wmf.16</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="118" case="first-letter">Draft</namespace>
      <namespace key="119" case="first-letter">Draft talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2300" case="first-letter">Gadget</namespace>
      <namespace key="2301" case="first-letter">Gadget talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2302" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition</namespace>
      <namespace key="2303" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Charles Kuhn</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>7518848</id>
    <revision>
      <id>767751186</id>
      <parentid>709460004</parentid>
      <timestamp>2017-02-27T19:12:54Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>GrahamHardy</username>
        <id>2956291</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>added [[Category:People from Bushnell, Illinois]] using [[WP:HC|HotCat]]</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="6450">{{for|the American art historian|Charles L. Kuhn}}
[[File:Chaskuhn.jpg|thumb|280px]]
'''Charles Harris Kuhn''' (March 20, 1892 &amp;ndash; 1989), nicknamed '''Doc Kuhn''', was a cartoonist best known as the creator of the comic strip ''[[Grandma (comic strip)|Grandma]]''. He usually signed his drawings and comic strips '''Chas. Kuhn'''.

Born in [[Prairie City, Illinois]], he was the son of James B. and Minnie Harris Kuhn. His father ran a restaurant and proudly displayed his son's drawings in the eatery's window. At age 12, he decided to become a cartoonist when the sale of his first cartoon brought him 50 cents. Kuhn grew up in [[Bushnell, Illinois]], and later remarked, "I hope some of the oldtimers remember me as a regular fellow."&lt;ref name=art/&gt;

==Cartoons and travels==
[[File:Charleskuhn66.jpg|thumb|260px|Charles Kuhn's ''[[Grandma (comic strip)|Grandma]]'' (May 1, 1966)]]
After high school, Kuhn worked in a plow factory, laboring ten hours a day, six days a week. He moved on to become a freight hustler, mill hand, steel tank worker and sign painter before enrolling at the Chicago Academy of Fine Arts (1913–14), where he studied cartooning in a class taught by [[Frank King (cartoonist)|Frank King]]. He soon landed an art job paying $10 a week. During [[World War I]], as Kuhn put it, he "shoveled coal and chow" as a Navy fireman on the ''U.S.S. Connecticut''.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.pbase.com/csw62/kuhn_charles Christopher Wheeler Gallery]&lt;/ref&gt; He also visited France in World War I. During the other travels of his youth, he spent time in the Canadian harvest fields and "stepped over the border into old Mexico."

Kuhn was a cartoonist with Denver's ''[[Rocky Mountain News]]'' from 1919 to 1921. He married his wife, the former Lois E. Stevens of Denver, in 1922, shortly after signing on with the ''[[Indianapolis News]]'', filling the position left open when editorial cartoonist [[Gaar Williams]] departed to join the ''[[Chicago Tribune]]''. Kuhn remained at the ''Indianapolis News'' as the paper's editorial cartoonist for the next 26 years. He later recalled, "My original idea was to set the world afire with my oh, so super-dandy editorial cartoons."&lt;ref name=art/&gt; Some of these editorial cartoons focused on the movement by [[Richard Lieber]] to establish state parks and recreational facilities in Indiana.

==Comic strip==
Kuhn was 55 when he decided to change careers. He left editorial cartoons behind when he created ''Grandma'', a comic strip inspired by his mother:
:My mother was always full of pep and vigor. One time at 75 years of age, she dressed up in my old Navy uniform, danced a jig and played a piece on her French harp just to help the neighborhood kids put on a backyard show. My comic ''Grandma'', in spirit at least, is my own beloved mother.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.newspaperarchive.com ''The Denton Record-Chronicle'', October 23, 1958.]&lt;/ref&gt;

''Grandma'' began April 14, 1947, distributed by Duke Richardson's Indianapolis-based Richardson Feature Service. A year later, the strip was picked up by [[King Features Syndicate]] which distributed it from June 28, 1948 until 1969. Kuhn was so totally absorbed by and devoted to his strip that when he was asked about hobbies, he answered, "''Grandma'' and creating toys for the kids." Toys belonging to the neighborhood kids were also a key topic in many ''Grandma'' strips; she sometimes reverted to a second childhood and played with the toys herself. Kuhn's other main interest was fishing.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.newspaperarchive.com ''Indiana Evening Gazette'' (Indiana, Pennsylvania), September 29, 1950.]&lt;/ref&gt;

Kuhn had a regular routine that involved starting to work each morning right at 8am, followed by the arrival of an assistant at 9am. Then, as he put it, "We soon have another ''Grandma'' rolling along." Lois Kuhn was also a collaborator, as he once revealed: "She's full of ''Grandma'' ideas."&lt;ref name=art&gt;[http://www.lileks.com/comics/kingfeatures/26.html ''Famous Artists'': "Chas. Kuhn"]&lt;/ref&gt;

For Kuhn, who had mastered the art of drawing early in his career, humor was the key factor in creating ''Grandma'':
:To me the most important requisite in a comic strip is real down-to-earth humor. That's 90 per cent of a strip; art ability makes up the other ten per cent. And to young cartoonists, I would like to say: keep plugging. You want to be ready when that fickle old lady, Opportunity, does knock.

The Kuhns lived in [[Acton, Indiana]] until 1964 when they moved to Florida. The move enabled Kuhn to spend more time fishing. When he retired in 1969 to begin full-time fishing, ''Grandma'' came to an end.
[[File:Grandmaseptember2853.jpg|center|thumb|610px|Charles Kuhn's ''[[Grandma (comic strip)|Grandma]]'' (September 28, 1953)]]

==Books==
In a curious and unlikely pairing, the David McKay company published a book which brought together reprints of both ''Grandma'' strips and ''Mandrake the Magician'' strips. ''Grandma'' is also featured in Maurice Horn's ''Women in the Comics'' (Chelsea House, 1977).

Kuhn was the author of several art instruction books: ''Boy and Girl Cartoonist: A Complete Course in Cartooning'', published by [[Saalfield Publishing Company]] in 1936, ''Kuhn Course in Cartooning; America’s Number One Cartoon Course'' (1944) and ''Doc Kuhn's Chalk Talk Tricks'' (Pearce Art School, Waukegan, Illinois).&lt;ref&gt;[http://goldenchalkclassics.blogspot.com/#kuhn Golden Chalk Classics]&lt;/ref&gt;

==Awards==
[[File:Chaskuhn429.jpg|right|thumb|240px|A cartoon from early in Charles Kuhn's career.]]
At the 1958 Chicago convention of the Grandmothers Club of America, Charles and Lois Kuhn were named Foster Grandparents of the Year. In addition to a plaque from the National Grandmother and Grandfather awards committee, actress [[Jane Darwell]] presented the Kuhns with their awards: miniature gold rocking chairs with red plush seats.

==References==
{{Reflist}}

==External links==
*[http://www.indiana.edu/~liblilly/lilly/mss/html/williams-kuh.html Indiana University: Williams-Kuhn Manuscripts]
*[http://speccoll.library.kent.edu/children/saalfield.html Kent State University: Saalfield Publishing Company Collection]

{{Authority control}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Kuhn, Charles}}
[[Category:1892 births]]
[[Category:1989 deaths]]
[[Category:American comic strip cartoonists]]
[[Category:People from McDonough County, Illinois]]
[[Category:Rocky Mountain News people]]
[[Category:People from Bushnell, Illinois]]</text>
      <sha1>d2vpwwdzhks3rrjvze5el3ycuigl885</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
