<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10.xsd" version="0.10" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <dbname>enwiki</dbname>
    <base>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.32.0-wmf.16</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="118" case="first-letter">Draft</namespace>
      <namespace key="119" case="first-letter">Draft talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2300" case="first-letter">Gadget</namespace>
      <namespace key="2301" case="first-letter">Gadget talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2302" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition</namespace>
      <namespace key="2303" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Chester Gould</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>67257</id>
    <revision>
      <id>851843663</id>
      <parentid>851151870</parentid>
      <timestamp>2018-07-24T23:51:13Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Kuru</username>
        <id>764407</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>rmv reference to clearly identified wikipedia mirror per [[WP:CIRCULAR]]</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="13045">{{Use mdy dates|date=August 2016}}
{{Infobox person
| name   = Chester Gould
| image =
| birth_date  = {{birth date|1900|11|20|mf=y}}
| birth_place = [[Pawnee, Oklahoma]], United States
| death_date  = {{death date and age|1985|5|11|1900|11|20|mf=y}}
| death_place = [[Woodstock, Illinois]], United States
| nationality = American
| occupation = [[Cartoonist]], writer
| spouse = Edna M. Gauger
| children = 1
}}
'''Chester Gould''' ({{IPAc-en|g|uː|l|d}}; November 20, 1900&amp;nbsp;– May 11, 1985)&lt;ref&gt;''[[Comics Buyer's Guide]]'' #1636 (December 2007); Page 135&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=Klassiekers&gt;{{cite book |last1=De Weyer |first1=Geert |title=100 stripklassiekers die niet in je boekenkast mogen ontbreken |year=2008 |publisher=Atlas |location=[[Amsterdam]] / [[Antwerp]] |language=Dutch |isbn=978-90-450-0996-4 |page=215 }}&lt;!--|accessdate=June 19, 2009 --&gt;&lt;/ref&gt; was an American [[cartoonist]], best known as the creator of the ''[[Dick Tracy]]'' [[comic strip]], which he wrote and drew from 1931 to 1977, incorporating numerous colorful and monstrous villains.

==Early life==

Chester Gould was born to Gilbert R. Gould, the son of a minister, and Alice Maud (née Miller).&lt;ref name="auto"&gt;[http://www.okhistory.org/publications/enc/entry.php?entry=GO017 Oklahoma Historical Society]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last=Reynolds|first=Moira Davison|title=Comic Strip Artists in American Newspapers, 1945–1980|year=2003|location=US|isbn=978-0-7864-1551-9|pages=67| url=http://www.mcfarlandbooks.com/book-2.php?id=978-0-7864-1551-9}}&lt;/ref&gt; All four of his grandparents were pioneer settlers of Oklahoma. He was a Christian,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last=O'Connell|first=Jean Gould|title=Chester Gould: A Daughter's Biography of the Creator of Dick Tracy|year=2007|publisher=McFarland|location=US|isbn=978-0-7864-2825-0|pages=13–18|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=DJai9JCtYhoC&amp;pg=PA11&amp;lpg=PA11&amp;dq=chester+gould+land+rush&amp;source=bl&amp;ots=5e0PFiFRQZ&amp;sig=93HxRvy7G1idrDyf2pjUfHTOtY4&amp;hl=en&amp;sa=X&amp;ved=0ahUKEwjBn6773IjTAhVN2mMKHRYiDokQ6AEIKzAD#v=onepage&amp;q=chester%20gould%20land%20rush&amp;f=false}}&lt;/ref&gt;but he was born [[Jewish]].&lt;ref&gt;To Life and Laughs! — Jewish Journal jewishjournal.com/old_stories/1221/ Oct 22, 1998 - And the 30s were dominated by two Jewish-created strips, the crime saga “Dick Tracy” (Chester Gould); and Al Capp's hillbilly opus “Li'l Abner” ...&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Jewish Comic Book Artists - Geni.com
https://www.geni.com/projects/Jewish-Comic-Book-Artists/25830 Chester Gould (November 20, 1900 – May 11, 1985) was an American cartoonist, best known as the creator of the Dick Tracy comic strip, which he wrote and ...&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Masters of American Comics - Newark Museum - The Jewish Museum ... https://www.nytimes.com/2006/10/13/arts/design/13comi.html Oct 13, 2006 - It means Frank King's languid “Gasoline Alley” and Chester Gould's “Dick Tracy,” which set the standard for hard-boiled grit and packed a ...&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Smart Watches Where They Came From And Where They Are Going ... https://jewishbusinessnews.com/.../smart-watches-where-they-came-from-and-where-t...
Sep 6, 2013 - Jewish and Israeli world business and financial global news. ... Its creator was Chester Gould and the new comic strip first appeared on October 4, ... Gould then continued to write and draw the character for 46 more years until ...&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;A prayer for the funny pages | The Jewish Standard jewishstandard.timesofisrael.com/a-prayer-for-the-funny-pages/ 
Dec 15, 2016 - We last checked in with Dick Tracy's Jewish partner Sam Catchem a year ... is sick in the cartoon world created by Chester Gould 85 years ago.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Jewish Cartoonists - shalomhaverim www.shalomhaverim.org/Judeografias/cartoonists.htm 
... Jordan B. Gorfinkel, comic book writer (Batman) and cartoonist; Chester Gould · Steve Greenberg, ... Shofar: An Interdisciplinary Journal of Jewish Studies.&lt;/ref&gt;
Fascinated by the comics since childhood, Gould quickly found work as a cartoonist. He was hired by [[William Randolph Hearst]]'s ''[[Chicago's American|Chicago Evening American]]'', where he produced his first comic strips, ''Fillum Fables'' (1924) and ''The Radio Catts''. He also drew a topical strip about Chicago, ''Why It's a Windy City''. Gould married Edna Gauger (1901–1994) in 1926, and their daughter, Jean, was born in 1927. A 1923 graduate, Gould is an alumnus of [[Northwestern University]] where he attended the [[Northwestern University School of Professional Studies|School of Professional Studies]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://exhibits.library.northwestern.edu/archives/exhibits/alumni/gould.html|title=Chester Gould : Alumni Exhibit: Northwestern University Archives|publisher=|accessdate=April 27, 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt;
[[File:BrightlightsbradyGould30.jpg|right|thumb|Proposed comic strip drawn by Chester Gould one year before creating ''Dick Tracy''. See this strip at full resolution at Three Men in a Tub.]]

His cousin [[Henry W. Gould]] is Professor Emeritus of Mathematics at [[West Virginia University]].

==''Dick Tracy''==
In 1931, Gould was hired as a cartoonist with the ''[[Chicago Tribune]]'' and introduced ''Dick Tracy'' in the newspaper ''The Detroit Mirror'' on Sunday, October 4, 1931.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last=O'Connell|first=Jean Gould|title=Chester Gould: A Daughter's Biography of the Creator of Dick Tracy|year=2007|publisher=McFarland|location=US|isbn=978-0-7864-2825-0|pages=5|url=http://www.mcfarlandpub.com/book-2.php?id=978-0-7864-2825-0}}&lt;/ref&gt; The original comic was based on a New York detective Gould was interested in. The comic then branched to the fictional character that became so famous.  He drew the comic strip for the next 46 years from his home in [[Woodstock, Illinois]].

In order to keep informed of police methods, Gould took courses in forensics and investigative procedures. He was later proud of having introduced in 1946, the two-way wrist radio for Tracy, and in 1947, the closed-circuit television, both of which were later invented, though in somewhat different forms.

Gould's stories were rarely pre-planned, since he preferred to improvise stories as he drew them. While fans praised this approach as producing exciting stories, it sometimes created awkward plot developments that were difficult to resolve. In one notorious case, Gould had Tracy in an inescapable [[deathtrap (plot device)|deathtrap]] with a [[Caisson (engineering)|caisson]]. When Gould depicted Tracy addressing Gould personally and having the cartoonist magically extract him, publisher [[Joseph Medill Patterson|Joseph Patterson]] vetoed the sequence and ordered it redrawn.  The strip also drew protests from those who felt that Mr. Gould's depiction of crime was too gruesome, that he poured on too much gore and carnage.&lt;ref&gt;https://www.nytimes.com/1985/05/12/us/chester-gould-cartoonist-dies-at-at-84.html?pagewanted=all&lt;/ref&gt;

Later in the strip's Gould period, the ''Tracy'' strip was widely criticized for being too right-wing in character and as excessively supportive of the police. Critics thought Gould ignored the [[rights of the accused]] and failed to support his agenda with an adequate story-line. The late 1950s also saw a newspaper readership growing less indulgent of Gould's politics.

[[Image:Dicktracy (mural).jpg|thumb|right|Dick Tracy mural in downtown [[Pawnee, Oklahoma]]]]

For instance, Gould introduced an malodorous, tobacco-spitting character, B.O. Plenty, with little significant complaint from readers in the 1940s. However, the 1960s introduction of crooked lawyer Flyface and his relatives, surrounded by swarming flies, created a negative reader reaction strong enough for papers to drop the strip in large numbers. There was then a dramatic change in the strip's setting, leaving behind the strip's origins as an urban crime drama for science fiction plot elements and regular visits to the moon. An increasingly fantastic procession of enemies and stories ensued. The ''[[Apollo 11]]'' moon landing prompted Gould to abandon this phase. Finally, ''Dick Tracy'' was beset by the overall trend in newspaper comics away from strips with continuing storylines and toward those whose stories are largely resolved within one series of panels.

Gould, his characters, and improbable plots were satirized in [[Al Capp]]'s comic strip ''[[Li'l Abner]]'' with the ''[[Fearless Fosdick]]'' sequences (supposedly drawn by "Lester Gooch"); a notable villain was Bomb Face, a gangster whose head was a bomb.

==Awards and exhibitions==
Chester Gould won the [[National Cartoonists Society]]'s [[Reuben Award]] in 1959 and 1977. The [[Mystery Writers of America]] honored Gould and his work with a Special [[Edgar Award]] in 1980. In 1995, the strip was one of 20 included in the [[Comic Strip Classics]] series of commemorative postage stamps and postcards.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.trussel.com/detfic/tracy.htm|title=Detective Fiction on Stamps: United States 1995: Dick Tracy|publisher=|accessdate=April 27, 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt;

''Dick Tracy: The Art of Chester Gould'' was an exhibition in [[Port Chester, New York]], at the [[National Cartoon Museum|Museum of Cartoon Art]] from October 4 through November 30, 1978. The exhibition was curated by Bill Crouch, Jr.

From 1991 until 2008, the art and artifacts of Gould's career were displayed in the Chester Gould-Dick Tracy Museum that operated from the Woodstock, Illinois, Old Courthouse on the Square. Visitors to the Museum saw original comic strips, correspondence, photographs, and much memorabilia, including Gould's drawing board and chair. In 2000, the Museum received a Superior Achievement Award from the Illinois Association of Museums, and in 2001, it was given an Award of Excellence from the Illinois State Historical Society. The museum continues today as a virtual museum online.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.dicktracymuseum.com/|title=The Chester Gould Dick Tracy Museum|publisher=|accessdate=April 27, 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Gould retired December 25, 1977, and died May 11, 1985, in [[Woodstock, Illinois]], of congestive heart failure.&lt;ref name=Klassiekers/&gt; Gould is buried in Oakland Cemetery in Woodstock.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.kcchronicle.com/2015/02/18/woodstock-natives-honor-dick-tracy-creator-chester-gould-with-documentary/ahjumm5/ ''Kane County Chronicle'']&lt;/ref&gt;

In 2005, Gould was inducted into the Oklahoma Cartoonists Hall of Fame in [[Pauls Valley, Oklahoma]], by [[Michael Vance]]. The Oklahoma Cartoonists Collection, created by Vance, is located in the Toy and Action Figure Museum.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.actionfiguremuseum.com/occ_bios.htm|title=OCC Bios|publisher=|accessdate=April 27, 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Books==
In 1983, two years before Gould's death, his only child, Jean Gould O'Connell, recorded extensive interviews with her father, who spoke at length about his early attempts during the 1920s to get syndicated and the birth of Dick Tracy. These interviews became a major source when she wrote his biography, ''Chester Gould: A Daughter's Biography of the Creator of Dick Tracy'', published by McFarland in 2007. A resident of [[Geneva, Illinois]], Jean Gould O'Connell contributed to the ''Dick Tracy'' storylines, appeared as a character in the strip and helped create the Chester Gould-Dick Tracy Museum. Her book was an Edgar Award nominee in 2008.

The entire run of ''Dick Tracy'' is being reprinted in a book series by [[IDW Publishing]]. The series began in 2006. The first volume includes the five sample strips that Gould used to sell his strip, followed by over 450 strips showing the series' beginning (from October 1931&amp;nbsp;– May 1933), along with a Gould interview, never previously published, by [[Max Allan Collins]]. Twenty-two more volumes in this series have published between 2006 and 2017, bringing the continuity to July 1967.

==References==
{{Reflist}}

==External links==
*[https://web.archive.org/web/20040130152441/http://www.pawneepolice.com/pawnee/dick_tracy_muriel.htm Commemorative Mural in Pawnee]
*[https://web.archive.org/web/20060106021759/http://www.reuben.org/ncs/awards.asp NCS Awards]
*[https://web.archive.org/web/20070919210748/http://crossandcrescent.com/2006/10/dick-tracy-turns-75 Article "'Dick Tracy' Turns 75"]
*[http://mystericale.com/index.php?issue=072&amp;body=file&amp;file=like_em_tough.htm/ Article "75 years of Continuous Crime-Stopping"]
*{{IMDb name|332333}}
*[https://web.archive.org/web/20100729055631/http://digital.library.okstate.edu/encyclopedia/entries/G/GO017.html Encyclopedia of Oklahoma History and Culture: Chester Gould]

{{Dick Tracy}}

{{Authority control}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Gould, Chester}}
[[Category:1900 births]]
[[Category:1985 deaths]]
[[Category:People from Woodstock, Illinois]]
[[Category:People from Pawnee, Oklahoma]]
[[Category:People from Stillwater, Oklahoma]]
[[Category:Chicago Tribune people]]
[[Category:American comic strip cartoonists]]
[[Category:Edgar Award winners]]
[[Category:Northwestern University alumni]]
[[Category:Reuben Award winners]]
[[Category:Will Eisner Award Hall of Fame inductees]]
[[Category:Dick Tracy]]</text>
      <sha1>h0z0y0vjs12lfc6mjkxrw3whgmc88dt</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
