<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10.xsd" version="0.10" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <dbname>enwiki</dbname>
    <base>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.32.0-wmf.16</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="118" case="first-letter">Draft</namespace>
      <namespace key="119" case="first-letter">Draft talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2300" case="first-letter">Gadget</namespace>
      <namespace key="2301" case="first-letter">Gadget talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2302" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition</namespace>
      <namespace key="2303" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>George Cruikshank</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>314465</id>
    <revision>
      <id>840213267</id>
      <parentid>830370813</parentid>
      <timestamp>2018-05-08T12:53:48Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Mitch Ames</username>
        <id>6326132</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>Remove supercategory of existing diffusing category per [[WP:SUBCAT]] using [[Project:AWB|AWB]]</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="17487">{{about||the American educator, newspaper editor and historian|George Cruikshank (editor)|people with a similar name|George Cruickshank (disambiguation)}}
{{Use dmy dates|date=March 2012}}
{{Use British English|date=March 2012}}

{{Infobox artist
| bgcolour      = #6495ED
| name          = George Cruikshank
| image         = George Cruikshank from NPG.jpg
| imagesize     =  200px
| alt           = 
| caption       = George Cruikshank, 1836
| birth_name    = &lt;!--unneeded--&gt;
| birth_date    = {{birth date|1792|9|27|df=y}}
| birth_place   = [[London]], England
| death_date    = {{death date and age|1878|2|1|1792|9|27|df=y}}
| death_place   = [[London]], England
| nationality   = British
| field         = Cartoonist (Caricaturist), [[Children's Literature]]
| training      = 
| movement      = 
| works         = 
| patrons       = 
| influenced by = 
| influenced    = 
| awards        =
| elected       =
| website       = 
}}
'''George Cruikshank''' (27 September 1792 – 1 February 1878) was a British [[caricaturist]] and book illustrator, praised as the "modern [[William Hogarth|Hogarth]]" during his life. His book illustrations for his friend [[Charles Dickens]], and many other authors, reached an international audience.

==Early life==
Cruikshank was born in London. His father, [[Isaac Cruikshank]], was one of the leading caricaturists of the late 1790s and Cruikshank started his career as his father's apprentice and assistant.

His older brother, [[Isaac Robert Cruikshank|Isaac Robert]], also followed in the family business as a caricaturist and illustrator. Cruikshank's early work was caricature; but in 1823, at the age of 31, he started to focus on book illustration. He illustrated the first, 1823 English translation (by [[Edgar Taylor (author)|Edgar Taylor]] and David Jardine) of ''[[Grimms' Fairy Tales]]'', published in two volumes as ''German Popular Stories''.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://doras.dcu.ie/17982/1/Niamh_Chapelle.pdf |title=Niamh Chapelle, 2001, p.72 |format=PDF |date= |accessdate=2013-11-22}}&lt;/ref&gt;

On 16 October 1827, he married Mary Ann Walker (1807–1849). Two years after her death, on 7 March 1851, he married Eliza Widdison. The two lived at 263 Hampstead Road, [[North London]].

Upon his death, it was discovered that Cruikshank had fathered 11 illegitimate children with a mistress named Adelaide Attree, his former servant, who lived close to where he lived with his wife. Adelaide was ostensibly married and had taken the married surname 'Archibold'.&lt;ref name="independent"&gt;{{cite news | url=https://www.independent.co.uk/news/uk/the-secret-life-of-a-virtuous-artist-john-wardroper-turned-sleuth-to-find-the-startling-truth-about-george-cruikshank-illustrator-and-friend-of-dickens-and-a-man-revered-as-a-stern-moralist-1559547.html | title=The secret life of a virtuous artist: John Wardroper turned sleuth to find the startling truth about George Cruikshank, illustrator and friend of Dickens, and a man revered as a stern moralist| author=John Wardroper|publisher=[[The Independent]] | date=25 October 1992 | accessdate=5 February 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Sociopolitical caricatures and illustrations==
Cruikshank's early career was renowned for his social caricatures of English life for popular publications.
He achieved early success collaborating with [[William Hone]] in his political satire ''The Political House That Jack Built'' (1819). [[File:The New Union Club Being a Representation of what took place at a celebrated Dinner given by a celebrated society.jpg|thumbnail|The New Union Club dinner with black guests]]In the same year he produced the remarkable anti-abolitionist ''New Union Club''. It satirised a dinner party organised by abolitionists with black guests.&lt;ref&gt;The caricature was devised in collaboration with Frederick Marryat (*[[Captain Marryat]]). See Temi Odumosu's article in ''The Slave in European Art: From Renaissance Trophy to Abolitionist Emblem'', ed Elizabeth McGrath and Jean Michel Massing, London (The Warburg Institute) and Turin 2012.&lt;/ref&gt;

His first major work was ''Pierce Egan's Life in London'' (1821)in which the characters Tom and
Jerry, two 'men about town' visit various London locations and taverns to enjoy themselves and carouse. This was followed by ''The Comic Almanack'' (1835–1853) and ''Omnibus'' (1842).
&lt;!-- Deleted image removed: [[File:Regent's brithday.jpg|thumb|left|''Merry Making on the Regent's Birthday'' 1812]] --&gt;
[[File:Cruikshank - Old Bumblehead.png|thumb|''Old Bumblehead the 18th trying on [[Napoleon]] Boots'' 1823]]

He gained notoriety with his political prints that attacked the royal family and leading politicians. In 1820 he received a royal bribe of £100 for a pledge "not to caricature His Majesty" ([[George IV of the United Kingdom]]) "in any immoral situation". His work included a personification of England named [[John Bull]] who was developed from about 1790 in conjunction with other British satirical artists such as [[James Gillray]], and [[Thomas Rowlandson]].&lt;ref&gt;Gatrell, Vic. ''City of Laughter: Sex and Satire in Eighteenth-Century London''. New York: Walker &amp; Co., 2006&lt;/ref&gt;

Cruikshank replaced one of his major influences, [[James Gillray]], as England's most popular satirist. For a generation he delineated [[Tories]], [[British Whig Party|Whigs]] and Radicals impartially. Satirical material came to him from every public event&amp;nbsp;– wars abroad, the enemies of Britain (he was highly patriotic), the frolic, among other qualities, such as the weird and terrible, in which he excelled. His hostility to enemies of Britain and a crude racism is evident in his illustrations commissioned to accompany [[William Hamilton Maxwell|William Maxwell's]] ''History of the Irish rebellion in 1798'' (1845) where his lurid depictions of incidents in the [[Irish Rebellion of 1798|rebellion]] were characterised by the [[simian]]-like portrayal of Irish rebels.  Among the other racially engaged works of Cruikshank there were caricatures about the "legal barbarities" of the Chinese, the subject given by his friend, Dr. W. Gourley, a participant in the ideological battle around the [[Second Opium War|Arrow War]], 1856–60. 
[[File:Cruikshank fagin cell.jpg|thumb|200px|right|''[[Fagin]] in his cell.''&lt;br&gt;Copperplate engraving, 1838]]

==Charles Dickens==
For [[Charles Dickens]], Cruikshank illustrated ''[[Sketches by Boz]]'' (1836), ''[[The Mudfog Papers]]'' (1837–38)  and ''[[Oliver Twist]]'' (1838). Cruikshank even acted in Dickens's amateur theatrical company.

On 30 December 1871 Cruikshank published a letter in ''[[The Times]]'' which claimed credit for much of the plot of ''Oliver Twist''. The letter launched a fierce controversy around who created the work. Cruikshank was not the first Dickens illustrator to make such a claim. [[Robert Seymour (illustrator)|Robert Seymour]] who illustrated the ''[[Pickwick Papers]]'' suggested that the idea for that novel was originally his; however, in his preface to the 1867 edition, Dickens strenuously denied any specific input.

The friendship between Cruikshank and Dickens soured further when Cruikshank became a fanatical [[teetotaler]] in opposition to Dickens's views of moderation.

In [[Somerset Maugham]]'s short story "Miss King", Cruickshank's influence is referenced: "She wore a large white cotton nightcap (on entering Ashenden has noticed the brown wig on a stand on the dressing-table) tied under the chin and a white voluminous nightdress that came high up in the neck. Nightcap and nightdress belonged to a past age and reminded you of Cruickshank's illustrations to the novels of Charles Dickens."

==Temperance and the Volunteers==
In the late 1840s, Cruikshank's focus shifted from book illustration to an obsession with [[temperance movement|temperance]] and [[anti-smoking]]. Formerly a heavy drinker, he now supported, lectured to, and supplied illustrations for the [[National Temperance Society]] and the Total Abstinence Society, among others. The best known of these are ''The Bottle'', 8 plates (1847), &lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|last=Beveridge|first=Allan|date=2006|title=Psychiatry in pictures|url=https://www.cambridge.org/core/journals/the-british-journal-of-psychiatry/article/psychiatry-in-pictures/6FE2F8E31CA295342E716867858E7778|journal=The British Journal of Psychiatry|language=en|volume=188|issue=1|pages=A2–A2|doi=10.1192/bjp.188.1.1-a2|issn=0007-1250|access-date=14 March 2018|via=}}&lt;/ref&gt;with its sequel, ''The Drunkard's Children'', 8 plates (1848), with the ambitious work, ''The Worship of Bacchus'', published by subscription after the artist's oil painting, now in the [[Tate Gallery, London]]. For his efforts he was made vice president of the [[National Temperance League]] in 1856.

When the invasion scare of 1859 led to the creation of the [[Volunteer Force (Great Britain)|Volunteer Movement]], Cruikshank was one of those who organised Rifle Volunteer Corps (RVCs). At first his unit was the 24th Surrey RVC, which recruited from working men who were total abstainers and was named 'Havelock's Own' in honour of Major-General Sir [[Henry Havelock]], a hero of the [[Indian Mutiny]] and pioneer of Temperance Clubs in the army. However, Cruikshank received little encouragement from the Lord-Lieutenant of Surrey, and was rebuked for crossing into Kent to recruit. Disgusted, he disbanded his unit in 1862 and began anew in Middlesex, organising the 48th Middlesex RVC (Havelock's Temperance Volunteers). The unit ran into financial difficulties and when Cruikshank was forced to retire due to age, he was replaced as commanding officer by Lt-Col Cuthbert Vickers, a wealthy shipowner. The 48th Middlesex merged with the 2nd City of London RVC, also a working-men's unit, composed mainly of printers from the Fleet Street area, and the combined unit had a long history as the [[City of London Rifles]].&lt;ref&gt;Ian F.W. Beckett, ''Riflemen Form: A study of the Rifle Volunteer Movement 1859–1908'', Aldershot: Ogilby Trusts, 1982, {{ISBN|0-85936-271-X}}, pp. 24–5, 45–6, 61 95 and Appendix VII.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Ray Westlake, ''Tracing the Rifle Volunteers'', Barnsley: Pen and Sword, 2010, {{ISBN|978-1-84884-211-3}}, p. 179.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Capt E.G. Godfrey, ''The "Cast Iron Sixth": A History of the Sixth Battalion London Regiment (The City of London Rifles)'', London: Old Comrades' Association, 1935//Uckfield: Naval &amp; Military Press, 2002, {{ISBN|1-84342-170-4}}, pp. 1–3.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.fusiliermuseumlondon.org/uncategorized/504/ ''Falling off the Wagon'' at Fusiliers Museum]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.london-gazette.co.uk/issues/32752/pages/7018/page.pdf Cuthbert Vickers probate, ''London Gazette'' 3 October 1922.]&lt;/ref&gt;

==Later years==
After he developed [[:wikt:palsy|palsy]] in later life, Cruikshank's health and work began to decline in quality. He died on 1&amp;nbsp;February 1878 and was originally buried in [[Kensal Green Cemetery]]. In November 1878 his remains were exhumed and reburied in [[St. Paul's Cathedral]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.victorianweb.org/art/parks/kensalgreen/12.html |title=Cruikshank's Grave Site on The Victorian Web |publisher=Victorianweb.org |date=2006-10-20 |accessdate=2013-11-22}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[Punch (magazine)|''Punch'' magazine]], which presumably did not know of his large illegitimate family, said in its obituary: "There never was a purer, simpler, more straightforward or altogether more blameless man. His nature had something childlike in its transparency."&lt;ref name="independent" /&gt;

In his lifetime he created nearly 10,000 prints, illustrations, and plates. There are collections of his works in the [[British Museum]] and the [[Victoria and Albert Museum]]. A [[Royal Society of Arts]] [[blue plaque]] commemorates Cruikshank at 293 Hampstead Road in [[Camden Town]].&lt;ref name='EngHet'&gt;{{cite web| url=http://www.english-heritage.org.uk/discover/blue-plaques/search/cruikshank-george-1792-1878|title=CRUIKSHANK, GEORGE (1792-1878)|publisher=English Heritage| accessdate=2012-10-23}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Samples of his work==
'''''[[The Life and Opinions of Tristram Shandy, Gentleman]]'''''
&lt;gallery mode=packed heights=180&gt;
File:George Cruikshank - Tristram Shandy, Plate I. The Effects of Trim's Eloquence.jpg|Plate I
File:George Cruikshank - Tristram Shandy, Plate II. Obadiah leading in Dr. Slop.jpg|Plate II
File:George Cruikshank - Tristram Shandy, Plate III. The Jack-boots transformed into Mortars.jpg|Plate III
File:George Cruikshank - Tristram Shandy, Plate IV. The long-nosed Stranger of Strasburg.jpg|Plate IV
File:George Cruikshank - Tristram Shandy, Plate V. My Uncle Toby on his Hobby-horse.jpg|Plate V
File:George Cruikshank - Tristram Shandy, Plate VI. Trim's relation of Tristram's misfortune.jpg|Plate VI
File:George Cruikshank - Tristram Shandy, Plate VII. The Quarrel of Slop and Susannah.jpg|Plate VII
File:George Cruikshank - Tristram Shandy, Plate VIII. The Smoking Batteries.jpg|Plate VIII
&lt;/gallery&gt;
'''Others'''
&lt;gallery mode=packed heights=180&gt;
File:Jacco1.jpg|[[Jacco Macacco]] at the [[Westminster-Pit]]''&lt;br&gt;1821.
File:1819 Prince Regent G Cruikshank caricature.png|An unflattering 1819 caricature of the [[George IV of the United Kingdom|Prince Regent]] illustrating "The Political House that Jack Built" by [[William Hone]].
File:1850-g-cruikshank-crinoline-parody.png|''A Splendid Spread'', early satire on the [[1850s in fashion|crinoline]] from ''The Comic Almanack'' for 1850.
File:Cruikshank-Self-Portrait-1858.jpg|George Cruikshank, ''Self-Portrait''.
File:Cruikshank-dandies.jpg|''Humming-birds—or—a Dandy Trio''. 1819.
File:Monstrosities-of-1818-Cruikshank.jpg|''Monstrosities of 1818'', extravagant clothing styles of men's and women's fashions.
File:Loo in the Kitchen.jpg|A group of servants gathered in a kitchen, ape the manners of their employers.
File:The old maid and her tom cat LCCN2006688809.jpg|Caricature of the [[Old Bailey]]
File:Spectacles-op.jpg|Caricature concerning the prices at the [[Covent Garden Theatre]]
File:British valour.jpg|1813 Caricature showing the Americans as cowardly in face of the British.
File:Cruikshank - Snuffing out Boney.png|''Snuffing out [[Napoleon Bonaparte|Boney]]'', 1814
File:1841 december 280.jpg|''December – A Swallow at Christmas (Rara avis in terris).''
&lt;/gallery&gt;

==References==
{{Reflist}}

==Further reading==
* Evans, Hilary and Mary: ''The Man Who Drew the Drunkard's Daughter: Life and Art of George Cruikshank, 1792-1878''. Frderick Muller, London. 1978. 
* Cruikshank, George. (1980). ''Graphic Works of George Cruikshank''. Dover Publications. {{ISBN|0-486-23438-X}}
* ''Catalogue of Political and Personal Satires Preserved in the Department of Prints and Drawings in the British Museum'', Mary Dorothy George. Vol VI 1938,  Vol VII, 1942 VOL VIII 1947, VOL IX 1949
* ''Dictionary of British Cartoonists and caricaturists 1730–1980'' Bryant and Heneage, Scolar Press 1994
* ''The Book Illustrations of George Cruikshank'' Buchanan-Brown, John. Charles Tuttle 1980
* ''George Cruikshank A Catalogue Raisonne of the work executed during the years 1896–1977'' Cohn, Albert M . Bookmans Journal, London 1924
* ''Bates, William, George Cruikshank : the artist, the humourist, and the man, with some account of his brother Robert. A critico-bibliographical essay'', Amsterdam, Emmering, 1972

==External links==
{{Commons|George Cruikshank}}
* [http://www.surlalunefairytales.com/illustrations/illustrators/cruikshank.html SurLaLune Fairy Tale Pages: Fairy Tale Illustrations of George Cruikshank]
* [http://www.cartoonstock.com/vintage/vintage_search.asp?x=a&amp;keyword=&amp;Category=Not+Selected&amp;Boolean=Or&amp;Artist=Cruikshank%2C+George&amp;submit=Search George Cruikshank cartoons at CartoonStock] (Commercial site)
* [http://www.cruikshankart.com/illustrations/ Online Gallery of Illustrations by George Cruikshank]
* [https://web.archive.org/web/20081204015405/https://library.rice.edu/collections/WRC/finding-aids/manuscripts/0297 George Cruikshank letters, 1845 and 1868] from the Woodson Research Center at Rice University
* [https://web.archive.org/web/20090417021945/https://library.rice.edu/collections/WRC/finding-aids/manuscripts/0493 Patten Research Material on George Cruikshank] from the Woodson Research Center at Rice University
* {{UK National Archives ID}}
* {{Gutenberg author |id=Cruikshank,+George | name=George Cruikshank}}
* {{Internet Archive author |sname=George Cruikshank}}
* [https://www.flickr.com/search/?tags=artist:name=%22George%20Cruikshank%22 Works by George Cruikshank on Flickr Commons]
* [http://www.lambiek.net/cruikshank_george.htm George Cruikshank] at [[Lambiek#Comiclopedia|Comiclopedia]]
*[http://www.oac.cdlib.org/findaid/ark:/13030/c8rj4gx8 Guide to the George Cruikshank Etchings.] Special Collections and Archives, The UC Irvine Libraries, Irvine, California.
* {{EB1911|wstitle=Cruikshank, George|volume=7|pages=523–524}}
* {{LCAuth|n80067117|George Cruikshank|632|ue}}

{{Victorian children's literature}}

{{Authority control}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Cruikshank, George}}
[[Category:1792 births]]
[[Category:1878 deaths]]
[[Category:English people of Scottish descent]]
[[Category:19th-century engravers]]
[[Category:British engravers]]
[[Category:Burials at Kensal Green Cemetery]]
[[Category:Burials at St Paul's Cathedral]]
[[Category:Charles Dickens]]
[[Category:English caricaturists]]
[[Category:English cartoonists]]
[[Category:English illustrators]]
[[Category:English satirists]]
[[Category:Artists from London]]</text>
      <sha1>hq8zr0wrui30ibmkvkb00hdt021cjd2</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
