<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10.xsd" version="0.10" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <dbname>enwiki</dbname>
    <base>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.32.0-wmf.16</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="118" case="first-letter">Draft</namespace>
      <namespace key="119" case="first-letter">Draft talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2300" case="first-letter">Gadget</namespace>
      <namespace key="2301" case="first-letter">Gadget talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2302" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition</namespace>
      <namespace key="2303" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>John Leech (caricaturist)</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>277716</id>
    <revision>
      <id>826963556</id>
      <parentid>821024552</parentid>
      <timestamp>2018-02-22T00:16:34Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Tom.Reding</username>
        <id>9784415</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor/>
      <comment>Fix [[:Category:Pages using deprecated image syntax]]; [[WP:GenFixes]] on, using [[Project:AWB|AWB]]</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="16994">{{Other people|John Leech}}
{{Use dmy dates|date=April 2012}}
{{Infobox person
| name= John Leech 
| image= JohnLeechHimself.jpg
| image_size= 230px
| caption= ''Portrait of John Leech''&lt;br&gt; Engraving published in ''[[Punch (magazine)|Punch]]''
| birth_date= {{birth date|1817|08|29|df=y}}
| birth_place= [[London]], [[England]]
| death_date= {{Death date and age|1864|10|29|1817|08|29|df=y}}
| death_place= London, England
| nationality= English 
| occupation= [[Caricaturist]] and [[illustrator]]
}}
'''John Leech''' (29 August 1817 &amp;ndash; 29 October 1864 in London) was an English [[caricaturist]] and [[illustrator]].&lt;ref name=ray&gt;{{cite book|last=Ray|first=Gordon N.|chapter=John Leech (1817 – 1864)|title=The illustrator and the book in England from 1790 to 1914|year=1991|publisher=Dover|pages=82|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=HsTU8eWtej8C&amp;pg=PA82|isbn=9780486269559}}&lt;/ref&gt; He is best known for his work for ''[[Punch (magazine)|Punch]]'', a humorous magazine for a  broad middle-class audience, combining verbal and graphic political satire with light social comedy. Leech catered to contemporary prejudices, such as [[anti-Americanism]] and [[antisemitism]] and supported acceptable social reforms. Leech's critical yet humorous cartoons on the [[Crimean War]] help shape public attitudes toward heroism, warfare, and Britons' role in the world.&lt;ref&gt;Richard D. Altick, "'Punch's First Ten Years: The Ingredients of Success", ''Journal of Newspaper &amp; Periodical History'' (1991) 7#2 pp. 5–16&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Henry J. Miller, "John Leech and the Shaping of the Victorian Cartoon: The Context of Respectability", ''Victorian Periodicals Review'' (2009) 42#3 pp. 267–291.&lt;/ref&gt;

==Early life==
John Leech was born in London.  His father, a native of Ireland, was the landlord of the London Coffee House on [[Ludgate Hill]], "a man", on the testimony of those who knew him, "of fine culture, a profound Shakespearian, and a thorough gentleman." His mother was descended from the family of [[Richard Bentley]]. It was from his father that Leech inherited his skill with the pencil, which he began to use at a very early age. When he was only three, he was discovered by [[John Flaxman]], who was visiting, seated on his mother's knee, drawing with much gravity. The sculptor admired his sketch, adding, "Do not let him be cramped with lessons in drawing; let his genius follow its own bent; he will astonish the world"&amp;mdash;advice which was followed. A mail-coach, done when he was six years old, is already full of surprising vigour and variety in its galloping horses. Leech was educated at [[Charterhouse School]], where [[William Makepeace Thackeray]], his lifelong friend, was a fellow pupil, and at sixteen he began to study for the medical profession at [[St Bartholomew's Hospital]], where he won praise for the accuracy and beauty of his anatomical drawings. He was then placed under a Mr Whittle, an eccentric practitioner, the original of "Rawkins" in [[Albert Richard Smith|Albert Smith]]'s ''Adventures of Mr Ledbury'', and afterwards under Dr John Cockle; but gradually he drifted into the artistic profession. His nickname also being "Blicky" stuck with him during his life, along with being famous.

==Artistic career==
[[Image:Comic History of Rome p 010 The Romans walking off with the Sabine Women.jpg|thumb|A scene from Leech's ''Comic History of Rome'', depicting the ''[[Rape of the Sabine Women]]''. The women are portrayed in Victorian costume being carried off from the "Corona et Ancora" ("Crown and Anchor", a common English pub sign in seafaring towns)]]

He was eighteen when his first designs were published, a quarto of four pages, entitled ''Etchings and Sketchings by A. Pen, Esq.'', comic character studies from the London streets. Then he drew some political [[lithograph]]s, did rough sketches for ''Bell's Life'', produced a popular parody on Mulready's postal envelope, and, on the death of Dickens illustrator [[Robert Seymour (illustrator)|Robert Seymour]] in 1836, unsuccessfully submitted his renderings to illustrate the ''[[Pickwick Papers]]''.

In 1840 Leech began his contributions to the magazines with a series of etchings in ''[[Bentley's Miscellany]]'', where [[George Cruikshank]] had published his plates to ''Jack Sheppard'' and ''[[Oliver Twist]]'', and was illustrating ''[[Guy Fawkes]]'' in feebler fashion.

In company with the elder master Leech designed for the ''[[Ingoldsby Legends]]'' and [[Stanley Thorn]], and until 1847 produced many independent series of etchings. These were not his best work; their technique is imperfect and we never feel that they express the artist's individuality, the [[Richard Savage (poet)|Richard Savage]] plates, for instance, being strongly reminiscent of Cruikshank, and ''The Dance at Stamford Hall'' of [[Hablot Browne]].

In 1845 Leech illustrated St Giles and St James in [[Douglas William Jerrold]]'s new ''Shilling Magazine'', with plates more vigorous and accomplished than those in Bentley, but it is in subjects of a somewhat later date, and especially in those lightly etched and meant to be printed with colour, that we see the artist's best powers with the needle and acid.

[[Image:Charles Dickens-A Christmas Carol-Title page-First edition 1843.jpg|thumb|left|Frontispiece of Dickens' ''[[A Christmas Carol]]'', first edition 1843, illustrated by Leech.]]  
Among such of his designs are four charming plates to [[Charles Dickens]]'s ''[[A Christmas Carol]]'' (1843), the broadly humorous etchings in the ''Comic History of England'' (1847&amp;ndash;1848),&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://posner.library.cmu.edu/Posner/books/book.cgi?call=942_A13CO|title=Posner Memorial Collection in Electronic Format|work=cmu.edu}}&lt;/ref&gt; and the still finer illustrations to the ''Comic History of Rome'' (1852)&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://posner.library.cmu.edu/Posner/books/book.cgi?call=937_A138C_1850|title=Posner Memorial Collection in Electronic Format|work=cmu.edu}}&lt;/ref&gt; &amp;mdash;which last, particularly in its minor woodcuts, shows some exquisitely graceful touches, as witness the fair faces that rise from the surging water in ''[[:File:Comic History of Rome p 052 Claelia and her Companions escaping from the Etruscan Camp.jpg|''Cloelia and her Companions Escaping from the Etruscan Camp.]]''

Among his other etchings are those in ''Young Master Troublesome'' or ''Master Jacky's Holidays'', and the frontispiece to ''Hints on Life, or How to Rise in Society'' (1845)&amp;mdash;a series of minute subjects linked gracefully together by coils of smoke, illustrating the various ranks and conditions of men, one of them&amp;mdash;the doctor by his patient's bedside&amp;mdash;almost equalling in vivacity and precision the best of Cruikshank's similar scenes.

Then in the 1850s come the numerous etchings of sporting scenes, contributed, together with woodcuts, to the Handley Cross novels by [[Robert Smith Surtees]].
{{Clear}}

==Lithographic work==
Turning to Leech's [[lithograph]]ic work, we have, in 1841, the ''Portraits of the Children of the Mobility'', an important series dealing with the humorous and pathetic aspects of London street "Arabs", which were afterwards so often and so effectively to employ the artist's pencil. Amid all the squalor which they depict, they are full of individual beauties in the delicate or touching expression of a face, in the graceful turn of a limb. The book is scarce in its original form, but in 1875 two reproductions of the outline sketches for the designs were published&amp;mdash;a lithographic issue of the whole series, and a finer photographic transcript of six of the subjects, which is more valuable than even the finished illustrations of 1841, in which the added light and shade is frequently spotty and ineffective, arid the lining itself has not the freedom which we find in some of Leech's other lithographs, notably in the Fly Leaves, published at the ''[[Punch magazine|Punch]]'' office, and in the inimitable subject of the nuptial couch of the Caudles, which also appeared, in woodcut form, as a political cartoon, with Mrs Caudle, personated by Brougham, disturbing by untimely loquacity the slumbers of the lord chancellor, whose haggard cheek rests on the woolsack for pillow.

==Wood engraving==
[[Image:SubstanceandShadow.jpg|thumb|''Substance and Shadow'', published in ''Punch'', 1843, the first use of the word ''[[cartoon]]'' to refer to a satirical drawing]]It was in work for the wood-engravers that Leech was most prolific and individual. Among the earlier of such designs are the illustrations to the ''Comic English'' and ''Latin Grammars'' (1840), to ''Written Caricatures'' (1841), to ''Hood's Comic Annual'', (1842), and to Albert Smith's ''Wassail Bowl'' (1843), subjects mainly of a small vignette size, transcribed with the best skill of such woodcutters as [[John Orrin Smith|Orrin Smith]], and not, like the larger and later ''Punch'' illustrations, cut at speed by several engravers working at once on the subdivided block.

It was in 1841 that Leech's connection with ''Punch'' began, a connexion which subsisted until his death, and resulted in the production of the best-known and most admirable of his designs. His first contribution appeared in the issue of 7 August, a full-page illustration&amp;mdash;entitled ''Foreign Affairs'' of character studies from the neighbourhood of [[Leicester Square]]. His cartoons deal at first mainly with social subjects, and are rough and imperfect in execution, but gradually their method gains in power and their subjects become more distinctly political, and by 1849 the artist is strong enough to produce the splendidly humorous national personification which appears in ''[[Benjamin Disraeli|Disraeli]] Measuring the British Lion.''

About 1845 we have the first of that long series of half-page and quarter-page pictures of life and manners, executed with a hand as gentle as it was skilful, containing, as [[John Ruskin|Ruskin]] has said, "admittedly the finest definition and natural history of the classes of our society, the kindest and subtlest analysis of its foibles, the tenderest flattery of its pretty and well-bred ways", which has yet appeared.

In addition to his work for the weekly issue of ''Punch'', Leech contributed largely to the ''Punch'' almanacks and pocket-books, from ''Once a Week'' between 1859 and 1862, to the ''[[Illustrated London News]]'', where some of his largest and best sporting scenes appeared, and to innumerable novels and miscellaneous volumes besides, of which it is only necessary to specify ''A Little Tour in Ireland'' (1859). This last piece is noticeable as showing the artist's treatment of pure landscape, though it also contains some of his daintiest figurepieces, like that of the wind-blown girl, standing on the summit of a pedestal, with the swifts darting around her and the breadth of sea beyond.

==Public exhibition==
In 1862 Leech appealed to the public with a very successful exhibition of some of the most remarkable of his ''Punch'' drawings. These were enlarged by a mechanical process, and coloured in oils by the artist himself, with the assistance and under the direction of his friend [[John Everett Millais]]. Millais had earlier painted a portrait of a child reading Leech's comic book ''Mr Briggs' Sporting Tour''.

==Character==
Leech was a rapid and indefatigable worker. Dean Hole said  he observed the artist produce three finished drawings on the wood, designed, traced, and rectified, "without much effort as it seemed, between breakfast and dinner". The best technical qualities of Leech's art, his precision and vivacity in the use of the line, are seen most clearly in the first sketches for his woodcuts, and in the more finished drawings made on [[tracing-paper]] from these first outlines, before the ''[[chiaroscuro]]'' was added and the designs were transcribed by the engraver. Turning to the mental qualities of his art, it would be a mistaken criticism which ranked him as a comic draughtsman. Like [[William Hogarth|Hogarth]] he was a true humorist, a student of human life, though he observed humanity mainly in its whimsical aspects,
:Hitting all he saw with shafts
:With gentle satire, kin to charity,
:That harmed not.
The earnestness and gravity of moral purpose which is so constant a note in the work of Hogarth is indeed far less characteristic of Leech, but there are touches of [[pathos]] and of tragedy in such of the ''Punch'' designs as the ''Poor Man's Friend'' (1845), and ''General Février turned Traitor'' (1855), and in ''The Queen of the Arena'' in the first volume of ''Once a Week'', which are sufficient to prove that more solemn powers, for which his daily work afforded no scope, lay dormant in their artist.

The purity and manliness of Leech's own character are impressed on his art. We find in it little of the exaggeration and grotesqueness, and none of the fierce political enthusiasm, of which the designs of [[James Gillray]] are so full. Compared with that of his great contemporary, George Cruikshank, his work is restricted both in compass of subject and in artistic dexterity.

==Gallery==
&lt;div align="center"&gt;
&lt;gallery caption="[[A Christmas Carol]] by [[Charles Dickens]]"&gt;
Image:Charles Dickens-A Christmas Carol-Title page-First edition 1843.jpg|First page of first edition of ''[[A Christmas Carol]]'' by [[Charles Dickens]]
Image:Marley's Ghost-John Leech, 1843.jpg|''[[Jacob Marley]]'s [[Ghost]]''
Image:Scrooges_third_visitor-John_Leech,1843.jpg|''The [[Ghost of Christmas Present]]''
Image:The Last of the Spirits-John Leech, 1843.jpg|''[[Ghost of Christmas Yet to Come]]''
&lt;/gallery&gt;

&lt;gallery caption="[[The Comic History of Rome]] by [[Gilbert Abbott à Beckett]]"&gt;
Image:Comic History of Rome Title.jpg|Title page of ''[[The Comic History of Rome]]''
Image:Comic History of Rome Table 01 Romulus and Remus discovered by a gentle shepherd.jpg|''[[Romulus and Remus]] discovered by a gentle [[Shepherd]]''.
Image:Comic History of Rome Table 04 The gallant Curtius leaping into the gulfs.jpg|''[[Marcus Curtius]] leaping into the Gulf''
Image:Comic History of Rome Table 06 Hannibal whilst even yet a child swears eternal hatred to the Romans.jpg|''[[Hannibal]] swears eternal hatred to the [[Ancient Rome|Romans]] as a child''.
Image:Comic History of Rome Table 08 The Mother of the Gracchi.jpg|''[[Cornelia Africana]], mother of the [[Gracchi]]''
&lt;/gallery&gt;

&lt;gallery caption="Other"&gt;
File:The end of opium-smoking.jpg|''The end of opium-smoking'', 1848
Image:John Leech00.jpg|''Two Ladies and a Gentleman in a Rowboat''
Image:The Battle of Bosworth Field - A Scene from the Great Drama of History.jpg|''The Battle of Bosworth Field, a Scene in the Great Drama of History'', illustrated by John Leech for [[Gilbert Abbott à Beckett]], mocking the Victorian attitude towards history.
&lt;/gallery&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

== References ==
{{Reflist}}
Biographies of Leech have been written by

* John Brown, ''John Leech, and Other Papers'', D. Douglas, 1882 ; HardPress Publishing, 2013 
* [[Frederick George Kitton|Frederick G. Kitton]], [http://catalog.hathitrust.org/Record/007663703 ''John Leech, artist and humorist: a biographical sketch''] (1883)
* [[William Powell Frith]], ''John Leech: His Life and Work'' (1891)

== Further reading ==
*  Houfe, Simon. "Leech, John (1817–1864)", ''Oxford Dictionary of National Biography'' (Oxford University Press, 2004); online edn, 2014 [http://www.oxforddnb.com/view/article/16322, accessed 13 June 2015]
*  Houfe, Simon. ''John Leech and the Victorian scene'' (1984) 
* Markovits, Stefanie. ''The Crimean War in the British Imagination'' (Cambridge University Press, 2009), Chapter on Leech's artwork regarding the Crimean war
* Miller, Henry J.  "John Leech and the Shaping of the Victorian Cartoon: The Context of Respectability," ''Victorian Periodicals Review'' (2009) 42#3 pp 267–291. 
* Thackeray, William Makepeace. "John Leech's Pictures of Life and Character",  ''Quarterly Review'' No. 191, Dec. 1854, [http://www.gutenberg.org/files/2646/2646-h/2646-h.htm online]
*{{Cite EB1911|wstitle=Leech, John}}

== External links ==
{{wikisource}}
{{commonscat|John Leech}}
{{Portal |Cartoons}}
*[http://www.john-leech-archive.org.uk/ The John Leech ''Punch'' magazine sketch archives]
* {{Gutenberg author | id=Leech,+John | name=John Leech}}
* {{FadedPage|id=Leech, John|name=John Leech|author=yes}}
* {{Internet Archive author |sname=John Leech |birth=1817 |death=1864}}
* {{LCAuth|n79054670|John Leech|84|ue}}

{{Authority control}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Leech, John}}
[[Category:English illustrators]]
[[Category:English caricaturists]]
[[Category:Artists from London]]
[[Category:1817 births]]
[[Category:1864 deaths]]
[[Category:Charles Dickens]]
[[Category:Punch (magazine) cartoonists]]
[[Category:Alumni of the Medical College of St Bartholomew's Hospital]]
[[Category:Artists' Rifles soldiers]]
[[Category:People educated at Charterhouse School]]
[[Category:Burials at Kensal Green Cemetery]]</text>
      <sha1>g0eor8ew97txbe41sbzopu4tjw1n7p2</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
