<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10.xsd" version="0.10" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <dbname>enwiki</dbname>
    <base>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.32.0-wmf.16</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="118" case="first-letter">Draft</namespace>
      <namespace key="119" case="first-letter">Draft talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2300" case="first-letter">Gadget</namespace>
      <namespace key="2301" case="first-letter">Gadget talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2302" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition</namespace>
      <namespace key="2303" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Mort Drucker</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>265918</id>
    <revision>
      <id>848744845</id>
      <parentid>848742351</parentid>
      <timestamp>2018-07-04T01:03:40Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Zingarese</username>
        <id>33444846</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor/>
      <comment>Reverted edits by [[Special:Contributions/2604:2000:4011:2800:8E:9333:79C3:9FE0|2604:2000:4011:2800:8E:9333:79C3:9FE0]] ([[User talk:2604:2000:4011:2800:8E:9333:79C3:9FE0|talk]]) ([[WP:HG|HG]]) (3.4.3)</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="13568">{{Use mdy dates|date=December 2014}}
{{Infobox comics creator
| name          = Mort Drucker
| image         = Mort Drucker.jpg
| imagesize     = 
| caption       = Drucker in November 2000
| birth_name    = Mort Drucker
| birth_date    = {{birth date and age|1929|03|22}}
| birth_place   = [[Brooklyn]], New York City
| nationality   = American
| signature     = 
| area          = [[Cartoonist]], artist
| notable works = [[Mad (magazine)|''Mad'']]
| awards        = 
| website     ={{url|adriansinnott.com/mortdrucker.html}}
}}
'''Mort Drucker''' (born March 22, 1929) is an American [[caricaturist]] and comics artist best known as a contributor for over five decades in ''[[Mad (magazine)|Mad]]'', where he specialized in satires on the leading feature films and television series. Some sources list his birth date as March 22 and others as March 29.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.tomrichmond.com/blog/2009/03/29/happy-80th-birthday-mort-drucker/ |last=Richmond |first=Tom |title=Happy 80th Birthday, Mort Drucker |website=Tom's MAD Blog! |publisher=MAD Magazine |date=March 30, 2009 |accessdate=April 23, 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In a 1985 ''[[Tonight Show]]'' appearance, when [[Johnny Carson]] asked [[Michael J. Fox]], "When did you really know you'd made it in show business?", Fox replied, "When Mort Drucker drew my head."&lt;ref&gt;MAD's Greatest Artists: Mort Drucker, 2012, Running Press, pg. 7&lt;/ref&gt;

==Early life==
Born in [[Brooklyn]], New York City,&lt;ref name=mort&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.reuben.org/ncs/members/bios/Drucker.jpg|title=Mort Drucker bio|publisher=National Cartoonists Society|format=JPG|accessdate=August 31, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; Drucker attended Brooklyn's [[Erasmus Hall High School]]. There he met his future wife Barbara, whom he married shortly after her graduation. The couple moved to [[Long Island]], living in [[Woodbury, Nassau County, New York|Woodbury]], where they brought up two daughters, Laurie and Melanie; their family eventually expanded with three grandchildren.&lt;ref name=man&gt;"Man Behind the Drawing Board", ''The Adventures of Bob Hope'' 87, 1963.&lt;/ref&gt;

==Career==
Drucker entered the comics field by assisting Bert Whitman on the newspaper comic strip ''Debbie Dean'' in 1947 when he was 18, based on a recommendation from [[Will Eisner]]. He then joined the staff of National Periodical Publications ([[DC Comics]]), where he worked as a retoucher. While at DC, Drucker also [[ghostwriting|ghosted]] "The Mountain Boys," Paul Webb's regular gag panel for [[Esquire Magazine]].&lt;ref name=man/&gt; Early in the 1950s, Drucker left his DC staff gig and began doing full-time freelance work for a number of comic book publishers such as [[Dell Comics|Dell]], [[Atlas Comics (1950s)|Atlas]] and [[St. John Publications|St. John's]], as well as several humor and war titles for his former employer.

===''Mad''===
In the fall of 1956, shortly after the departure of ''Mad'''s founding editor [[Harvey Kurtzman]], Drucker found his way to ''Mad''. His first visit to the magazine's offices coincided with a [[World Series]] broadcast, and publisher [[Bill Gaines]] told Drucker that if the [[Brooklyn Dodgers]] won the game, he would be given a drawing assignment. The Dodgers did win. Capricious though Drucker's alleged audition process may have been, it made for a good anecdote. Years later, Gaines unsurprisingly confessed, "We would have hired him anyway."

By the time he wound down his ''Mad'' career 55 years later, Drucker held the longest uninterrupted tenure of any ''Mad'' artist.  Drucker has the most bylined articles by any ''Mad'' artist who does not also write his own material, with more than 400.

Drucker had arrived at the ''Mad'' offices with pages from his [[Hopalong Cassidy]] comic book work for [[DC Comics]] and some of his "Mountain Boys" strips, as well as a humorous "little situation" featuring [[The Lone Ranger]] and [[Tonto]] that he had specifically drawn for the interview.  Though this work was unlike the likenesses and continuities he would become best known for, the ''Mad'' staff reacted favorably.  The first to review Drucker's portfolio was ''Mad'' associate editor [[Nick Meglin]], who admitted, "I didn't spot how great he was at caricatures.  Not at first.  But then, he wasn't that great then."  Drucker himself says that he "just wanted to be an artist... to get paid for drawing anything," and only started focusing on caricature work because he started getting more and more of those assignments.  "That's when I realized I'd found my calling," said Drucker.&lt;ref&gt;Evanier, Mark, ''MAD Art'', Watson-Guptill Publications, 2002&lt;/ref&gt; At the time of Drucker's arrival, ''Mad'' did not regularly feature TV and movie satires; editor [[Al Feldstein]] credited Drucker's style and ability for the decision to start featuring them in every issue.

Meglin called Drucker "number one in a field of one."  [[Charles Schulz]] wrote, "Frankly, I don't know how he does it, and I stand in a long list of admirers... I think he draws everything the way we would all like to draw."  In 2012, referring to Drucker's splash page for ''Mad'''s parody of ''[[The Godfather]]'', the Comics Reporter's [[Tom Spurgeon]] wrote, "The way he draws [[James Caan]]'s eyebrow is worth some folks' entire careers."&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.comicsreporter.com/index.php/bundled_tossed_untied_and_stacked052212/ |title=Bundled, Tossed, Untied And Stacked |first=Tom |last=Spurgeon |date=May 22, 2012 |website=The Comics Reporter |publisher=Tom Spurgeon |accessdate=April 23, 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In 2012, Drucker discussed his art style, and how he applied it to his ''Mad'' assignments:

&lt;blockquote&gt;I've always considered a caricature to be the complete person, not just a likeness.  Hands in particular have always been a prime focus for me as they can be as expressive of character as the exaggerations and distortions a caricaturist searches for.  I try to capture the essence of the person, not just facial features... I've discovered through years of working at capturing a humorous likeness that it's not about the features themselves as much as the space between the features.  We all have two eyes, a nose, a mouth, hair and jaw lines, but yet we all look different.  What makes that so is the space between them.

The artist is actually creating his own storyboard for the film.  I become the "camera" and look for angles, lighting, close-ups, wide angles, long shots-- just as a director does to tell the story in the most visually interesting way he can.  My first sketches are as much composition and design ideas as they are character and action images... I don't want to get too involved in the juicy parts since some of what I'm doing will be modified or discarded as I get further involved in the storytelling.  I then stand back and look at the page as a complete unit to make sure it's designed well: "Hmmm, three close-up panels in a row of characters talking.  Better change that middle panel to a far shot.  Maybe make that panel an open vignette."  ...Then I place the facing pages together and look at how the spread holds together, and sometimes make changes based on that.&lt;ref&gt;MAD's Greatest Artists: Mort Drucker, 2012, Running Press, pg. 13&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

===Other work===
Drucker also remained active for DC, illustrating ''War Stories'', among other titles. Beginning in 1959, he spent four years drawing DC's ''[[The Adventures of Bob Hope]]'' comic book.&lt;ref name=man/&gt;  Drucker credits this stint as a key moment in his career, because it focused his work on caricature.&lt;ref&gt;MAD's Greatest Artists: Mort Drucker, 2012, Running Press, pg. 12&lt;/ref&gt;

In 1962, Drucker teamed with the prolific humor writer [[Paul Laikin]] on the highly successful ''JFK Coloring Book'' (Kanrom Publishers), which sold 2,500,000 copies.  Two decades later, Drucker illustrated similar coloring books on [[Ollie North]] and [[Ronald Reagan]].&lt;ref name=man/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;''Pacific Stars and Stripes'', August 24, 1987.&lt;/ref&gt; His film posters include [[Universal Studios|Universal]]'s ''[[American Graffiti]]'' (1973), directed by [[George Lucas]]&lt;ref name=mort/&gt; with Drucker also drawing the [[high school yearbook]] pictures in the [[film trailer]].

Drucker also pursued assignments in television animation, movie poster art and magazine illustration, including covers for ''[[Time (magazine)|Time]]'', some of which are in the [[National Portrait Gallery (United States)|National Portrait Gallery]] of the [[Smithsonian Institution]]. His album covers include art for the pop band [[The Bears (band)|The Bears]]&lt;ref&gt;http://www.adrianbelew.net/index.php?option=com_content&amp;view=article&amp;id=58&amp;Itemid=64&lt;/ref&gt; and the [[Anthrax (American band)|Anthrax]] album ''[[State of Euphoria]],'' as well as humor albums in the vein of his own "JFK Coloring Book" including "The LBJ Menagerie" and "The New First Family, 1968."  In addition to books collecting his own work, he has provided illustrations for numerous books by others, including [[children's literature|children's books]], humor books and satire. He drew the prop cartoons used in the 1957 Broadway musical comedy, ''Rumple'', starring [[Gretchen Wyler]], [[Elliott Gould]] and [[Eddie Foy, Jr.]]&lt;ref name=man/&gt;

Between 1984 and 1987, Drucker collaborated with [[Jerry Dumas]] (and [[John Reiner]]) on the daily comic strip ''Benchley''. Set in the [[White House]], the plot revolved around the fictive character Benchley who acted as the assistant and admirer of contemporary president [[Ronald Reagan]]. Dumas commented, "Nobody ever did a strip about the government. It's a wonderful place to set a strip. There's so much room for humor in the White House."&lt;ref&gt;"Comic strip set in White House", ''Lethbridge Herald'' ([[Lethbridge]], [[Alberta, Canada|Alberta]], Canada), July 5, 1984.&lt;/ref&gt; ''Benchley'' was syndicated by the [[Register and Tribune Syndicate]].&lt;ref name="(editor)"&gt;{{cite book|author=Gary Dowell, Greg Holman, Don Mangus, James L. Halperin (editor)|title=HCA Comics Dallas Auction Catalog #824|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=8FcK3PE35EkC|publisher=Heritage Capital Corporation|isbn=978-1-59967-133-8|page=268 ([https://books.google.com/books?id=8FcK3PE35EkC&amp;pg=PA268&amp;lpg=PA268&amp;dq=Benchley+Jerry+Dumas+Mort+Drucker link])}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In 1990, Drucker designed the Supercup for Target. The following year, for the United Fresh Fruit and Vegetable Association, Drucker and executive Mitchell Erick created the Frugies (pronounced ''fru-jees'') to promote June as National Fresh Fruit and Vegetable Month. The campaign included such characters as Lord Mushroom, Pepe L'Pepper, Penelope Pear and Adam Apple.&lt;ref&gt;''Frederick News-Post'', June 12, 1991.&lt;/ref&gt;

==Awards==
Mort Drucker's ''Time'' covers are in the collection of the [[National Portrait Gallery (United States)|National Portrait Gallery]]. He was recognized for his work with the [[National Cartoonists Society]] Special Features Award (1985, 1986, 1987, 1988), its [[Reuben Award]] (1987), and induction into the Society's Hall of Fame (2017).&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.reuben.org/ncs/awards.asp National Cartoonists Society Awards]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;http://www.reuben.org/2017/06/10073/&lt;/ref&gt; Drucker was awarded an Honorary Doctor of Fine Arts degree from the Art Institute of Boston.

==Bibliography==
*''MAD's Greatest Artists: Mort Drucker'' by Mort Drucker. Running Press, 2012.
*''Tomatoes from Mars'' by Arthur Yorinks and Mort Drucker.  Di Capua, 1999.
*''Whitefish Will Rides Again!'' by Arthur Yorinks and Mort Drucker.  Di Capua, 1994.
*''Draw 50 Famous Caricatures'' by Mort Drucker and Lee J. Ames. Doubleday, 1990.
*''The Ronald Reagan Coloring Book'' by Mort Drucker and Paul Laikin.  Andrews and McMeel, 1988.
*''Familiar Faces: The Art of Mort Drucker'' by David Duncan and Mort Drucker.  Stabur Press, 1988.
*''The Ollie North Coloring Book'' by Mort Drucker and Paul Laikin. Andrews McMeel, 1987.
*''Benchley, Book 1'' by Mort Drucker.  Blackthorne, 1987.
*''Mort Drucker's MAD Show-Stoppers'' by Mort Drucker.  EC, 1985.
*''What to Name Your Jewish Baby'' by Bill Adler and Mort Drucker and Arnie Kogen.  Dutton, 1969.
*''My Son, the Daughter'' by Mort Drucker.  Kanrom, 1964.
*''Political Wind-Ups'' by Alexander Roman and Mort Drucker.  Kanrom, 1962.
*''JFK Coloring Book'' by Alexander Roman and Mort Drucker.  Kanrom, 1962.

===Illustrations for books by others===
*''A Book of Jean's Own'', [[Maria Schneider (cartoonist)|Maria Schneider]] writing as Jean Teasdale. St. Martin's Griffin, 2010.
*''Christopher Lee's Treasury of Terror'', edited by [[Russ Jones]]. Pyramid, 1966.

==References==
{{Reflist}}

==External links==
{{commons category}}
*[http://www.adriansinnott.com/mortdrucker.html Mort Drucker official site]
*[http://madcoversite.com/ugoi-mort_drucker.html Mort Drucker's ''Mad'' contributions]
*[http://www.tomrichmond.com/blog/2006/09/29/the-mort-drucker-caricature-story/ Tom Richmond: "The Mort Drucker Caricature Story"]

{{Mad magazine}}
{{Madcontribs}}
{{Society of Illustrators' Hall of Fame}}
{{Authority control}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Drucker, Mort}}
[[Category:1929 births]]
[[Category:American cartoonists]]
[[Category:American caricaturists]]
[[Category:Artists from New York City]]
[[Category:Film poster artists]]
[[Category:Album-cover and concert-poster artists]]
[[Category:Living people]]
[[Category:Mad (magazine) cartoonists]]
[[Category:People from Brooklyn]]
[[Category:Jewish American artists]]
[[Category:Reuben Award winners]]
[[Category:People from Woodbury, Nassau County, New York]]
[[Category:Erasmus Hall High School alumni]]</text>
      <sha1>ro9umz7xt6omdr57kb8ygk9stmmd9eo</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
