<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10.xsd" version="0.10" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <dbname>enwiki</dbname>
    <base>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.32.0-wmf.16</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="118" case="first-letter">Draft</namespace>
      <namespace key="119" case="first-letter">Draft talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2300" case="first-letter">Gadget</namespace>
      <namespace key="2301" case="first-letter">Gadget talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2302" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition</namespace>
      <namespace key="2303" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Allan Sherman</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>157548</id>
    <revision>
      <id>851580261</id>
      <parentid>845497790</parentid>
      <timestamp>2018-07-23T08:03:25Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>InternetArchiveBot</username>
        <id>27015025</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>Rescuing 1 sources and tagging 0 as dead. #IABot (v2.0beta3) ([[User:Feminist|Feminist]])</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="35433">{{Use mdy dates|date=July 2011}}
{{Infobox person
 | name             = Allan Sherman
 | image            = Allen Sherman the Loner 1965.JPG 
 | caption          = Sherman as a sheriff on ''[[The Loner]]'' in 1965.       
 | birthname        = Allan Copelon
 | birth_date       = {{birth date|1924|11|30|mf=y}}
 | birth_place      = [[Chicago]], [[Illinois]], United States
 | death_date       = {{death date and age|1973|11|20|1924|11|30|mf=y}}
 | death_place      = [[Los Angeles, California]], United States
 | occupation       = Comedy writer, television producer, singer, actor
 | yearsactive      = 1951–1973
 | death_cause      = [[Emphysema]]
 | resting_place    = [[Hillside Memorial Park Cemetery]]    
 | spouse           = Dee Chackes (15 June 1945 – 1966; divorced)
 | children         = 2
}}

'''Allan Sherman''' (born '''Allan Copelon'''&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.sjlmag.com/2013/11/hello-fadduh-comic-genius-allan.html]&lt;/ref&gt;; November 30, 1924&amp;nbsp;– November 20, 1973) was an American [[comedy writer]], television producer, singer and actor who became famous as a song [[parody|parodist]] in the early 1960s. His first album, ''[[My Son, the Folk Singer]]'' (1962), became the fastest-selling record album up to that time.&lt;ref name=thomas62&gt;Thomas, Bob (Associated Press). "Fat and fortyish but star no less," ''Ottawa Herald'', December 13, 1962, page 10: ''"Warner Brothers Records report that it is the fastest-selling album in history, having sold 575,000 in six weeks. With the Christmas season coming up, it might push over a million."'' Retrieved 14 April 2016 via NewspaperArchive.com&lt;/ref&gt; His biggest hit single was "[[Hello Muddah, Hello Fadduh (A Letter from Camp)|Hello Muddah, Hello Fadduh]]", a comic novelty in which a boy describes his summer camp experiences to the tune of [[Amilcare Ponchielli|Ponchielli]]'s ''[[Dance of the Hours]]''.  He is not to be confused with the songwriter [[Al Sherman]], who, coincidentally, also died in the fall of 1973.

==Early life==
Sherman was born in Chicago, to Percy Copelon and Rose Sherman. Percy was an auto mechanic and race car driver who, like his son, suffered from obesity (he weighed over 350 pounds), and died while attempting a 100-day diet. His family was Jewish. Sherman's parents divorced when he was in grade school, and the son adopted his mother's maiden name. Due to his parents constantly moving to new residences, he attended over a dozen public schools in Chicago, New York, Los Angeles, and Miami. He attended the [[University of Illinois]], where he earned mostly "C" grades and contributed a humor column to ''The Daily Illini'', the college newspaper, but never received a degree because he was expelled for breaking into a campus sorority house with his then-girlfriend.{{vague|date=July 2016|reason=Was it her sor. hse (e.g. to  conceal her being out  beyond a curfew? Was it a different sorority house, and if so w/ what motive? Also bcz inquiring minds want to know what penalty she incurred, and whether in his case "it wasn't the crime but the" attitude once caught}}{{citation needed|date=July 2016|reason=now do you get it, about the value of requiring refs???}}

==Television writer and producer==
Sherman devised a game show he intended to call ''I Know a Secret''. Television producer [[Mark Goodson]] used Sherman's idea and turned it into ''[[I've Got a Secret]]'', which ran on [[CBS]] from 1952 to 1967. Rather than paying him for the concept, Mark Goodson-[[Bill Todman]] Productions made Sherman the show's producer. Sherman was reported to be warm and kindhearted to all who worked for him. However, differences occurred between Sherman and anyone who was in a position to try to restrain his creativity.&lt;ref&gt;Goodson-Todman executive [[Gil Fates]] relates typical Sherman stunts in his memoir about ''[[What's My Line?]]''.&lt;/ref&gt; As producer of ''I've Got a Secret'', which was broadcast live, he showed a fondness for large-scale stunts that had the potential to teeter on the brink of disaster. He once released 100 rabbits onstage as an [[Easter]] surprise for the Madison Square [[Boys &amp; Girls Clubs of America|Boys Club]], whose members were seated in the studio. The boys were invited to come up onstage to collect their prize. Although the resultant melee made a good story, it did not necessarily make for good TV.

The relationship between Goodson, Todman and Sherman became strained when he proposed that [[Tony Curtis]] teach the panel how to play some games he had played as a child growing up in New York City. However, Curtis had never actually played any of the games that Sherman had brought the props for. The props for Sherman's concept failed and the spot, which aired June 11, 1958, was a disaster and Sherman was removed as producer. Despite this, Goodson and Todman invited Sherman back several times as a guest on their shows in later years after he achieved celebrity status following the release of his albums.

Sherman also produced a short-lived 1954 game show, ''[[What's Going On (TV series)|What's Going On]]?'', which was technologically ambitious, with studio guests interacting with multiple live cameras in remote locations. In 1961, he produced a daytime game show for Al Singer Productions called ''Your Surprise Package'', which aired on CBS with host [[George Fenneman]].

==Song parodies==
In 1951, Sherman recorded a 78-rpm single with veteran singer Sylvia Froos which contained "A Satchel and a Seck", parodying "[[A Bushel and a Peck]]" from ''[[Guys and Dolls (musical)|Guys and Dolls]]'', coupled with "Jake's Song", parodying "[[Sam's Song (song)|Sam's Song]]", a contemporary hit for [[Bing Crosby]] and his son [[Gary Crosby (actor)|Gary]]. The single sold poorly and when Sherman wrote his autobiography, he did not make reference to it. Later, he found that the song parodies he performed to amuse his friends and family were taking on a life of their own. Sherman lived in the [[Brentwood, Los Angeles, California|Brentwood]] section of [[Westside (Los Angeles County)|West Los Angeles]] next door to [[Harpo Marx]], who invited him to perform his song parodies at parties attended by Marx's show-biz friends. After one party, [[George Burns]] phoned an executive at [[Warner Bros. Records]] and persuaded him to sign Sherman to a contract. The result was an [[Gramophone record|LP]] of these parodies, ''[[My Son, the Folk Singer]]'', which was released in 1962. It sold over one million copies, and was awarded a [[music recording sales certification|gold disc]].&lt;ref name="The Book of Golden Discs"&gt;{{cite book
| first= Joseph
| last= Murrells
| year= 1978
| title= The Book of Golden Discs
| edition= 2nd
| publisher=Barrie and Jenkins Ltd
| location= London
| page= 152
| isbn= 0-214-20512-6}}&lt;/ref&gt; The album was so successful that it was quickly followed by ''[[My Son, the Celebrity]]'', which ended with "Shticks of One and Half a Dozen of the Other", fragments of song parodies including [[Robert Burns]]' "Comin' Thro' the Rye": "Do not make a stingy [[sandwich]], pile the cold cuts high;/Customers should see [[salami]] comin' thru the [[rye]]" and "All day, all night, '[[Cary Grant]],'" a takeoff on "[[Marianne (Terry Gilkyson song)|Marianne]]".

In 1962, capitalizing on his success, [[Jubilee Records]] re-released Sherman's 1951 single on the album ''More Folk Songs by Allan Sherman and His Friends'', which was a compilation of material by various [[Borscht Belt]] comedians, such as Sylvia Froos, [[Fyvush Finkel]] and Lee Tully, along with the Sherman material.

As suggested by the albums' titles, Sherman's first two LPs were mainly reworkings of old [[folk song]]s to infuse them with Jewish humor. His first minor hit was "Sarah Jackman" (pronounced "Jockman"), a takeoff of "[[Frère Jacques]]" in which he and a woman (Christine Nelson) exchange family gossip ("Sarah Jackman, Sarah Jackman,/How's by you? How's by you?/How's by you the family?/How's your sister Emily?" etc.). The popularity of "Sarah Jackman" (as well as the album ''My Son, the Folk Singer'') was enhanced after President [[John F. Kennedy]] was spotted in a hotel lobby singing the song. By his peak with ''[[My Son, the Nut]]'' in 1963, however, Sherman had broadened both his subject matter and his choice of [[parody]] material and begun to appeal to a larger audience.

Sherman wrote his parody lyrics in collaboration with [[Lou Busch]]. A few of the Sherman/Busch songs are completely original creations, featuring original music as well as lyrics, rather than new lyrics applied to an existing melody. The Sherman/Busch originals&amp;nbsp;– notably "Go to Sleep, Paul Revere" and "Peyton Place"&amp;nbsp;– are [[novelty song]]s, showing genuine melodic originality as well as deft lyrics.

However, Sherman had trouble in getting permission to record for profit from some well-known composers and lyricists, who did not tolerate parodies or satires of their melodies and lyrics, including [[Irving Berlin]], [[Richard Rodgers]], [[George Gershwin|George]] and [[Ira Gershwin]], [[Meredith Willson]], [[Alan Jay Lerner]], and [[Frederick Loewe]], as well as the estates of [[Lorenz Hart]], [[Oscar Hammerstein II|Oscar Hammerstein]], [[Kurt Weill]], and [[Bertolt Brecht]], which prevented him from releasing parodies or satires of their songs. In the late 1950s, Sherman was inspired by a recording of a nightclub musical show called ''My Fairfax Lady'', a parody of ''[[My Fair Lady]]'' set in the Jewish section of Los Angeles that was performed at [[Billy Gray (comedian)|Billy Gray]]'s Band Box. Sherman then wrote his own song parodies of ''My Fair Lady'', which appeared as a [[bootleg recording]] in 1964, and were only officially released in 2005 on ''My Son, the Box''. Alan Jay Lerner did not approve of having the parody being performed; however, he reluctantly settled to allow the performances of "Fairfax Lady", on the strict conditions that the show could only be allowed to be performed inside the Fairfax Theater, without any touring company, and that the musical could not be videotaped or recorded for any album.

Although Sherman believed that all the songs parodied on ''My Son, the Folk Singer'' were in the [[public domain]], two of them, "Matilda" and "Water Boy"&amp;nbsp;– parodied as "My Zelda" and "[[Seltzer water|Seltzer]] Boy", respectively&amp;nbsp;– were actually under copyright, and Sherman was sued for copyright infringement.&lt;ref&gt;Sherman, Allan. ''A Gift of Laughter'' and Wallace, Irving and Wallenchensky, David. ''The People's Almanac of the 20th Century''&lt;/ref&gt;

In 1963's ''My Son, the Nut'', Sherman's pointed parodies of classical and popular tunes dealt with [[automation]] in the workplace ("Automation", to the tune of "[[Fascination (1932 song)|Fascination]]"), [[Spaceflight|space travel]] ("Eight Foot Two, Solid Blue", to "[[Five Foot Two, Eyes of Blue]]"), the exodus from the city to the suburbs ("Here's to the Crabgrass", to the tune of "English Country Garden"), and his own bulky contours ("Hail to Thee, Fat Person", which claims his [[obesity]] was a public service similar to the [[Marshall Plan]]). Six cartoon bears were printed on back of every album.

==A Top 40 hit==
One track from ''My Son, the Nut'', a spoof of [[summer camp]] entitled "[[Hello Muddah, Hello Fadduh (A Letter from Camp)|Hello Muddah, Hello Fadduh]]", became a surprise novelty hit, reaching No. 2 on the national [[Billboard Hot 100|''Billboard'' Hot 100]] chart for three weeks in late summer 1963. The lyrics were sung to the tune of one segment of [[Amilcare Ponchielli|Ponchielli]]'s ''[[Dance of the Hours]]'', familiar to the public because of its use in the [[Walt Disney]] film ''[[Fantasia (1940 film)|Fantasia]]''. That December, Sherman's "[[The Twelve Gifts of Christmas]]" single appeared on ''Billboard''{{'}}s separate Christmas chart. Sherman had one other Top 40 hit, a 1965 take-off on the [[Petula Clark]] hit "[[Downtown (Petula Clark song)|Downtown]]" called "[[Crazy Downtown]]", which spent one week at #40. Two other Sherman singles charted in the lower regions of the ''Billboard'' 100: an updated "Hello Mudduh, Hello Fadduh" (#59 in 1964), and "The Drinking Man's Diet" (#98 in 1965). Sherman's "The End of a Symphony", spotlighting [[Arthur Fiedler]]'s [[Boston Pops Orchestra]], reached #113 on the "Bubbling Under" chart in 1964, but did not make the Hot 100.

The songs on Sherman's next album ''My Name Is Allan'' (1965) were thematically connected: except for a couple of original novelty songs with music by Sherman and Busch, all the songs on the album are parodies of songs that had won, or were nominated for, the [[Academy Award for Best Song]]. They included "[[That Old Black Magic]]", "[[Secret Love (Doris Day song)|Secret Love]]", "[[The Continental (song)|The Continental]]", "[[Chim Chim Cher-ee]]" and "[[Call Me Irresponsible]]".  The cover of the album bore a childhood photograph of Sherman. That, and the album's title, were references to [[Barbra Streisand]]'s album ''[[My Name Is Barbra]]'', released earlier that year, which featured a cover photograph of the singer as a young girl.

During his brief heyday, Sherman's parodies were so popular that he had at least one contemporary imitator: ''My Son the Copycat'' was an album of song parodies performed by [[Stanley Ralph Ross]], co-written by Ross and [[Bob Arbogast]]. Lest there be any doubt of whom Ross is copying, his album's cover bears a crossed-out photo of Sherman. One of the songs on this album is a fat man's lament, "I'm Called Little Butterball", parodying "I'm Called Little Buttercup" from [[Gilbert and Sullivan]]'s [[operetta]] ''[[HMS Pinafore]]''. Sherman would later parody this same song as "Little Butterball"&amp;nbsp;– with the same subject matter&amp;nbsp;– on his album ''[[Allan in Wonderland]]''. The song may have had more poignancy for Sherman, as he, unlike Stanley Ross, was genuinely overweight. Sherman also parodied Gilbert and Sullivan's "Titwillow" from ''[[The Mikado]]'', in the song "The Bronx Bird-Watcher" (on ''My Son, the Celebrity''), as well as [[Cultural influence of Gilbert and Sullivan|several other Gilbert and Sullivan songs]].

==Later work==
In 1965, Sherman published an autobiography, ''A Gift of Laughter'', and, for a short period at least, he was culturally ubiquitous. He sang on and guest-hosted ''[[The Tonight Show Starring Johnny Carson|The Tonight Show]]'', was involved in the production of [[Bill Cosby]]'s first three albums, appeared in the [[Macy's Thanksgiving Day Parade]], and sang "The Dropouts' March" on the March 6, 1964, edition of the [[NBC]] satirical program ''[[That Was The Week That Was]]''.

Also in 1964, Sherman narrated his own version of [[Sergei Prokofiev|Prokofiev]]'s ''[[Peter and the Wolf]]'' in a live concert at [[Tanglewood]] with the [[Boston Pops]] under [[Arthur Fiedler]]. The concert, which was released as the album ''Peter and the Commissar'', also included "Variations on '[[How Dry I Am]]'", with Sherman as [[Conductor (music)|conductor]], and "The End of a Symphony". In "Variations", Fiedler was the guest soloist, providing solo hiccups. In 2004, [[Collector's Choice Music|Collector's Choice]] reissued the complete [[RCA Victor]] album on CD.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.amazon.com/Commissar-Arthur-Fiedler-Boston-Sherman/dp/B0002LO7GU |title=Peter &amp; The Commissar: Arthur Fiedler &amp; The Boston Pops With Allan Sherman: Music |publisher=Amazon.com |date= |accessdate=April 25, 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Sherman's later albums grew more pointedly satirical and less light-hearted, skewering protesting students ("The Rebel"), consumer debt ("A Waste of Money", based on "[[A Taste of Honey (song)|A Taste of Honey]]"), and the [[generation gap]] ("Crazy Downtown" and "Pop Hates [[the Beatles]]").

Sherman was often tapped to produce specialty song parodies for corporations. An album of six paper-cup and vending machine related songs, titled ''Music to Dispense With'', was created for the Container Division of the [[Scott Paper Company]] for distribution to its vendors and customers. It consisted of the tracks "Makin' Coffee" (a parody of "[[Makin' Whoopee]]"), "Vending Machines", "There Are Cups", "That's How the Change Is Made", "The Wonderful Tree in the Forest" and "Scott Cups".&lt;ref name="scott"&gt;{{cite web|url=http://dmdb.org/discographies/sherman.disco.html#scott|title=Music To Dispense With Created By Allan Sherman For The Container Division Of Scott Paper Company|last=Morris|first=Jeff|date=November 21, 2005|work=The [[Dr Demento|Demented]] Music Database!|accessdate=January 6, 2010| archiveurl= https://web.archive.org/web/20100105060643/http://dmdb.org/discographies/sherman.disco.html| archivedate= January 5, 2010 &lt;!--DASHBot--&gt;| deadurl= no}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Sherman also created a group of eight "public education" radio spots for Encron carpet fibers, singing their praises to the tunes of old public-domain songs. Entitled ''Allan Sherman Pours It On for Carpets Made with Encron Polyester'', it featured an introduction by Sherman and comprised the tracks "Encron Is a Brand New Fiber" (to the tune of "[[Shine On, Harvest Moon]]"), "Put Them All Together, They Spell Encron" (to the tune of [[Eddy Arnold]]'s "M-O-T-H-E-R"), "There's a Fiber Called Encron" (to the tune of William H. Hill's "[[There is a Tavern in the Town]]"), "Encron Alive, Alive-O" (to the tune of "[[Molly Malone]]"), "Encron's the Name", "Why They Call It Encron" (to the tune of "[[Let Me Call You Sweetheart]]"), "Encron, Encron" (to the tune of "[[Daisy Bell]]") and "Encron Is a Great New Fiber" (to the tune of "Take Me to the Fair").&lt;ref name="encron"&gt;{{cite web|url=http://dmdb.org/discographies/sherman.disco.html#encron|title=Allan Sherman Pours It On For Carpets Made With Encron Polyester|last=Morris|first=Jeff|date=November 21, 2005|work=The [[Dr Demento|Demented]] Music Database!|accessdate=January 6, 2010| archiveurl= https://web.archive.org/web/20100105060643/http://dmdb.org/discographies/sherman.disco.html| archivedate= January 5, 2010 &lt;!--DASHBot--&gt;| deadurl= no}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Decline==
{{refimprove section|date=October 2017}}
Sherman's career success was short-lived: after peaking in 1963, his popularity declined rather quickly. After the [[assassination of John F. Kennedy]], impersonator [[Vaughn Meader]] vowed to never again do a Kennedy impression, and perhaps because of this ominous shadow&amp;nbsp;– Meader was a very popular parody impressionist of the day&amp;nbsp;– and the resulting reluctance to book such acts, the public saw less of Sherman's type of comedy.&lt;ref name=LATimes&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.petabit.com/steve/LATimes_Granada.html |title=Los Angeles Times: The Boy in Camp Granada |publisher=Petabit.com |date= |accessdate=November 9, 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt; Beginning in 1964, Sherman was among many American acts whose sales were affected badly  by the [[British Invasion]] (which, in fair measure, Sherman skewered in the song "Pop Hates the Beatles", a spoof of "[[Pop! Goes the Weasel]]").

By 1965, he had released two albums that did not make the Top 50 and in 1966 [[Warner Bros.]] dropped him from the label. His last album for the company, ''Togetherness'', was released in 1967 to poor reviews and poorer sales. All of his previous releases had been recorded in front of a live studio audience&amp;nbsp;– or in the case of ''Live, Hoping You Are the Same'', recorded during a Las Vegas performance&amp;nbsp;– but ''Togetherness'' was not, and the lack of an audience and their response affected the result, as did the nondescript backup singers and studio orchestra.

On November 13, 1965 Sherman made a rare prime time television acting appearance in "The Sheriff of Fetterman's Crossing," an episode of [[Rod Serling|Rod Serling's]] short-lived Western series ''[[The Loner]]'' (1965–66). Sherman played Walton Peterson Tetley, a local schnook who went off to war and rose to regiment cook before returning home a hero thanks to tall tales and yarn-spinning. The town hails its conquering hero and Tetley is appointed sheriff. Series star [[Lloyd Bridges]] as William Colton, a wandering Union veteran, comes to town and signs on to be Tetley's deputy, discovering quickly his boss' utter incompetence in the office. Tetley receives a threatening note from a gunslinger challenging this purported hero to a gunfight when he arrives on the noon stage, at which point the story becomes a parody of iconic Western movie ''[[High Noon]]'' (1952). Colton sets to teaching the shivering-in-his-boots sheriff courage and gunmanship. Sherman's semi-serious and sympathetic performance was strong and his presence an affable one.

In 1966, Sherman visited Australia. He did a television series in Melbourne, Victoria, for a live audience. During the performance, he sang a parody of "Molly Malone." It included a play on the word "but" (butt) which did not elicit a laugh. What Sherman did not know is that Australians use the word "bum" where Americans would say "butt" (although butt would become popular in later years.)  Otherwise, Sherman was well received by the audience. Afterward, he met with some of his fans and signed at least one autograph.

In 1969, Sherman wrote the book and lyrics&amp;nbsp;– with music by [[Albert Hague]]&amp;nbsp;– for ''[[The Fig Leaves Are Falling]]'', a flop [[Broadway theater|Broadway musical]] that ran only four performances, despite direction by [[George Abbott]] and a cast that included [[Barry Nelson]], [[Dorothy Loudon]], and [[David Cassidy]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|author=The Broadway League |url=http://ibdb.com/production.php?id=3446 |title=The official source for Broadway Information |publisher=IBDB |date= |accessdate=November 9, 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;  Still creative, in 1973, Sherman published the controversial ''[[The Rape of the A*P*E*]]'', which detailed his point of view on American [[Religious fanaticism|Puritanism]] and the [[sexual revolution]].

In 1971, Sherman was the voice of [[Dr. Seuss]]'s ''[[The Cat in the Hat]]''  for the [[The Cat in the Hat (TV special)|television special]]. He reprised the role for ''[[Dr. Seuss on the Loose]]'', his last project before his death.

==Death==
In his last years, Sherman's alcoholism and weight gain caused severe deterioration of his health; he later developed [[diabetes]] and struggled with [[lung disease]].&lt;ref name=cohen&gt;{{cite web|url=http://jangle04.home.mindspring.com/sherman3.html |title=Allan Sherman: Hail to Thee, Fat Person - by David Holzel - page 3 |publisher=Jangle04.home.mindspring.com |date= |accessdate=November 9, 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt; In 1966, his wife Dee filed for divorce&lt;ref name=offing&gt;(Editor's note.) "My favorite jokes," ''Parade'' magazine, August 21, 1966, page number illegible: '' "Unfortunately his domestic life of late has been none too good, and a divorce is in the offing." '' Retrieved 14 April 2016 via NewspaperArchive.com.&lt;/ref&gt; and received full custody of their son and daughter.{{Citation needed|date=March 2012}}

Sherman lived on unemployment benefits for a time and moved into the [[Motion Picture &amp; Television Country House and Hospital]] for a short time to lose weight.&lt;ref name=cohen/&gt; He died of [[emphysema]] at his home in West Hollywood at age 48. He is entombed in [[Culver City, California]]'s [[Hillside Memorial Park Cemetery]].&lt;ref&gt;{{Find a Grave|2367}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Legacy==
Sherman was the inspiration for a new generation of developing parodists such as [["Weird Al" Yankovic]], who pays homage to Sherman on the cover of [["Weird Al" Yankovic (album)|his first LP]]. Sherman's hit song "Hello Muddah, Hello Fadduh" has been translated into other languages. In one notable example, the Dutch-Swedish poet [[Cornelis Vreeswijk]] translated the song loosely into Swedish as "Brev från kolonien" (Letter from Summer Camp), which reached fourth on the Swedish popular music chart Svensktoppen in the summer of 1965&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.sr.se/Diverse/AppData/Isidor/files/2023/3463.txt |title=SVENSKTOPPEN: Date: 1965-01-02 |publisher=Sr.se |accessdate=November 9, 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt; and is still popular in Sweden today.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://lyricsplayground.com/alpha/songs/b/brevfrankolonien.shtml |title=BREV FRAN KOLONIEN - Lyrics - International Lyrics Playground |publisher=Lyricsplayground.com |date=October 10, 2007 |accessdate=November 9, 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;

A ''Best of Allan Sherman'' CD was released in 1990, and a [[boxed set]] of most of his songs was released in 2005 under the title ''My Son, the Box''. In 1992 a [[musical revue]] of his songs titled ''Hello Muddah, Hello Faddah'' ran for over a year [[off-off-Broadway]]; other productions ran [[Off-Broadway]] for four months in 2001&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.lortel.org/LLA_archive/index.cfm?search_by=show&amp;id=106 |title=Lortel Archives-The Internet Off-Broadway Database |publisher=Lortel.org |date= |accessdate=November 9, 2012 |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20121006184127/http://www.lortel.org/LLA_archive/index.cfm?search_by=show&amp;id=106 |archive-date=October 6, 2012 |dead-url=yes |df=mdy-all }}&lt;/ref&gt; and toured in 2003. A children's book based on the song "Hello Muddah, Hello Fadduh", with illustrations by [[Syd Hoff]], was published in 2004.

On March 14, 2006, [[National Public Radio]] profiled Sherman on ''All Things Considered''.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|last=Sherman |first=Allan |url=https://www.npr.org/templates/story/story.php?storyId=5279983 |title=Allan Sherman: Beyond 'Hello Muddah, Hello Fadduh' |publisher=NPR |date=March 14, 2006 |accessdate=November 9, 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In 2010, eight of Allan Sherman's Warner Bros. albums were individually released on CD:
*''[[My Son, the Folk Singer]]''
*''[[My Son, the Celebrity]]''
*''[[My Son, the Nut]]''
*''[[Allan in Wonderland]]''
*''[[For Swingin' Livers Only!]]''
*''My Name Is Allan''
*''Allan Sherman: Live! (Hoping You Are the Same)''
*''Togetherness''

Sherman's son, Robert, later became a [[game show]] producer, producing for Mark Goodson during the 1970s and 1980s, including ''[[Password Plus]]'', ''[[Blockbusters (U.S. game show)|Blockbusters]]'', ''[[Body Language (game show)|Body Language]]'' and ''[[Super Password]]''.

==In popular culture==
* Sherman's song "Ratt Fink" was covered by punk rock band [[Misfits (band)|The Misfits]] on their 1979 single "[[Night of the Living Dead]]". It was also covered by Ex-[[Misfits (band)|Misfits]] guitarist [[Bobby Steele]] by his band [[The Undead]]. Sherman wrote the song as a parody of "[[Rag Mop]]," originally performed by [[Johnnie Lee Wills]] and popularized by [[The Ames Brothers]] in 1950.
* In the "[[Three Gays of the Condo]]" episode of ''[[The Simpsons]]'', [["Weird Al" Yankovic]] makes a guest appearance. When Homer asks Yankovic if he got the two songs he recorded and sent in, Yankovic replies that he did. When Homer asks which he liked better, Yankovic replies, "They were pretty much the same, Homer." Homer then mutters angrily, "Yeah, like you and Allan Sherman."  Other references to Sherman came in the episode "[[Marge Be Not Proud]]" when Bart hides an answering machine tape in a copy of his (fictitious) ''Camp Granada'' album&amp;nbsp;– "where no one would ever listen to it," and in "[[A Midsummer's Nice Dream]]" where Homer shows Bart and Lisa his copy of another fictional Sherman album, ''[[Helter Skelter (Manson scenario)|Helter Shmelter]]: Sorry For the Mess''.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://simpsonswiki.net/wiki/Allan_Sherman%27s_Helter_Shmelter_-_Sorry_For_the_Mess |title=Allan Sherman's Helter Shmelter - Sorry For the Mess - Wikisimpsons, the Simpsons Wiki |publisher=Simpsonswiki.net |date=August 13, 2012 |accessdate=November 9, 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;
*The group [[Capitol Steps]] used "Hello Mullah, Hello Faddah" as a parody in ''Fools On The Hill (Songs of 1992)''.
*Dutch comedian [[Rijk de Gooyer]] sang two Dutch versions of "Hello Mulla, Hello Faddah" named "Brief uit La Courtine"(Letter from La Courtine") and "Brief naar La Courtine" (Letter to La Courtine). In the first one, he describes his adventures as a soldier in the Dutch base at [[La Courtine]], and in the second, his father replies to the first letter.

==Discography==

===Albums===
{| class="wikitable" style=text-align:center;
|-
!Year
!Title
![[Billboard 200|''Billboard'' 200]]
![[Record label|Record Label]]
|- 
|rowspan="1"| 1962
|align=left| ''[[My Son, the Folk Singer]]''
| 1
| [[Warner Bros. Records]]
|- 
|rowspan="2"| 1963
|align=left| ''[[My Son, the Celebrity]]''
| 1
| Warner Bros. Records
|- 
|align=left| ''[[My Son, the Nut]]''
| 1
| Warner Bros. Records
|- 
|rowspan="3"| 1964
|align=left| ''[[Allan in Wonderland]]''
| 25
| Warner Bros. Records
|- 
|align=left| ''[[Peter and the Commissar]]''
| 53
| [[RCA Victor]]
|- 
|align=left| ''[[For Swingin' Livers Only!]]''
| 25
| Warner Bros. Records
|- 
|rowspan="1"| 1965
|align=left| ''My Name Is Allan''
| 88
| Warner Bros. Records
|- 
|rowspan="1"| 1966
|align=left| ''Allan Sherman: Live!!! (Hoping You Are the Same)''
| 
-
| Warner Bros. Records
|- 
|rowspan="1"| 1967
|align=left| ''Togetherness''
| 
-
| Warner Bros. Records
|- 
|}

===Singles===
{| class="wikitable" style=text-align:center;
|-
!rowspan="2"|Year
!rowspan="2"|Titles (A-side, B-side)&lt;br&gt;&lt;small&gt;Both sides from same album except where indicated
!colspan="3"|Chart positions
!rowspan="2"|Album
|-
![[Billboard Hot 100|US]]
![[Adult Contemporary (chart)|AC]]
![[UK Singles Chart|UK]]
|- 
|rowspan="2"| 1963
|align=left| "[[Hello Muddah, Hello Fadduh (A Letter from Camp)|Hello Muddah, Hello Fadduh!&lt;small&gt; (A Letter From Camp)]]&lt;/small&gt;"&lt;br&gt;&lt;small&gt;b/w "Rat Fink"
| 2
| —
| 14
|align="left"|''[[My Son, the Nut|My Son, The Nut]]''
|-
|align=left| "[[The Twelve Gifts of Christmas|The Twelve Gifts Of Christmas]]"&lt;br&gt;&lt;small&gt;b/w "(You Came A Long Way From St. Louis)&lt;br&gt;You Went The Wrong Way, Old King Louie" (from ''My Son, The Nut'')
| 5&lt;br&gt;&lt;small&gt; (Christmas charts)&lt;/small&gt;
| —
| —
|align="left"|''[[For Swingin' Livers Only!]]''
|-
|rowspan="5"| 1964
|align="left"| "My Son, The Vampire"&lt;br&gt;&lt;small&gt;b/w "I Can't Dance" (from ''Allan In Wonderland'')
| —
| —
| —
|align="left"|Non-album track
|-
|align="left"| "(Heart) Skin"&lt;br&gt;&lt;small&gt;b/w "The Drop-Outs March"
| —
| —
| —
|align="left"|''Allan In Wonderland''
|-
|align=left| "Hello Mudduh, Hello Fadduh!&lt;small&gt; (A Letter From Camp)"&lt;/small&gt;&lt;small&gt; (1964 version)&lt;/small&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;small&gt;b/w Original version of A-side (from ''My Son, The Nut'')
| 59
| 9
| —
|align="left"|Non-album track
|-
|align="left"|"The End Of A Symphony"—Part 1&lt;br&gt;&lt;small&gt;b/w Part 2&lt;br&gt;With The Boston Pops Orchestra—Arthur Fiedler, conductor
| —
| —
| —
|align="left"|''Peter and The Commissar''
|-
|align="left"|"Pop Hates The Beatles"&lt;br&gt;&lt;small&gt;b/w "Grow, Mrs. Goldfarb"&lt;br&gt;Unreleased
| —
| —
| —
|align="left"|''For Swingin' Livers Only!''
|-
|rowspan="2"| 1965
|align=left| "[[Crazy Downtown]]"&lt;br&gt;&lt;small&gt;b/w "The Drop-Outs March" (from ''Allan In Wonderland'')
| 40
| 6
| —
|align="left"|Non-album track
|-
|align=left| "The Drinking Man's Diet"&lt;br&gt;&lt;small&gt;b/w "The Laarge Daark Aardvark Song"
| 98
| 21
| —
|align="left"|''My Name Is Allan''
|-
|1966
|align="left"|"Odd Ball"&lt;br&gt;&lt;small&gt;b/w "His Own Little Island"
| —
| —
| —
|align="left"|Non-album tracks
|-
|1967
|align="left"|"Westchester Hadassah"&lt;br&gt;&lt;small&gt;b/w "Strange Things In My Soup"
| —
| —
| —
|align="left"|''Togetherness''
|-
|1968
|align="left"| "The Fig Leaves Are Falling"&lt;br&gt;&lt;small&gt;b/w "Juggling"
| —
| —
| —
|align="left"|Non-album tracks
|-
|}

===Musical theater===
*''The Fig Leaves Are Falling'' (1969)&amp;nbsp;– [[Musical theater|musical]]&amp;nbsp;– lyricist and book-writer
**Songs: "All Is Well in Larchmont," "Lillian," "All of My Laughter," "Give Me a Cause," "Today I Saw a Rose," "We," "For Our Sake," "Light One Candle," "Oh, Boy," "The Fig Leaves Are Falling," "For the Rest of My Life," "I Like It," "Broken Heart," "Old Fashioned Song," "Lillian, Lillian, Lillian," "Did I Ever Really Live?" The music was composed by [[Albert Hague]].

==Filmography==
*''[[My Son, The Vampire]]'' (1963) introductory segment. Filmed repackage of the 1952 film ''[[Mother Riley Meets the Vampire]]''
*''[[Fractured Flickers]]'' (1 episode, 1963) as himself
*''[[The Loner]]'' (1 episode, 1965) as Walter Peterson Tetley
*''[[The Cat in the Hat (TV special) |The Cat in the Hat]]'' (1971) as The Cat in the Hat/Narrator (voice)
*''Wacky Taxi'' (1972) as Nervous Man
*''[[Dr. Seuss on the Loose]]'' (1973) as The Cat in the Hat (voice)

==See also==
*[[Hello Muddah, Hello Faddah! (musical review &amp; children's book)]]
* [[Camp Granada]]

==References==

===Bibliography===
*''Instant Status'' (or ''Up Your Image'') (G.P. Putnam &amp; Sons, 1964) (tear-out pages of celebrity thank you letters you can address to yourself and leave around your home or office to impress people)
*''I Can't Dance!'' (children's picture book, illustrated by Syd Hoff) (Harper &amp; Row, 1964)
*''A Gift of Laughter: The Autobiography of Allan Sherman'' (Atheneum, 1965)
*''[[The Rape of the A*P*E*]]&amp;nbsp;– The Official History of the Sex Revolution 1945–1973: The Obscening of America. An R*S*V*P* Document'' ([[Playboy Press]], 1973) {{ISBN|0-87216-453-5}}
**The title page notes that "APE" stands for "American Puritan Ethic" and "RSVP" for "Redeeming Social Value Pornography"
*''Hello Muddah, Hello Faddah'', (children's picture book based on song) (Dutton Books, 2004) {{ISBN|0-525-46942-7}}

===Notes===
{{Reflist}}

==External links==
{{wikiquote}}
*{{IMDb name|id=0792369|name=Allan Sherman}}
* {{Allmusic|class=artist|id=p228}}
* {{Find a Grave|2367}}
* [http://dmdb.org/discographies/sherman.disco.html Complete Discography]
* {{webarchive |url=https://web.archive.org/web/20041204100042/http://www.musicalstages.co.uk/international/canada/hellomuddah_canada.htm |date=December 4, 2004 |title=Review of ''Hello Muddah, Hello Fadduh'', the Allan Sherman Musical Revue }}
* [http://www.tabletmag.com/jewish-arts-and-culture/theater-and-dance/130689/allan-sherman# Josh Lambert in Tablet Magazine reviewing Mark Cohen's biography, Overweight Sensation: The Life and Comedy of Allan Sherman]

{{Authority control}}

{{Allan Sherman}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Sherman, Allan}}
[[Category:1924 births]]
[[Category:1973 deaths]]
[[Category:American satirists]]
[[Category:American male singers]]
[[Category:Songwriters from Illinois]]
[[Category:American television producers]]
[[Category:Parodists]]
[[Category:American male voice actors]]
[[Category:Parody musicians]]
[[Category:American entertainment industry businesspeople]]
[[Category:American male comedians]]
[[Category:Jewish American musicians]]
[[Category:Jewish American songwriters]]
[[Category:Jubilee Records artists]]
[[Category:RCA Victor artists]]
[[Category:Deaths from emphysema]]
[[Category:Grammy Award winners]]
[[Category:Fairfax High School (Los Angeles) alumni]]
[[Category:Male actors from Chicago]]
[[Category:Burials at Hillside Memorial Park Cemetery]]
[[Category:20th-century American male actors]]
[[Category:American novelty song performers]]
[[Category:20th-century American singers]]
[[Category:20th-century American businesspeople]]
[[Category:Disease-related deaths in California]]
[[Category:Comedians from Illinois]]
[[Category:People from Brentwood, Los Angeles]]
[[Category:Jewish American comedians]]
[[Category:American comedy musicians]]
[[Category:Warner Bros. Records artists]]</text>
      <sha1>6s525fa3jqtnz7ulkpvsuqr396d5o2b</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
