<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10.xsd" version="0.10" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <dbname>enwiki</dbname>
    <base>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.32.0-wmf.16</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="118" case="first-letter">Draft</namespace>
      <namespace key="119" case="first-letter">Draft talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2300" case="first-letter">Gadget</namespace>
      <namespace key="2301" case="first-letter">Gadget talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2302" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition</namespace>
      <namespace key="2303" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Benny Hill</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>151404</id>
    <revision>
      <id>854175865</id>
      <parentid>854175805</parentid>
      <timestamp>2018-08-09T13:30:02Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Stapmoshun</username>
        <id>31379431</id>
      </contributor>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="25583">{{EngvarB|date=August 2014}}
{{Infobox comedian 
| name                 = Benny Hill
| image                = Benny_Hill.JPG
| caption              = Wax figure of Hill
| birth_name           = Alfred Hawthorne Hill
| native_name          = 
| native_name_lang     = 
| birth_date           = {{Birth date|df=yes|1924|1|21}}&lt;ref name="NYTimes"&gt;
{{cite news |newspaper=New York Times |date=21 April 1992 |title=Benny Hill, 68, English Comedian And Creator of TV Show, Is Dead |url=https://www.nytimes.com/1992/04/21/arts/benny-hill-67-english-comedian-and-creator-of-tv-show-is-dead.html |author=Craig Wolff}}&lt;/ref&gt;
| birth_place          = {{nowrap|[[Southampton]], Hampshire, England}}
| death_date           = {{Death date and age|df=yes|1992|4|20|1924|1|21}}
| death_place          = [[Teddington]], London, England
| resting_place        = 
| resting_place_coordinates = 
| medium               = {{Flat list|
*Television
*film
*recording
}}
| nationality          = British
| education            = 
| alma_mater           = 
| active               = 1937–1992
| employer             = 
| genre                = {{Flat list|
*[[Slapstick]]
*[[burlesque]]
*[[double entendre]]
}}
| subject              = 
| influenced           = &lt;!--deprecated--&gt;
| spouse               = 
| domesticpartner      = 
| children             = 
| parents              = 
| relatives            = 
| notable_work         = {{nowrap|''[[The Benny Hill Show]]'' (1955–91)&lt;br&gt;''[[Who Done It? (1956 film)|Who Done It?]]'' (1956)}}&lt;br&gt;''[[Light Up the Sky! (film)|Light Up the Sky!]]'' (1960)&lt;br&gt;''[[Those Magnificent Men in their Flying Machines]]'' (1965)&lt;br&gt;{{nowrap|''[[Chitty Chitty Bang Bang]]'' (1968)&lt;br&gt;''[[The Italian Job]]'' (1969)}}
| memorials            = 
| signature            = 
| website              = 
| footnotes            = 
| module               = 
}}

'''Alfred Hawthorne''' "'''Benny'''" '''Hill''' (21 January 1924&lt;!--He was born on 21 January 1924. ref birth indexes for 1st quarter (Jan, Feb, Mar) 1924 reveal "Alfred H. Hill" registered Southampton - mother's maiden name "Cave". This is CORRECT - Please do not change to 1925.--&gt; – 20 April 1992) was an English comedian and actor, best remembered for his television programme ''[[The Benny Hill Show]]'', an amalgam of slapstick, burlesque, and ''double entendre'' in a format that included live comedy and filmed segments, with him at the focus of almost every segment. 

Hill was a prominent figure in British culture for nearly four decades, and his show proved to be one of the great success stories of television comedy and was among the most-watched programmes in the UK; the audience peaked at more than 21 million in 1971.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.bfi.org.uk/features/mostwatched/1970s.html |title=Features &amp;#124; Britain's Most Watched TV &amp;#124; 1970s |publisher=British Film Institute (BFI) |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20051122221511/http://www.bfi.org.uk/features/mostwatched/1970s.html |archive-date=22 November 2005 |accessdate=22 October 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Early life==
Alfred Hawthorne Hill was born on 21 January 1924 in [[Southampton]], on the south coast of England. His father, Alfred Hill (later manager of a surgical appliance shop&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://oxfordindex.oup.com/view/10.1093/ref:odnb/51126|title=Hill, Alfred Hawthorne [Benny] (1924–1992), comedian : Oxford Dictionary of National Biography - oi|author=|date=|publisher=Oxford University Press|website=oup.com|doi=10.1093/ref:odnb/51126}}&lt;/ref&gt;  that mostly sold condoms&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=mPBVO649SEI|title=Living Famously...|author=|date=|website=www.youtube.com|access-date=9 January 2018|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20180125145125/https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=mPBVO649SEI|archive-date=25 January 2018|dead-url=yes|df=dmy-all}}&lt;/ref&gt;), and grandfather, Henry Hill, had both been circus clowns.&lt;ref name="NYTimes"/&gt; After leaving school, Hill worked at [[Woolworths Group|Woolworths]],&lt;ref name=sabotimes&gt;{{cite news | url=http://www.sabotagetimes.com/funny/the-truth-about-benny-hill/ | title=The Truth About Benny Hill | author=Collins, Andrew | work=[[Sabotage Times]] | date=16 April 2012 | accessdate=16 April 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt; as a [[milkman]], a bridge operator, a driver, and a drummer before becoming assistant stage manager with a touring revue. He was [[Conscription|called up]] in 1942 and trained as a mechanic in the [[British Army]]. He served as a mechanic, truck driver, and [[searchlight]] operator in [[Normandy]] after September 1944&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.jodavidsmeyer.com/combat/military/benny-hill.htm |title=Benny Hill in WWII - British Army |publisher=CombatFan |accessdate=22 January 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt; and later transferred to the [[Combined Services Entertainment]]&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web
 | title = Benny Hill Obituary | work  = Telegraph | publisher = Telegraph Media
 | url = https://www.telegraph.co.uk/news/obituaries/7547472/Benny-Hill.html
 | date = 22 April 1992 | accessdate =31 March 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt; division before the end of the war.

Inspired by the "star comedians" of British [[music hall]] shows, Hill set out to make his mark in show business. He changed his name to "Benny" in homage to his favourite comedian, [[Jack Benny]].&lt;ref name=sabotimes/&gt;

==Career==
After the Second World War, Hill worked as a performer on radio. His first appearance on television was in 1950. In addition, he attempted a sitcom anthology, ''Benny Hill'', which ran from 1962 to 1963, in which he played a different character in each episode. In 1964, he played [[Nick Bottom]] in an all-star TV film production of [[William Shakespeare]]'s ''[[A Midsummer Night's Dream]]''. He also had a radio programme lasting for three series called ''Benny Hill Time'', on [[BBC Radio]]'s [[BBC Light Programme|Light Programme]], from 1964 to 1966. It was a topical show, such as a March 1964 episode which featured James Pond, 0017, in "From Moscow with Love" and his version of "The Beatles". He played a number of characters in the series, such as Harry Hill and Fred Scuttle.

===Films and recordings===
Hill's film credits include parts in five full-length feature films including ''[[Who Done It? (1956 film)|Who Done It?]]'' (1956), ''[[Light Up the Sky! (film)|Light Up the Sky!]]'' (1960), ''[[Those Magnificent Men in their Flying Machines]]'' (1965), ''[[Chitty Chitty Bang Bang]]'' (1968), in which he played the relatively straight role of the Toymaker, and ''[[The Italian Job]]'' (1969). He also made two [[Short film|short]]-subject films, ''The Waiters'' (1969) and ''Eddie in August'' (1970), the latter being a TV production. Finally, a clip-show film spin-off of his early [[Thames Television]] shows (1969–73), called ''[[The Best of Benny Hill]]'' (1974), was a theatrically released compilation of ''[[The Benny Hill Show|Benny Hill Show]]'' episodes. 

Hill's audio recordings include "[[Gather in the Mushrooms]]" (1961), "[[Pepys' Diary (song)|Pepys' Diary]]" (1961), "[[Transistor Radio (song)|Transistor Radio]]" (1961), "[[Harvest of Love]]" (1963), and "[[Ernie (The Fastest Milkman in the West)]]", which was the [[UK Singles Chart]] Christmas number-one single in 1971.&lt;ref name="British Hit Singles &amp; Albums"&gt;{{cite book
| first= David
| last= Roberts
| year= 2006
| title= British Hit Singles &amp; Albums
| edition= 19th
| publisher= Guinness World Records Limited
| location= London
| isbn= 1-904994-10-5
| page= 252}}&lt;/ref&gt; He also appeared in the 1986 video of the song "[[Anything She Does]]" by the band [[Genesis (band)|Genesis]].

===''The Benny Hill Show''===
{{Main|The Benny Hill Show}}
Hill had struggled on stage and had uneven success in radio, but in television, he found a form that played to his strengths. ''The Benny Hill Show'' had a music hall-derived format combining live on-stage comedy and filmed segments, and its humour relied on slapstick, innuendo, and parody. Recurring players on his show during the BBC years included [[Patricia Hayes]], [[Jeremy Hawk]], Peter Vernon, [[Ronnie Brody]], and his co-writer from the early 1950s to early 1960s, [[Dave Freeman (British writer)|Dave Freeman]]. Short, bald [[Jackie Wright]] was a frequent supporting player, who in many sketches had to put up with Hill slapping him on the top of his head.

Hill remained mostly with the BBC through to 1968, except for a few sojourns with [[ITV (TV network)|ITV]] station [[Associated TeleVision|ATV]] between 1957 and 1960 and again in 1967. In 1969, his show moved from the BBC to Thames Television, where it remained until cancellation in 1989, with an erratic schedule of one-hour specials. The series showcased Hill's talents as an imaginative writer, comic performer, and impressionist. He may have bought scripts from various comedy writers, but if so, they never received an onscreen credit (some evidence indicates he bought a script from one of his regular cast members in 1976, [[Cherri Gilham]], to whom he wrote from Spain and told her he was using her "Fat Lady idea on the show" in January 1977).

The most common running gag in Hill's shows was the closing sequence, the "run-off", which was literally a [[running gag]] in that it featured various members of the cast chasing Hill, along with other stock comedy characters such as policemen, vicars, and old women. This was commonly filmed using "under-cranking" camera techniques, and included other comic devices such as characters running off one side of the screen and reappearing running on from the other. The tune used in all the chases, [[Boots Randolph]]'s "[[Yakety Sax]]", is so strongly associated with the show that it is commonly referred to as "The Benny Hill Theme". It has been used as a form of [[parody]] in many ways by television shows and a small number of films. The [[Wachowskis]] used the same style (and musical theme) in a scene in the film ''[[V for Vendetta (film)|V for Vendetta]]'' (2006)&lt;ref&gt;{{Citation|title=V for Vendetta (2005)|url=https://www.imdb.com/title/tt0434409/soundtrack?ref_=tt_trv_snd|accessdate=2017-05-31}}&lt;/ref&gt;{{Citation needed|date= May 2016}}. 

From the start of the 1980s, the show featured a troupe of attractive young women, known collectively as "Hill's Angels". They would appear either on their own in a dance sequence, or in character as foils against Hill. [[Sue Upton]] was one of the longest-serving members of the Angels.  [[Jane Leeves]] appeared, as well. [[Henry McGee]] and [[Bob Todd]] joined Jackie Wright as comic supporting players, and the later shows also featured "Hill's Little Angels", a group of cute children including the families of [[Dennis Kirkland]] (the show's director) and Sue Upton.

The [[alternative comedy|alternative comedian]] [[Ben Elton]] made a headline-grabbing allegation, both on the TV show ''[[Saturday Live (UK TV series)|Saturday Live]]'' and in the pages of ''[[Q (magazine)|Q]]'' magazine (in its January 1987 issue), that ''The Benny Hill Show'' was single-handedly responsible for the incidences of rape in England during the period in question, and also suggested the programme incited other acts of violence against women.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |url=http://findarticles.com/p/articles/mi_m1282/is_n10_v44/ai_12270127/ |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20050303062641/http://www.findarticles.com/p/articles/mi_m1282/is_n10_v44/ai_12270127 |dead-url=yes |archive-date=2005-03-03 |title=The Benny Hill Show }} &lt;/ref&gt; A writer in ''[[The Independent]]'' newspaper, though, opined that Elton's assault was, "like watching an elderly uncle being kicked to death by young thugs".&lt;ref&gt;Jemima Lewis [https://www.independent.co.uk/opinion/commentators/jemima-lewis-why-did-the-british-disown-benny-hill-479887.html "Why did the British disown Benny Hill?"] ''The Independent'', 27 May 2006&lt;/ref&gt; Elton later claimed his comment was taken out of context, and he appeared in a parody for ''[[Harry Enfield and Chums]]'', Benny Elton, where Elton ends up being chased by angry women, accompanied by the "Yakety Sax" theme, after trying to force them to be more feminist rather than letting them make their own decisions.

In response to the accusations of sexism, defenders of Hill have said the show used traditional comic stereotypes to reflect universal human truths in a way that was not malicious and fundamentally harmless. Hill's friend and producer [[Dennis Kirkland]] said it was the women who chased Hill in anger for undressing them, all of which was done accidentally by some ridiculous means. An article on 27 May 2006 in ''[[The Independent]]'' quoted Hill and Kirkland as saying they believed this misrepresentation demonstrated critics could not have watched his programmes.{{Citation needed|date= November 2011}}

In an episode about Hill transmitted as part of the documentary series ''Living Famously'', [[John Howard Davies]], the head of Light Entertainment at Thames Television, who had cancelled the show, stated  he did so for three reasons: "The audiences were going down, the programme was costing a vast amount of money, and he (Hill) was looking a little tired."{{Citation needed|date= November 2011}}

The loss of his show was devastating for Hill (or, as one former supporting player put it, "He started to die from there",{{citation needed|date=December 2014}}) and what followed was a self-inflicted decline in his health. In 1990, a new show was produced complete with Hill and his usual team, called ''Benny Hill's World Tour: New York!''.

In February 1992, Thames Television, which received a steady stream of requests from viewers for ''The Benny Hill Show'' repeats, finally gave in and put together a number of re-edited shows. Hill died on 20 April 1992, the same day that a new contract arrived in the post from [[ITV Central|Central Independent Television]], for which he was to have made a series of specials. He had turned down competing offers from Carlton and Thames.

==Celebrity fans==
[[Johnny Carson]] and side-kick [[Ed McMahon]] were both fans of Hill and tried several times to get him to come to [[Los Angeles]] and be a guest on Carson's ''[[The Tonight Show]]''.  Hill always declined, citing not wanting to travel the great distance to California.

Radio and TV host [[Adam Carolla]] claimed that he was a fan of Hill and that he considered Hill "as American as [[the Beatles]]". Indeed, during an episode of ''[[The Man Show]]'', Carolla performed in what was billed as a tribute to "our favourite Englishman, Sir Benny Hill" (Hill was never knighted) in more risqué versions of some of the sketches. Carolla played a rude and lecherous waiter, a typical Hill role, and the sketch featured many of the staples of Hill's shows, including a [[Jackie Wright]]-esque bald man, as well as the usual scantily clad women.

[[Michael Jackson]] was a Hill fan: "I just love your Benny Hill," the young Jackson told a bemused English music-press critic during a 1970s tour, "he's so funny!" During the decline in Benny Hill's health, he was visited by Jackson, who was in the UK at the time.

The British prog-rock band [[Genesis (band)|Genesis]] may have been fans of Hill. In 1987, they filmed a video for their song "[[Anything She Does]]", featuring Benny as his character Fred Scuttle, an incompetent security guard who lets a ridiculous number of fans backstage at a Genesis concert.

In ''Benny Hill: The World's Favourite Clown'', filmed shortly before his death, celebrities such as [[Burt Reynolds]], [[Michael Caine]], [[John Mortimer]], [[Mickey Rooney]], and [[Walter Cronkite]], among others, expressed their appreciation of and admiration for Hill and his humour – and in Reynolds' case, the appreciation extended to the Hill's Angels, as well. More surprisingly, perhaps, the novelist [[Anthony Burgess]] made no secret of his admiration for Hill. Burgess, whose novels were often comic, relished language, wordplay, and dialect, admired the verbal and comedic skill that underlay Hill's success. Reviewing a biography of Hill, ''Saucy Boy'', in the ''Guardian'' in 1990, Burgess described Hill as "a comic genius steeped in the British music-hall tradition" and "one of the great artists of our age". A meeting between the two men was described in a newspaper article by Burgess and recalled in the ''Telegraph'' newspaper by the satirist [[Craig Brown (satirist)|Craig Brown]].&lt;ref name="test"&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.telegraph.co.uk/comment/personal-view/3622509/Way-of-the-world.html|title=Way of the world|author=Craig Brown|date=21 January 2006|work=Telegraph.co.uk|accessdate=5 July 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In 2006, broadcaster and critic [[Garry Bushell]] launched a campaign to erect a statue of Hill in Southampton, with the support of [[Barbara Windsor]], [[Brian Conley]], and other British comedy favourites. Those taking part in the first fundraising concert included [[Neville Staple]], [[Right Said Fred]], and [[Rick Wakeman]].

In a June 2011 interview with ''[[The Observer]]'', the American rapper [[Snoop Dogg]] declared himself to be a fan of Hill.&lt;ref&gt;Day, Elizabeth, [https://www.theguardian.com/music/2011/jun/19/snoop-dogg-doggumentary-interview Snoop Dogg: 'Women are getting empowered. Now I have a daughter, I understand'], ''The Observer'', Sunday 19 June 2011. Retrieved 22 June 2011.&lt;/ref&gt;

==Personal life==
[[File:Benny Hill lived here.JPG|thumb|left|[[Blue plaque]] commemorating Benny Hill, at his former residence in [[Kensington, London]]]]

Hill never owned his own home in London, and instead preferred to rent a flat rather than buy one.&lt;ref name="everything2.com"&gt;{{cite web|url=http://everything2.com/title/Benny+Hill|title=Benny Hill|author=|date=|work=everything2.com|accessdate=5 July 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt; He rented a double-room apartment in the [[London]] district [[Queen's Gate]] for 26 years until around 1986 when he moved to Fairwater House in [[Teddington]]. While looking for somewhere to live, he stayed at 22 Westrow Gardens in [[Southampton]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.memorialmatters.com/memorials.php?page=Alfred-Hill&amp;section=bio|title=Tribute to Alfred Hawthorne  Hill on MemorialMatters.com|author=|date=|work=memorialmatters.com|accessdate=5 July 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt;  He also never owned a car, although he could drive.

Despite being a millionaire many times over, he continued with the frugal habits that he picked up from his parents, notably his father, such as buying cheap food at supermarkets, walking for miles rather than paying for a [[taxi]] unless someone picked up the tab for a [[limousine]], and constantly patching and mending the same clothes even when the balance on his account at the [[Halifax Building Society]] reached seven figures.&lt;ref name="everything2.com"/&gt; In one of his obituaries, a story was told of how he reportedly refused to mend his mother's leaky roof because it was "too expensive",{{cn|date=August 2016}} and after she died, he kept the family home in Southampton as a shrine to her and did not change a thing at all. 

Hill never married nor had children. He had proposed to two women, but neither accepted. Because of his eccentricity and reclusive lifestyle, rumours circulated that he was [[gay]], but he always laughingly denied them.&lt;ref name=neatorama.com&gt;{{cite web|last1=Cellania|first1=Miss|title=The Strange Life of Benny Hill|url=http://www.neatorama.com/2013/10/24/The-Strange-Life-of-Benny-Hill/|website=neatorama.com|publisher=&lt;!-- Blank --&gt;|accessdate=5 July 2015|date=24 October 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Hill was a huge [[Francophile]] and enjoyed his visits to [[France]], notably to [[Marseilles]], where until the 1980s, he could go to outdoor cafes anonymously, travelling on public transport and socialising with local women.&lt;ref name="neatorama.com"/&gt; He spoke [[French language|French]] fluently and also knew  basic [[German language|German]], [[Spanish language|Spanish]], [[Dutch language|Dutch]], and [[Italian language|Italian]].&lt;ref name="neatorama.com"/&gt;  Foreign travelling was the only luxury that he permitted himself, and even then, he would stay in modest accommodations rather than [[five-star hotel]]s.&lt;ref name="everything2.com"/&gt;

==Death==
Benny Hill's health declined in the late 1980s. After a mild heart attack on 24 February 1992, doctors told him he needed to lose weight and recommended a [[heart bypass]]. He declined, and a week later was found to have [[renal failure|kidney failure]]. He died at the age of 68 on 20 April 1992.&lt;ref name="NYTimes"/&gt; On 22 April, after several days of unanswered telephone calls, his producer, Dennis Kirkland, climbed a ladder to the window of Hill's second-floor flat&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://flashbak.com/the-rise-fall-and-lonely-death-of-benny-hill-371668/|title=The Rise, Fall, and Lonely Death of Benny Hill|author=|date=22 January 2017|website=flashbak.com}}&lt;/ref&gt; and upon seeing the body through a window, had the neighbours call the police. The police broke into the flat and found Hill, dead, sitting in his armchair in front of the television. The cause of death was recorded as [[coronary thrombosis]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|last=Took|first=Barry|title=Hill, Alfred Hawthorne [Benny] (1924–1992), comedian|url=http://www.oxforddnb.com/view/article/51126|work=Oxford Dictionary of National Biography|publisher=Oxford University Press|accessdate=6 June 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; Hill's body was buried at [[Hollybrook Cemetery]] near his birthplace in Southampton on 26 April 1992. 

During the night of 4 October 1992, following speculation in the media that Hill had been buried with a large amount of gold and jewellery, grave robbers excavated the grave at Hollybrook Cemetery and broke open its coffin, the open grave's condition being found by a passer-by the following morning. After a police examination of the scene, the coffin was reclosed and the grave filled back in by cemetery workers, and as a security measure, a 1-ft-thick concrete slab was placed over it.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.heraldscotland.com/news/12587521.Grave_of_Benny_Hill_desecrated/|title=Grave of Benny Hill desecrated|author=|date= 5 October 1992|website=HeraldScotland}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Legacy==
In 1998, [[Channel 4]] featured Hill in one of its ''Heroes of Comedy'' programmes. On 28 December 2006, Channel 4 broadcast the documentary ''Is Benny Hill Still Funny?'' The programme featured an audience that comprised a [[Cross-sectional data|cross-section]] of young adults who had little or no knowledge of Hill, to discover whether his comedy was valid to a generation that enjoyed the likes of ''[[Little Britain]]'', ''[[The Catherine Tate Show]]'', and ''[[Borat]]''. The participants were asked to watch a 30-minute compilation that included examples of Hill's humour from both his BBC and ITV shows. The responses and results demonstrated that none of the sample of viewers took offence at any of the sketches shown. His silent "Wishing Well" sketch was discovered to be the most popular.{{citation required|date=July 2018}}

==References==
'''Notes'''
{{Reflist|30em}}

'''Bibliography'''
* Lewisohn, Mark. ''Funny, Peculiar – The True Story of Benny Hill''
* Smith, John. ''Benny Hill Story'' New York: St. Martin's Press, 1989
* GRO – Alfred H. Hill born MAR qtr 1924 2c 52 SOUTHAMPTON, mmn = Cave
* GRO – Alfred Hawthorne Hill died: APR 1992 14 1352 [[Richmond-upon-Thames]], aged 68, his date of birth was 21 January 1924

==External links==
{{wikiquote}}
{{Commonscat}}
{{Portal|Biography}}
* {{official website|http://www.bennyhill.co.uk/}}
* {{IMDb name|0001350}}
* {{tcmdb name|id=86373|name=Benny Hill}}
* {{cite web |url= https://www.telegraph.co.uk/news/obituaries/7547472/Benny-Hill.html |title= Benny Hill |publisher= Daily Telegraph |work= Obituary |date= 22 Apr 1992 }}
* {{FAG|481}}
* {{cite web |url= http://www.museum.tv/eotv/bennyhillsh.htm |title= Benny Hill |website= [[Museum of Broadcast Communications]] |date= 25 Oct 2013 |first= Albert |last= Moran }}
* {{cite web |url= http://laughterlog.com/2009/03/19/benny-hill/ |title= Benny Hill |publisher= Laugh Magazine |work= List of appearances on television, radio and record |first= Peter |last= Tatchell |date= 2001 &lt;!-- issue= 22 --&gt; }}
* [http://eastleighso50.tripod.com/id5.html The Eastleigh Photograph Archive] Photos of the dairy and streets where Benny worked as a milkman, inspiring the song "Ernie (The Fastest Milkman in the West)"
* [http://www.tnsf.ca/bennyhill The Benny Hill Songbook] Lyrics, guitar chords and transcripts
* [https://downstairslounge.wordpress.com/2015/01/13/benny-hill-sings/ Benny Hill Sings?] Benny Hill's 1965 debut LP on Pye records
* [http://news.bbc.co.uk/local/hampshire/hi/people_and_places/newsid_8186000/8186192.stm BBC Hampshire] BBC article on Benny Hill's Hampshire connections
* [http://www.runstop.de/ Benny's Place] featuring [[Louise English]] &amp; Hill's Angels


{{Use dmy dates|date=August 2014}}

{{Authority control}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Hill, Benny}}
[[Category:1924 births]]
[[Category:1992 deaths]]
[[Category:English comedy musicians]]
[[Category:English male comedians]]
[[Category:English male film actors]]
[[Category:People educated at Bournemouth School]]
[[Category:People from Southampton]]
[[Category:Pye Records artists]]
[[Category:20th-century English male actors]]
[[Category:British sketch comedians]]
[[Category:British novelty song performers]]
[[Category:20th-century English musicians]]
[[Category:20th-century British comedians]]
[[Category:Deaths from thrombosis]]
[[Category:English male television actors]]
[[Category:British male comedy actors]]
[[Category:Deaths from coronary thrombosis]]</text>
      <sha1>d24i9zp6f5kj5s6vonxyd12wxfcn9c2</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
