<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10.xsd" version="0.10" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <dbname>enwiki</dbname>
    <base>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.32.0-wmf.16</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="118" case="first-letter">Draft</namespace>
      <namespace key="119" case="first-letter">Draft talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2300" case="first-letter">Gadget</namespace>
      <namespace key="2301" case="first-letter">Gadget talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2302" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition</namespace>
      <namespace key="2303" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Chico Marx</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>169610</id>
    <revision>
      <id>853946132</id>
      <parentid>852121721</parentid>
      <timestamp>2018-08-07T23:40:01Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <ip>47.18.27.169</ip>
      </contributor>
      <comment>Clarified content.</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="15635">{{Infobox person
| image        = Chico Marx - signed.jpg
| caption      = Chico Marx around 1930
| birth_name   = Leonard Marx
| birth_date   = {{birth date|1887|03|22}}
| birth_place  = [[Manhattan, New York City]], U.S.
| death_date   = {{death date and age|1961|10|11|1887|03|22}}
| death_place  = [[Hollywood, California]], U.S.
| death_cause  = [[Arteriosclerosis]]
| burial_place = [[Forest Lawn Memorial Park (Glendale)|Forest Lawn Memorial Park Cemetery]], Los Angeles
| occupation   = Actor, bandleader, comedian
| yearsactive  = 1910–1960
| height       = 5 ft 6 in
| other_names  = Leo Marx
| spouse       = {{unbulleted list|{{marriage|Betty Karp&lt;br&gt;|1917|1940|reason=divorced}}|{{marriage|Mary De Vithas&lt;br&gt;|1958|&lt;!--As marriage ended with his death, year is omitted per Template:Marriage instructions---&gt;}}}}
| children     = 1
| parents      = [[Sam Marx|Sam "Frenchie" Marx]] &lt;br&gt; [[Minnie Marx|Minnie Schönberg]]
| relatives    = [[Harpo Marx]] &lt;small&gt;(brother)&lt;/small&gt;&lt;br&gt; [[Groucho Marx]] &lt;small&gt;(brother)&lt;/small&gt; &lt;br&gt; [[Gummo Marx]] &lt;small&gt;(brother)&lt;/small&gt; &lt;br&gt; [[Zeppo Marx]] &lt;small&gt;(brother)&lt;/small&gt;&lt;br&gt; [[Al Shean]] &lt;small&gt;(maternal uncle)&lt;/small&gt;
}}

'''Leonard''' "'''Chico'''" '''Marx''' (March 22, 1887 – October 11, 1961) was an American [[comedian]], musician, bartender, actor and film star.&lt;ref  name=NYTobit/&gt; He was a member of the [[Marx Brothers]] (with [[Groucho Marx]], [[Harpo Marx]], and [[Zeppo Marx]]). His persona in the act was that of a charming, dim-witted albeit crafty con artist, seemingly of rural Italian origin, who wore shabby clothes and sported a curly-haired wig and [[Tyrolean hat]]. In virtually every film that includes the main trio of the Marx Brothers, Chico is seen working with [[Harpo Marx]], usually as partners in crime. Leonard was the oldest of the Marx Brothers to live past early childhood (first-born Manfred Marx had died in infancy). In addition to his work as a performer, he played an important role in the management and development of the act in its early years.

==Early years==
He was born on March 22, 1887.&lt;ref name=NYTobit/&gt;&lt;ref name=age&gt;During his lifetime, his year of birth had commonly been given as 1891 instead of the true year of 1887. As a result, obituaries reported his age at the time of his death as 70 rather than 74.&lt;/ref&gt;

Billing himself as Chico, he used an Italian persona for his onstage character; stereotyped ethnic characters were common with vaudevillians. His non-Italian-ness was specifically referred to three times on film. In their second feature, ''[[Animal Crackers (1930 film)|Animal Crackers]]'', he recognizes someone he knows to be a shady character impersonating a respected art collector:

&lt;blockquote&gt;'''Ravelli''' (Chico): "How is it you got to be Roscoe W. Chandler?"&lt;br /&gt; '''Chandler''': "Say, how did ''you'' get to be an ''Italian''?"&lt;br /&gt; '''Ravelli''': "Never mind—whose confession is this?"&lt;/blockquote&gt;

In ''[[Duck Soup (1933 film)|Duck Soup]]'', when Chico impersonates Groucho but retains his accent, [[Margaret Dumont]] asks what happened to his voice. Chico replies, "Well, maybe sometime I go to Italy and I'm practicing the language." To which Dumont replies, "Your dialect is perfect."

In ''[[A Night at the Opera (film)|A Night at the Opera]]'', which begins in Italy, his character, Fiorello, claims not to be Italian, eliciting a surprised look from [[Groucho Marx|Groucho]]:

&lt;blockquote&gt;'''Driftwood''' (Groucho): "Well, things certainly seem to be getting better around the country."&lt;br /&gt; '''Fiorello''' (Chico): "Well, I wouldn't know about that; I'm a stranger here myself."&lt;/blockquote&gt;

A scene in the film ''[[Go West (1940 film)|Go West]]'', in which Chico attempts to placate an Indian chief of whom Groucho has run afoul, has a line that plays a bit on Chico's lack of Italian nationality, but is more or less proper Marxian wordplay:
&lt;blockquote&gt;'''S. Quentin Quayle''' (Groucho): "Can you talk Indian?"&lt;br&gt;'''Joe Panello''' (Chico): "I was born in Indianapolis!"&lt;/blockquote&gt;

There are moments, however, where Chico's characters appear to be genuinely Italian; examples include the film ''[[The Big Store]]'', in which his character Ravelli runs into an old friend he worked with in Naples (after a brief misunderstanding due to his accent), the film ''[[Monkey Business (1931 film)|Monkey Business]]'', in which Chico claims his grandfather sailed with [[Christopher Columbus]], and their very first outing ''[[The Cocoanuts]]'', where Mr. Hammer (Groucho) asks him if he knew what an auction was, in which he responds "I come from Italy on the [[Atlantic Ocean|Atlantic Auction]]!"  Chico's character is often assumed to be dim-witted, as he frequently misunderstands words spoken by other characters (particularly Groucho). However, he often gets the better of the same characters by extorting money from them, either by con or blackmail; again, Groucho is his most frequent target.

[[File:Chico Marx 1909.jpg|thumb|right|Chico Marx playing cards with himself; taken at [[Rockaway Beach, New York]], c. 1909]]
Chico was a talented [[pianist]]. He originally started playing with only his right hand and fake playing with his left, as his teacher did so herself. Chico eventually acquired a better teacher and learned to play the piano correctly. As a young boy, he gained jobs playing piano to earn money for the Marx family. Sometimes Chico even worked playing in two places at the same time. He would acquire the first job with his piano-playing skills, work for a few nights, and then substitute [[Harpo Marx|Harpo]] on one of the jobs. (During their boyhood, Chico and Harpo looked so much alike that they were often mistaken for each other.)

In the brothers' last film, ''[[Love Happy]]'', Chico plays a piano and [[violin]] [[duet]] with 'Mr. Lyons' ([[Leon Belasco]]). Lyons plays some ornate riffs on the violin; Chico comments, "Look-a, Mister Lyons, I know you wanna make a good impression, but please don't-a play better than me!"

In a record album about the Marx Brothers, narrator [[Gary Owens]] stated that "although Chico's technique was limited, his repertoire was not." The opposite was true of Harpo, who reportedly could play only two tunes on the piano, which typically thwarted Chico's scam and resulted in both brothers' being fired.
[[File:Marx Brothers 1931.jpg|left|thumb|150px|The Marx Brothers, from top: Chico, Harpo, Groucho, and Zeppo Marx]]
Groucho Marx once said that Chico never practiced the pieces he played. Instead, before performances he soaked his fingers in hot water. He was known for 'shooting' the keys of the piano. He played passages with his thumb up and index finger straight, like a gun, as part of the act. Other examples of his keyboard flamboyance are found in ''[[A Night at the Opera (film)|A Night at the Opera]]'' (1935), where he played the piano for a group of delighted children, and ''[[A Night in Casablanca]]'' (1946), where he played a rendition of "The Beer Barrel Polka".

Chico became the unofficial manager of the [[Marx Brothers]] after their mother, [[Minnie Marx|Minnie]], died in 1929.&lt;ref name=NYTobit/&gt; As manager, he cut a deal to get the brothers a percentage of a film's gross receipts—the first of its kind in [[Hollywood]]. Furthermore, it was Chico's connection with [[Irving Thalberg]] of [[Metro-Goldwyn-Mayer]] that led to Thalberg's signing the Brothers when they were in a career slump after ''Duck Soup'' (1933), the last of their films for [[Paramount Pictures|Paramount]].

For a while in the 1930s and 1940s, Chico led a [[big band]]. Singer [[Mel Tormé]] began his professional career singing with the Chico Marx Orchestra. Through the 1950s, Chico occasionally appeared on a variety of television anthology shows and some television commercials, most memorably with Harpo in "The Incredible Jewelry Robbery", a pantomime episode of ''[[General Electric Theater]]'' in 1959.

===Pronunciation and origin of name===
[[File:Chico Marx The College Bowl 1950.jpg|thumb|Chico was the star of a 1950 [[American Broadcasting Company|ABC]] television comedy, ''The College Bowl''. He played the role of a campus malt shop owner who dispensed both sodas and advice to the students.]]
His nickname (acquired during a card game in Chicago in 1915) was originally spelled '''Chicko'''. A typesetter accidentally dropped the "k" in his name and it became Chico.{{citation needed|date=August 2015}} It was still pronounced "Chick-oh" although those who were unaware of its origin tended to pronounce it "Cheek-oh". Numerous radio recordings from the 1940s exist where announcers and fellow actors mispronounce the nickname, but Chico apparently felt it was unnecessary to correct them. As late as the 1950s, Groucho was happy to use the wrong pronunciation for comedic effect. A guest on ''[[You Bet Your Life]]'' told the quizmaster she grew up around [[Chico, California|Chico]] (California) and Groucho responded, "I grew up around Chico myself. You aren't Gummo, are you?"

During Groucho's live performance at [[Carnegie Hall]] in 1972, he states that his brother got the name Chico because he was a "chicken-chaser" (early 20th century slang for womanizer). "In England now, they call them birds."&lt;ref&gt;[https://archive.org/download/OTRR_An_Evening_With_Groucho_Singles/AnEveningWithGroucho_06_MyFamily_HowWeGotOurNames.mp3 Groucho Live At Carnegie Hall]&lt;/ref&gt;

===Gambling===
&lt;!--[[File:Marx Brothers 1948.jpg|right|thumb|[[Marx Brothers|The Marx Brothers]] (clockwise from bottom: Groucho, Chico, and Harpo) by [[Yusuf Karsh]] in 1948]]--&gt;
[[File:Harpo and Chico Marx General Electric Theater 1959.JPG|thumb|right|Harpo and Chico Marx in "The Incredible Jewelry Robbery" on ''[[General Electric Theater]]'' in 1959]]
As well as being a compulsive womanizer, Chico had a lifelong [[gambling]] habit. His favorite gambling pursuits were card games, horse racing, dog racing, and various sports betting. His addiction cost him millions of dollars by his own account. When an interviewer in the late 1930s asked him how much money he had lost from gambling, he answered, "Find out how much money Harpo's got. That's how much I've lost." Gummo Marx, in an interview years after Chico's death, said: "Chico's favorite people were actors who gambled, producers who gambled, and women who screwed." Referring to Chico's love life, [[George Jessel (actor)|George Jessel]] quipped, "Chico didn't button his fly until he was seventy."&lt;ref&gt;Bader, Robert S., Four of the Three Musketeers: The Marx Brothers On Stage, Northwestern University Press, 2017, pg. 132&lt;/ref&gt;

Chico's lifelong gambling addiction compelled him to continue in show business long after his brothers had retired in comfort from their Hollywood income, and in the early 1940s he found himself playing in the same small, cheap halls in which he had begun his career 30 years earlier.  The Marx Brothers' penultimate film, ''[[A Night in Casablanca]]'' (1946), was made for Chico's benefit since he had filed for bankruptcy a few years prior. Because of his out-of-control gambling, the brothers finally took the money as he earned it and put him on an allowance, on which he stayed until his death.

Chico had a reputation as a world-class [[pinochle]] player, a game he and Harpo learned from their father. Groucho said Chico would throw away good cards (with the knowledge of spectators) to make the play "more interesting". Chico's last public appearance was in 1960, playing cards on the television show ''[[Championship Bridge]]''. He and his partner lost the game.

==Personal life==
Chico was born in [[Manhattan, New York City]]. His parents were [[Sam Marx]] (called "Frenchie" throughout his life), and his wife, [[Minnie Marx|Minnie Schoenberg Marx]]. Minnie's brother was [[Al Shean]]. The Marx family was Franco-German Jewish. His father was a native of [[Alsace]] who worked as a tailor and his mother was from [[East Frisia]] in [[Germany]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://judaisme.sdv.fr/perso/marxbr/geneal.htm ''La famille paternelle des Marx Brothers''] {{fr icon}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news|first= |last= |title=Mrs. Minnie Marx. Mother of Four Marx Brothers, Musical Comedy Stars, Dies |work =New York Times |date=September 16, 1929}} Viewed 2007-08-21.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news|title=Samuel Marx, Father of Four Marx Brothers of Stage and Screen Fame|url=http://timesmachine.nytimes.com/timesmachine/1933/05/12/105134141.html?pageNumber=17|newspaper=New York Times|date=May 12, 1933|page=17|accessdate=2008-06-27}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Chico was married twice. His first marriage was to Betty Karp in 1917. Their union produced one daughter named Maxine (1918–2009). His first marriage was plagued by his infidelity, ending in divorce in 1940; he was very close to his daughter Maxine and gave her acting lessons.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.newsfromme.com/archives/2009_09_20.html#017760|author=Evanier, Mark|title=News from me|date=Sep 20, 2009|archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20090924174234/http://www.newsfromme.com/archives/2009_09_20.html|archivedate=Sep 24, 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Chico's second marriage was to Mary De Vithas. They married in 1958, three years before his death.&lt;ref name=NYTobit/&gt;

==Death==
[[File:Chicograve.jpg|thumb|right|Grave]]
Chico died of [[arteriosclerosis]] at age 74 on October 11, 1961, at his Hollywood home.&lt;ref name=NYTobit&gt;{{cite news|title=Chico Marx, Stage and Film Comedian, Dies at 70. Oldest of 5 Brothers Took Role of Italian Piano Player. Team Business Manager|url=http://timesmachine.nytimes.com/timesmachine/1961/10/12/101477032.html?pageNumber=29|accessdate=12 August 2016|newspaper=New York Times|date=October 12, 1961|page=29}}&lt;/ref&gt; He was the eldest brother and the first to die.&lt;ref name=age/&gt;

He is entombed in a crypt at [[Forest Lawn Memorial Park (Glendale)|Forest Lawn Memorial Park Cemetery]] in [[Glendale, California]]. Chico's younger brother [[Gummo Marx|Gummo]] is in a crypt across the hall from him.

==Portrayals==

Many actors have portrayed Chico in stage revivals of Marx Brothers works, including Peter Slutsker, Les Marsden and [[Matt Roper]].

==References==
{{Reflist}}

==External links==
{{Portal|Biography|Film}}
{{commons category}}
* {{IMDb name|555597}}
* {{Tcmdb name}}
* {{YouTube|yZyhosgpS48|Chico plays piano in ''Animal Crackers''}}
* {{YouTube|3kDHD4Bs_EI|Chico plays piano in ''Horse Feathers''}}
* {{YouTube|jkCiRSDPIzk|Chico plays piano in ''A Night at the Opera''}}
* {{YouTube|T5MCn2juMS0|Chico plays piano in ''A Day at the Races''}}
* [https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=HM2op9y3tms How to play piano like Chico Marx]
* [http://www.marx-brothers.org/living/chico.htm Chico Marx at Marx Brothers.org]
* [http://www.marx-brothers.org/news.htm News - The Marx Brothers]
* {{YouTube|xPoeyMqC18A|Chico Marx on Championship Bridge with Charles Goren}}
{{Marx Brothers}}

{{Authority control}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Marx, Chico}}
[[Category:1887 births]]
[[Category:1961 deaths]]
[[Category:20th-century American comedians]]
[[Category:Male actors from New York City]]
[[Category:American male film actors]]
[[Category:American comedy musicians]]
[[Category:American male comedians]]
[[Category:American people of Alsatian-Jewish descent]]
[[Category:American pianists]]
[[Category:Burials at Forest Lawn Memorial Park (Glendale)]]
[[Category:American people of German-Jewish descent]]
[[Category:Jewish American male actors]]
[[Category:Comedians from New York City]]
[[Category:Vaudeville performers]]
[[Category:Marx Brothers]]
[[Category:20th-century American male actors]]
[[Category:Jewish American comedians]]
[[Category:American male comedy actors]]</text>
      <sha1>feg6gq59jwam9bgceyiqlw3u1iyzmi6</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
