<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10.xsd" version="0.10" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <dbname>enwiki</dbname>
    <base>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.32.0-wmf.16</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="118" case="first-letter">Draft</namespace>
      <namespace key="119" case="first-letter">Draft talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2300" case="first-letter">Gadget</namespace>
      <namespace key="2301" case="first-letter">Gadget talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2302" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition</namespace>
      <namespace key="2303" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Craig Charles</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>5829</id>
    <revision>
      <id>855563380</id>
      <parentid>855563288</parentid>
      <timestamp>2018-08-19T07:13:11Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Z0</username>
        <id>33373980</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor/>
      <comment>Reverted edits by [[Special:Contributions/78.149.103.124|78.149.103.124]] ([[User talk:78.149.103.124|talk]]) ([[WP:HG|HG]]) (3.4.4)</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="51588">{{Use British English|date=June 2013}}
{{Infobox person
| name         = Craig Charles
| image        = Craig Charles.jpg
| image_size   = 220px
| caption      = Charles in May 2009
| birth_name = Craig Joseph Charles
| birth_date   = {{birth date and age|1964|07|11|df=y}}
| birth_place  = [[Liverpool]], Merseyside, England
| residence    = [[Altrincham]], [[Greater Manchester]], England&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.theguardian.com/culture/2017/dec/03/on-my-radar-craig-charles-basquiat-boom-for-real-don-winslow-altrincham-market-john-bishop|title=On my radar: Craig Charles’s cultural highlights|author=Sarah Harford|date=3 December 2017|work=The Guardian}}&lt;/ref&gt;
| occupation   = Actor, television presenter, comedian, author, poet, DJ
| years_active = 1981–present
| spouse       = [[Cathy Tyson]]&lt;br /&gt;(1984–1989; divorced)&lt;br /&gt;Jackie Fleming&lt;br /&gt;(1999–present)
| children     = 3
}}
'''Craig Joseph Charles''' (born 11 July 1964) is a British actor, comedian, author, poet, television presenter and DJ. He is best known for playing [[Dave Lister]] in the science fiction sitcom ''[[Red Dwarf]]'' and [[Lloyd Mullaney]] in the soap opera ''[[Coronation Street]]'', as a funk and soul DJ on [[BBC Radio 6 Music]] and [[BBC Radio 2]], and as the presenter of the gladiator-style game show ''[[Robot Wars (TV series)|Robot Wars]]'' from 1998 to 2004.

Charles first appeared on television as a [[Performance poetry|performance poet]], which led to minor presenting roles. After finding fame in ''Red Dwarf'', he regularly featured on national television with celebrity appearances on many popular shows while he continued to host a wide variety of programmes.

Charles is also known for narrating the comedy endurance show ''[[Takeshi's Castle#United Kingdom|Takeshi's Castle]]''. From 2017, he has hosted ''[[The Gadget Show]]'' for [[Channel 5 (UK)|Channel 5]]. His acting credits include playing inmate Eugene Buffy in the ITV drama ''The Governor'', and leading roles in the British films ''Fated'' and ''Clubbing to Death''. He has toured the UK extensively as a stand-up comedian.

Charles has hosted ''[[The Craig Charles Funk and Soul Show]]'' on BBC radio since 2002, and performs DJ sets at numerous clubs and festivals, nationally and internationally. In September 2015, he left ''Coronation Street'' after ten years, to film new episodes of ''Red Dwarf''.

== Early life ==
Charles was born in [[Liverpool]] to a [[Guyana|Guyanese]] father&lt;ref&gt;''Liverpool Echo'', 22 November 2005, [http://www.thefreelibrary.com/Actor+Craig's+tribute+to+much-loved+father.-a0138994015 "Actor Craig's tribute to much-loved father"]&lt;/ref&gt; and Irish mother.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.independent.co.uk/news/people/profiles/my-secret-life-craig-charles-47-dj-and-actor-7893368.html|title=My Secret Life: Craig Charles, 47, DJ and actor|author=Holly Williams|date=27 June 2012|work=The Independent}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.bbc.co.uk/comedy/people/craig_charles_person_page.shtml "Craig Charles person page"] bbc.co.uk&lt;/ref&gt; He grew up on the [[Cantril Farm]] housing estate&lt;ref&gt;''The Independent'', 30 June 2012, Holly Williams [https://www.independent.co.uk/news/people/profiles/my-secret-life-craig-charles-47-dj-and-actor-7893368.html "My Secret Life: Craig Charles, 47, DJ and actor"], London&lt;/ref&gt; with his older brother, Dean (who died in 2014), and younger brother, Emile. He attended [[West Derby Comprehensive|West Derby Comprehensive School]] followed by Childwall Hall College of Further Education, studying [[GCE Advanced Level|A-levels]] in History, Government and Politics, English Literature and General Studies.&lt;ref&gt;''The Independent'', 11 February 1999, [https://www.independent.co.uk/news/people/profiles/education-passedfailed-craig-charles-1070071.html "Education: Passed/Failed Craig Charles"], London&lt;/ref&gt; Charles won a national competition, run by ''[[The Guardian]]'' newspaper, for a poem he wrote when he was 12 years old.&lt;ref&gt;Interview with Charles by Chris Jarvis, ''Fully Booked'', BBC TV, 1998&lt;/ref&gt;  On leaving school Charles spent time working in a studio at Central Hall, Renshaw Street, Liverpool. His eloquence in conversation and in his poetry (which he shared with colleagues) was something new at the time. With his gradual flowering as a poet emerged a certain boldness and self-confidence. {{according to whom|date= February 2017}}

== Early career ==
Charles began his career as a contemporary and urban performance poet on the British [[cabaret]] circuit. His performances were considered original, with Charles described as having a natural ironic wit which appealed to talent scouts. In 1981, Charles climbed on stage at a [[Teardrop Explodes]] concert and recited a humorous, but derogatory, poem about the band's singer, [[Julian Cope]]. He was invited to open subsequent gigs for the group and went on to perform as a support act in pubs and clubs for the following three years,&lt;ref&gt;''Q magazine'', April 1987, David Housham "Craig Charles: Compulsive Listening", pp. 25–26&lt;/ref&gt; and at events such as the ''Larks in the Park'' music festival at [[Sefton Park]] (1982). He performed poetry at Liverpool's [[Everyman Theatre, Liverpool|Everyman Theatre]] (1983) with such poets as [[Roger McGough]] and [[Adrian Henri]].

Charles was involved in the Liverpool music scene, writing and singing lyrics for a number of local rock bands.&lt;ref&gt;Craig Charles, Introduction to ''No Other Blue'', Penguin Books Ltd, London, 1997&lt;/ref&gt; In 1980, he played keyboards, bass and provided voice in the rock band ''Watt 4''.&lt;ref&gt;''Daily Post'', 16 September 2003, Chris Brown [http://webspace.webring.com/people/wj/junostar/CCicnetwork.html "A club that rocked when punk was in its prime"], Liverpool&lt;/ref&gt; He performed his political rap lyrics as a 'Wordsmith'. In 1983, Charles was invited to record a session on the [[John Peel]] BBC Radio show, performing his poems backed by a band. This was his first professional engagement.&lt;ref&gt;The Craig Charles Funk and Soul Show, BBC Radio 6 Music, 12 May 2012&lt;/ref&gt; He recorded a further Peel Session in 1984.&lt;ref&gt;AL Peters, "Craig Charles The Wordsmith, ''The John Peel Radio Show'', 1984", [http://www.groovinrecords.co.uk/ Groovin' Records]&lt;/ref&gt;

Charles realised he was using poetry as a vehicle for his sense of humour and progressed into stand-up comedy. He was part of the ''[[Red Wedge]]'' comedy tour in 1986, which aimed to raise awareness of the social problems of the time, in support of the [[Labour Party (UK)|Labour Party]]. He also performed his first one-man show in 1986,&lt;ref&gt;[http://special.lib.gla.ac.uk/sta/search/detaile.cfm?EID=19588 ''Raising the Roof for the Gateway Exchange''], 29 August 1986, Edinburgh Festival Fringe&lt;/ref&gt; which premiered in Edinburgh, and then toured internationally.&lt;ref&gt;''The Glasgow Herald'', 13 August 1987, Andrew Young [https://news.google.com/newspapers?nid=2507&amp;dat=19870813&amp;id=yDpAAAAAIBAJ&amp;sjid=WFkMAAAAIBAJ&amp;pg=2116,2850085 ''The Fringe: Craig Charles'']&lt;/ref&gt; Charles was a guest on programmes including [[Janice Long]]'s [[BBC Radio 1|Radio 1]] show,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.mrsoulsbury.com/2011/04/april-podcast-with-craig-charles-and.html|title=Mr Soulsbury: April Podcast with Craig Charles and Ewan Hoozami!|author=Make Design Enjoy|publisher=}}&lt;/ref&gt; and was a regular panellist on [[Ned Sherrin]]'s chat show ''[[Loose Ends (radio)|Loose Ends]]'' (1987–88) on [[BBC Radio 4]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|title=Champion of funk soul brothers|url=https://www.independent.co.uk/news/media/champion-of-funk-soul-brothers-6151442.html|publisher=The Independent, 7 March 2005 | location=London|first=Ian|last=Burrell|date=7 March 2005}}&lt;/ref&gt;

== Television career ==

=== Performance poetry ===
Charles first appeared on television as the resident poet on the arts programme ''Riverside'' on [[BBC Two|BBC2]] and on the day-time BBC1 chat show ''[[Pebble Mill at One]]''.&lt;ref&gt;''Birmingham Mail'', 2 July 2011, [http://www.birminghammail.net/news/top-stories/2011/07/02/craig-charles-returns-to-birmingham-for-the-mostly-jazz-festival-97319-28979805/ "Craig Charles returns to Birmingham for the Mostly Jazz festival"]&lt;/ref&gt; Charles was the resident poet on the [[Channel 4]] programme ''Black on Black'' (1985)&lt;ref&gt;"Craig Charles poet/broadcaster", ''Black on Black'', 1985, [http://www.search.digitalhandsworth.org.uk/engine/resource/exhibition/standard/child.asp?txtKeywords=&amp;lstContext=&amp;lstResourceType=&amp;lstExhibitionType=3&amp;chkPurchaseVisible=&amp;txtDateFrom=&amp;txtDateTo=&amp;x1=&amp;y1=&amp;x2=&amp;y2=&amp;scale=&amp;theme=&amp;album=&amp;viewpage=%2Fengine%2Fresource%2Fexhibition%2Fstandard%2Fchild.asp&amp;originator=%2Fengine%2Fcustom%2Fgallery.asp&amp;page=&amp;records=&amp;direction=&amp;pointer=&amp;text=0&amp;resource=598&amp;exhibition=445&amp;offset=16 Digital Handsworth]&lt;/ref&gt; and its entertainment-based successor ''Club Mix'' (1986), and he appeared, weekly, as a [[John Cooper Clarke]]-style 'punk poet' on the BBC2 pop music programme ''[[Oxford Road Show]]'' (ORS). Charles performed his political poems as stand-up comedy on the late-night show ''[[Saturday Live (UK TV series)|Saturday Live]]'' (1985–87) and on the prime-time BBC1 chat show ''Wogan'' (1986–87), where he performed a topical poem in a weekly feature. He also appeared as a guest on shows including ''Open Air'' (1988). Charles included significant acting in his performance style, enabling him to put the emotion across.&lt;ref&gt;Charles interviewed on the Steve Jones Show, LBC Radio (London), 16 March 1989&lt;/ref&gt;
In September 2015, Charles performed his "epic" poem ''Scary Fairy and the Tales of the Dark Wood'' live with the [[BBC Philharmonic]] orchestra, in a concert to be broadcast on BBC Radio 2's ''[[Friday Night is Music Night]]'' at Halloween.

=== ''Red Dwarf'' ===
[[File:Craig Charles (03).jpg|thumb|190px|Craig Charles in 2009]]
Charles acquired cult status in 1988 in his first television acting role as the Liverpudlian slob [[Dave Lister]] in science fiction comedy series ''[[Red Dwarf]]''. Charles has appeared in all twelve series. Charles' younger brother, Emile Charles, guest-starred in the Series III episode "[[Timeslides]]", and the songs "Bad News" and "Cash" in this episode were written by Charles and performed by his band.&lt;ref&gt;Andrew Ellard, ''Red Dwarf series III DVD boxset Collector's Booklet'', Grant Naylor Productions, 2003, pp. 8&lt;/ref&gt; The role has involved Charles playing a variety of alternative characters, including a gangster, a cowboy and angelic and evil versions of Lister,&lt;ref&gt;''TV Zone'', November 1993, Carrie Cantor "Red Dwarf Interview: Lager Lout Lister", pp. 8–11&lt;/ref&gt; and in him carrying out a wide range of stunts, and acting involving special effects. All series, except VII and IX, were recorded in front of a studio audience. Along with [[Danny John-Jules]] [Cat], Charles is one of only two cast members to appear in every episode of ''Red Dwarf'' to date.

Charles reads the audiobook editions of both the ''Red Dwarf'' novel ''[[Last Human]]'' and his book ''The Log: A Dwarfer's Guide to Everything'', and he regularly attends sci-fi, comedy and memorabilia conventions in connection with the ''Red Dwarf'' franchise. During ''[[Red Dwarf: Back to Earth|Back to Earth]]'', Lister visits the set of ''Coronation Street'', where he meets the actor Craig Charles.&lt;ref&gt;''Blokely'', 7 November 2012, James York &amp; Richard Luck [http://blokely.com/entertainment/craig-charles-interview-red-dwarf-x " Craig Charles: Funk &amp; Soul x Sci-fi"]&lt;/ref&gt;

=== ''Robot Wars'' ===
Charles presented ''[[Robot Wars (TV series)|Robot Wars]]'' on BBC2 (1998–2003) and Channel 5 (2003–04), from series 2 until series 7, which included two ''Extreme'' series and numerous 'specials'. Charles was the main host and presided over the arena in which teams of amateur engineers battled their home-made radio-controlled robots against each other, and against the house robots. Charles introduced the show, enthusiastically announced the results of the battles and spoke to the contestants after the main events. He ended each episode with a short ''Robot Wars''-themed poem. Charles' son, Jack, appeared on the show on several occasions, and was a contestant on "Team Nemesis" during series 4. Charles also hosted the ''Robot Wars Live'' UK tour, in 2001 and shows performed at the [[Wembley Arena]]. On 13 January 2016, The BBC announced that the show would be rebooted with 6 episodes in the year. On 14 January 2016, Charles posted a tweet on his Twitter page saying that he would love to present the new series, however he received no reply from the BBC. On 3 February 2016, [[Dara Ó Briain]] was announced as Charles' replacement as the presenter. The BBC also stated that they had denied Charles' request to reprise his role by stating that they don't comment on individual casting enquiries.

=== ''Takeshi's Castle'' ===
Charles provided the English [[voice-over]] commentary for the [[Challenge TV|Challenge]] and [[Ftn (TV channel)|Ftn]] (2002–04) rebroadcast of the popular game show ''[[Takeshi's Castle#United Kingdom|Takeshi's Castle]]'' originally by [[Tokyo Broadcasting System]] in Japan. In each episode, between 100 and 142 contestants attempted to pass a series of wacky and near-impossible physical challenges to reach the Show Down at the castle against a Japanese actor [[Takeshi Kitano]] for a chance to win large cash prizes. Charles co-wrote the programme and commentated throughout all 122 episodes of the four series, and also some special and "best of" episodes. He provided comedy insights into the contestants' abilities, which were designed to appeal to adult audiences, as well as younger viewers - and also coined the term "Keshi Heads" to describe fans of the show.

Charles' commentary was so well received that the reboot featuring [[Dick and Dom]] on the voice-overs did not fare as well because he wasn't there, according to complaints that Challenge received via social media. To this day, the Challenge rebroadcasts of ''Takeshi's Castle'' regularly place in the weekly top 10 for ratings with an average of 130,000 viewers per episode.

=== ''Coronation Street'' ===
In 2005, Charles joined the main cast of ''[[Coronation Street]]'',&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |title=Lloyd Mullaney character page|url=http://www.itv.com/coronationstreet/characters/lloyd-mullaney}}&lt;/ref&gt; playing philandering taxicab driver, [[Lloyd Mullaney]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Corrie's Craig Charles on being romantic, ''This Morning'' ITV interview with Charles, 6 September 2011|url=http://www.itv.com/thismorning/showbiz/corries-craig-charles/|deadurl=yes|archiveurl=https://archive.is/20120905075242/http://www.itv.com/thismorning/showbiz/corries-craig-charles/|archivedate=5 September 2012|df=dmy-all}}&lt;/ref&gt; Charles introduced aspects of the character himself, making Lloyd a [[Northern Soul]] DJ and record collector, and funk music enthusiast. Charles has chosen funk and soul songs playing as backing tracks during scenes,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Craig's a Soul Man at Heart, by Jade Wright, Liverpool Echo, 27 September 2013|url=http://www.liverpoolecho.co.uk/whats-on/film-tv/liverpool-man-craig-charles-soul-6101371}}&lt;/ref&gt; and posters for [[The Craig Charles Funk and Soul Show#The Craig Charles Funk &amp; Soul Club|The Craig Charles Funk &amp; Soul Club]] and Red Dwarf have appeared in the background.

Charles portrayed Lloyd as tough, but kind hearted and romantic, and the character was popular with viewers. Charles added a comedy element to the role, but was also involved in traumatic and emotional scenes with intricate storylines. In 2010, his character was involved in the show's dramatic 50th anniversary tram crash storyline, which was broadcast live. Charles presented documentaries for the show, including ''50 Years of Corrie Stunts'' (2010), which is included on the ''Tram Crash'' DVD. In November 2011, Charles took time off from ''Coronation Street'' to film a new series of ''Red Dwarf'', returning in April 2012.&lt;ref&gt;[http://futureradio.co.uk/audio/by/title/kate_roma_interviews_craig_charles "Kate Roma Interviews Craig Charles"] {{webarchive|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20140529090517/http://futureradio.co.uk/audio/by/title/kate_roma_interviews_craig_charles |date=29 May 2014 }}, Future Radio, Norwich, 27 April 2012&lt;/ref&gt; In February 2014 an online mini-series, ''Steve &amp; Lloyd's Streetcar Stories'', ran alongside the television show's storyline.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Steve &amp; Lloyd's Streetcar Stories written by Chris Fewtrell|url=http://www.itv.com/coronationstreet/streetcar-stories}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In May 2015, Craig announced he would be leaving ''Coronation Street'' for ''Red Dwarf.'' &lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.itv.com/news/2015-05-03/craig-charles-quits-coronation-street-to-head-back-in-space-with-red-dwarf/|title=Craig Charles quits Coronation Street to head back into space with Red Dwarf|work=ITV News}}&lt;/ref&gt; Lloyd left in a red Cadillac during the live episode on 23 September, although his final pre-recorded farewell scenes with Steve were shown during the following episode.

=== Other acting roles ===
Charles has acted in episodes of popular dramas such as ''[[The Bill]]'' (1995), ''[[EastEnders]]'' (2002) and ''[[Holby City]]'' (2003) and in the comedy ''[[The 10 Percenters]]'' (1996). Charles played the emotionally disturbed and violent prisoner, Eugene Buffy, in the highly successful [[Lynda La Plante]] drama series ''The Governor'' (1996); the title role in the Channel 4 pirate sitcom ''[[Captain Butler]]'' (1997); the warden of a women's prison in the Canadian sci-fi fantasy ''[[Lexx]]'' (2001);&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Lexx with Lister|url=http://www.oblongpictures.com/lexx/sfx77.htm}}&lt;/ref&gt; Detective Chief Inspector Mercer in seven episodes of the BBC soap opera ''[[Doctors (2000 TV series)|Doctors]]'' (2003); and soccer agent, Joel Brooks, in the [[Sky (UK and Ireland)|Sky]] TV football soap ''[[Dream Team (TV series)|Dream Team]]'' (2004).

=== Other presenting roles ===
Charles has presented children's television programmes, including ''What's That Noise?'' (1989) and ''[[Parallel 9]]'' (1992) on [[BBC One|BBC1]] and ''Go Getters'' (1994) on ITV. He was the travelling reporter for the highly acclaimed, but controversial, BBC '[[mockumentary]]' ''[[Ghostwatch]]'', which tricked viewers into believing it was a live investigation into ghost sightings in a suburban home on Halloween night (1992). Charles presented the [[virtual reality]] game show ''Cyberzone'' (1993) on [[BBC Two|BBC2]]; the late-night entertainment show ''Funky Bunker'' (1997) on ITV; the reality show ''[[Jailbreak (TV series)|Jailbreak]]'' (2000) on [[Channel 5 (UK)|Channel 5]]; the discussion show ''Amazing Space: The Pub Guide to the Universe'' (2001) on [[National Geographic Channel|National Geographic]]; and the late-night current affairs chat show ''Weapons of Mass Distraction'' (2004) on ITV.

=== Other appearances ===
Charles has appeared on celebrity editions of ''[[University Challenge]]'' (1998), ''[[Can't Cook, Won't Cook]]'' (1998), ''[[The Weakest Link]]'' (2004), ''[[The Chase (UK game show)|The Chase]]'' (2012) and ''[[Pointless]]'' (2013), and comedy panel shows such as ''[[Have I Got News for You]]'' (1995), ''[[Just a Minute]]'' (1995) and ''[[They Think It's All Over (TV series)|They Think It's All Over]]'' (1996) and [[Keith Lemon]]'s [[Through the Keyhole]] (2014). He was a team captain on the sci-fi quiz series ''[[Space Cadets (game show)|Space Cadets]]'' (1997) on [[Channel 4]], which guest starred [[William Shatner]]. Charles has opened the [[The National Lottery Draws|National Lottery draw]] (1997) and his home has featured on ''[[Through the Keyhole]]''. Charles was a contestant in the ''[[Celebrity Poker Club]]'' tournament (2004) on Challenge, where he reached the semi-finals, and in the Channel 4 reality game show, ''[[The Games (UK TV series)|The Games]]'' (2005), which documented the contestants' intensive training regime and each live [[Olympic Games]]-style sporting event.

From 16 November 2014, Charles took part in [[I'm a Celebrity...Get Me Out of Here! (UK series 14)|the fourteenth series]] of ''[[I'm a Celebrity...Get Me Out of Here! (UK TV series)|I'm a Celebrity...Get Me Out of Here!]]''.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url= http://www.digitalspy.co.uk/tv/s100/im-a-celebrity/news/a609383/im-a-celebrity-lineup-confirmed-michael-buerk-kendra-craig-charles.html |title=I'm a Celebrity lineup confirmed: Michael Buerk, Kendra, Craig Charles |first=Alex |last=Fletcher |work=Digital Spy |date=11 November 2014 |accessdate=21 November 2014}}&lt;/ref&gt; However, on 20 November, Charles left the series soon after learning of his brother Dean's death from a heart attack.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |first=Tina |last=Miles |url=http://www.liverpoolecho.co.uk/news/liverpool-news/im-celebrity-star-liverpools-craig-8138833 |title=I'm A Celebrity star Liverpool's Craig Charles rocked by brother's death |publisher=Liverpool Echo |date= 19 November 2014 |accessdate= 19 November 2014}}&lt;/ref&gt;

== Radio ==
As well as his early appearances on shows such as Radio 4's ''[[Loose Ends (radio)|Loose Ends]]'' (1987–88), and ''Kaleidoscope'', in the early 1990s, Charles could be heard on the London Radio Station [[Kiss 100]] (Kiss FM) as the Breakfast show presenter. In 1995, Charles played the Porter in [[Steven Berkoff]]'s adaptation of [[William Shakespeare|Shakespeare's]] ''[[Macbeth]]'', on Radio 4.

Since 2002, Charles has been a DJ on [[BBC Radio 6 Music]] presenting ''[[The Craig Charles Funk and Soul Show]]'', on air on Saturday evenings 6pm to 9pm, where he plays a diverse range of [[funk]] and [[soul (music)|soul]] music, from classic tracks to the latest releases, and provides publicity for less familiar bands. Charles explains the context for the music and carries out interviews with guest musicians. He was with the station at its launch, and while it was being tested during the previous year, under the name Network Y. Charles has also hosted the station's Breakfast Show (2004), and sits in for other presenters including [[Andrew Collins (broadcaster)|Andrew Collins]], Phil Wilding and [[Phill Jupitus]] and [[Radcliffe &amp; Maconie]].

From January until November 2014, Charles also broadcast the Funk and Soul Show live on [[BBC Radio 2]], immediately after his 6 Music show. He regularly sits in for [[Janice Long]], [[Steve Wright (DJ)|Steve Wright]] and [[Jo Whiley]], and has presented numerous programmes on the station, including ''The Craig Charles Soul All-Nighter'' (2011), which he hosted continuously for 12 hours,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|last=Tyler|first=Lee|title=Craig Charles: The funk, the whole funk and nothin' but the funk|url=http://www.bluesandsoul.com/feature/534/craig_charles_the_funk_the_whole_funk_and_nothin_but_the_funk/|newspaper=Blues And Soul magazine|date=15 May 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; and the ''Beatleland'' (2012) documentary on ''[[The Beatles]]''. Charles has also chosen music as a guest of other broadcasters such as [[Ken Bruce]] on Radio 2 and [[Liz Kershaw]] on 6 Music.  Charles covered for [[Graham Norton]] on Radio 2's Saturday mid-morning show during Norton's 10-week 2015 summer break.
From 16 April 2016, Charles presents the House Party on Saturday nights on [[BBC Radio 2]], with the show airing between 10pm and midnight.

== Music ==
Charles has been involved in the music industry through much of his career. His bands have included ''Watt 4'' (1980), in which he played keyboards and sang, ''Craig Charles and the Beat Burglars'' (1989), ''The Sons of Gordon Gekko'' (1989), where he wrote lyrics and also composed tunes and ''The Eye'' (2000–02), with whom he recorded the rock album "Giving You The Eye, Live at the Edinburgh Festival". Charles plays guitar and piano.

In 1987, Charles provided the poem track used for the opening credits of the BBC series ''The Marksman'' (in which he also acted), which is included on the album "The Marksman: Music from the BBC TV series". Charles wrote lyrics for Suzanne Rhatigan's album ''To Hell With Love'' (1992). In 1993, Charles was signed to the [[Acid Jazz Records|Acid Jazz]] record label.&lt;ref&gt;Interview with Charles by Terry Christian, ''The Word'', Channel 4, 1994&lt;/ref&gt;

In 2009, Charles formed the [[The Craig Charles Funk and Soul Show#The Fantasy Funk Band|Fantasy Funk Band]] from the leading British musicians in the genre, and has presented the band at festivals, including [[Glastonbury Festival|Glastonbury]] and the BBC's [[The Proms|Proms in the Park]]. As a continuation of his 6 Music show, Charles regularly takes the [[The Craig Charles Funk and Soul Show#The Craig Charles Funk &amp; Soul Club|Craig Charles Funk &amp; Soul Club]] to varied venues across the UK and abroad, and to the major UK music festivals. He performs live DJ sets, occasionally comperes and curates events, including his own Craig Charles Fantasy Weekender, and has broadcast the radio show live from festival locations.

In 2012, Charles released the compilation album ''The Craig Charles Funk &amp; Soul Club'', on CD and as a digital download, as part of a three-album deal&lt;ref&gt;''Metro'', 28 November 2012, Andrew Williams [http://www.metro.co.uk/tv/919157-craig-charles-i-only-thought-red-dwarf-would-last-two-series "Craig Charles"], London&lt;/ref&gt; with Freestyle Records.&lt;ref&gt;Freestyle Records, 26 November 2012 [http://www.freestylerecords.co.uk/index.php/the-craig-charles-funk-soul-club/ "ALBUM: The Craig Charles Funk &amp; Soul Club"]&lt;/ref&gt; The second volume was released in the same format in 2013, and the third in 2014. He followed these with a ''Craig Charles Funk and Soul Classics'' album of 3 CDs in 2015.

== Stand-up comedy and theatre ==
Charles returned to stand-up comedy between 1995&lt;ref&gt;''The Independent'', 20 September 1995, [http://www.highbeam.com/doc/1P2-4740730.html "Comedy: Craig Charles Speaks, Duke of York's Theatre, London"], London&lt;/ref&gt; and 2001, regularly touring his one-man adult-rated shows nationally and releasing the videos ''Craig Charles: Live on Earth!'' (1995), ''Live Official Bootleg'' (1996) and ''Sickbag'' (2000). International performances included the Great Norwegian Comedy Festival and the [[Melbourne International Comedy Festival]].

Charles appeared in the [[John Godber]] comedy play ''[[Teechers]]'', in which he swapped in and out of various roles, at the Arts Theatre, London, and at the [[Edinburgh Festival]] (1989), and he played Idle Jack in the [[pantomime]] ''Dick Whittington'', at the [[Hull New Theatre]] (1997).&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title= 'Hull In Print: The show must go on', Hull City Council, 2009|url=http://static.hullcc.gov.uk/hullinprint/archive/october2009/show_must_go_on.php}}&lt;/ref&gt; In 2000, he performed the show ''Craig Charles and His Band'' at the Edinburgh Festival.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Star Challenge: Hanging on the telephone with...Craig Charles, ''The Mirror'', 25 July 2000|url=http://www.thefreelibrary.com/Star+Challenge%3A+Hanging+on+the+telephone+with...+Craig+Charles.-a063660220}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Charles has a regular slot at Butlins Minehead House Of Fun Weekend every November for 3 nights, of DJ'ing, Comedy and singing.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.bigweekends.com/the-weekends/specialist-music-weekends/madness-house-of-fun-weekender.aspx#ito=FW_Madness&lt;/ref&gt;

== Film roles ==
Charles played Eddie in the 1987 political drama ''[[Business as Usual (film)|Business as Usual]]''. In 2006, Charles starred in two British feature films: the fantasy film ''Fated'' and the gangster film ''Clubbing to Death''. Charles voiced Zipper the Cat in the animation ''Prince Cinders'' (1993) and Asterix in ''[[Asterix Conquers America]]'' (1994). Roles in short films include playing Keith Dennis in the comedy ''The Colour of Funny'' (1999) and Mark in the drama ''Ten Minutes'' (2004).

== Writing ==
In 1993, Charles worked with Russell Bell on the ''Craig Charles Almanac of Total Knowledge'', writing about his 'streetwise' sense of humour on a range of topics, from the world's most embarrassing stories to how to explain the mysteries of the universe. In 1997, Charles and Bell wrote Charles' ''Red Dwarf'' character's book ''The Log'', in which Lister decides to leave a log detailing mankind's greatest achievements. In 1998, Charles published ''No Other Blue'', a collection of his poetry, with illustrations by Philippa Drakeford, on diverse personal subjects including prison, his mother's final illness, love and politics at home and abroad. More recently he has written a series of nursery rhymes titled "Scary Fairy and the Tales of the Dark Wood".

In 2000, Charles wrote his first autobiography about his experiences growing up in Liverpool, titled ''No Irish, No Niggers''. In 2007, he announced he would release his autobiography, planned for March 2008, published by [[Hodder Headline]] and titled ''On the Rocks'', which would cover the recent incidents in his life and be based on much of his journal, which Charles said he kept while in rehab.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news
|date=1 June 2007
|url=http://www.reddwarf.co.uk/index.cfm?frameset=deck01/deck_fs.html&amp;page=craigs_story.html
|title= Charles writing Autobiography
|publisher=Official Red Dwarf Website
|accessdate=1 June 2007
}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Charles has been involved in journalism and has had a column in ''[[Time Out (magazine)|Time Out]]'' magazine. In 1994, he launched a single issue of ''Comedy'' magazine with articles dedicated to the comedy circuit. In 2005 and 2006, Charles was a monthly columnist for the ''[[Liverpool Echo]]'' newspaper. His television writing credits include The Easter Stories (1994), Funky Bunker (1997) and Takeshi's Castle (2002).

== Personal life ==

=== Legal issues and acquittal ===
In July 1994, Charles and a friend were arrested and [[Remand (detention)|remanded]] in custody for three months on a rape charge.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|work=The Independent|date= 4 January 1997|first=James|last= Rampton |url=https://www.independent.co.uk/life-style/profile-craig-charles-the-inside-story-1281538.html |title=Profile: Craig Charles: The Inside Story|location=London}}&lt;/ref&gt; In March 1995, both men were acquitted in their trial. After being cleared, Charles spoke of the need to restore anonymity for those accused of rape. He stated that "the fact that my name and address along with my picture can appear on the front of the papers before the so-called 'victim' has even signed a statement proves that anonymity for rape defendants is a must and that the law must be changed."&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|work= News at Ten|date= 3 March 1995|title=Craig Charles cleared of rape}}&lt;/ref&gt; While in prison, Charles was attacked by a man wielding a makeshift knife.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|date=31 July 2003|url=http://news.bbc.co.uk/1/hi/uk_politics/3055859.stm|title= The trauma of being falsely accused|publisher=BBC News|accessdate=27 December 2006 | location=London}}&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Drug use ===
In June 2006, newspaper allegations of [[crack cocaine]] use resulted in Charles being suspended from both ''Coronation Street''&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|date=29 September 2006|url=http://news.bbc.co.uk/1/hi/entertainment/5391724.stm|title= Charles to make Street comeback|publisher=BBC News|accessdate=27 December 2006 | location=London}}&lt;/ref&gt; and BBC Radio 6 Music. In August, Charles was arrested and released on bail pending further enquiries, and in September he accepted a [[Police caution|caution]] for possession of a [[Misuse of Drugs Act 1971|Class A drug]].&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news|date=22 September 2006
|url=http://news.bbc.co.uk/1/hi/england/5370492.stm|title= Actor Charles given drugs caution|publisher=BBC News
|accessdate=27 December 2006 | location=London}}&lt;/ref&gt; Charles returned to hosting his 6 Music show from November 2006 and filming ''Coronation Street'' from January 2007.

==Credits ==
&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Craig Charles CV, United Agents|url=http://unitedagents.co.uk/craig-charles#profile-1}}, 2007&lt;/ref&gt;

===Filmography===
{| class="wikitable" style="width:100%;"
|-
! Year !! Title !! Role !! Notes
|-
|(early 1980s)
|''Riverside''
|Resident poet
|Arts review programme
|-
|(early 1980s)
|''[[Pebble Mill at One]]''
|Resident poet
|Daily magazine show. Performed in front of [[Princess Anne]]
|-
|1984
|''Lift Off''
|Himself—interviewee
|Documentary
|-
|1985
|''Black on Black''
|Resident poet
|Channel 4's first multicultural programme. Including the poem "Halt"
|-
|1985–1987
|''[[Saturday Live (UK TV series)|Saturday Live]]''
|Himself—stand up
|Live poetry stand-up comedy. Series 1: VHS (1986), DVD (2007). Series 2: VHS (1987), DVD (2008)
|-
|1986
|''Club Mix''
|Resident poet
|Entertainment-based successor to Black on Black
|-
|1986
|''Red Wedge''
|Himself
|Stand-up comedy tour
|-
|1986
|''[[Edinburgh Festival Fringe]]''
|Himself—poet
|August
|-
|1986–87
|''[[Wogan]]''
|Himself—poet
|Chat show. Co-hosted and performed weekly topical poem on current affairs
|-
|1987
|''[[Business as Usual (film)|Business as Usual]]''
|Eddie
|Drama feature film. VHS (1988)
|-
|1987
|''Craig Charles''
|Himself—stand up
|Poetry at Assembly Rooms, Edinburgh Festival Fringe, 7–29 August
|-
|1987
|''Video View''
|Himself—presenter
|TV series
|-
|1987
|''[[Night Network]]''
|Himself—presenter
|
|-
|1987
|''The Marksman''
|McFadden
|TV drama miniseries, wrote opening poem and played a murderer, aired December
|-
|1988
|''Open Air''
|Himself—interviewee
|Aired 23 February
|-
|1988
|''Craig Goes Mad in Melbourne''
|Himself—host
|Behind the scenes at the International Comedy Festival, 1–11 June
|-
|1988
|''TOR! Total Football''
|Himself—presenter
|Introducing highlights in official film of European Football Championships
|-
|1988–99, 2009, 2012, 2016-Present
|''[[Red Dwarf]]''
|[[Dave Lister]]
|Has appeared in all 73 episodes over 12 series
|-
|1989
|''Daytime Live''
|Himself—interviewee
|Aired 6 January
|-
|1989
|''[[Teechers]]''
|Multiple characters
|[[John Godber]] stage play
|-
|1989
|''Star Test: Craig Charles''
|Himself—interviewee
|Interviewed by a computer on chat show, aired 18 April
|-
|1989
|''Dogs of War''
|Voiceover
|3D computer video game. Voiced story speech and one character
|-
|1989
|''What's That Noise?''
|Himself—host
|Children's music show
|-
|1991
|''[[Comic Relief (charity)|Comic Relief]]''
|Dave Lister
|Short television film
|-
|1991
|''Them and Us''
|Himself—host
|Consumer rights series
|-
|1991
|''[[You Bet]]''
|Himself—contestant
|Celebrity game show
|-
|1992
|''The Last Cigarette''
|Himself
|Encouraging giving up smoking, aired 8 March
|-
|1992
|''Open to Question''
|Himself—interviewee
|Audience questions from young people on topical issues, 23 March
|-
|1992
|''[[Parallel 9]]''
|Himself
|Children's magazine show. Including episode 1.13, aired 18 July
|-
|1992
|''Weather Watch''
|Himself—presenter
|Educational TV series investigating different aspect of the weather
|-
|1992
|''Wogan''
|Himself
|Chat show, 23 October
|-
|1992
|''[[Ghostwatch]]''
|Himself—reporter
|Drama, aired 31 October (Halloween). DVD (2002)
|-
|1993
|''[[That's Showbusiness]]''
|Himself—contestant
|Quiz show, BBC1, aired 2 February
|-
|1993
|''Cyberzone''
|Himself—host
|All 10 episodes of the world's first virtual reality game show
|-
|1993
|''Cyberpunks and Technophobes''
|Himself
|TV series
|-
|1993
|''[[A Word in Your Ear]]
|Himself—contestant
|Game show, BBC1
|-
|1993
|''Super Mario All Stars''
|Himself—presenter
|Nintendo video game on VHS
|-
|1993
|''Dinosaurs: The Myths &amp; The Reality''
|Himself—narrator
|Animated documentary. VHS (1993), DVD (2006)
|-
|1993
|''Prince Cinders''
|Zipper the Cat
|Voice of character in animated film of [[Babette Cole]]'s book. VHS (1993), DVD (2007)
|-
|1993
|''[[Telly Addicts]]''
|Himself—contestant
|Aired 13 September and 29 December
|-
|1993
|''[[Pebble Mill]]''
|Himself—interviewee
|Performed song, 29 October
|-
| 1993
|''Funny Stories''
|Himself—voice
|Audiobook anthology of stories for children
|-
|1993
|''[[The Big Breakfast]]''
|Himself—guest presenter
|Magazine show
|-
|1994
|''Go Getters''
|Himself—host
|Children's programme
|-
|1994
|''The Easter Stories''
|Judas Iscariot
|Drama series. Episode: "Judas' Tale"
|-
|1994
|''[[Batchelors]] Mushy Peas''
|Himself—voiceover
|TV Commercial
|-
|1994
|''[[Asterix Conquers America]]''
|[[Asterix]] (voice)
|Animated feature film, English language version
|-
|1994
|''[[The Word (TV series)|The Word]]''
|Himself—interviewee
|Late night magazine show
|-
|1994
|''Red Dwarf: Smeg Ups''
|Dave Lister
|Video release (archive footage)
|-
|1994
|''[[Big Break]] in Wonderland''
|Himself—contestant
|Charity Christmas special of snooker competition, aired 27 December
|-
|1995
|''Red Dwarf: Smeg Outs''
|Dave Lister
|Video release (new and archive footage)
|-
|1995
|''[[Breakfast with Frost]]''
|Himself—guest
|Chat show with Sir [[David Frost]], 5 March
|-
|1995
|''May the 4 Be with You''
|Himself—presenter
|"Starburst Vol. 2" VHS (1996)
|-
|1995
|''Craig Charles: Live on Earth!''
|Himself—stand up
|VHS video release of live stand-up comedy stage show. Also co-producer
|-
|1995
|''[[Just a Minute]]''
|Himself—contestant
|TV version of radio panel game, 21 July
|-
|1995
|''Beam Me Up Scotty!''
|Himself—presenter
|Aired 26 August
|-
|1995
|''[[The Bill]]''
|Martin Bailey
|Episode: "Honey Pot", 31 October
|-
|1995
|''[[Have I Got News for You]]''
|Himself—contestant
|Guest panelist on satire quiz show. Series 10, episode 7, 8 December
|-
|1996
|''Craig Charles Live Official Bootleg''
|Himself
|VHS video documentary of stand-up show
|-
|1996
|''[[They Think It's All Over (TV series)|They Think It's All Over]]''
|Himself—contestant
|Series 2, episode 3, aired 26 March
|-
|1996
|''The Governor''
|Eugene Buffy
|Drama from [[Lynda La Plante]]. All 6 episodes of series 2. DVD (2012)
|-
|1996
|''Cyberspace''
|Himself—narrator
|TV series
|-
|1996
|''[[The 10 Percenters]]''
|Bobby Titan
|Episode: "Revenge" playing a rap singer
|-
|1997
|''[[The Big Breakfast]]''
|Himself—guest
|Aired 6 January
|-
|1997
|''Night Fever''
|Himself—contestant
|Pop music quiz including singing
|-
|1997
|''[[Captain Butler]]''
|Captain Butler
|All 6 episodes
|-
|1997
|''Bully: Ha Bloody Ha''
|Himself—interviewee
|Educational show discussing celebrities' memories of school bullies, aired 28 August
|-
|1997
|''[[Pulling Power]]''
|Himself—guest
|Motoring show, aired 24 September
|-
|1997
|''[[Space Cadets (game show)|Space Cadets]]''
|Team captain
|Comedy sci-fi quiz, all 10 episodes
|-
|1997
|''Funky Bunker''
|Himself—host
|Late night chat show. 13 episodes. Also co-writer
|-
|1997
|''[[The National Lottery Draws|The National Lottery Live]]''
|Himself—presenter
|Opened the draw, 5 November
|-
|1997
|''English Express Language Skills''
|Himself—presenter
|Schools education series
|-
|1997–98
|''Dick Whittington and His Wonderful Cat''
|Idle Jack
|Pantomime stage play
|-
|1998
|''Can't Smeg, Won't Smeg''
|Dave Lister—contestant
|Special edition of ''[[Can't Cook, Won't Cook]]'', aired 14 February
|-
|1998
|''Universe Challenge''
|Himself—contestant
|Special ''Red Dwarf'' edition of ''[[University Challenge]]'', aired 14 February
|-
|1998
|''[[Children in Need]]''
|Dave Lister
|''Red Dwarf'' short episode
|-
|1998
|''The Selfish Crocodile''
|Narrator
|Audiobook edition of children's book
|-
|1998
|''[[Fully Booked]]''
|Himself—interviewee
|Magazine show
|-
|1998–2004
|''[[Robot Wars (TV series)|Robot Wars]]''
|Himself—host
|Series 2–7 (after replacing [[Jeremy Clarkson]])
|-
|1999–2000
|''[[Ripley's Believe It or Not!]]''
|Himself—host
|UK presenter
|-
|1999
|''The Colour of Funny''
|Keith Dennis
|Short comedy film
|-
|2000
|''Craig Charles: Sickbag''
|Himself
|VHS video release of live stand-up comedy show
|-
|2000
|''Craig Charles and His Band''
|Himself
|Edinburgh Festival, August. Recording album ''Giving You The Eye''
|-
|2000
|''[[Jailbreak (TV series)|Jailbreak]]''
|Himself—host
|Reality challenge show
|-
|2001
|''Top Ten TV Sci-Fi''
|Himself—interviewee
|Documentary
|-
|2001
|''Porridge Selection Box''
|Himself
|Worldwide VHS video release. Introduced clips
|-
|2001
|''[[Lexx]]''
|The Warden
|Canadian sci-fi series. Episode: "P4X" [[Hattie Hayridge]] from ''Red Dwarf'' as his wife. Series 4, Vol. 1 DVD (2001)
|-
|2001
|''Don't Walk''
|Narrator (voice)
|Short film
|-
|2001
|''Amazing Space: The Pub Guide to the Universe''
|Himself—host
|Discussion series with guest experts on space related topics
|-
|2002
|''EastEnders: Ricky and Bianca''
|Vince
|''[[EastEnders]]'' spin-off drama, aired 20 May
|-
|2002
|''[[The Saturday Show (BBC TV series)|The Saturday Show]]''
|Himself—interviewee
|Magazine show, 1 June
|-
|2002–04
|''[[Takeshi's Castle#United Kingdom|Takeshi's Castle]]''
|Himself—commentator
|UK voiceover of Japanese comedy challenge show. Also co-writer
|-
|2003
|''The Sitcom Story''
|Himself
|TV documentary
|-
|2003
|''[[Sushi TV]]''
|Himself—narrator
|UK version of Japanese TV clip show (after replacing [[Julian Clary]])
|-
|2003
|''[[Doctors (2000 TV series)|Doctors]]''
|DCI Mercer
|7 episodes of soap opera
|-
|2003
|''Monstrous Bosses''
|Himself—presenter
|Links between clips in a battle between two comedy characters, 10–11 May
|-
|2003
|''Lovable Rogues''
|Himself—presenter
|Links between clips, aired 3 August
|-
|2003
|''[[Holby City]]''
|Adrian Summers
|Episode: "Full Circle", aired 16 December
|-
|2004
|''Ten Minutes''
|Mark
|Short comedy film, launched at the BAFTA and Cannes Film Festival in 2003. Film release July 2004
|-
|2004
|''[[Britain's Best Sitcom]]''
|Himself
|TV documentary
|-
|2004
|''Weapons of Mass Distraction''
|Himself—presenter
|Satirical comedy chat show exploring tabloid newspaper world
|-
|2004
|''Celebrities Disfigured''
|Himself (disguised)
|Documentary exploring attitudes to disfigurement, aired 17 April
|-
|2004
|''[[The Weakest Link]]''
|Himself—contestant
|Charity edition of quiz show. "Stars of the '90s". Reached 3rd place, aired 4 August
|-
|2004
|''Comedy Connections''
|Himself—interviewee
|Documentary episode on Red Dwarf, aired 30 August
|-
|2004
|''Public Opinion''
|Himself—interviewee
|Panel show, opinions on celebrities from members of the public, aired 21 September
|-
|2004
|''[[Celebrity Poker Club]]''
|Himself—contestant
|Challenge, series 3, reached semi-finals
|-
|2004
|''[[Dream Team (TV series)|Dream Team]]''
|Joel Brooks
|Soccer agent in Sky TV football drama
|-
|2005
|''Forty Years of Fuck''
|Himself—interviewee
|BBC documentary examining swearing on TV
|-
|2005
|''[[The Games (UK TV series)|The Games]]''
|Himself—contestant
|Reality game show for charity, based on the Olympic Games. Series 3.
|-
|2005
|''Athletes in Training''
|Himself—contestant
|Live feed, following ''The Games'' contestants through their intensive training regime
|-
|2005–15
|''[[Coronation Street]]''
|[[Lloyd Mullaney]]
|Principal cast in soap opera, first appearance 20 June 2005
|-
|2006
|''Fated''
|Pedro
|Feature film. DVD (2011)
|-
|2006
|''Clubbing to Death''
|Carl Begsley
|Feature film. Not yet released (in post production)
|-
|2008–present
|''[[The Craig Charles Funk and Soul Show#The Craig Charles Funk &amp; Soul Club|The Craig Charles Funk &amp; Soul Club]]''
|Himself—DJ
|Live DJ performances throughout the UK, and occasionally abroad
|-
|2009
|''[[Carpool (web series)|Carpool]]''
|Himself—interviewee
|Video-podcast interview by [[Robert Llewellyn]] of ''Red Dwarf''
|-
|2010
|''[[UK Festival Awards]]''
|Himself
|Hosted award ceremony at [[The O2|The IndigO2]], London, 18 November
|-
|2010
|''[[Robert Llewellyn]]'s [[Carpool (TV series)|Carpool]]''
|Himself—interviewee
|Chat show. Episode 1.5: aired 2 December
|-
|2010
|''50 Years of Corrie Stunts''
|Himself—voiceover
|[[Coronation Street]] documentary, aired 6 December. On Tram Crash DVD (2010)
|-
|2011
|''Zombie Carnage''
|Frank
|Promotional trailer for feature film
|-
|2011
|''Cast Mates''
|Himself
|Coronation Street online Q&amp;A, 31 August
|-
|2011
|''[[This Morning (TV programme)|This Morning]]''
|Himself—Interviewee
|Daytime entertainment show, 6 September
|-
|2012
|''[[BBC Breakfast]]''
|Himself—interviewee
|News programme, 10 March
|-
|2012
|''[[Loose Women]]''
|Himself—interviewee
|Chat show, 15 March
|-
|2012
|''Motorbike Diaries: Mad in the Med''
|Himself—narrator
|Travel documentary series from [[Danny John-Jules]] of ''Red Dwarf''
|-
|2012
|''[[Evidently... John Cooper Clarke]]''
|Himself—interviewee
|Documentary on the poet [[John Cooper Clarke]]'s life and career, aired 30 May
|-
|2012
|''[[This Morning (TV programme)|This Morning]]''
|Himself—interviewee
|Chat show, 6 July
|-
|2012
|''[[Loose Women]]''
| Himself—interviewee
|Chat show, 25 September
|-
|2012
|''[[The Alan Titchmarsh Show]]''
| Himself—interviewee
|Chat show, 28 September
|-
|2012
|''We're Smegged''
|Himself—interviewee
|Documentary on the making of Red Dwarf X. On series X DVD, released 19 November
|-
|2012
|''[[This Morning (TV programme)|This Morning]]''
|Himself—interviewee
|Chat show, 19 November
|-
|2012
|''The Craig Charles Funk &amp; Soul Club''
|Music compiler
|Compilation album, released on Freestyle Records as CD and digital download, 26 November
|-
|2012
|''[[The Chase (UK game show)|The Chase]]''
|Himself—contestant
|Celebrity edition of quiz show for 'Text Santa' charity appeal, ITV1, 21 December
|-
|2013
|''[[Glastonbury Festival]]''
|Himself—presenter
|Introduced acts (also interviewed musicians and performed DJ set), BBC Four, 28–30 June
|-
|2013
|''[[The Proms|Proms in the Park]]''
|Himself
|Presented the Fantasy Funk Band at the BBC Proms, Hyde Park, London, 7 September
|-
|2013
|''[[Pointless Celebrities]]''
|Himself—contestant
|Charity edition of quiz show, with [[Danny John-Jules]] from [[Red Dwarf]], BBC1, aired 17 August
|-
|2013
|''Craig Charles Fantasy Weekender''
|Himself
|Funk and soul music festival, Bristol, 24–26 August
|-
|2013
|''[[This Morning (TV programme)|This Morning]]''
|Himself
|'Take a Moment' appeal, ITV1, 25 September
|-
|2013
|''[[Surprise, Surprise (TV series)|Surprise, Surprise]]''
|Himself
|With [[Simon Gregson]] and [[Sue Cleaver]] of [[Coronation Street]], ITV1, 27 October
|-
|2013
|''The Craig Charles Funk &amp; Soul Club 2''
|Music compiler
|Compilation album, Freestyle records, released 25 November
|-
|2014
|''Steve &amp; Lloyd's Streetcar Stories''
|[[Lloyd Mullaney]]
|[[Coronation Street]] mini-series, online, 3–12 February
|-
|2014
|''[[BBC Radio 6 Music]] Festival''
|Himself
|Introduced acts, presented radio, DJ set, poetry performance at Festival Fringe, 1 March 
|-
|2014
|''[[Lorraine (TV programme)|Lorraine]]''
|Himself—interviewee
|Chat show, ITV1, 28 April
|-
|2014
|''[[I'm a Celebrity...Get Me Out of Here! (UK TV series)|I'm a Celebrity... Get Me Out of Here]]''
|Himself—contestant
|Game show, withdrew on day 4 due to personal reasons 
|-
|2014
|''[[Keith Lemon]]'s [[Through the Keyhole]]''
|Himself—panellist
|ITV1 game show
|-
|2014
|''The Craig Charles Funk &amp; Soul Club 3''
|Music compiler
|Compilation album, Freestyle records, released 24 November
|-
|2015
|''Craig Charles Funk and Soul Club Classics''
|Music compiler
|Compilation album box set, [[Sony Music Entertainment|Sony Music]], released 18 September
|-
|2015
|''Witches, Wizards and Scary Fairies''
|Himself—narrator
|Live performance of ''Scary Fairy'' poetry with the [[BBC Philharmonic]] Orchestra, 29 September
|-
|2015
|''[[BBC Breakfast]]''
|Himself—interviewee
|BBC One news programme, 17 September
|-
|2015
|''[[The One Show]]''
|Himself—interviewee
|BBC One chat show, 30 September
|-
|2016
|''Celebrity Home Secrets''
|Himself
|Series 1, Episode 2, 5 September
|-
|2017–present 
| [[The Gadget Show]]
| Co-host alongside [[Jon Bentley (TV presenter)|Jon Bentley]], [[Ortis Deley]] and Georgie Barrat
| Series regular 
|}

=== Radio ===
{| class="wikitable"
! scope="col" width="80"  | Year
! scope="col" width="300" | Programme
! scope="col" width="200" | Role
! scope="col" width="300" | Notes
|-
|1983
|''John Peel Show''
|Himself—guest
|Recorded 6 poems during "Peel Session", aired 17 March
|-
|1984
|''John Peel'' Show
|Himself—guest
|Radio. Recorded 3 song, aired 14 February
|-
|1987–1989
|''[[Loose Ends (radio)|Loose Ends]]''
|Himself—panelist
|Regular guest on [[Ned Sherrin]]'s chat show
|-
|1989
|''The Steve Jones Show''
|Himself—interviewee
|16 March
|-
|1992–93
|''The Craig Charles Breakfast Show''
|Himself—host
|Radio show
|-
|1995
|''Macbeth''
|The Porter
|[[Steven Berkoff]]'s [[Macbeth]], aired 28 December
|-
|2002–present
|''[[The Craig Charles Funk and Soul Show|The Craig Charles Funk &amp; Soul Show]]''
|Himself—host
|First broadcast 15 March 2002
|-
|2004
|''Craig Charles Breakfast Show''
|Himself—host
|
|-
|2005
|''One Nation Under a Groove''
|Himself—presenter
|Radio 2 documentary. The Story of George Clinton &amp; P-Funk, aired 12 February
|-
|2011
|''The Craig Charles Soul All-nighter''
|Himself—host
|27–28 August
|-
|2012
|''[[The Craig Charles Funk and Soul Show#The Fantasy Funk Band|Fantasy Funk Band]] at Maida Vale''
|Himself—presenter
|Review for BBC Radio 6 Music's 10th anniversary
|-
|2012
|''Beatleland''
|Himself—presenter
|Documentary on [[the Beatles]] in Liverpool, aired 10 October
|-
|2013
|''Didn't It Rain: When the Blues came to Britain''
|Himself—narrator
|Music history documentary, BBC Radio 2, aired 24 October
|-
|2015
|''Sarah and Dan's Extra Edition''
|Himself—interviewee
|BBC Radio 5 Live, 24 September
|-
|2015
|''Witches, Wizards and Scary Fairies''
|Narrator
|"Scary Fairy" poetry performance with the [[BBC Philharmonic]] orchestra, BBC Radio 2, airs 30 October 2015
|}

== Bibliography ==

===Published===
* 1993, ''Craig Charles Almanac of Total Knowledge'', (with Russell Bell), [[Penguin Books]]
* 1997, ''The Log: A Dwarfer's Guide to Everything'', (with Russell Bell), Penguin Books
* 1998, ''No Other Blue'', (illustrations by Philippa Drakeford), Penguin Books

===Unpublished===
* 2000, ''No Irish, No Niggers'', Penguin Books 
* 2008, ''On the Rocks'', [[Hodder Headline]]&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Charles, speaking to Simon Fitzpatrick and Ema Lea, PlanetSmeg, 2010|url=http://www.planetsmeg.com/cgi-bin/pagegen.pl?listerinterview}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==References==
{{Reflist|30em}}

== External links ==
* {{IMDb name|id=0153002|name=Craig Charles}}
* {{bbc programme|b0072ky7|The Craig Charles Funk and Soul Show}} (BBC Radio 6 Music)
* {{bbc programme|b076bt50|The Craig Charles House Party}} (BBC Radio 2)
* {{worldcat id|lccn-no96-42308}}
* [http://ftvdb.bfi.org.uk/sift/individual/295158?view=credit Craig Charles] BFI site

{{Use dmy dates|date=February 2012}}

{{Authority control}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Charles, Craig}}
[[Category:1964 births]]
[[Category:English people of Guyanese descent]]
[[Category:English people of Irish descent]]
[[Category:English radio DJs]]
[[Category:English radio personalities]]
[[Category:English male comedians]]
[[Category:English male poets]]
[[Category:English male radio actors]]
[[Category:English male soap opera actors]]
[[Category:English male television actors]]
[[Category:English television presenters]]
[[Category:English writers]]
[[Category:Male actors from Liverpool]]
[[Category:Comedians from Liverpool]]
[[Category:BBC Radio 2 presenters]]
[[Category:Black English male actors]]
[[Category:Robot Wars presenters]]
[[Category:People acquitted of rape]]
[[Category:Living people]]
[[Category:20th-century British comedians]]
[[Category:21st-century British comedians]]
[[Category:British male comedy actors]]</text>
      <sha1>fjig3rvl7ftwx7km7ahlmyz94dgz445</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
