<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10.xsd" version="0.10" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <dbname>enwiki</dbname>
    <base>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.32.0-wmf.16</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="118" case="first-letter">Draft</namespace>
      <namespace key="119" case="first-letter">Draft talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2300" case="first-letter">Gadget</namespace>
      <namespace key="2301" case="first-letter">Gadget talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2302" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition</namespace>
      <namespace key="2303" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Dudley Moore</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>46208</id>
    <revision>
      <id>854052031</id>
      <parentid>846304852</parentid>
      <timestamp>2018-08-08T16:46:10Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Odysseus.i52</username>
        <id>34231814</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>/* Personal life */</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="33660">{{Infobox person
 | name             = Dudley Moore
 | honorific_suffix     = [[Order of the British Empire|CBE]]
 | image            = Dudley Moore.jpg
 | caption          = Moore at the [[43rd Primetime Emmy Awards|43rd Emmy Awards]], 25 August 1991
 | birth_date       = {{Birth date|1935|4|19|df=y}}
 | birth_place      = [[Charing Cross]], [[London]], England
 | death_date       = {{Death date and age|2002|3|27|1935|4|19|df=y}}
 | death_place      = [[Plainfield, New Jersey]], US
 | spouse           = {{marriage|[[Suzy Kendall]] |1968|1972|end=divorced}} &lt;br&gt;{{marriage|[[Tuesday Weld]]|1975|1980|end=divorced}} &lt;br&gt;{{marriage|Brogan Lane|1988|1991|end=divorced}} &lt;br&gt;{{marriage|Nicole Rothschild|1994|1998|end=divorced}}
 | alma_mater       = [[Magdalen College, Oxford]]
 | occupation       = Actor, comedian, musician
 | years_active     = 1961–1998
 | children         = 2&lt;ref&gt;[https://www.telegraph.co.uk/culture/3634457/Dad-was-messed-up-but-I-forgive-him.html]&lt;/ref&gt;
}}

'''Dudley Stuart John Moore''', [[Order of the British Empire|CBE]] (19 April 1935{{spaced ndash}}27 March 2002) was an English actor, comedian, musician and composer.

Moore first came to prominence in the UK as one of the four writer-performers in the comedy revue ''[[Beyond the Fringe]]'' from 1960, and with one member of that team, [[Peter Cook]], collaborated on the television series ''[[Not Only... But Also]]''. The [[double act]] worked on other projects until the mid-1970s, by which time Moore had settled in Los Angeles to concentrate on his film acting.

His solo career as a comedy film actor was heightened by the success of hit Hollywood films, particularly ''[[Foul Play (1978 film)|Foul Play]]'' (1978), ''[[10 (film)|10]]'' (1979) and ''[[Arthur (1981 film)|Arthur]]'' (1981). For ''Arthur'', Moore was nominated for the [[Academy Award for Best Actor]] and won a [[Golden Globe Award]]. He received a second Golden Globe for his performance in ''[[Micki &amp; Maude]]'' (1984).

==Early life==
Moore was born at the original [[Charing Cross Hospital]] in [[central London]], the son of Ada Francis (née Hughes), a secretary, and John Moore, a railway electrician. His father was Scottish, from [[Glasgow]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=https://www.telegraph.co.uk/news/obituaries/1389041/Dudley-Moore.html |title=Obituaries: Dudley Moore |publisher=Telegraph Media Group Limited – Telegraph.Co.UK |date=22 March 2002 |accessdate=23 April 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt; 
Moore was brought up in [[Dagenham]], [[Essex]]. He was notably short at {{convert|5|ft|2|in|m|abbr=on}} and was born with [[club feet]] that required extensive hospital treatment and, coupled with his diminutive stature, made him the butt of jokes from other children. His right foot responded well to corrective treatment and had straightened itself by the time he was six, but his left foot became permanently twisted and consequently his left leg below the knee was withered. This was something of which he remained very self-conscious throughout his life.

Moore became a [[choirboy]] at the age of six. At age eleven he earned a scholarship to the [[Guildhall School of Music and Drama|Guildhall School of Music]], where he took up harpsichord, organ, violin, musical theory and composition.&lt;ref name=official&gt;{{cite web |url=http://dudleymoore.com/about/bio.htm |title=The Official Site of Dudley Moore: Biography |publisher=The Estate of Dudley Moore - DudleyMoore.com |accessdate=24 April 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt; He rapidly developed into a highly talented pianist and organist and was playing the pipe organ at local church weddings by the age of 14. He attended [[The Sydney Russell School|Dagenham County High School]] where he received musical tuition from a dedicated teacher, Peter Cork, who became a friend and confidant to Moore and continued to correspond with him until 1994.

Moore's musical talent won him an [[organ scholar]]ship to [[Magdalen College, Oxford]], where he was tutored by the composer [[Bernard Rose (musician)|Bernard Rose]].&lt;ref name=official/&gt;&lt;ref name="rose"&gt;{{cite news | title=Bernard Rose (Obituary) | url=https://www.independent.co.uk/news/people/obituary-bernard-rose-1312755.html | work=The Independent | date=3 December 1996 | accessdate=28 May 2014|archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20170822093958/http://www.independent.co.uk/news/people/obituary-bernard-rose-1312755.html |archivedate=22 August 2017|deadurl=no}}&lt;/ref&gt; While studying music and composition there, he also performed with [[Alan Bennett]] in the [[The Oxford Revue|Oxford Revue]]. During his university years, Moore had developed a love of [[jazz]] music and soon became an accomplished jazz pianist and composer. He began working with such leading musicians as [[John Dankworth]] and [[Cleo Laine]].

In 1960 he left Dankworth's band to work on ''Beyond the Fringe''.

==Career==

===''Beyond the Fringe''===
[[File:Beyond the Fringe original cast.JPG|thumb|Moore (left) in ''Beyond the Fringe'', c1963]]
[[Johnny Bassett|John Bassett]], a graduate of Wadham College, Oxford recommended Moore, his jazz bandmate and a rising cabaret talent, to producer Robert Ponsonby, who was putting together a comedy revue entitled ''[[Beyond the Fringe]]''. Bassett also chose [[Jonathan Miller]]. Moore then recommended Alan Bennett, who in turn suggested Peter Cook.

''Beyond the Fringe'' was at the forefront of the 1960s UK [[satire boom]], although the show's original runs in Edinburgh and the provinces in 1960 had had a lukewarm response. When the revue transferred to the [[Fortune Theatre]] in London, in a revised production by [[Donald Albery]] and [[William Donaldson]], it became a sensation, thanks in some part to a favourable review by [[Kenneth Tynan]].&lt;ref&gt;Humphrey Carpenter ''That Was Satire That Was'', pp. 122–23; Tynan's review is extensively quoted.&lt;/ref&gt; There were also a number of musical items in the show, using Dudley Moore's music, most famously an arrangement of the [[Colonel Bogey March]] which resists Moore's repeated attempts to bring it to an end.

In 1962 the show transferred to the [[John Golden Theatre]] in New York, with its original cast. President [[John F. Kennedy]] attended a performance on 10 February 1963. The show continued in New York until 1964.

===Partnership with Peter Cook===
When Moore returned to the UK he was offered his own series on the [[BBC]], ''[[Not Only... But Also]]'' (1965, 1966, 1970). It was commissioned specifically as a vehicle for Moore, but when he invited [[Peter Cook]] on as a guest, their [[double act|comedy partnership]] was so notable that it became a permanent fixture of the series. Cook and Moore are most remembered for their sketches as two working class men, [[Pete and Dud]], in macs and cloth caps, commenting on politics and the arts, but they also fashioned a series of one-off characters, usually with Moore in the role of interviewer to one of Cook's upper class eccentrics.

The pair developed an unorthodox method for scripting the material, using a tape recorder to tape an ad-libbed routine that they would then have transcribed and edited. This would not leave enough time to fully rehearse the script, so they often had a set of cue cards. Moore was famous for '[[corpsing]]' — the programmes often went on live, and Cook would deliberately make him laugh in order to get an even bigger reaction from the studio audience. The BBC [[wiped]] much of the series, though some of the soundtracks (which were issued on record) have survived.

In 1968 Cook and Moore briefly switched to [[Associated TeleVision|ATV]] for four one-hour programmes entitled ''[[Goodbye Again (TV)|Goodbye Again]]'', however, they were not as critically well-received as the BBC shows.

On film, Moore and Cook appeared in the 1966 British comedy film ''[[The Wrong Box]]'', before co-writing and co-starring in ''[[Bedazzled (1967 film)|Bedazzled]]'' (1967)&lt;ref name=la&gt;{{cite web |url=http://projects.latimes.com/hollywood/star-walk/dudley-moore/ |title=Hollywood Star Walk: Dudley Moore |work=Patrick Kevin Day, Los Angeles Times - Projects.LATimes.com |date=23 February 2010 |accessdate=23 April 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt; with [[Eleanor Bron]]. The film was directed by [[Stanley Donen]]. The pair closed the decade with appearances in the ensemble caper film ''[[Monte Carlo or Bust]]'' and [[Richard Lester]]'s ''[[The Bed Sitting Room (film)|The Bed Sitting Room]]'', based on the play by [[Spike Milligan]] and [[John Antrobus]].

In 1968 and 1969 Moore embarked on two solo comedy ventures, firstly in the film ''30 Is a Dangerous Age, Cynthia'' and secondly, on stage, for an Anglicised adaptation of [[Woody Allen]]'s ''Play It Again, Sam'' at the [[Gielgud Theatre|Globe Theatre]] in London's [[West End of London|West End]].

[[File:Peter Cook Dudley Moore Good Evening 1974.JPG|thumb|left|Moore (right) with [[Peter Cook]] in 1974]]
In the 1970s the relationship between Moore and Cook became increasingly strained as the latter's alcoholism began affecting his work. However, in 1971, Cook and Moore took sketches from ''Not Only....But Also'' and ''Goodbye Again'', together with new material, to create the stage revue ''Behind the Fridge''. This show toured Australia in 1972 before transferring to New York City in 1973, re-titled as ''Good Evening''. Cook frequently appeared on and off stage the worse for drink. Nonetheless, the show proved very popular and it won [[Tony Award|Tony]] and [[Grammy Award]]s.

When the Broadway run of ''Good Evening'' ended, Moore stayed on in the U.S. to pursue his film acting ambitions in Hollywood, but the pair reunited to host ''[[Saturday Night Live]]'' on 24 January 1976 during the SNL first season. They performed a number of their classic stage routines, including "[[One Leg Too Few]]" and "Frog and Peach", among others, in addition to participating in some skits with the show's ensemble.

It was during the Broadway run of ''Good Evening'' that Cook persuaded Moore to take the humour of Pete and Dud farther on [[gramophone record|long-playing records]] as [[Derek and Clive]]. [[Chris Blackwell]] circulated [[Bootleg recording|bootleg]] copies to friends in the music business and the popularity of the recording convinced Cook to release it commercially as ''[[Derek and Clive (Live)]]'' (1976). Two further "Derek and Clive" albums, ''[[Derek and Clive Come Again]]'' (1977) and ''[[Derek and Clive Ad Nauseam]]'' (1978), were later released. The latter was also filmed for a documentary, ''[[Derek and Clive Get the Horn]]''. In the film it is clear tensions between the two men were at a breaking point, with Moore at one point walking out of the recording room singing, 'Breaking up is so easy to do.' In 2009, it came to light that, at the time, three separate British police forces had wanted them to be prosecuted under obscenity laws for their "Derek and Clive" comedy recordings.

The last significant appearance for the partnership was in 1978's ''[[The Hound of the Baskervilles (1978 film)|The Hound of the Baskervilles]]'', where Moore played [[Dr. Watson]] to Cook's [[Sherlock Holmes]], as well as three other roles: in drag; as a one-legged man; and at the start and end of the film as a flamboyant and mischievous pianist. He also wrote the film's score. Co-star [[Terry-Thomas]] described it as "the most outrageous film I ever appeared in&amp;nbsp;... there was no magic&amp;nbsp;... it was bad!".&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last1=Thomas |first1=Terry|last2=Daum|first2=Terry|title=Terry-Thomas Tells Tales: An Autobiography |date=1990|publisher=Robson Books|isbn=9780860516620|page=117|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=fjQeAAAAMAAJ|accessdate=1 March 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt; The film was not a success critically or financially.

Moore and Cook eventually reunited for the annual American benefit for the homeless, ''[[Comic Relief USA|Comic Relief]]'', in 1987, and again in 1989 for a British audience at the [[Amnesty International]] benefit ''[[The Secret Policeman's Biggest Ball]]''.

Moore was deeply affected by the death of Cook in 1995, and for weeks would regularly telephone Cook's home in London, just to hear his friend's voice on the telephone answering machine. Moore attended Cook's memorial service in London and, at the time, many people who knew him noted that Moore was behaving strangely and attributed it to grief or drinking. In November 1995, Moore teamed up with friend and humorist [[Martin Lewis (humorist)|Martin Lewis]] in organising a two-day salute to Cook in Los Angeles that Moore co-hosted with Lewis.

In December 2004 the [[Channel 4]] television station in the United Kingdom broadcast ''[[Not Only But Always]]'', a TV film dramatising the relationship between Moore and Cook, although the principal focus of the production was on Cook. Around the same time the relationship between the two was also the subject of a stage play called ''[[Pete and Dud: Come Again]]'' by Chris Bartlett and [[Nick Awde]]. For this production Moore is the main subject. Set in a chat-show studio in the 1980s, it focuses on Moore's comic and personal relationship with Cook and the directions their careers took after the split of the partnership.

===Music===
During the 1960s he formed the Dudley Moore Trio, with drummer [[Chris Karan]] and bassist Pete McGurk. Following McGurk's suicide in June 1968, Peter Morgan joined the group as his replacement.&lt;ref&gt;Chilton. John., 2004, ''Who's Who of British Jazz'', London: Continuum, p.240 {{ISBN|9780826472342}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Moore's admitted principal musical influences were [[Oscar Peterson]] and [[Erroll Garner]]. In an interview he recalled the day he finally mastered Garner's unique left-hand strum and was so excited that he walked around for several days with his left hand constantly playing that cadence. His early recordings included "[[My Blue Heaven (song)|My Blue Heaven]]", "Lysie Does It", "Poova Nova", "Take Your Time", "[[(Back Home Again in) Indiana|Indiana]]", "Sooz Blooz", "[[Baubles, Bangles &amp; Beads]]", "Sad One for George" and "[[Autumn Leaves (1945 song)|Autumn Leaves]]". The trio performed regularly on British television, made numerous recordings and had a long-running residency at Peter Cook's London nightclub, the [[The Establishment (club)|Establishment]]. Amongst other albums, they recorded ''[[The Dudley Moore Trio]]'', ''Dudley Moore plays The Theme from Beyond the Fringe and All That Jazz'', ''The World of Dudley Moore'', ''The Other Side Of Dudley Moore'' and ''Genuine Dud''.

Moore was a close friend of record producer [[Christopher Gunning|Chris Gunning]] and played piano (uncredited) on the 1969 single "Broken Hearted Pirates" which Gunning produced for [[Simon Dupree and the Big Sound]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.bbc.co.uk/mediacentre/proginfo/2013/24/r2-sounds-of-the-60s.html |title=Sounds Of The 60s |publisher=bbc.co.uk |date=8 June 2013 |accessdate=23 April 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt; In 1976 he played piano on [[Larry Norman]]'s album ''[[In Another Land (album)|In Another Land]]'', in particular on the song ''The Sun Began to Rain''. In 1981 he recorded ''Smilin' Through'' with Cleo Laine.

He composed the soundtracks for the films ''[[Bedazzled (1967 film)|Bedazzled]]'' (1967), ''30 Is a Dangerous Age, Cynthia'' (1968), ''[[Inadmissible Evidence (film)|Inadmissible Evidence]]'' (1968), ''[[Staircase (film)|Staircase]]'' (1969), ''[[The Hound of the Baskervilles (1978 film)|The Hound of the Baskervilles]]'' (1978) and ''[[Six Weeks]]'' (1982), among others.

===Later career in film, television and music===
In the late 1970s Moore moved to [[Hollywood, California|Hollywood]], where he had a supporting role in the hit film ''[[Foul Play (1978 film)|Foul Play]]'' (1978) with [[Goldie Hawn]] and [[Chevy Chase]]. The following year saw his breakout role in [[Blake Edwards]]'s ''[[10 (film)|10]]'', which became one of the [[1979 in film|biggest box-office hits of 1979]] and gave him an unprecedented status as a romantic leading man. Moore followed up with the comedy film ''[[Wholly Moses]]!'', which was not a major success.

In 1981 Moore appeared in the title role of the comedy ''[[Arthur (1981 film)|Arthur]]'', an even bigger hit than ''10''. Co-starring [[Liza Minnelli]] and Sir [[John Gielgud]], it was both commercially and critically successful, Moore receiving an [[Academy Award|Oscar]] nomination for Best Actor, whilst Gielgud won the Best Supporting Actor Oscar for his role as Arthur's stern but compassionate manservant. Moore lost to [[Henry Fonda]] (for ''[[On Golden Pond (1981 film)|On Golden Pond]]''). He did, however, win a Golden Globe award for Best Actor in a Musical/Comedy. In the same year, on British television, Moore was the featured guest subject on ''[[An Audience With...]]''.

His subsequent films, ''[[Six Weeks]]'' (1982), ''[[Lovesick (1983 film)|Lovesick]]'' (1983), ''[[Romantic Comedy (1983 film)|Romantic Comedy]]'' (1983) and ''[[Unfaithfully Yours (1984 film)|Unfaithfully Yours]]'' (1984) were only moderate successes, but he had another hit in 1984, starring in the [[Blake Edwards]] directed ''[[Micki &amp; Maude|Micki + Maude]]'', co-starring [[Amy Irving]]. This won him another Golden Globe for Best Actor in a Musical/Comedy.

Later films, including ''[[Best Defense]]'' (1984), ''[[Santa Claus: The Movie]]'' (1985), ''[[Like Father Like Son (1987 film)|Like Father Like Son]]'' (1987), ''[[Arthur 2: On the Rocks]]'', a sequel to the original, ''[[Crazy People]]'' (1990), ''[[Blame It on the Bellboy]]'' (1992) and an [[The Mighty Kong|animated adaptation of ''King Kong'']], were inconsistent in terms of both critical and commercial reception. Moore eventually disowned the ''Arthur'' sequel, but, in later years, Cook would wind him up by claiming he preferred ''Arthur 2: On the Rocks'' to ''Arthur''.

In 1986 he once again hosted ''Saturday Night Live'', albeit without Peter Cook this time.

Moore was the subject of the British ''[[This Is Your Life (UK TV series)|This Is Your Life]]''—for a second time—in March 1987 when he was surprised by [[Eamonn Andrews]] at his Venice Beach restaurant; he had previously been honoured by the programme in December 1972.

In addition to acting, Moore continued to work as a composer and pianist, writing scores for a number of films and giving piano concerts, which were highlighted by his popular parodies of classical favourites. He also appeared as Ko-Ko in Jonathan Miller's production of ''[[The Mikado]]'' in [[Los Angeles]] in March 1988.

In the 1990s Moore starred as a man named David trying to catch chickens in a series of popular [[Tesco]] adverts. He stated, in a later interview, that he was paid "£20,000 for each advert".{{citation needed|date=August 2015}} In 1991 he released the album ''Songs Without Words'' and in 1992 ''Live From an Aircraft Hangar'', recorded at London's [[Royal Albert Hall]].

He collaborated with the conductor [[Georg Solti|Sir Georg Solti]] in 1991 to create a Channel 4 television series, ''Orchestra!'', which was designed to introduce audiences to the symphony orchestra. He later worked with the American conductor [[Michael Tilson Thomas]] on a similar television series, ''Concerto!'' (1993), likewise designed to introduce audiences to classical music concertos.

Moore appeared in two series for [[CBS]], ''[[Dudley (TV series)|Dudley]]'' (1993) and ''[[Daddy's Girls (1994 TV series)|Daddy's Girls]]'' (1994), however both were cancelled before the end of their run.

Moore had been interviewed for ''[[The New York Times]]'' in 1987 by the music critic Rena Fruchter, herself an accomplished pianist, and the two became close friends. By 1995 Moore's film career was on the wane and he was having trouble remembering his lines, a problem he had never previously encountered. It was for this reason he was sacked from [[Barbra Streisand]]'s film ''[[The Mirror Has Two Faces]]''.&lt;ref name="Deat"&gt;{{cite news |title=Tributes flood in for Moore |url=http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/entertainment/1898076.stm |publisher=BBC News |accessdate=25 August 2011|date=28 March 2002}}&lt;/ref&gt; However, his difficulties were, in fact, due to the onset of the medical condition that eventually led to his death. Opting to concentrate on the piano, he enlisted Fruchter as an artistic partner. They performed as a duo in the US and [[Australia]]. However, his disease soon started to make itself apparent there as well, as his fingers would not always do what he wanted them to do. Further symptoms such as slurred speech and loss of balance were misinterpreted by the public and the media as a sign of drunkenness. Moore himself was at a loss to explain this. He moved into Fruchter's family home in [[New Jersey]] and stayed there for five years, but this, however, placed a great strain both on her marriage and her friendship with Moore, and she later set him up in the house next door.

===Entrepreneur===
Moore co-owned, with producer [[Tony Bill]], a fashionable restaurant in [[Venice, Los Angeles|Venice]], California (1980s–2000), named [[72 Market Street Oyster Bar and Grill]]. He played the piano whenever he was there.{{citation needed|date=May 2017}}

==Personal life==
Moore was married and divorced four times: to actresses [[Suzy Kendall]] (15 June 1968 - 15 September 1972), [[Tuesday Weld]] (20 September 1975 - 18 July 1980; by whom he had a son in 1976), Brogan Lane (21 February 1988 - 1991), and Nicole Rothschild (16 April 1994 - 1998; one son, born in 1995).&lt;ref name=wives-times&gt;{{cite news |url=https://www.independent.co.uk/life-style/the-wives-and-times-of-cuddly-dudley-1337512.html |title=The wives and times of cuddly Dudley |author=Daniel Jeffreys |work=The Independent |date=17 June 1996 |accessdate=23 April 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt;

He maintained good relationships with Kendall, Weld and Lane, but expressly forbade Rothschild to attend his funeral. At the time his illness became apparent, he was going through a difficult divorce from Rothschild while at the same time sharing a house in Los Angeles with her and her previous husband.&lt;ref name=wives-times/&gt;

Moore dated [[Susan Anton]] in the early 1980s, with a lot of talk being made of their height difference: Moore at {{convert|5|ft|2+1/2|in|m}} and Anton at {{convert|5|ft|11|in|m}}.

==Illness and death==
In April 1997, after spending five days in a New York hospital, Moore was informed that he had calcium deposits in the [[basal ganglia]] of his brain and irreversible frontal lobe damage. In September 1997 Moore underwent quadruple [[heart bypass]] surgery in London. He also suffered four strokes.&lt;ref name=disease&gt;{{Cite news |url=http://news.bbc.co.uk/1/hi/uk/461376.stm | title=Dudley Moore has rare brain disease |work=BBC News |date=30 September 1999 |accessdate=29 March 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In June 1998 Nicole Rothschild was reported to have told an American television show that Moore was "waiting to die" due to a serious illness, but these reports were denied by [[Suzy Kendall]].&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news |url=http://news.bbc.co.uk/1/hi/entertainment/109902.stm |title=Health fears for Dudley Moore |work=BBC News |date=9 June 1998 |accessdate=29 March 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;

On 30 September 1999, Moore announced that he was suffering from the terminal degenerative brain disorder [[progressive supranuclear palsy]] (PSP), some of the early symptoms being so similar to intoxication that he had been reported as being drunk, and that the illness had been diagnosed earlier in the year.&lt;ref name=disease/&gt;

Dudley Moore died on the morning of 27 March 2002,&lt;ref name=la/&gt; as a result of [[pneumonia]], secondary to immobility caused by the palsy, in [[Plainfield, New Jersey]] at age 66. Rena Fruchter was holding his hand when he died, and she reported his final words were, "I can hear the music all around me".&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=https://books.google.com/books?id=6H8vBgAAQBAJ&amp;pg=PT248 |title=There's Been A Life! |publisher=|accessdate=24 April 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://lists.monstersandcritics.com/popculture/people/famous-last-words/ |title=Famous last words |work=Julian James, Monster lists - Lists.MonstersAndCritics.com |accessdate=24 April 2016 |deadurl=yes |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20160612111046/http://lists.monstersandcritics.com/popculture/people/famous-last-words/ |archivedate=12 June 2016 |df=dmy-all }}&lt;/ref&gt; Moore was interred at [[Hillside Cemetery (Scotch Plains, New Jersey)|Hillside Cemetery]] in [[Scotch Plains, New Jersey]]. Fruchter later wrote a memoir of their relationship (''Dudley Moore'', [[Ebury Press]], 2004).

==Honours and awards==
In 1981 Moore won the Golden Globe for Best Actor for his role in Arthur, for which he was also Oscar-nominated. In November 2001, Moore was appointed a [[Order of the British Empire|Commander of the Order of The British Empire]] (CBE). Despite his deteriorating condition, he attended the ceremony at [[Buckingham Palace]] on 16 November to collect his honour in a wheelchair.&lt;ref name="Deat" /&gt;

==Filmography and television shows==
{{Div col|colwidth=30em}}
* ''[[The Third Alibi]]'' (1961) – Piano accompanist (uncredited)
* ''Flatland'' (1965) (short) – A Square (voice) 
* ''[[The Wrong Box]]'' (1966) – John Finsbury
* ''[[Bedazzled (1967 film)|Bedazzled]]'' (1967) – Stanley Moon
* ''[[30 Is a Dangerous Age, Cynthia]]'' (1968) – Rupert Street
* ''[[Monte Carlo or Bust!]]'' (1969) (aka ''Those Daring Young Men in Their Jaunty Jalopies'') – Lt. Barrington
* ''[[The Bed Sitting Room (film)|The Bed Sitting Room]]'' (1969) – Police Sergeant
* ''[[Alice's Adventures in Wonderland (1972 film)|Alice's Adventures in Wonderland]]'' (1972) – Dormouse
* ''Saturday Night at the Baths'' (1975) – Himself – in theater audience (uncredited)
* ''[[Foul Play (1978 film)|Foul Play]]'' (1978) – Stanley Tibbets
* ''[[The Hound of the Baskervilles (1978 film)|The Hound of the Baskervilles]]'' (1978) – Doctor Watson / Mrs. Ada Holmes / Mr. Spiggot / Piano Player
* ''[[Derek and Clive Get the Horn]]'' (1979) – Derek
* ''[[10 (film)|10]]'' (1979) – George Webber
* ''[[The Muppet Show]]'' (1979) (TV) – Himself – Special Guest Star
* ''[[Horizon (BBC TV series)|BBC Horizon]]: "It's About Time" '' (1979)
* ''[[Wholly Moses!]]'' (1980) – Harvey Orchid / Herschel
* ''[[Arthur (1981 film)|Arthur]]'' (1981) – Arthur Bach
* ''[[Six Weeks]]'' (1982) – Patrick Dalton
* ''[[Lovesick (1983 film)|Lovesick]]'' (1983) – Saul Benjamin
* ''[[Romantic Comedy (1983 film)|Romantic Comedy]]'' (1983) – Jason Carmichael
* ''[[Unfaithfully Yours (1984 film)|Unfaithfully Yours]]'' (1984) – Claude Eastman
* ''[[Best Defense]]'' (1984) – Wylie Cooper
* ''[[Micki &amp; Maude|Micki + Maude]]'' (1984) – Rob Salinger
* ''[[Santa Claus: The Movie]]'' (1985) – Patch
* ''[[The Adventures of Milo and Otis]]'' (1986) – Narrator (English version, voice)
* ''[[Like Father Like Son (1987 film)|Like Father Like Son]]'' (1987) – Dr. Jack Hammond / Chris Hammond
* ''[[Arthur 2: On the Rocks]]'' (1988) – Arthur Bach
* ''[[Crazy People]]'' (1990) – Emory Leeson
* ''Orchestra!'' (1991) (TV)
* ''[[Blame It on the Bellboy]]'' (1992) – Melvyn Orton
* ''[[Really Wild Animals]]'' (1993–1998) – Spin
* ''[[Dudley (TV series)|Dudley]]'' (1993) – Dudley Bristol
* ''Concerto!'' (1993) (TV)
* ''[[The Pickle]]'' (1993) – Planet Cleveland Man (uncredited)
* ''[[Daddy's Girls (1994 TV series)|Daddy's Girls]]'' (1994) (TV) – Dudley Walker
* ''[[Parallel Lives (film)|Parallel Lives]]'' (1994) – Imaginary Friend / President Andrews
* ''[[Oscar's Orchestra]]'' (1994) – Oscar
* ''[[The Disappearance of Kevin Johnson]]'' (1995) – Dudley Moore
* ''A Weekend in the Country'' (1996) – Simon Farrell
* ''[[The Mighty Kong]]'' (1998) – Carl Denham / King Kong (voice) (final film role)
{{div col end}}

==Discography==

===UK chart singles===
* "Goodbye-ee", 1965, Peter Cook and Dudley Moore
* "The Ballad of Spotty Muldoon", 1965, Peter Cook and Dudley Moore&lt;ref name="British Hit Singles &amp; Albums"&gt;{{cite book
| first= David
| last= Roberts
| year= 2006
| title= [[British Hit Singles &amp; Albums]]
| edition= 19th
| publisher= Guinness World Records Limited 
| location= London
| isbn= 1-904994-10-5
| page= 119}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Jazz discography===
* ''Strictly For The Birds b/w Duddly Dell'', 1961 ([[Parlophone]] R 4772) - The Dudley Moore Trio (Derek Hogg, drums; Hugo Boyd, double bass)
* ''From Beyond The Fringe'', 1966 ([[Atlantic Records]]Standard 2 017)
* ''[[The Dudley Moore Trio]]'', 1969 ([[Decca Records]] (UK) / [[London Records]] (US) PS558)
* ''Dudley Moore plays The Theme from Beyond the Fringe and All That Jazz'', 1962 (Atlantic 1403)
* ''The World of Dudley Moore'', (Decca SPA 106)
* ''The Other Side Of Dudley Moore'', (Decca LK 4732)
* ''Genuine Dud'', (Decca LK 4788)
* ''The Music of Dudley Moore'', ([[EMI Records|EMI Australia]] ([[Cube Records]]) TOOFA.14-1/2)
* ''Dudley Down Under'', (Cube ICS 13)
* ''Dudley Moore at the Wavendon Festival'', ([[Black Lion Records]] BLP 12151)
* ''Smilin' Through'' – [[Cleo Laine]] and Dudley Moore, (Finesse Records FW 38091)
* ''Strictly For The Birds'' – Cleo Laine and Dudley Moore, ([[CBS]] A 2947)
* ''The Theme From "Beyond The Fringe" and All That Jazz'', (Collectibles COL 6625)
* ''Live From an Aircraft Hangar'' (Martine Avenue Productions MAPI 8486)
* ''Songs Without Words'', 1991 (GRP/BMG LC 6713)
* ''The First Orchestrations'' – Dudley Moore and [[Richard Rodney Bennett]], – played by [[Johnny Bassett|John Bassett and his Band]], (Harkit Records HRKCD 8054)
* ''Jazz Jubilee'', (Martine Avenue Productions MAPI 1521)
* ''The Dudley Moore Trio'' at Sydney Town Hall, 2 May 1978 (with Peter Morgan, Bass &amp; Chris Karan, Drums) Produced by Peter Wall.
* ''Today, The Dudley Moore Trio -'' again with Morgan and Karan {see above} recorded at United Sound, Sydney in 1971, with some mono tracks added from a London 1961 session. No details.

===Comedy discography===

* ''Beyond The Fringe'' (West End recording) (1961)
* ''Beyond The Fringe'' (Broadway recording) (1962)
* ''Not Only Peter Cook But Also Dudley Moore'' (1965)
* ''Once Moore With Cook'' (1966)
* ''Goodbye Again'' (1968)
* ''Not Only But Also'' (1971)
* ''Behind The Fridge'' (1971)
* ''The World Of Pete &amp; Dud'' (1974)
* ''Good Evening'' (1974)
* ''[[Derek and Clive (Live)]]'' (1976)
* ''[[Derek and Clive Come Again]]'' (1977)
* ''[[Derek and Clive Ad Nauseam]]'' (1978)

==Bibliography==
* Dudley Moore (1966). ''Originals. Arranged as Piano Solos Transcribed from the Decca L.P. 'The Other Side of Dudley Moore'''. Essex Music.

==References==
{{Reflist}}

==Further reading==
* Roger Wilmut, ''From Fringe to Flying Circus: Celebrating a Unique Generation of Comedy 1960–1980'', Eyre Methuen Ltd, 1980
* {{Cite book| author=Alexander Games| title=Pete &amp; Dud: An Illustrated Biography| publisher=Andre Deutsch| year=1999 | isbn= 0-233-99642-7}}
* {{Cite book| author=Peter Cook and Dudley Moore| title=Dud and Pete The Dagenham Dialogues| publisher=Methuen| year=2003| isbn=978-0-413-77347-0}}
* {{Cite book| author=Chris Bartlett and Nick Awde | title=Pete and Dud: Come Again | publisher=Methuen Drama | year=2006 | isbn=0-413-77602-6 }}
* ''Dudley Moore'', Rena Fruchter, Ebury Press, 2004.
* ''Fallen Stars'', Julian Upton, Headpress, 2004.
* {{cite book | author=William Cook | title=One Leg Too Few: The Adventures of Peter Cook and Dudley Moore | publisher=Arrow | year=2014 | isbn=978-0099559924 }}

==External links==
{{Wikiquote}}
{{Portal|Biography}}
* [https://www.youtube.com/user/MADWORLD1427#p/c/140D8E98AFA33FCF/9/CXEZv14dJKA "The Films of Dudley Moore"], film clip compilation, 5 minutes
* {{IMDb name|1545}}
* {{TV Guide|148187}}
* [http://www.tv.com/people/dudley-moore/ Dudley Moore] on [http://www.tv.com/ TV.com]
* [https://web.archive.org/web/20060512103906/http://archives.cnn.com/2002/SHOWBIZ/Movies/03/27/death.dudley/ Obituary at CNN.com]
* [http://www.bbc.co.uk/radio/aod/radio4_aod.shtml?radio4/affectionately_dudley "Affectionately Dudley"], 2006 Radio 4 programme

{{Navboxes
| title = Awards for Dudley Moore
| list =
{{GoldenGlobeBestActorMotionPictureMusicalComedy 1981–2000}}
{{Grammy Award for Best Spoken Word Album 1970s}}
}}

{{Use British English|date=September 2010}}
{{Use dmy dates|date=April 2016}}

{{Authority control}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Moore, Dudley}}
[[Category:Dudley Moore| ]]
[[Category:1935 births]]
[[Category:2002 deaths]]
[[Category:Alumni of Magdalen College, Oxford]]
[[Category:Best Musical or Comedy Actor Golden Globe (film) winners]]
[[Category:Burials in New Jersey]]
[[Category:English jazz pianists]]
[[Category:Commanders of the Order of the British Empire]]
[[Category:Deaths from pneumonia]]
[[Category:Deaths from progressive supranuclear palsy]]
[[Category:English classical organists]]
[[Category:English expatriates in the United States]]
[[Category:English male film actors]]
[[Category:English male comedians]]
[[Category:English satirists]]
[[Category:English male television actors]]
[[Category:Grammy Award winners]]
[[Category:People from Dagenham]]
[[Category:People from Hammersmith]]
[[Category:English people of Scottish descent]]
[[Category:20th-century English male actors]]
[[Category:21st-century English male actors]]
[[Category:Burials at Hillside Cemetery (Scotch Plains, New Jersey)]]
[[Category:Infectious disease deaths in New Jersey]]
[[Category:Disease-related deaths in New Jersey]]
[[Category:Stroke survivors]]
[[Category:20th-century classical musicians]]
[[Category:20th-century pianists]]
[[Category:20th-century English musicians]]
[[Category:20th-century British comedians]]
[[Category:British male comedy actors]]</text>
      <sha1>cgba5yj1m9pv51nfw850cn9qm7teu1z</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
