<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10.xsd" version="0.10" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <dbname>enwiki</dbname>
    <base>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.32.0-wmf.16</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="118" case="first-letter">Draft</namespace>
      <namespace key="119" case="first-letter">Draft talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2300" case="first-letter">Gadget</namespace>
      <namespace key="2301" case="first-letter">Gadget talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2302" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition</namespace>
      <namespace key="2303" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Edgar Bergen</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>140875</id>
    <revision>
      <id>855564065</id>
      <parentid>854712333</parentid>
      <timestamp>2018-08-19T07:22:22Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <ip>2603:9000:B380:3C00:4854:55BA:3FA0:6D2D</ip>
      </contributor>
      <comment>/* Audio */</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="25012">{{Redirect|Charlie McCarthy}}
{{Refimprove|date=November 2008}}

{{Infobox person
| name         = Edgar Bergen
| image        = EdgarBergenandCharlieMcCarthyStageDoorCanteen1.jpg
| caption      = Bergen with his ventriloquist dummy Charlie McCarthy in ''[[Stage Door Canteen (film)|Stage Door Canteen]]'' (1943)
| birth_name   = Edgar John Berggren
| birth_date   = {{Birth date|1903|02|16|mf=y}}
| birth_place  = [[Chicago|Chicago, Illinois]], U.S.
| death_date   = {{Death date and age|1978|09|30|1903|02|16|mf=y}}
| death_place  = [[Paradise, Nevada]], U.S.
| resting_place= [[Inglewood Park Cemetery]]
| occupation   = Actor, comedian, [[ventriloquist]]
| years_active = 1922–1978
| spouse       = {{marriage|[[Frances Bergen|Frances Westerman]]|1945|September 30, 1978|end=died}}
| children     = 2, including [[Candice Bergen]]
}}  
'''Edgar John Bergen''' (born '''Edgar John Berggren''', February 16, 1903&amp;nbsp;– September 30, 1978) was an American actor, comedian and radio performer, best known for his proficiency in [[ventriloquism]] and his characters '''Charlie McCarthy''' and '''Mortimer Snerd'''. He was also the father of actress [[Candice Bergen]].

==Early life==
[[File:Edgar Bergen and Charlie McCarthy 1926.jpg|thumb|Bergen and Charlie when they were vaudeville performers in 1926]]
Bergen was born in [[Chicago]], [[Illinois]], one of five children and the youngest of two sons of [[Sweden|Swedish]] immigrants Nilla Svensdotter (née Osberg) and Johan Henriksson Berggren.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|author=Tammy Luce |url=http://home.comcast.net/~buff.flyer2/mccarthy/Bergen_bio_new.html |title=Bergan Bio |publisher=Home.comcast.net |date=1978-09-21 |access-date=2013-12-13 |deadurl=yes |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20131018024043/http://home.comcast.net/~buff.flyer2/mccarthy/Bergen_bio_new.html |archivedate=2013-10-18 |df= }}&lt;/ref&gt; He lived on a farm near [[Decatur, Michigan]] until he was 4 when his family returned to Sweden where he learned the language. He taught himself ventriloquism from a pamphlet called "The Wizard's Manual" when he was 11 after his family returned to Chicago.  He attended [[Lake View High School (Chicago, Illinois)|Lake View High School]]. After his father died when he was just 16, he went out to work as an apprentice accountant, a furnace stoke, a player piano operator, and a projectionist in a silent-movie house. The famous ventriloquist Harry Lester was so impressed by Edgar that he gave the teenager almost daily lessons for three months in the fundamentals of ventriloquism. In the fall of 1919, Edgar paid Chicago woodcarver Theodore Mack $36 to sculpt a likeness of a rascally red-headed [[Ireland|Irish]] newspaperboy he knew. The head went on a [[Ventriloquism|dummy]] named Charlie McCarthy, which became Bergen's lifelong [[sidekick]]. He had created the body himself, using a nine-inch length of broomstick for the backbone, and rubber bands and cords to control the lower jaw mechanism of the mouth.

For college he attended [[Northwestern University]] where he was enrolled in the pre-med program to please his mother. He switched to Speech &amp; Drama but never completed his degree.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://exhibits.library.northwestern.edu/archives/exhibits/alumni/bergen.html |title=Edgar Bergen: Alumni Exhibit: Northwestern University Archives |publisher=Exhibits.library.northwestern.edu |date= |access-date=2013-12-13}}&lt;/ref&gt; He gave his first public performance at Waveland Avenue Congregational Church located on the northeast corner of Waveland and Janssen. He lived across the street from the church. In 1965, he gave the church a generous contribution, a thoughtful letter, and a photograph of himself which had been requested by the minister and was displayed in the church's assembly room which was dedicated to Bergen. He cut out an "R" and a "G" from his family name and went from Berggren to Bergen on the showbills. Between June 1922 and August 1925, he performed every summer on the professional Chautauqua circuit and at the Lyceum theater in Chicago. Bergen had an interest in aviation, becoming a private pilot.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|magazine=AOPA Pilot|date=May 2014|page=79|title=A Plane-Crazy America}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==''The Chase and Sanborn Hour''==
{{unreferenced section|date=September 2016}}
[[File:Chase and Sanborn Hour.jpg|thumb|Edgar Bergen and his dummy Charlie McCarthy with W.C. Fields on The Chase and Sanborn Hour]]
His first performances were in [[vaudeville]], at which point he legally changed his last name to the easier-to-pronounce "Bergen". He worked in one-reel [[short subject|movie shorts]], but his real success was on the radio. He and Charlie were seen at a New York party by [[Elsa Maxwell]] for [[Noël Coward]], who recommended them for an engagement at the famous [[Rainbow Room]]. It was there that two producers saw Bergen and Charlie perform. They then recommended them for a guest appearance on [[Rudy Vallée]]'s program.

Their initial appearance (December 17, 1936) was so successful that the following year they were given regular cast rolls as part of ''[[The Chase and Sanborn Hour]]''. Under various sponsors (and two different networks), they were on the air from May 9, 1937 to July 1, 1956. The popularity of a ventriloquist on radio, when one could see neither the dummies nor his skill, surprised and puzzled many critics, then and now. Even knowing that Bergen provided the voice, listeners perceived Charlie as a genuine person, but only through artwork rather than photos could the character be seen as truly lifelike. Thus, in 1947, Sam Berman caricatured Bergen and McCarthy for the network's glossy promotional book, ''NBC Parade of Stars: As Heard Over Your Favorite NBC Station''.

Bergen's skill as an entertainer, especially his characterization of Charlie, carried the show (many of which have survived).{{citation needed|date=November 2010}} Bergen's success on radio was paralleled in the [[United Kingdom]] by [[Peter Brough]] and his dummy [[Archie Andrews (puppet)|Archie Andrews]] (''[[Educating Archie]]'').

For the radio program, Bergen developed other characters, notably the slow-witted Mortimer Snerd and the man-hungry Effie Klinker. The star remained Charlie, who was always presented as a highly precocious child (albeit in [[top hat]], cape, and [[monocle]])—a debonair, girl-crazy, child-about-town. As a child, and a wooden one at that, Charlie could get away with [[double entendres]] which were otherwise impossible under broadcast standards of the time.

:'''Charlie:''' "May I have a kiss good-bye?"
:'''[[Dale Evans]]:''' "Well, I can't see any harm in that!"
:'''Charlie:''' "Oh. I wish you could. A harmless kiss doesn't sound very thrilling."

Charlie and [[Mae West]] had this conversation on December 12, 1937.
:'''Charlie:''' "Not so loud, Mae, not so loud! All my girlfriends are listening."
:'''Mae:''' "Oh, yeah! You’re all wood and a yard long."
:'''Charlie:''' "Yeah."
:'''Mae:''' "You weren’t so nervous and backward when you came up to see me at my apartment. In fact, you didn’t need any encouragement to kiss me."
:'''Charlie:''' "Did I do that?"
:'''Mae:''' "Why, you certainly did. I got marks to prove it. An' splinters, too."

Charlie's feud with [[W. C. Fields]] was a regular feature of the show.
:'''W. C. Fields:''' "Well, if it isn't Charlie McCarthy, the woodpecker's pinup boy!"

:'''Charlie:''' "Well, if it isn't W.C. Fields, the man who keeps Seagram's in business!"

:'''W. C. Fields:''' "I love children. I can remember when, with my own little unsteady legs, I toddled from room to room."
:'''Charlie:''' "When was that? Last night?"

:'''W. C. Fields:''' "Quiet, Wormwood, or I'll whittle you into a venetian blind."
:'''Charlie:''' "Ooh, that makes me shutter!"

:'''W. C. Fields:''' "Tell me, Charles, is it true that your father was a [[Gateleg table|gate-leg table]]?"
:'''Charlie: '''"If it is, your father was under it."

:'''W. C. Fields:''' "Why, you stunted spruce, I'll throw a Japanese beetle on you."
:'''Charlie:''' "Why, you bar-fly you, I'll stick a wick in your mouth, and use you for an alcohol lamp!"

:'''Charlie:''' "Pink elephants take aspirin to get rid of W. C. Fields."

:'''W.C. Fields:''' "Step out of the sun Charles. You may come unglued."
:'''Charlie:''' "Mind if I stand in the shade of your nose?"
[[File:Edgar Bergen Charlie McCarthy 1947.JPG|thumb|150px|Bergen and Charlie with an NBC-produced comic book ''On the Air'', 1947.]]
Bergen was not the most technically skilled ventriloquist—Charlie McCarthy frequently twitted him for moving his lips—but Bergen's sense of comedic timing was superb, and he handled Charlie's snappy dialog with aplomb. Bergen's wit in creating McCarthy's striking personality and that of his other characters was the making of the show. Bergen's popularity as a ventriloquist on radio, where the trick of "throwing his voice" was not visible, suggests his appeal was primarily the personality he applied to his characters.

Bergen and McCarthy are sometimes credited with "saving the world" because, on the night of October 30, 1938, when [[Orson Welles]] performed his ''[[The War of the Worlds (radio)|War of the Worlds]]'' radio play that panicked many listeners, most of the American public had instead tuned to Bergen and McCarthy on another station and never heard Welles' play. Conversely, it has also been theorized that Bergen inadvertently contributed to the hysteria. When the musical portion of Bergen's show, ''The Chase and Sanborn Hour'', aired approximately 12 minutes into the show, many listeners adjusted their dial and found the ''War of the Worlds'' presentation already underway with a realistic-sounding reporter detailing terrible events.

[[Ray Noble (musician)|Ray Noble]] was the musical director and composer, and teenage singer Anita Gordon provided the songs on his show. Gordon was said to have been discovered by Charlie, who had a crush on her.

In the fall (autumn) of 1948, Edgar and Charlie faced serious competition from [[ABC Radio Network|ABC's]] "jackpot" quiz show, ''[[Stop the Music (American TV series)|Stop the Music]]'', which suddenly drew more listeners ([[Fred Allen]] faced a similar problem because he directly appeared before them). In December 1948, Edgar announced he was temporarily "retiring" from radio, admitting that ''Stop the Music'' was too popular to compete with. His final NBC broadcast was on December 26, 1948.

==''The Charlie McCarthy Show''==
{{unreferenced section|date=September 2016}}
In October 1949, Bergen went to [[CBS Radio Network|CBS]], with a new weekly program, ''The Charlie McCarthy Show'', sponsored by [[Coca-Cola]]. After their sponsorship ended in June 1952, [[Richard Hudnut]], on behalf of "Lanolin Plus" cosmetics, primarily sustained the series until the end of the 1953–54 season. In October 1954, [[Kraft Foods]] sponsored a new ''Edgar Bergen Hour''. After Kraft's departure, the series continued with participating sponsors as a 55-minute series in the fall of 1955. However, because more people were watching television on Sunday nights than listened to radio (and advertisers preferred to sponsor TV shows by then), the series finally ended on July 1, 1956.

==Comic strip==
In addition to his work as a ventriloquist, Bergen was also an actor and comic strip creator. He established the syndicated comic strip ''Mortimer &amp; Charlie'', which ran in newspapers from July 1939 to May 1940, illustrated first by [[Ben Batsford]] and then by [[Carl Buettner]]. The comic strip's writer was uncredited, but some of the gags certainly were lifted from the hit radio show.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://strippersguide.blogspot.com/2008/03/obscurity-of-day-mortimer-and-charlie.html|title=Obscurity of the Day: Mortimer and Charlie. Holtz, Allan. Stripper's Guide|publisher=Strippersguide.blogspot.com|access-date=2013-12-13}}&lt;/ref&gt; Between 1947 and 1954 [[Harvey Eisenberg]] also drew a comic strip based on Charlie McCarthy, scripted by Bergen. &lt;ref&gt;https://www.lambiek.net/artists/e/eisenberg_harvey.htm&lt;/ref&gt;

==Films==
[[File:Edgar Bergen &amp; Mortimer Snerd in Stage Door Canteen.jpg|left|thumb|200px|In the film ''[[Stage Door Canteen (film)|Stage Door Canteen]]'' (1943) with Mortimer Snerd]]
Bergen and his alter ego Charlie McCarthy were given top billing in several films, including the [[Technicolor]] extravaganza ''[[The Goldwyn Follies]]'' (1938), opposite the [[Ritz Brothers]]. That year they also appeared in ''[[You Can't Cheat an Honest Man]]'' with [[W. C. Fields]]. At the height of their popularity in 1937, Bergen was presented an [[Academy Honorary Award|Honorary Oscar]] (in the form of a wooden Oscar statuette) for his creation of Charlie McCarthy.  Bergen, along with Charlie McCarthy and Mortimer Snerd were also featured in the 1938 film ''[[Letter of Introduction (film)|Letter of Introduction]]''.{{citation needed|date=July 2016}}

As an actor alone, Bergen portrayed the timid suitor of the sister Trina in ''[[I Remember Mama (film)|I Remember Mama]]'' (1948), and appeared in ''[[Captain China]]'' (1949), ''[[The Hanged Man (1964 film)|The Hanged Man]]'' (1964) and ''[[Don't Make Waves]]'' (1967). Other film roles for the team include ''[[Look Who's Laughing]]'' (1941) and ''[[Here We Go Again (film)|Here We Go Again]]'' (1942), both with [[Fibber McGee and Molly]]. Charlie McCarthy wore a US Army uniform in ''[[Stage Door Canteen (film)|Stage Door Canteen]]'' (1943) with Mortimer Snerd. Bergen and McCarthy were also featured in [[Disney]]'s ''[[Fun and Fancy Free]]'' (1947). He later cameoed in all-star films such as ''[[The Phynx]]'' (1970), ''[[Won Ton Ton, the Dog Who Saved Hollywood]]'' (1976), and ''[[The Muppet Movie]]'' (1979). In 1977, Bergen  had made a guest appearance  on a second-season episode of ''[[The Muppet Show]]'', the highly acclaimed television comedy/variety program  produced by [[Jim Henson]] who considered Bergen a major inspiration.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last1=Garlen|first1=Jennifer C.|last2=Graham|first2=Anissa M.|title=Kermit Culture: Critical Perspectives on Jim Henson's Muppets|year=2009|publisher=McFarland &amp; Company|isbn=078644259X|page=218}}&lt;/ref&gt; His daughter Candice had also guest-starred on the show during its first season. Bergen died shortly after filming his ''Muppet Movie'' scene, which was also his final public appearance,  and was subsequently dedicated to him. In 2009 Bergen was featured in the comedy documentary ''I'm No Dummy'',&lt;ref&gt;[http://digitalcinemareport.com/node/1165 "Hollywood's Corporate Delusion"], ''Digital Cinema Report'' @ imdb.com; accessed July 22, 2016.&lt;/ref&gt; directed by [[Bryan W. Simon]].

==Television appearances==
{{refimprove section|date=July 2016}}
[[File:Edgar Bergen Ellen Corby The Homecoming Waltons 1974.JPG|thumb|Bergen with [[Ellen Corby]] in ''The Homecoming: A Christmas Story''.]]
[[File:Dick Powell Show Premiere Episode 1961.JPG|thumb|Guest stars for the 1961 premiere episode of [[The Dick Powell Show]], "Who Killed Julie Greer?".  Standing, from left: [[Ronald Reagan]], [[Nick Adams (actor, born 1931)|Nick Adams]], [[Lloyd Bridges]], [[Mickey Rooney]], Edgar Bergen, [[Jack Carson]], [[Ralph Bellamy]], [[Kay Thompson]], [[Dean Jones (actor)|Dean Jones]]. Seated, from left, [[Carolyn Jones]] and [[Dick Powell]].]]
Although his regular series never made the transition to [[television]], Bergen made numerous appearances on the medium during his career.  His first appearance was with Charlie McCarthy on [[NBC]]'s pioneering television variety show [[Hour Glass]] in November 1946.   In a filmed [[Thanksgiving]] special, billed as his official TV debut, sponsored by [[Coca-Cola]] on [[CBS]] in 1950, the new character Podine Puffington was introduced; this saucy Southern belle was as tall as a real woman, in contrast to Bergen's other sit-on-the-knee sized characters. On Christmas Day that same year, Bergen and McCarthy appeared as guests on Walt Disney's first television show, ''[[One Hour in Wonderland]]''.

In 1954, Bergen was a co-host on a memorable TV musical special, ''[[General Foods 25th Anniversary Show: A Salute to Rodgers and Hammerstein]]''.

On December 26, 1954, Bergen appeared on [[What's My Line]] as a mystery guest. Bergen also hosted the television game show ''[[Who Do You Trust?|Do You Trust Your Wife?]]'' in 1956–1957, later succeeded, in a daytime edition, by [[Johnny Carson]].

He appeared in the [[Christmas]] 1957 episode of [[National Broadcasting Company|NBC]]'s ''[[The Gisele MacKenzie Show]]''. In 1958 Bergen appeared with his 12-year-old daughter [[Candice Bergen|Candice]] on an episode of ''[[You Bet Your Life]]'' starring [[Groucho Marx]]. In 1959, he appeared in the second episode titled "Dossier" of the NBC [[espionage]] [[television series|series]] ''[[Five Fingers (TV series)|Five Fingers]]'' starring [[David Hedison]]. On May 21, 1959, he guest-starred with Charlie McCarthy on NBC's ''[[The Ford Show|The Ford Show, Starring Tennessee Ernie Ford]]''. Bergen continued to appear regularly on television during the 1960s and into the 1970s, appearing on [[The Tonight Show]] as late as 1977. He guest-starred as Charlie in the 1960 episode "Moment of Fear" of [[Columbia Broadcasting System|CBS]]'s ''[[The DuPont Show with June Allyson]]''. He did a stint as one of the ''What's My Line?'' mystery guests on the popular Sunday night CBS series. His colleague [[Paul Winchell]] happened to be a panel member during that episode.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=YU98KwL_pQ8&amp;feature=related |title=Edgar Bergen-What's My Line|publisher=YouTube|date=2008-09-13|access-date=2013-12-13}}&lt;/ref&gt; Bergen appeared on the NBC interview program ''[[Here's Hollywood]]''.

Bergen appeared as Grandpa Zeb Walton in the original [[The Waltons|Waltons]] television movie, ''The Homecoming: A Christmas Story'' (1971). The role was played by [[Will Geer]] in the subsequent TV series. During the run of ''The Waltons'' — which took place throughout  the 1930s and 1940s—the voices of Bergen and Charlie McCarthy were sporadically heard from the Waltons' radio, as family members regularly tuned in for that program.

==Family==
[[File:Yancy Derringer cast 2.JPG|left|thumb|[[X Brands]], [[Frances Bergen]], and [[Jock Mahoney]] in ''[[Yancy Derringer]]'' (1959)]]
In 1941, Bergen met 19-year-old [[Frances Bergen|Frances Westerman]], who had graduated from Los Angeles High School the year before, in the audience of Bergen's radio program as the guest of a member of his staff. Sitting in the front row, the young fashion model's legs caught 38-year-old Bergen's attention and he asked to meet her. The two were married in Mexico after years of long-distance courtship, on June 28, 1945. On May 9, 1946 Frances gave birth to future actress [[Candice Bergen]], whose first performances were on Bergen's radio show. Their second child was film and television editor Kris Bergen. Frances also acted, appearing in several movies, co-starring in the 1958 television series ''[[Yancy Derringer]]'', and guest-starring in numerous other shows.

==Death==
In mid-September 1978 he announced that he was retiring after over 50 years in show business and sending his monocled, top-hatted partner, Charlie McCarthy, to the [[National Museum of American History]] at the  [[Smithsonian Institution]] in [[Washington, D.C.]].  He opened at [[Caesar's Palace Hotel]] Las Vegas on September 27, for a two-week "Farewell to show business" engagement. He died three days later on September 30, 1978.

Bergen was interred with his parents (who are buried under their true surname of "Berggren"), in [[Inglewood Park Cemetery]], [[Inglewood, California]]. Edgar Bergen's wife of 33 years, Frances Westerman Bergen, died at [[Cedars-Sinai Medical Center]] in [[Los Angeles, California|Los Angeles]], on October 2, 2006, aged 84, from undisclosed causes.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.mercurynews.com/mld/mercurynews/news/local/states/california/northern_california/15671633.htm|title=San Jose Breaking News, Sports, Weather, Traffic|work=mercurynews.com}}&lt;/ref&gt; She is also buried in Inglewood Cemetery. In 1990, Bergen was elected to the [[Radio Hall of Fame]], the same year that ''The Charlie McCarthy Show'' was selected as an honored program. A message in the [[closing credits]] dedicates ''[[The Muppet Movie]]'' (which featured Edgar and Charlie in their last screen appearance) to the memory and magic of Edgar. In 1991, the United States Postal Service honored him with a 29-cent commemorative stamp.

==Hollywood Walk of Fame==
Bergen was inducted into the [[Hollywood Walk of Fame]] with three stars in 1960, for his contributions to television, [[List of actors with Hollywood Walk of Fame motion picture stars|motion pictures]], and radio. The stars are located at 6425, 6766, and 6801 [[Hollywood Boulevard]], respectively.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.walkoffame.com/edgar-bergen |title=Hollywood Walk of Fame - Edgar Bergen |website=walkoffame.com |publisher=Hollywood Chamber of Commerce |access-date=November 16, 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Filmography==
*1938: ''[[The Goldwyn Follies]]'' as Himself
*1938: ''[[Letter of Introduction (film)|Letter of Introduction]]'' as Himself 
*1939: ''[[You Can't Cheat an Honest Man]]'' as The Great Edgar
*1939: ''Charlie McCarthy, Detective'' as Himself
*1941: ''[[Look Who's Laughing]]'' as Himself
*1942: ''[[Here We Go Again (film)|Here We Go Again]]'' as Himself / Charlie McCarthy / Mortimer Snerd
*1943: ''[[Stage Door Canteen (film)|Stage Door Canteen]]'' as Himself
*1944: ''[[Song of the Open Road]]'' as Himself
*1947: ''[[Fun and Fancy Free]]'' as Himself / Charlie McCarthy / Mortimer Snerd
*1948: ''[[I Remember Mama (film)|I Remember Mama]]'' as Mr. Thorkelson
*1950: ''[[Captain China]]'' as Mr. Haasvelt
*1950: ''Charlie's Haunt'' as Himself
*1953: ''Mystery Lake'' as Dr. Sorenson
*1964: ''[[The Hanged Man (1964 film)|The Hanged Man]]'' (TV Movie) as Hotel Clerk
*1965: ''One Way Wahine'' as Sweeney
*1967: ''[[Don't Make Waves]]'' as Madame Lavinia
*1968: ''Rogue's Gallery'' as Roy Benz
*1970: ''[[The Phynx]]'' as Edgar Bergen
*1976: ''[[Won Ton Ton, the Dog Who Saved Hollywood]]'' as Professor Quicksand
*1979: ''[[The Muppet Movie]]'' as Himself / Charlie McCarthy (final film role)

==See also==
{{Portal bar|Biography}}

==References==
{{reflist|30em}}

==Further reading==
* Bergen, Candice. ''Knock Wood''.
* [http://www.old-time.com/otrlogs2/charlie_mg.html Grams, Jr., Martin. "''The Edgar Bergen and Charlie McCarthy Show'': An Episode Guide and Brief History"]
* [[Dave Strickler|Strickler, Dave]]. ''Syndicated Comic Strips and Artists, 1924–1995: The Complete Index.'' Cambria, California: Comics Access, 1995. {{ISBN|0-9700077-0-1}}
* Funni, Arthur. Thesis: ''The Radio Years of Bergen and McCarthy''. Margaret Herrick Library, 2000.

==External links==
{{Commons category}}
{{wikiquote}}
* [http://www.charliemccarthy.org "Edgar Bergen"] Website
* {{IMDb name|1944}}
* {{tcmdb name|id=14411|name=Edgar Bergen}}
* {{Find a Grave|84}}
* {{AllMovie name|5593}}
* {{rhof|id=170|name=Edgar Bergen}}
* [http://www.bobolinkbooks.com/BALLAST/Dummies.html Knock On Wood: An Insider's View of Belly Speaking]

===Audio===
* Edgar Bergen and Charlie McCarthy's first show for [http://jack_benny.podomatic.com/entry/eg/2010-01-25T13_50_52-08_00 The Chase And Sanborn Hour 1937-05-09 (01) Guest: Ann Harding, with a new introduction.]
* [http://jack_benny.podomatic.com/entry/eg/2009-08-03T09_42_32-07_00 Edgar Bergen and Charlie McCarthy 1942-05-03 Guest: Judy Garland]
*[http://zootradio.com/Bergen_And_McCarthy.php Zoot Radio, Free Edgar Bergen and Charlie McCarthy old time radio shows]
*[http://www.outlawsgameroom.com/old-time-radio/g/edgar-bergen-and-charlie-mccarthy Outlaws Old Time Radio presents Edgar Bergen and Charlie McCarthy]

===Video===
* {{YouTube|user=EddieInDecaturMovie|EddieInDecaturMovie}} – ''Eddie in Decatur'', a 15-part documentary about Bergen's early life in Michigan

{{Academy Honorary Award}}
{{Screen Actors Guild Lifetime Achievement Award}}

{{Authority control}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Bergen, Edgar}}
[[Category:1903 births]]
[[Category:1930s American radio programs]]
[[Category:1940s American radio programs]]
[[Category:1950s American radio programs]]
[[Category:1978 deaths]]
[[Category:Academy Honorary Award recipients]]
[[Category:American male film actors]]
[[Category:American people of Swedish descent]]
[[Category:American male radio actors]]
[[Category:Burials at Inglewood Park Cemetery]]
[[Category:Deaths from renal failure]]
[[Category:Disease-related deaths in Nevada]]
[[Category:National Radio Hall of Fame inductees]]
[[Category:Peabody Award winners]]
[[Category:People from Van Buren County, Michigan]]
[[Category:Vaudeville performers]]
[[Category:Ventriloquists' dummies]]
[[Category:Ventriloquists]]
[[Category:20th-century American male actors]]
[[Category:Northwestern University School of Communication alumni]]</text>
      <sha1>nuhhfwuge1a26gy5n6gy8gnzp3x2fyh</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
