<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10.xsd" version="0.10" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <dbname>enwiki</dbname>
    <base>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.32.0-wmf.16</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="118" case="first-letter">Draft</namespace>
      <namespace key="119" case="first-letter">Draft talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2300" case="first-letter">Gadget</namespace>
      <namespace key="2301" case="first-letter">Gadget talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2302" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition</namespace>
      <namespace key="2303" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Eric Morecambe</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>86253</id>
    <revision>
      <id>846836875</id>
      <parentid>843761717</parentid>
      <timestamp>2018-06-21T05:30:51Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>KolbertBot</username>
        <id>31691822</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor/>
      <comment>Bot: [[User:KolbertBot|HTTP→HTTPS]] (v485)</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="21782">{{EngvarB|date=November 2017}}
{{Use dmy dates|date=November 2017}}
{{refimprove|date=December 2012}}
{{Infobox person
| name         = Eric Morecambe 
| honorific_suffix = [[Officer of the Order of the British Empire|OBE]]
| image        = File:EricMorecambe1963.jpg
| caption      = Bronze bust of Morecambe by Victor Heyfron, 1963
| birth_name   = John Eric Bartholomew
| birth_date   = {{Birth date|df=y|1926|5|14}}
| birth_place  = [[Morecambe]], Lancashire, England
| death_date = {{Death date and age|df=y|1984|5|28|1926|5|14}}
| death_place = [[Tewkesbury]], Gloucestershire, England
| employer     = 
| occupation   = Comedian, actor, entertainer, singer
| years_active = 1941–1984
| spouse       = {{marriage|Joan Bartlett|11 December 1952|28 May 1984}} (his death)
| children     = 3 (1 adopted)
}}

'''John Eric Bartholomew''', {{post-nominals|country=GBR|OBE}} (14 May 1926 – 28 May 1984), known by his [[stage name]] '''Eric Morecambe''', was an English comedian who together with [[Ernie Wise]] formed the award-winning [[double act]] [[Morecambe and Wise]]. The partnership lasted from 1941 until Morecambe's death in 1984. Morecambe took his stage name from his home town, the [[seaside resort]] of [[Morecambe]] in Lancashire.

He was the co-star of the television series ''The Morecambe &amp; Wise Show'', which for one Christmas episode gained UK viewing figures of over twenty-seven million people.&lt;ref&gt;[https://www.theguardian.com/lifeandstyle/2009/oct/17/eric-morecambe-son-gary "Eric Morecambe: Growing up with a comic legend"], ''The Guardian'', 17 October 2009&lt;/ref&gt; One of the most prominent comedians in [[British popular culture]], in 2002 he was named one of the [[100 Greatest Britons]] in a BBC poll.&lt;ref&gt;[http://news.bbc.co.uk/1/hi/entertainment/tv_and_radio/2208671.stm "100 great British heroes"]. BBC News. Retrieved 15 February 2014&lt;/ref&gt;

Morecambe, who had previously suffered heart attacks in November 1968 and March 1979 as well as undergoing bypass surgery, collapsed from a heart attack as he left the stage of the [[Roses Theatre]] in [[Tewkesbury]], following a performance; he died in hospital a few hours later.

==Early life and childhood career==
Eric Morecambe was born in Morecambe, Lancashire as John Eric Bartholomew to George and Sadie Bartholomew (Sarah Elizabeth née Robinson). Sadie took work as a waitress to raise funds for his dancing lessons. During this period, Eric Bartholomew won numerous talent contests, including one in [[Hoylake]] in 1940 for which the prize was an audition in Manchester for [[Jack Hylton]]. Three months after the audition, Hylton invited Morecambe to join a revue called ''Youth Takes a Bow'' at the [[Nottingham]] Empire, where he met the then [[Ernie Wise|Ernest Wiseman]]. The two soon became very close friends, and with Sadie's encouragement started to develop a [[double act]].

When the two were eventually allowed to perform their double act on stage (in addition to their solo spots), Hylton was impressed enough to make it a regular feature in the revue. However, the duo were separated when they came of age for their [[Conscription in the United Kingdom|War Service]] during the final stages of the [[World War II|Second World War]]. Wise joined the [[Merchant Navy]], while Morecambe was conscripted to become a [[Bevin Boy]] and worked as a coal miner in [[Accrington]] from May 1944 onwards.

==Career==
===Bartholomew and Wiseman===
After the war, Morecambe and Wise began performing on stage and radio and secured a contract with the [[BBC]] to make a television show, where they started the short-lived show ''[[Running Wild (1954 TV series)|Running Wild]]'' in 1954. They returned to the stage to hone their act, and later made appearances on ''[[Sunday Night at the London Palladium]]'' and ''[[Double Six (TV series)|Double Six]]''.&lt;ref&gt;{{IMDb title |id=tt5280068 |title=Double Six}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===''Two of a Kind'': 1961–68===
In 1961, [[Lew Grade]] offered the duo a series for the London-based [[ITV (TV network)|ITV]] station [[Associated Television|ATV]]. Entitled ''[[Two of a Kind (UK TV series)|Two of a Kind]]'', it was written by [[Dick Hills and Sid Green]]. An [[British Actors' Equity Association|Equity]] strike halted that show, but Morecambe and Wise were members of the Variety Artists' Federation, then a separate trade union unaffiliated with Equity. Green and Hills later appeared in the series as "Sid" and "Dick".

The sixth Morecambe and Wise series for ATV was planned from the start to be aired in the United Kingdom as well as exported to the United States and Canada. It was taped in colour and starred international guests, often American. Prior to its British run, it was broadcast in North America by the ABC network as a summer replacement for re-runs of ''[[The Hollywood Palace]]'', under the title ''The Piccadilly Palace'', from 20 May to 9 September 1967. All but two episodes of this series are now believed to be lost, with the surviving two episodes existing only as black-and-white copies, bearing the UK titles. 

The duo had appeared in the US on ''[[The Ed Sullivan Show]]''. In 1968, Morecambe and Wise left ATV to return to the BBC.

===With the BBC: 1968–78===
While Morecambe was recuperating from a heart attack, Hills and Green, who believed that Morecambe would probably never work again, quit as writers. Morecambe and Wise were in [[Barbados]] at the time and learned of their writers' departure only from the steward on the plane. [[John Ammonds]], the show's producer, replaced Hills and Green with [[Eddie Braben]]. Theatre critic [[Kenneth Tynan]] stated, Braben made Wise's character a comic who was not funny, while Morecambe became a straight man who was funny. Braben made them less hostile to one another.

Morecambe and Wise did annual [[BBC]] Christmas shows from 1968 to 1977, with the 1977 show having an estimated audience of 28,385,000. In 1976, they were both appointed [[British honours system|OBEs]]. (Morecambe's wife, Joan, was to receive her own OBE in 2015 for her work with children's charities.)&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.thevisitor.co.uk/news/local/royal-nod-for-eric-morecambe-s-widow-1-7232756|title=Royal nod for Eric Morecambe's widow|publisher=thevisitor.co.uk}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===With Thames Television: 1978–83===
The pair left the BBC for [[ITV (TV network)|ITV]] in January 1978, signing a contract with the London station [[Thames Television]].

Morecambe suffered a second heart attack at his home in [[Harpenden]], Herts on 15 March 1979; this led to a [[heart bypass]] operation, performed by [[Magdi Yacoub]] on 25 June 1979. At that time, Morecambe was told he only had three months to live.&lt;ref&gt;TVAM interview with Morecambe, 18 April 1984&lt;/ref&gt;

Morecambe increasingly wanted to move away from the double act, and into writing and playing other roles. In 1980, he played the "Funny Uncle" in a dramatisation of the [[John Betjeman]] poem "Indoor Games Near Newbury", part of an ITV special titled ''Betjeman's Britain''. Produced and directed by Charles Wallace, it spawned the start of a working relationship that led to a follow-up in 1981 for [[Paramount Pictures]] titled ''Late Flowering Love'' in which Morecambe played an RAF major. The film was released in the UK with ''[[Raiders of the Lost Ark]]''. In 1981, Morecambe published ''Mr Lonely'', a [[tragicomedy|tragicomic novel]] about a stand-up comedian. He began to focus more on writing.

Morecambe and Wise made a series for showing during the autumns of 1980 to 1983. They also appeared together recalling their music hall days in a one-hour special on ITV on 2 March 1983, called ''Eric &amp; Ernie's Variety Days''. During this time Morecambe published two other novels: ''The Reluctant Vampire'' (1982) and its sequel, ''The Vampire's Revenge'' (1983). Morecambe and Wise's final show together was the 1983 Christmas special for ITV.

Morecambe and Wise worked on a television movie in 1983, ''[[Night Train to Murder]]'', which was broadcast on ITV in January 1985. Continuing his collaboration with Wallace, Morecambe also acted in a [[Short film|short]] comedy film called ''[[The Passionate Pilgrim (film)|The Passionate Pilgrim]]'' opposite [[Tom Baker]] and [[Madeline Smith]], again directed by Wallace for [[Metro-Goldwyn-Mayer|MGM/UA]]. It was released in the cinema with the James Bond film ''[[Octopussy]]'' and later with ''[[WarGames]]''. Wallace and Morecambe were halfway through filming a fourth film when Morecambe died. It was never completed.

==Personal life==
Eric Morecambe married Joan Bartlett on 11 December 1952. They had three children: Gail (born 14 September 1953); Gary (born 21 April 1956) and Steven (born 1970 and [[adoption|adopted]] in 1974). 

In his leisure time, Eric was a keen [[birdwatcher]], and the statue of him at Morecambe shows him wearing his binoculars. The [[RSPB]] named a hide after him at the nearby [[Leighton Moss nature reserve]] in recognition of his support. In 1984 the RSPB bought the 459 ha (1,100 acre) Old Hall Marshes Reserve near [[Tolleshunt D'Arcy]] in Essex for £780,000 helped by donations to the ''Eric Morecambe Memorial Appeal''.&lt;ref&gt;RSPB Birds magazine, ''Old Essex Coast:Old Hall Marshes'', p. 50 (Spring 2005)&lt;/ref&gt;

Morecambe was the [[Nephew and niece|nephew]] of the rugby league footballer [[Jack Bartholomew|John "Jack" Bartholomew]].&lt;ref&gt;Tom Mather (2010). "Best in the Northern Union", pp. 128–142. {{ISBN|978-1-903659-51-9}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Morecambe was sympathetic to the [[Conservative Party (UK)|Conservative Party]] and sent a message of support (along with various celebrities) to [[Margaret Thatcher]] after she won the [[United Kingdom general election, 1979|1979 general election]], wishing her luck during the [[European Parliament election, 1979 (United Kingdom)|1979 European election campaign]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.margaretthatcher.org/archive/1979-cac-releases-1.asp |title=Transition to power &amp;#124; Margaret Thatcher Foundation |publisher=Margaretthatcher.org |accessdate=23 February 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt; His message ended, "God bless you, Maggie, and good luck in the European Campaign and it is your round next."&lt;ref&gt;http://www.margaretthatcher.org/document/18571C4EE5504F98867695BDF539C16E.pdf&lt;/ref&gt;

===Health===
====Heart problems====
{{Unreferenced section|date=September 2015}}
In a diary entry from 17 August 1967, when Morecambe and Wise were appearing in [[Great Yarmouth]] as part of a summer season, Morecambe noted, "I have a slight pain on the left side around my heart. It's most likely wind, but I've had it for about four days. That's a hell of a time to have wind."

Morecambe was a [[hypochondriac]], but he rarely wrote about his health concerns until after his first heart attack. At the time, Morecambe was smoking 60 cigarettes a day and drinking heavily. He suffered a near-fatal heart attack on 8 November 1968 at the age of 42, after a show, while driving back to his hotel outside [[Leeds]].

Morecambe had been appearing with Wise during a week of midnight performances at the [[Batley Variety Club|Variety Club]] in [[Batley]], Yorkshire. Morecambe and Wise appeared there in December 1967 for a week, making £4,000. After that, they were booked to play a New York City nightclub, the [[Royal Variety Performance]] and then eight weeks in pantomime the coming winter.

Morecambe headed back to his hotel, and recounted in an interview with [[Michael Parkinson]] in November 1972 that, as the pains spread to his chest, he became unable to drive. He was rescued by a passerby as he stopped the car.  The first hospital they found had no [[Accident and Emergency]]. At the second one, a heart attack was immediately diagnosed.

After leaving hospital, Morecambe gave up his cigarette habit to start smoking a [[Smoking pipe (tobacco)|pipe]], as he mentioned that he was trying to do in August 1967. He also stopped doing summer and winter seasons and reduced many of his public engagements. Morecambe took six months off, returning for a press call at the BBC Television centre in May 1969. In August of that year, Morecambe and Wise returned to the stage at the [[Bournemouth Winter Gardens]], and received a four-minute standing ovation.

Morecambe suffered a second heart attack in March 1979&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.televisionheaven.co.uk/morecambe_and_wise_2.htm|title=ERIC MORECAMBE AND ERNIE WISE - PART 2 - A TELEVISION HEAVEN BIOGRAPHY|website=www.televisionheaven.co.uk|accessdate=28 January 2018}}&lt;/ref&gt; and underwent bypass surgery in June.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.morecambeandwise.com/viewpage.aspx?pageid=351|title=This Is Their Life - morecambeandwise.com|website=www.morecambeandwise.com|accessdate=28 January 2018}}&lt;/ref&gt;

====Death====
Morecambe took part in a charity show, hosted by close friend and comedian [[Stan Stennett]], at the [[Roses Theatre]] in [[Tewkesbury]], Gloucestershire, on Sunday 27 May 1984. His wife Joan, who was in the audience, recalled that Morecambe was "on top form".&lt;ref&gt;Joan Morecambe, ''Morecambe and Wife'', p. 180 (1985)&lt;/ref&gt;

After the show had ended and Morecambe had first left the stage, the musicians returned and picked up their instruments. He rushed back onto the stage to join them and played various instruments making six curtain calls. On leaving the stage for the final time as the [[Front curtain|house tabs]] fell, he stepped into the wings and collapsed with his third heart attack in 16 years. He was rushed to [[Cheltenham General Hospital]], where he died just before 3 a.m on Monday 28 May.&lt;ref&gt;''Morecambe &amp; Wise'', Graham McGann, (1999), p. 300&lt;/ref&gt;

His funeral was held on 4 June at [[St Nicholas Church, Harpenden]] with the principal address delivered by [[Dickie Henderson]]. There was a private cremation service at [[Garston, Hertfordshire|Garston]]. His ashes were later returned to the church for burial in the Garden of Remembrance.{{citation needed|date=October 2017}}&lt;!-- WP:RS needed; removed link to WP:SPS (Twitter, FB, WP)--&gt;

==Legacy==
[[File:Eric Morecambe - geograph.org.uk - 737011.jpg|thumb|Statue of Eric Morecambe in [[Morecambe]], Lancashire, England]]
* A larger-than-life statue of Morecambe, created by sculptor [[Graham Ibbeson]], was unveiled by [[Elizabeth II|the Queen]] at Morecambe in July 1999 and is surrounded by inscriptions of many of his favourite catchphrases and an exhaustive list of guest stars who appeared on the show. The statue was vandalised in October 2014, having had one of its legs sawn off, it was moved to London for repair and was restored on 11 December 2014.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.bbc.co.uk/news/uk-england-lancashire-30432651 |title=Eric Morecambe statue returns after attempted theft – BBC News |publisher=BBC |accessdate=23 February 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt; 
[[File:Eric Morecombe Statue Lea Valley Walk.jpg|thumb|Sculpture of Eric Morecambe, Upper [[Lea Valley Walk]] between Harpenden and [[Luton]], England]]
* In the English town of [[Harpenden]] in Hertfordshire, where Morecambe and his family lived from the 1960s until his death, the public concert hall is named after him, with a portrait of Morecambe hanging in the foyer. Morecambe often referred to Harpenden in his comedy, with a band once appearing on the show named ''The Harpenden Hot-Shots'' and in a Casanova sketch he introduced himself as Lord Eric, Fourth Duke of Harpenden "and certain parts of [[Birkenhead]]". Morecambe was the guest of honour, and performed the opening ceremony at the 75th Anniversary Fete of St George's School, Harpenden. Commenting openly to the headmaster, after his opening speech, "Right, now that's over, can we go and get an ice cream".
* In 1999 Morecambe was voted the funniest person of the 20th century in a British internet poll; Morecambe pulled in 26 percent of the votes, beating his contemporary performer [[Tommy Cooper]] and [[Monty Python]] member [[John Cleese]] to the coveted position.
* A [[West End theatre|West End]] Show, ''[[The Play What I Wrote]]'', appeared in 2001 as a tribute to the duo. Directed by [[Kenneth Branagh]], each performance featured a different guest celebrity, including [[Kylie Minogue]], who was said to be particularly keen to participate. Guest stars included [[Roger Moore]], [[Nigel Havers]] and most notably [[Prince Charles]], who was a fan of the duo.
* ''The Play What I Wrote'' later transferred to [[Broadway theatre|Broadway]], and was only moderately rewritten to allow for the fact that Eric and Ernie were virtually unknown in the US save for a handful of performances on ''[[The Ed Sullivan Show]]'' in the 1960s, prior to their big success. The show toured the UK in 2003.
* In 2003, Morecambe's eldest son Gary released ''"Life's Not Hollywood, It's [[Cricklewood]]"'', a biography of his father from the point of view of his family, using family photos and extracts from previously unseen diaries. The book revealed Morecambe as a toned down version of his on-screen persona, prone to occasional bouts of mild depression and overwork.
* In a 2005 poll to find ''The Comedian's Comedian'', he was voted as the fourth greatest comedy act ever by fellow comedians and comedy insiders.
* [[Kenilworth Road]] Stadium, the home of [[Luton Town F.C.]], has a suite named after Morecambe; he was a vociferous supporter and one-time president of the club and voiced his enthusiasm on the television, often shouting ''Luton for the Cup!'' and once brandishing a sign mid-way through a sketch with [[Glenda Jackson]] to much applause and cheers. He once appeared wearing a Luton rosette on the show.
* [[J D Wetherspoon]] opened a public house called ''The Eric Bartholomew'' in Morecambe on 4 April 2004.
* In 2007 the author William Cook produced the book ''Morecambe &amp; Wise Unseen'' which charts many of the early career moves of both Morecambe and [[Ernie Wise]]. It focuses largely on their time struggling to make a living prior to their break into television in the 1960s and is illustrated with many personal family photographs and previous unseen views of the act.
* At the [[Roses Theatre]] in [[Tewkesbury]], the Eric Morecambe Room is used by local and national companies for conferences and meetings.
* There is a [[bird hide]] named after him at [[Leighton Moss RSPB reserve]], which is on Morecambe Bay, near Carnforth, Lancashire.&lt;ref name="Gazette"&gt;{{cite web | url=http://www.thewestmorlandgazette.co.uk/news/10014481.Eric_Morecambe_s_daughter_brings_sunshine_to_new_Leighton_Moss_bird_hide/?ref=mmsp | title=Eric Morecambe's daughter brings sunshine. | work=[[Westmorland Gazette]] | year=2012 | accessdate=25 January 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* The play ''[[Morecambe (play)|Morecambe]]'' was created as a celebration of the life of Eric Morecambe. It played at the Edinburgh fringe festival in 2009 and subsequently transferred to London's [[West End theatre|West End]] before embarking on a UK tour in 2010.
* In February 2016 Morecambe's 1968 [[Jensen Interceptor]], which he had bought for £4,500, was offered for sale at £150,000.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.bbc.co.uk/news/uk-england-beds-bucks-herts-35630972 |title=Eric Morecambe's Jensen Interceptor for sale at £150,000 – BBC News |publisher=BBC |accessdate=23 February 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Bibliography==
* ''Mister Lonely'' (novel) by Eric Morecambe (1981) {{ISBN|0-413-48170-0}}
* ''Stella'' (novel) by Eric Morecambe (completed by Gary Morecambe) (2012) {{ISBN|9780007395071}}

==References==
{{Reflist|2}}

==Further reading==
* ''Morecambe and Wife'' – Joan Morecambe and Michael Leitch (1985) {{ISBN|0-7207-1616-0}}
* ''Morecambe and Wise : Behind the Sunshine'' – Gary Morecambe, Martin Sterling (1995) {{ISBN|0330341405}}
* ''Morecambe &amp; Wise'' – Graham McCann (1998) {{ISBN|1-85702-735-3}}
* ''Memories of Eric'' – Gary Morecambe and Martin Sterling (1999) {{ISBN|978-0-233996691}}
* ''Eric Morecambe : Life's not Hollywood, it's Cricklewood'' – Gary Morecambe (2003) {{ISBN|0-563-52186-4}}
* ''Eric Morecambe Unseen : The Lost Diaries Jokes and Photographs'' – William Cook (ed.) (2005) {{ISBN|0-00-723465-1}}
* ''You'll Miss Me When I'm Gone : The life and work of Eric Morecambe'' – Gary Morecambe (2009) {{ISBN|978-0-00-728732-1}}
* ''Eric Morecambe Lost and Found'' – Gary Morecambe (ed.)(2012) {{ISBN|9781849543361}}
* ''Who Killed Eric Morecambe? (the decline &amp; fall of British television)'' – Charles Wallace (Nov 2012) {{ASIN|B00A4COP64|country=uk}}
* ''Driving Mr Morecambe : A Chauffeur's Story'' – Michael Fountain, Paul Jenkinson (2013) {{ISBN|9780755207329}}
* ''Morecambe and Wise: Bring Me Sunshine'' – Gary Morecambe (2013) {{ISBN|9781780973982}}

==External links==
{{Commons category|Eric Morecambe}}
* [http://www.morecambeandwise.co.uk/ The Morecambe &amp; Wise homepage]
* [http://www.morecambeandwise.com/ Morecambeandwise.com News Reviews And Information]
* [http://www.morecambemoments.com/ Eric Morecambe website run by daughter Gail Morecambe]
* {{IMDb name|603449}}

{{Morecambe and Wise}}
{{Navboxes
|title= Awards for Eric Morecambe
|list1=
{{British Academy Television Award for Best Entertainment Performance}}
{{BAFTA Academy Fellowship Award}}
}}
{{Authority control}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Morecambe, Eric}}
[[Category:1926 births]]
[[Category:1984 deaths]]
[[Category:Burials in Hertfordshire]]
[[Category:English male comedians]]
[[Category:English male television actors]]
[[Category:Luton Town F.C.]]
[[Category:Officers of the Order of the British Empire]]
[[Category:People from Morecambe]]
[[Category:Morecambe and Wise]]
[[Category:Deaths onstage]]
[[Category:Bevin Boys]]
[[Category:20th-century English male actors]]
[[Category:English miners]]
[[Category:Hypochondriacs]]
[[Category:20th-century British comedians]]
[[Category:British male comedy actors]]</text>
      <sha1>cupop1gnozz5k6skwuvfuknzogonx8o</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
