<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10.xsd" version="0.10" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <dbname>enwiki</dbname>
    <base>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.32.0-wmf.16</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="118" case="first-letter">Draft</namespace>
      <namespace key="119" case="first-letter">Draft talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2300" case="first-letter">Gadget</namespace>
      <namespace key="2301" case="first-letter">Gadget talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2302" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition</namespace>
      <namespace key="2303" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Jacques Tati</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>236680</id>
    <revision>
      <id>856043408</id>
      <parentid>851728803</parentid>
      <timestamp>2018-08-22T13:36:38Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Xyen2001</username>
        <id>2299172</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor/>
      <comment>/* Filmography */</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="42791">{{Infobox person
| name        = Jacques Tati
| image       = Jacques Tati.jpg
| caption     = Jacques Tati as [[Monsieur Hulot]]
| birth_name  = Jacques Tatischeff
| birth_date  = {{Birth date|df=yes|1907|10|9}}
| birth_place = [[Le Pecq]], France
| death_date  = {{Death date and age|df=yes|1982|11|5|1907|10|9}}
| death_place = [[Paris]], France
| spouse      = Micheline Winter (1944–1982; his death)
| occupation = Filmmaker, actor, screenwriter, director
| years_active =
}}
'''Jacques Tati''' ({{IPA-fr|tati|lang}}; born '''Jacques Tatischeff''', {{IPA-fr|tatiʃɛf|pron}}; 9 October 1907 – 5 November 1982)&lt;ref name="sensesofcinema"&gt;{{cite web|url=http://sensesofcinema.com/2002/great-directors/tati/|title=Jacques Tati • Great Director profile • Senses of Cinema|website=sensesofcinema.com|accessdate=23 May 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt; was a French filmmaker, actor, and screenwriter. Throughout his long career, he worked as a comic actor, writer, and director. In a poll conducted by ''[[Entertainment Weekly]]'' of the Greatest Movie Directors, Tati was voted the 46th greatest of all time. With only six feature-length films to his credit as director, he directed fewer films than any other director on this list of 50.

Tati's ''[[Playtime]]'' (1967) ranked 43rd in the 2012 ''[[Sight &amp; Sound]]'' critics' poll of the greatest films ever made.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.bfi.org.uk/films-tv-people/4ce2b6b3291db/sightandsoundpoll2012|title=Votes for Playtime (1967)|publisher=British Film Institute|accessdate=12 February 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt;

As [[David Bellos]] puts it, "Tati, from ''l'Ecole des facteurs'' to ''Playtime'', is the epitome of what an ''auteur'' is (in film theory) supposed to be: the controlling mind behind a vision of the world on film".&lt;ref&gt;Jacques Tati, His Life and Art, David Bellos, Random House. [https://books.google.ch/books?hl=fr&amp;id=hCCN-Gac0YMC&amp;dq=Jacques+Tati+%22cinema+d%27auteur%22+-wikipedia&amp;q=auteur#v=snippet&amp;q=auteur&amp;f=false]&lt;/ref&gt;

==Family origins==
Jacques Tati was of Russian, Dutch, and Italian ancestry.  His father, George Emmanuel Tatischeff, born in 1875 in Paris (d. 1957), was the son of Dmitry Tatishchev (Дмитрий Татищев), General of the [[Imperial Russian Army]] and [[military attaché]] to the Russian Embassy in Paris. The Tatischeffs (also spelled Tatishchev) were a Russian noble family of patrilineal [[Rurikid]] descent.  Whilst stationed in Paris Dmitri Tatischeff married a French woman, Rose Anathalie Alinquant. (Russian sources indicate that she was a circus performer and that they never married.)&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.russian.rfi.fr/kultura/20110220-multfilm-illyuzionist-i-docheri-zhaka-tati|title=Кинопанорама - Мультфильм «Иллюзионист» и дочери Жака Тати|date=20 February 2011|website=rfi.fr|accessdate=23 May 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Under suspicious circumstances Dmitri Tatischeff died from injuries sustained in a horse-riding accident shortly after the birth of George Emmanuel. As a child George Emmanuel experienced turbulent times, such as being forcibly removed from France and taken to Russia to live. In 1883 his mother brought him back to France where they settled on the estate of [[Le Pecq]], near [[Saint-Germain-en-Laye]] on the outskirts of Paris.&lt;ref&gt;{{harvsp|Bellos|2002|loc=1}}, " Une famille bien française : les Tatischeff "&lt;/ref&gt; In 1903, Georges-Emmanuel Tatischeff married the Dutch-Italian Marcelle Claire van Hoof (d. 1968). Together they had two children, Natalie (b. 1905) and Jacques.  Claire's Dutch father, a friend of [[van Gogh]], whose clients included [[Toulouse-Lautrec]],&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.yalerecord.com/david-lynch-on-jacques-tati/|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20111109014917/http://www.yalerecord.com/david-lynch-on-jacques-tati/|dead-url=no|archive-date=9 November 2011|title=and Lynch on Mon Oncle", Jacques Tatischeff at 109sec|website=yalerecord.com|accessdate=23 May 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt; was the owner of a prestigious picture-framing company near the [[Place Vendôme]] in Paris, and he brought Georges-Emmanuel into the family business. Subsequently, Georges-Emmanuel became the director of the company Cadres Van Hoof, and the Tatischeff family enjoyed a relatively high standard of living.&lt;ref&gt;{{harvsp|Bellos|2002|loc=2}}, "Les Cadres Van Hoof".&lt;/ref&gt;

==Early life==
Jacques Tatischeff appears to have been an indifferent student, yet excelled in the sports of tennis and horse riding. He left school in 1923 at the age of 16 to take up an apprenticeship in the family business, where he was trained as a picture framer by his grandfather. Between 1927 and 1928 he completed his military national service at [[Saint-Germain-en-Laye]] with the Cavalry's 16th Regiment of Dragoons.&lt;ref&gt;{{harvsp|Bellos|2002|loc=3}}, "Le dragon".&lt;/ref&gt; Upon graduating the military he took on an internship in London where he was first introduced to the sport of [[Rugby football|rugby]]. Returning to Paris, he joined the semi-professional rugby team Racing Club de France, whose captain was [[Alfred Sauvy]] and whose supporters included [[Tristan Bernard]]. It was at the Racing Club de France that Jacques Tatischeff first discovered his comic talents, entertaining his teammates during intervals with hilarious impersonations of their sporting endeavours. He also first met [[Jacques Broido]], and they would become lifelong friends.&lt;ref&gt;{{harvsp|Bellos|2002|loc=4}}, "Drôle d'école".&lt;/ref&gt;

Between 1931 and 1932 the [[Great Depression in France|global economic crisis reached France]]&lt;ref&gt;Il a conservé le statut et la rémunération d'apprenti, n'ayant pas réussi l'examen pour devenir ouvrier.&lt;/ref&gt; at the same time he left both the Racing Club de France and, to his family's disapproval, his apprenticeship at Cadres Van Hoof. Giving up a relatively comfortable middle-class lifestyle for one of a struggling performing artist during this difficult economic time, he developed a collection of highly physical mimes that would become his ''Impressions Sportives'' (''Sporting Impressions''). Each year from 1931 to 1934 he would participate in an amateur show organised by Alfred Sauvy.&lt;ref&gt;{{harvsp|Bellos|2002|p=56 et 57}} : affiches pour 1931 (''Sport muet par Jacques Tattischeff'') et 1933, où il est cité en haut de l'affiche : ''J. Taticheff''.&lt;/ref&gt;

==Career==
===Early work===
Although he had likely played music hall engagements before, his act was first mentioned in 1935, when he performed at the gala for the newspaper ''[[Le Journal]]'' to celebrate the French victory in the competition to set the transatlantic crossing record from [[Normandy]]. Among the honourable spectators was the influential writer [[Colette]]. Tati's act also caught the attention of [[Max Trebor]], who offered him an engagement at the Theatre-Michel, where he quickly became the star act. After his success there, Tati tried to make it in London, playing a short season at the [[Finsbury Park Empire]] in March 1936. Upon his return to Paris in the same year, he was immediately hired as top billing at the ABC Théâtre&lt;ref name=ABC&gt;[[:fr:ABC (music-hall)|ABC_(music-hall)]] French Wikipedia for l'ABC&lt;/ref&gt; alongside the singer [[Marie Dubas]], where he would work uninterrupted until the outbreak of the Second World War.&lt;ref&gt;{{harvsp|Bellos|2002|loc=6, 8, 10}}.&lt;/ref&gt; It was for Tati's performances of his now finely tuned ''Impressions Sportives'' at the ABC that the previously impressed Colette wrote,

&lt;blockquote&gt;"From now on no celebration, no artistic or acrobatic spectacle can do without this amazing performer, who has invented something quite his own...His act is partly ballet and partly sport, partly satire and partly a charade. He has devised a way of being both the player, the ball and the tennis racquet, of being simultaneously the football and the goalkeeper, the boxer and his opponent, the bicycle and the cyclist. Without any props, he conjures up his accessories and his partners. He has suggestive powers of all great artists. How gratifying it was to see the audience's warm reaction! Tati's success says a lot about the sophistication of the allegedly "uncouth" public, about its taste for novelty and its appreciation of style. Jacques Tati, the horse and rider conjured, will show all of Paris the living image of that legendary creature, the centaur."&lt;ref&gt;Colette, "Spectacles de Paris", '''Le Journal''', 28 June 1936, quoted in {{harvsp|Bellos|2002|loc=63}}.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

During the 1930s he also performed at the [[Scala (Berlin)|Scala]] in Berlin between 1937 and 1938, and began to experiment with film acting in the following shorts:

*1932 : ''Oscar, champion de tennis'' directed by [[Jack Forrester (director)|Jack Forrester]] written by and starring Jacques Tati (film lost);
*1934 : ''On demande une brute'' directed by [[Charles Barrois (b.1890)|Charles Barrois]], with Jacques Tati as (''Roger''), Enrico Sprocani as ''le clown Rhum'' (''Enrico'');
*1935 : ''[[Gai dimanche]]'' directed by [[Jacques Berr]], wrote and starring Jacques Tati and Enrico Sprocani; and
*1936 : ''Soigne ton gauche'' directed by [[René Clément]], starring Jacques Tati (''Roger''), Jacques Broido (''sparring partner''), Max Martel (''the postman'').

===World War II===
In September 1939 Tati was conscripted back into his 16th Regiment of Dragoons which was then incorporated into the [[3rd Division Legere de Cavalerie]] (DLC). He saw action in the [[Battle of Sedan (1940)|Battle of Sedan]], in May 1940, when the German Army marched through the [[Ardennes]] into northern France. The 3rd DLC retreated from [[Meuse]] to [[Mussidan]] in the [[Dordogne]] where the division was demobilised after the [[Second Armistice at Compiègne|Armistice]] was declared on 22 June 1940.

Returning to Paris, Tati resumed his civilian profession as a cabaret performer, finding employment at [[Léon Volterra]]'s Lido de Paris, where he performed his ''Sporting Impressions'' from 1940 to 1942.

Considered as a possible substitute for [[Jean-Louis Barrault]] in ''[[Les Enfants du Paradis]]'', he played the ghost in ''Sylvie and the Ghost'' (''[[Sylvie et le fantôme]]'') (Claude Autant-Lara appeared as Sylvie) and also appeared as The Devil in the same film.  Here he met Fred Orain, studio director of St. Maurice and the [[Victorine Studios|Victorine]] in [[Nice]].

===Jacques Tati, director===
In early 1946 Jacques Tati and Fred Orain founded the production company [[Cady-Films]], which would produce Tati's first three films.

With the exception of his first and last films, Tati played the gauche and socially inept lead character, [[Monsieur Hulot]]. With his trademark raincoat, umbrella and pipe, Hulot is among the most memorable comic characters in cinema. Several themes recur in Tati's work, most notably in ''[[Mon Oncle]]'', ''[[Play Time]]'' and ''[[Trafic]]''. They include Western society's obsession with material goods, particularly American-style consumerism, the pressure-cooker environment of modern society, the superficiality of relationships among France's various social classes, and the cold and often impractical nature of space-age technology and design.

==="L'École des facteurs" ("The School for Postmen")===
[[René Clément]] was first approached to direct "[[L'École des facteurs]]", but as he was preoccupied directing ''[[La Bataille du rail]]'', directing duties fell to Tati, who would also star in this short comedy of rural life. Encouragingly, L'École des facteurs was enthusiastically well received upon release, winning the [[Max Linder Prize]] for film comedy in 1947.

===''Jour de fête (The Big Day)''===
Tati's first major feature, ''[[Jour de fête]]'' (''The Big Day''), is about an inept rural village postman who interrupts his duties to inspect the traveling fair that has come to town. Influenced by too much wine and a documentary on the rapidity of the American postal service, he goes to hilarious lengths to speed his mail deliveries aboard his bicycle. Tati filmed it in 1947 in the village of [[Sainte-Sévère-sur-Indre]] where he had found refuge during the war. Due to the reluctance of French distributors, ''Jour de fête'' was first successfully released in London in March 1949 before obtaining a French release on 4 July 1949, where it became a great public success, receiving the 1950 [[Le Grand prix du cinéma français]]. The film was intended to be the first French feature film shot in colour; Tati simultaneously shot the film in black and white as an insurance policy. The newly developed Thomson colour system proved impractical, as it could not deliver colour prints. ''Jour de fête'' was therefore released only in black and white. Unlike his later films, it has many scenes with dialogue, and offers a droll, affectionate view of life in rural France. The colour version was restored by his younger daughter, film editor and director Sophie Tatischeff, and released in 1995. The film won the Prize for Best Original Script at the [[Venice Film Festival]].

===''Les Vacances de Monsieur Hulot (Monsieur Hulot's Holiday)''===
Tati's second film, ''[[Les Vacances de Monsieur Hulot]]'' (Monsieur Hulot's Holiday), was released in 1953. ''Les Vacances'' introduced the character of Mr. Hulot and follows his adventures in France during the mandatory August vacation at a beach resort, lampooning several hidebound elements of French political and social classes. It was shot almost entirely in the tiny west-coast seaside village of [[Saint-Marc-sur-Mer]] in the [[Loire Atlantique]] region. The hotel in which Mr. Hulot stays (l'Hôtel de la Plage) is still there,&lt;ref&gt;[http://book.bestwestern.com/bestwestern/productInfo.do?propertyCode=93667 "l'Hotel de la Plage"]&lt;/ref&gt; and a statue memorialising the director has been erected on the beach.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news| url=https://www.theguardian.com/travel/2010/apr/24/france-jacques-tati-seaside-beach | location=London | work=The Guardian | first=Michael | last=Simkins | title=Happy vacances: Jacques Tati's France | date=24 April 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; Tati had fallen in love with the coast while staying in nearby Port Charlotte with his friends, Mr. and Mrs. Lemoine, before the war, and resolved to return one day to make a film there.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.annuaire-mairie.fr/info-departement-loire-atlantique-44.html|title=le département de la Loire|website=Annuaire-Mairie|accessdate=23 May 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt; The film was widely praised by critics, and earned Tati an [[Academy Awards|Academy Award]] nomination for [[Academy Award for Writing Original Screenplay|Best Original Screenplay]], which was shared with [[Henri Marquet]]. Production of the movie would also see the reintroduction of Jacques Lagrange into Tati's life, beginning a lifelong working partnership with the painter, who would become his set designer. Les Vacances de Monsieur Hulot remains one of the best-loved French films of that period. The film's comic influence has extended well beyond France and can be found as recently as 2007 in the [[Rowan Atkinson]] comic vehicle ''[[Mr. Bean's Holiday]]''.&lt;ref&gt;[http://uk.rottentomatoes.com/m/mr_beans_holiday/articles/1670498/mr_beans_holiday_is_a_jolly_day_at_the_beach R ''Mr Bean's Holiday'']{{dead link|date=September 2017 |bot=InternetArchiveBot |fix-attempted=yes }}&lt;/ref&gt;

[[André Bazin]], founder of the influential journal ''[[Cahiers du cinéma]]'', wrote in his 1957 essay, "Fifteen Years of French Cinema", that,

&lt;blockquote&gt;"Tati could easily have made lots of money with sequels featuring his comic character of the little rural mailman. He chose instead to wait for four years, and, after much reflection, he revised his formula completely. The result this time was an extraordinary masterpiece about which one can say, I think, that it is the most radical innovation in comic cinema since the Marx Brothers: I am referring, of course, to ''Les Vacances de M. Hulot''."&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.brightlightsfilm.com/64/64bazinfrenchcinema.php''|title=André Bazin: Fifteen Years of French Cinema 1957|website=brightlightsfilm.com|accessdate=23 May 2017}}{{dead link|date=January 2018 |bot=InternetArchiveBot |fix-attempted=yes }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

Various problems would delay the release of Tati's follow-up to his international hit. In 1955 he suffered a serious car accident that physically impaired his left hand. Then a dispute with Fred Orain ensued and Tati broke away from Cady Films to create his own production company, Spectra Films, in 1956.

===''Mon Oncle (My Uncle)''===
Tati's next film, 1958's ''[[Mon Oncle]]'' (''My Uncle''), was his first film to be released in colour. The plot centers on Mr. Hulot's comedic, quixotic and childlike struggle with postwar France's obsession with modernity and American-style consumerism, entwined with the relationship he has with his nine-year-old nephew Gérard. ''Mon Oncle'' quickly became an international success, and won that year's [[Academy Award for Best Foreign Language Film]], a [[Jury Prize (Cannes Festival)|Special Prize]] at [[Cannes Film Festival|Cannes]], as well as the [[New York Film Critics Circle Awards|New York Film Critics Award]]. In Place de la Pelouse ([[Saint-Maur-des-Fossés]]) stands a bronze statue of Tati as Monsieur Hulot talking to a boy, in a pose echoing the movie's poster designed by [[Pierre Étaix]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://translate.google.com/translate?hl=en&amp;sl=fr&amp;u=http://regis.moulu.free.fr/Tati.htm&amp;ei=yAYdTZ_XHYGqsAOK8qG4Ag&amp;sa=X&amp;oi=translate&amp;ct=result&amp;resnum=6&amp;sqi=2&amp;ved=0CEMQ7gEwBQ&amp;prev=/search?q=jacques+tati+statue+saint+maur&amp;hl=en&amp;client=firefox-a&amp;rls=org.mozilla:en-US:official&amp;prmd=ivnso|title=Google Translate|website=translate.google.com|accessdate=23 May 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt;

On receiving his Oscar, Tati was offered any treat that the Academy could bestow on him. To their surprise, Tati simply requested the opportunity to visit [[Stan Laurel]], [[Mack Sennett]] and [[Buster Keaton]] at their nursing homes. Keaton reportedly said that Tati's work with sound had carried on the true tradition of silent cinema.&lt;ref&gt;{{harvsp|Bellos|1999|p=226}}, " The Old World and the New ".&lt;/ref&gt;

As guest artistic director at [[American Film Institute|AFI]] FEST 2010, [[David Lynch]] selected Tati's ''Mon Oncle'' alongside ''[[Hour of the Wolf]]'' (Dir [[Ingmar Bergman]]), ''[[Lolita (1962 film)|Lolita]]'' (Dir [[Stanley Kubrick]]), ''[[Rear Window]]'' (Dir [[Alfred Hitchcock]]) and ''[[Sunset Boulevard (film)|Sunset Boulevard]]'' (Dir [[Billy Wilder]]) to be screened in his sidebar program, explaining that,

&lt;blockquote&gt;"I picked these particular films because they are the ones that have inspired me most. I think each is a masterpiece."&lt;ref&gt;{{citation|url=http://blog.afi.com/afifest/index.php/2010/10/25/films-selected-david-lynch/ |title=Films Selected by David Lynch |deadurl=yes |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20120324060604/http://blog.afi.com/afifest/index.php/2010/10/25/films-selected-david-lynch/ |archivedate=24 March 2012 |df= }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

Of Tati, Lynch would add in a conversation with [[Jonathan Rosenbaum]], "You know, I feel like in a way he's a kindred soul... That guy is so creative, it's unbelievable. I think he's one of the all-time greats."&lt;ref name="Rosenbaum"&gt;{{citation |url=http://www.jonathanrosenbaum.net/?p=16206&lt;/|title= Tati's Influence on David Lynch |last=Rosenbaum|first=Jonathan|date=22 July 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===''Play Time''===
Considered by many his masterpiece, ''[[Play Time]]'' (1967), shot in [[70mm]], was to be the most ambitious yet risky and expensive work of Tati's career. "After the success of Mon Oncle in 1958, Jacques Tati had become fed up with Monsieur Hulot, his signature comic creation. With international renown came a growing dissatisfaction with straightforward scenarios centered around one lovable, recognizable figure. So he slowly inched his way toward a new kind of film, a supremely democratic film that would be about "everybody".&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.criterion.com/current/posts/115-playtime,|title=Playtime|website=criterion.com|accessdate=23 May 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt; It took nine years to make, and he had to borrow heavily from his own resources to complete the picture. "At the time of its making, ''Playtime'' (1967) was the most expensive film in French history."&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.ebertfest.com/seven/playtime.htm|title="Roger Ebert, Ebertfest, Playtime"|website=ebertfest.com|accessdate=23 May 2017|deadurl=yes|archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20160317141508/http://ebertfest.com/seven/playtime.htm|archivedate=17 March 2016|df=dmy-all}}&lt;/ref&gt; "Playtime is the big leap, the big screen. I'm putting myself on the line. Either it comes off or it doesn't. There's no safety net." On the outskirts of Paris, Tati famously built an entire glass and steel mini-city (nicknamed Tativille) for the film, which took years to build and left him mired in debt.

In the film, Hulot and a group of American tourists lose themselves in the futuristic glass and steel of commercially globalised modern Parisian suburbs, where only human nature and a few reflective views of the old city of Paris, itself, still emerge to breathe life into the sterile new metropolis. ''Play Time'' had even less of a plot than his earlier films, and Tati endeavored to make his characters, including Hulot, almost incidental to his portrayal of a modernist and robotic Paris. ''Play Time'' was originally 155 minutes in length, but Tati soon released an edited version of 126 minutes, and this is the version that became a general theatre release in 1967. Later versions appeared in 35mm format. In 1979, a copy of the film was revised again to 108 minutes, and this re-edited version was released on VHS video in 1984. Though ''Play Time'' was a critical success ([[François Truffaut]] praised it as "a film that comes from another planet, where they make films differently"), it was a massive and expensive commercial failure, eventually resulting in Tati's bankruptcy. "Tati had approached everybody from [[Darryl F Zanuck]] to the prime minister [[Georges Pompidou]] in a bid to get the movie completed. His personal overdrafts began to mount, and long before Playtime was finished," Bellos notes, "Tati was in substantial debt to the least forgiving of all creditors, the Collectors of Taxes." When he failed to pay off his loans, his films were impounded by the banks".&lt;ref name="The Guardian Tati for Now"&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.theguardian.com/culture/2002/may/21/artsfeatures.cannes2002|title=Tati for now|first=Geoffrey|last=Macnab|date=21 May 2002|publisher=|accessdate=23 May 2017|via=The Guardian}}&lt;/ref&gt; Tati was forced to sell the family house of Saint-Germain shortly after the death of his mother, Claire Van Hoof, and move back into Paris. Spectra Films was then placed into administration, concluding in the liquidation of the company in 1974, with an auction of all movie rights held by the company for little more than 120,000 francs.

In 1969, with reduced means, Jacques Tati created a new production company, CEPEC, to oversee his opportunities in movie and TV production.

====Spin-offs of ''Play Time''====
While on the set of ''Play Time'', Tati made a short film about his comedic and cinematic technique, ''[[Cours du soir]]'' (''Evening Classes'', 1967), in which Tati gives a lesson in the art of comedy to a class of would-be actors.

In 1971 Tati "''Suffered the indignity of having to make an advert for [[Lloyds Bank (historic)|Lloyds Bank]] in England''"&lt;ref name="The Guardian Tati for Now"/&gt; in which he depicted the bank of the future as being dehumanized with money dispensed from a computerized counter. "''The message of the advert was that however modern Lloyds are, technology isn't everything and you'll always be able to speak to a "friendly member of staff or understanding manager" in their branches''".&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://money-watch.co.uk/8078/bank-of-the-future-in-1971|title=Bank Of The Future (In 1971)|date=15 February 2011|website=money-watch.co.uk|accessdate=23 May 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt;

====Reception====
In August 2012 the [[British Film Institute]], polled 846 critics, programmers, academics and distributors to find "The Top 50 Greatest Films of All Time" and ''Play Time'' was voted 42nd in the list&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.bfi.org.uk/news/50-greatest-films-all-time|title=The 50 Greatest Films of All Time - Sight &amp; Sound|website=bfi.org.uk|accessdate=23 May 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt; In the corresponding "Directors Poll" by the BFI, Playtime was awarded the accolade of being seen as the 37th greatest film of all time by his fellow directors.

[[Steven Spielberg]] has said he was paying a "very slight homage" to ''Play Time'' in his 2004 film ''[[The Terminal]]'',&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.ew.com/ew/article/0,,613634,00.html|title=''The Terminal'' is a summer movie we can't wait to see|date=21 April 2004|website=ew.com|accessdate=23 May 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt; adding, "I thought of two directors when I made Terminal. I thought this was a tribute to [[Frank Capra]] and his honest sentiment, and it was a tribute to Jacques Tati and the way he allowed his scenes to go on and on and on. The character he played in ''Monsieur Hulot's Holiday'' and ''Mon Oncle'' was all about resourcefulness and using what's around him to make us laugh".&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.dga.org/Craft/DGAQ/All-Articles/0604-Winter2006-07/DGA-Interview-Steven-Spielberg.aspx|title=Age &amp; Innocence - Steven Spielberg|website=www.dga.org|accessdate=23 May 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===''Trafic (Traffic)''===
The Dutch-funded ''[[Trafic]]'' (''Traffic''), although originally designed to be a TV movie, received a theater release in 1971 and placed Monsieur Hulot back at the centre of the action.  It was the last Hulot film, and followed the vein of earlier works that lampooned modern society. In the film, Hulot is a bumbling automobile inventor traveling to an exhibition in a gadget-filled recreational vehicle. Despite its modest budget, Trafic was still very much a Tati film, carefully staged and choreographed in its scenes and effects.

===''Parade''===
Tati's last completed film, ''[[Parade (1974 film)|Parade]]'', a film produced for Swedish television in 1973, is more or less a filmed circus performance featuring Tati's mime acts and other performers.

===''Forza Bastia''===
In 1978, Tati began filming a short documentary on [[Corsica]]n football team [[SC Bastia]] playing the [[1977–78 UEFA Cup|UEFA Cup Final]], "[[Forza Bastia]]", which he did not complete. His younger daughter, Sophie Tatischeff, later edited the remaining footage, which was released in 2002 after her own death from lung cancer in 2001.

===Unmade films===
====''Confusion''====
Before his death Tati had plans for at least one more film. ''Confusion'', a planned collaboration with pop duo [[Sparks (band)|Sparks]], was a story about a futuristic city (Paris) where activity is centred around television, communication, advertising, and modern society's infatuation with visual imagery.

In the original script an aging Mr. Hulot was slated to be accidentally killed on-air. [[Ron Mael]] and [[Russell Mael]] would have played two American TV studio employees brought to a rural French TV company to help them out with some American technical expertise and input into how TV is really done.  While the script still exists, ''Confusion'' was never filmed.  What would have been its title track, "Confusion", appears on Sparks' 1976 ''[[Big Beat (album)|Big Beat]]'' album with the internal sleeve of its 2006 re-mastered CD featuring a letter announcing the pending collaboration, as well as a photo of the Mael brothers in conversation with Tati.&lt;ref name="Galliano"&gt;{{cite news|url=http://entertainment.timesonline.co.uk/tol/arts_and_entertainment/music/classical/article6895801.ece|title=Striking Sparks with Bergman – The Mael brothers' new album takes a poke at Hollywood|last=Galliano|first=Joseph|date=30 October 2009|work=The Times|accessdate=24 April 2010 | location=London}}&lt;/ref&gt;

====Film Tati No. 4, ''The Illusionist''====

Catalogued in the CNC (Centre National de la Cinématographie) archives under the title 'Film Tati Nº 4',&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.sonyclassics.com/theillusionist/presskit.pdf|title=Sony Classics, The Illusionist presskit"|website=sonyclassics.com|accessdate=23 May 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt; written in the late 1950s, the treatment was to have been the follow-up to Tati's internationally successful ''Mon Oncle''. It tells the bittersweet tale of a modestly talented magician – referred to only as the Illusionist – who, during a tour of decaying music halls in Eastern Europe, protectively takes an impoverished young woman under his wing.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.nytimes.com/2010/10/31/movies/31kehr.html|title=Sylvain Chomet’s ‘Illusionist’ Uses Scenario by Jacques Tati|first=Dave|last=Kehr|date=29 October 2010|publisher=|accessdate=23 May 2017|via=NYTimes.com}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The semi-autobiographical script that Tati wrote in 1956 was released internationally as an animated film, ''[[The Illusionist (2010 film)|The Illusionist]]'', in 2010.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news| url=http://entertainment.timesonline.co.uk/tol/arts_and_entertainment/film/article1380045.ece | location=London | work=The Times | title=Cut the cute | date=17 February 2007 | first1=Fiona | last1=Hamilton | first2=Sam | last2=Coates | first3=Michael | last3=Savage}}&lt;/ref&gt; Directed by [[Sylvain Chomet]], known for ''[[The Triplets of Belleville]]'', the main character is an animated caricature of Tati himself.

Controversy dogged the release of ''The Illusionist'',&lt;ref name="blogs.suntimes.com"/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[https://www.telegraph.co.uk/culture/film/film-news/7833404/Jacques-Tatis-ode-to-his-illegitimate-daughter.html "Jacques Tatis ode to his illegitimate daughter".  2010-06-16  ''Daily Telegraph'']. Accessed 2010-08-19&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.timeout.com/film/features/show-feature/10454/sylvain-chomet-the-trials-of-making-the-illusionist.html  "Sylvain Chomet: the trials of making "''The Illusionist''"''Time Out'' Magazine]. Accessed 2010-08-19&lt;/ref&gt; ''with [[The Guardian]]'' reporting:
&lt;blockquote&gt;In 2000, the screenplay was handed over to Chomet by Tati's daughter, Sophie, two years before her death. Now, however, the family of Tati's illegitimate and estranged eldest child, Helga Marie-Jeanne Schiel, who lives in the north-east of England, are calling for the French director to give her credit as the true inspiration for the film. The script of ''L'illusionniste'', they say, was Tati's response to the shame of having abandoned his first child [Schiel] and it remains the only public recognition of her existence. They accuse Chomet of attempting to airbrush out their painful family legacy again.&lt;ref&gt;[https://www.theguardian.com/world/2010/jan/31/jacques-tati-lost-film-family-illusionniste "Jacques Tati's lost film reveals family's pain". ''Guardian'' article 2010-01-31.]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

Tati's former colleagues at the Lido de Paris were appalled at his caddish behaviour and shunned him. As a result, he moved first to Berlin then to the village of [[Sainte-Sévère-sur-Indre]], which later inspired his hugely successful film, ''Jour de Fête''.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news| url=http://www.independent.ie/entertainment/film-cinema/illusions-of-grandeur-2306371.html | work=Irish Independent | title=Illusions of grandeur | date=21 August 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.nonfiction.fr/article-807-la_posterite_de_m_hulot.htm|title=La postérité de M. Hulot|website=nonfiction.fr|accessdate=23 May 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Personal life==
At the Lido de Paris he met and fell in love with the young Austrian/[[Czech people|Czech]] dancer Herta Schiel, who had fled Vienna with her sister Molly at the time of the [[Anschluss]]. In the summer of 1942 Herta gave birth to their daughter, Helga Marie-Jeanne Schiel. Due to pressure from his sister Nathalie, Tati refused to recognise the child and was forced by Volterra to depart from the Lido at the end of the 1942 season.&lt;ref name="Nonfiction"&gt;David Bellos, " [http://www.nonfiction.fr/article-807-la_posterite_de_m_hulot.htm La postérité de M. Hulot] ", sur ''non-fiction'', 25 mars 2008.&lt;/ref&gt; In 1943, after a short engagement at the ABC,&lt;ref name=ABC /&gt; where [[Édith Piaf]] was headlining, Tati left Paris under a cloud, with his friend [[Henri Marquet]], and they settled in the Village of [[Sainte-Sévère-sur-Indre]]. While residing there they completed the script for ''[[L'École des facteurs]]'' (''The School for Postmen'') that would later provide material for his first feature, ''[[Jour de fête]]''.

Herta Schiel would remain in Paris throughout the war, where she would make acquaintance with the physician [[Jacques Weil]] when he was called upon to treat her sister Molly for the then-incurable [[tuberculosis]] (TB). Through Weil, second in command of the Juggler network of the [[SOE F Section networks]], both sisters were recruited into the [[French Resistance]].&lt;ref name="blogs.suntimes.com"&gt;[http://blogs.suntimes.com/ebert/pages-for-twitter/the-shame-of-jacques-tati.html''Roger Ebert's Journal''; "The secret of Jacques Tati" 2010-05]. Accessed 2010-08-19  {{webarchive|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20100531154045/http://blogs.suntimes.com/ebert/pages-for-twitter/the-shame-of-jacques-tati.html |date=31 May 2010 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

In 1944, Tati returned to Paris and, after a brief courtship, married Micheline Winter.

On 23 October 1946 Tati's second child was born, [[Sophie Tatischeff|Sophie Catherine Tatischeff]].

1949 was the year of the birth of Tati's son, Pierre-François Tatischeff, also known as Pierre Tati. Both Pierre and Sophie would go on to work in the French film industry in various capacities, beginning in the early 1970s.  Notably, they both worked on [[Jean-Pierre Melville]]'s last film, ''[[Un flic]]'' (1972).

==Death==
Weakened by serious health problems, Tati died on 4 November 1982, of a pulmonary embolism, leaving a final scenario called ''Confusion'' that he had completed with Jacques Lagrange.

In ''[[Paris Match]]'', [[Philippe Labro]] reported the death of Jacques Tati under the heading,
"Adieu Monsieur Hulot. On le pleure mort, il aurait fallu l'aider vivant !" ("Goodbye, Monsieur Hulot. In death we cry, in life we did not help!")&lt;ref&gt;''[[Paris Match]]'', 19 novembre 1982, no. 1747.&lt;/ref&gt;

== Legacy ==
=== ''Les Films de Mon Oncle'' ===
During the 1980s, concerned that their father's legacy would be permanently lost, Pierre and Sophie Tatischeff tracked the rights to their father's ''oeuvre'' to a bank in Switzerland. The bank, unable to trace the owner who had made the deposit, eventually returned the rights to Pierre and Sophie as heirs to their father's estate.{{Clarify|date=March 2017}}

In 1995 after a year of meticulous work, Sophie with the aid of film technician Francois Ede was able for the first time to release a colour print of ''Jour de Fete'' as Tati had originally intended.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.jonathanrosenbaum.net/1998/01/jour-de-fete/|title=Jour de fete - Jonathan Rosenbaum|website=www.jonathanrosenbaum.net|accessdate=23 May 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Having lost her brother Pierre to a traffic accident and having herself been diagnosed terminally ill, Sophie Tatischeff took the initiative to set up Les Films de Mon Oncle in 2001 to preserve, restore, and circulate the work of Jacques Tati. Enrolling the service of [[Jérôme Deschamps]], the artistic and cultural mission of Les Films de Mon Oncle is to allow audiences as well as researchers to (re-)discover the work of Tati the filmmaker, his archives, and to ensure its influence around the world.

The restoration of ''PlayTime'' began in 1998 when Sophie Tatischeff made the acquaintance of Jean-Rene Failot, technical director of the [[Gulliver Arane]], the only remaining large-format film laboratory in Europe.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://in70mm.com/news/2004/playtime/index.htm|title=The restoration of "Play Time"|website=in70mm.com|accessdate=23 May 2017|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20170509185154/http://www.in70mm.com/news/2004/playtime/index.htm|archive-date=9 May 2017|dead-url=yes|df=dmy-all}}&lt;/ref&gt; Because of difficulties acquiring appropriate funding, the restored version of ''PlayTime'' was not presented until 2002 at the 55th Cannes Film Festival, eight months after the death of Sophie Tatischeff. In 2004, Les Films de Mon Oncle completed the restoration of ''My Uncle'', the English version of ''Mon Oncle''. This was followed by demanding editorial work for the DVDs of these films including original bonuses and a double CD titled ''Tati Sonorama!'' with the complete collection of film scores and soundtrack clips.

In 2009 the partner of Deschamps, Macha Makeïeff, designed the exhibition "{{Lang|fr|Jacques Tati, deux temps, trois mouvements}}" at the [[Cinémathèque Française]] in Paris, for which she is co-curator along with [[:fr:Stéphane Goudet|Stephane Goudet]], and installed the full-scale mythical Villa Arpel, the set of ''Mon Oncle'' created by Jacques Tati and his friend [[:fr:Jacques Lagrange (peintre)|Jacques Lagrange]], at the 104 (Paris, 19th arrondissement).

In 2014 Les Films de Mon Oncle formed a partnership with ''[[StudioCanal]]'', entitled ''[[Vivendi]]'', who now oversee international distribution of the oeuvre of Jacques Tati, having released digitally restored versions of all his short and long films as boxsets in both DVD and Blu-Ray.

==Filmography==
{| class="wikitable sortable" style="text-align:center"
|-
! width="33" | Year !!  Title !! width=65 | Director !! width=65 | Screenwriter !! Actor !! Role !! Notes
|-
| 1932
| style="text-align:left"| ''Oscar, champion de tennis''
|
|
| {{yes}}
| Oscar
| Short film
|-
| 1934
| style="text-align:left"| ''On demande une brute''
|
| {{yes}}
| {{yes}}
| Roustabat
| Short film
|-
| 1935
| style="text-align:left"| ''[[Gai dimanche]]''
| {{yes}}
| {{yes}}
| {{yes}}
| {{unknown}}
| Short film&lt;br/&gt;Co-directed with Jacques Berr
|-
| 1936
| style="text-align:left"| ''Soigne ton gauche''
|
| {{yes}}
| {{yes}}
| Roger
| Short film
|-
| 1938
| style="text-align:left"| ''Retour à la terre''
|
| {{yes}}
| {{yes}}
| {{unknown}}
| Short film
|-
| 1946
| style="text-align:left"| ''[[Sylvie et le fantôme]]''&lt;br/&gt;(''Sylvie and the Ghost'')
|
|
| {{yes}}
| The Ghost of Alain de Francigny
|
|-
| 1947
| style="text-align:left"| ''[[L'École des facteurs]]''&lt;br/&gt;(''School for Postmen'')
| {{yes}}
| {{yes}}
| {{yes}}
| Postman
|Short film
|-
| 1947
| style="text-align:left"| ''[[Le Diable au corps (1947 film)|Le Diable au corps]]''&lt;br/&gt;(''Devil in the Flesh'')
|
|
| {{yes}}
| Officer at bar
|
|-
| 1949
| style="text-align:left"| ''[[Jour de fête]]''&lt;br/&gt;(''The Big Day'')
| {{yes}}
| {{yes}}
| {{yes}}
| François, the postman
|
|-
| 1953
| style="text-align:left"| ''[[Les Vacances de M. Hulot]]''&lt;br/&gt;(''Monsieur Hulot's Holiday'')
| {{yes}}
| {{yes}}
| {{yes}}
| [[Monsieur Hulot]]
|Also uncredited producer
|-
| 1958
| style="text-align:left"| ''[[Mon oncle]]''&lt;br/&gt;(''My Uncle'')
| {{yes}}
| {{yes}}
| {{yes}}
| Monsieur Hulot
|Also producer
|-
| 1967
| style="text-align:left"| ''[[Play Time]]''
| {{yes}}
| {{yes}}
| {{yes}}
| Monsieur Hulot
|
|-
| 1967
| style="text-align:left"| ''[[Cours du soir]]''&lt;br/&gt;(''Evening Classes'')
|
| {{yes}}
| {{yes}}
| Monsieur Hulot
|Short film
|-
| 1971
| style="text-align:left"| ''[[Trafic]]'' (''Traffic'')
| {{yes}}
| {{yes}}
| {{yes}}
| Monsieur Hulot
|Also uncredited editor
|-
| 1972
| style="text-align:left"| ''Obraz uz obraz''
|
|
| {{yes}}
| Zak
|Episode: "1.5"
|-
| 1974
| style="text-align:left"| ''[[Parade (1974 film)|Parade]]''
| {{yes}}
| {{yes}}
| {{yes}}
| Circus performer
|
|-
| 1978
| style="text-align:left"| ''[[Forza Bastia]]''
| {{yes}}
| {{yes}}
|
|
|Documentary short
|-
| 2010
| style="text-align:left"| ''[[The Illusionist (2010 film)|The Illusionist]]''
|
| {{yes}}
|
|
|Original screenplay only
|-
|}

==Awards==
* Cannes festival 1958: Grand prix for ''Mon Oncle''&lt;ref name="festival-cannes.com"&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.festival-cannes.com/en/archives/ficheFilm/id/3482/year/1958.html |title=Festival de Cannes: Mon Oncle |accessdate=2009-02-10|work=festival-cannes.com}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* [[31st Academy Awards|Academy Awards 1958]]: Best Foreign Language Film for ''Mon Oncle''&lt;ref name="Oscars1959"&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://www.oscars.org/oscars/ceremonies/1959 |title=The 31st Academy Awards (1959) Nominees and Winners |accessdate=2011-10-27|work=oscars.org}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* [[6th Moscow International Film Festival]], Silver Prize for ''[[Playtime]]''.&lt;ref name="Moscow1969"&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.moscowfilmfestival.ru/miff34/eng/archives/?year=1969 |title=6th Moscow International Film Festival (1969) |accessdate=2012-12-17 |work=MIFF |deadurl=yes |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20130116194825/http://www.moscowfilmfestival.ru/miff34/eng/archives/?year=1969 |archivedate=16 January 2013 |df= }}&lt;/ref&gt;
* In 1977, he received an honorary ''[[César Award|César]]'' from the French Film Institute for his lifetime contribution to cinema.

==References==
{{Reflist|30em}}

==External links==
{{Commons category}}
*{{IMDb name|0004244|Jacques Tati}}
*[http://www.lib.berkeley.edu/MRC/frenchbib.html#tati Tati Bibliography] via UC Berkeley
*[http://www.tativille.com/ The Official Jacques Tati website]
*[http://filmsdefrance.com/FDF_jtati.html Jacques Tati profile at FilmsdeFrance.com]
*[http://graphikdesigns.free.fr/jacques-tati-confusion.html "Confusion" Jacques Tati's unfinished film]
*[http://www.villagevoice.com/2009-12-15/film/jacques-tati-retro-at-moma/ Museum of Modern Art retrospective] in the Village Voice
*[https://www.telegraph.co.uk/culture/film/film-news/7833404/Jacques-Tatis-ode-to-his-illegitimate-daughter.html Jacques Tati's ode to his illegitimate daughter, The Telegraph, 16 June 2010]

{{Jacques Tati}}
{{AcademyAwardBestForeignLanguageFilm 1947–1960}}
{{Honorary César}}

{{Authority control}}
{{Use dmy dates|date=May 2017}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Tati, Jacques}}
[[Category:Jacques Tati| ]]
[[Category:1907 births]]
[[Category:1982 deaths]]
[[Category:People from Le Pecq]]
[[Category:French people of Russian descent]]
[[Category:French people of Dutch descent]]
[[Category:French people of Italian descent]]
[[Category:French comedians]]
[[Category:French male film actors]]
[[Category:French male television actors]]
[[Category:French film directors]]
[[Category:French satirists]]
[[Category:French mimes]]
[[Category:Rurikids]]
[[Category:20th-century French male actors]]
[[Category:Male actors of Italian descent]]
[[Category:Directors of Best Foreign Language Film Academy Award winners]]</text>
      <sha1>0gq1v35vzxyyom12y1kjndeqt8lg9fu</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
