<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10.xsd" version="0.10" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <dbname>enwiki</dbname>
    <base>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.32.0-wmf.16</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="118" case="first-letter">Draft</namespace>
      <namespace key="119" case="first-letter">Draft talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2300" case="first-letter">Gadget</namespace>
      <namespace key="2301" case="first-letter">Gadget talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2302" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition</namespace>
      <namespace key="2303" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Jim Varney</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>255887</id>
    <revision>
      <id>856047057</id>
      <parentid>856042304</parentid>
      <timestamp>2018-08-22T14:09:24Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Dimadick</username>
        <id>24198</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>Reverted changes in dates</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="25860">{{Use mdy dates|date=October 2016}}
{{Infobox person
| name        = Jim Varney
| image       = Jim Varney.jpg
| alt         =
| caption     = Varney in the film ''The Expert'' (1995)
| birth_name  = James Albert Varney Jr.
| birth_date  = {{Birth date|1949|06|15}}
| birth_place = [[Lexington, Kentucky]], U.S.
| death_date  = {{Death date and age|2000|02|10|1949|06|15}}
| death_place = [[White House, Tennessee]], U.S.
| resting_place = [[Lexington Cemetery]]
| occupation  = Actor, comedian, writer
| years_active = 1976–2000
| known_for = {{plainlist|
*[[Ernest P. Worrell]] in the ''Ernest'' film series
*[[List of Toy Story characters#Slinky Dog|Slinky Dog]] from the [[Toy Story (franchise)|''Toy Story'' franchise]]
}}
| spouse= {{marriage|Jacqueline Drew|1977|1983|reason=divorced}}&lt;br/&gt;{{marriage|Jane Varney|1988|1991|reason=divorced}}
}}

{{COI|date=February 2018}}

'''James Albert Varney Jr.''' (June 15, 1949&amp;nbsp;– February 10, 2000) was an American actor, comedian, and writer. He is best known for his role as [[Ernest P. Worrell]], who was used in numerous television commercial advertising campaigns and films&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|title= Ernest P. Gets Rich With Vern|work= Sun Sentinel|date=|url= http://articles.sun-sentinel.com/1985-07-07/entertainment/8501270652_1_ernest-p-worrell-dr-otto-talks|accessdate=October 6, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="auto"&gt;{{cite news|title=Jim Varney; Comedic Actor Played Rube Ernest P. Worrell in Commercials, Movies|work= Los Angeles Times|date=February 11, 2000|url=http://articles.latimes.com/2000/feb/11/news/mn-63437|accessdate=October 6, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="auto1"&gt;{{cite news|title=Jim Varney, 50, Who Turned 'Ernest' Character into a Career|work=New York Times|date=February 11, 2000|url=https://www.nytimes.com/2000/02/11/arts/jim-varney-50-who-turned-ernest-character-into-a-career.html|accessdate=October 6, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; and a [[Daytime Emmy Award]]. He gained further notability for playing [[The Beverly Hillbillies#J.D. "Jed" Clampett|Jed Clampett]] in the film version of ''[[The Beverly Hillbillies (film)|The Beverly Hillbillies]]'' (1993) and providing the voice of [[List of Toy Story characters#Slinky Dog|Slinky Dog]] in ''[[Toy Story]]'' (1995) and ''[[Toy Story 2]]'' (1999).

==Early life==
Varney was born in [[Lexington, Kentucky]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.biography.com/people/jim-varney-9542369|title=Jim Varney Biography; Film Actor, Television Actor, Comedian (1949–2000)|website=biography.com|accessdate=April 12, 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt; As a child, he displayed the ability to memorize long poems and significant portions of the material from books, which he used to entertain family and friends. When Varney was a boy, his mother would turn on cartoons for him to watch. His mother discovered that Varney quickly began to imitate the cartoon characters, so she started him in children's theater when he was eight years old. Varney began his interest in theater as a teenager, winning state titles in drama competitions while a student at Lafayette High School&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=1967 Lafayette High Yearbook|url=http://www.classmates.com/yearbooks/Lafayette-High-School/124898?page=132|website=classmates.com|accessdate=July 28, 2014}}&lt;/ref&gt; (class of 1968) in Lexington. 

At the age of fifteen, he portrayed [[Ebenezer Scrooge]] in a local theater production, and by 17, he was performing professionally in [[nightclub]]s and coffee houses. Varney studied [[Shakespeare]] at the [[Barter Theatre]] in Abingdon, Virginia, and performed in an [[Opryland USA|Opryland]] folk show in its first year of operation, in the 1970s. He listed a former teacher, Thelma Beeler, as being a mentor in his becoming an actor. When he was 24, Varney was an actor at the Pioneer Playhouse in [[Danville, Kentucky|Danville]], Kentucky. The theater was adjacent to an [[American frontier|Old West]]-themed village, and before the show, the audience would tour the village where apprentices would play townsfolk. Varney and the company usually played in the outdoor theater to audiences of only a few dozen people. He would regale the young apprentices by throwing knives into trees. He performed in ''[[Blithe Spirit (play)|Blithe Spirit]]'', ''Boeing 707'' and an original musical, ''Fire on the Mountain''. He once jokingly threatened a long-haired apprentice, John Lino Ponzini, that he would take him up to [[Hazard, Kentucky]], where he (Ponzini) wouldn't make it down Main Street without the townsfolk giving him a crewcut.&lt;ref name="auto1"/&gt;

==Career==
{{moresources|section|date=February 2018}}
===Television commercials===
In 1980, the first commercial featuring Varney as "Ernest" advertised an appearance by the [[Dallas Cowboys Cheerleaders]] at [[Beech Bend Park]], an [[amusement park]] located near [[Bowling Green, Kentucky]]. The character was franchised for use in markets all over the country and was often used by [[dairy|dairies]] to advertise milk products. For example, the dairy bar and hamburger chain [[Braum's]] ran several advertisements using Ernest's [[catchphrase]] (as it was spelled in his registered trademark), "KnoWhutImean, Vern?" [[Purity Dairies]], based in Nashville, Pine State Dairy in Raleigh, NC, and Oakhurst Dairy in Maine ran commercials that were nearly identical, but with the dairy name changed.{{Citation needed|date=September 2010}}

For the same agency, Varney created a different character, Sgt. Glory, a humorless [[drill instructor]] who harangued cows of the client dairy into producing better milk. In another spot, Sgt. Glory's home was shown as he had a date, which was so heavily decorated with the products of the sponsor and advertising specialty items that it was essentially devoid of any other decor. The Sgt. Glory character also appeared in an advertisement for a southern grocery chain, Pruitt's Food Town, in which he drilled the checkout clerks on proper behavior: "Bread on top. Repeat: Bread on top." He approaches one of them at the end of the commercial with a look of menace and says, "You're not smilin'." The checkout bagger gives a very nervous and forced smile.{{Citation needed|date=September 2010}}

Varney also starred as Ernest in a series of commercials that ran in the [[New Orleans]] area (and throughout the Gulf South) as a spokesman for natural gas utilities. In one, he is seen kneeling down in front of Vern's desk under a lamp hanging from the ceiling, stating, "Natural Gas, Vern; it's hot, fast, and cheap. Hot, fast, cheap; kinda like your first wife, Vern, you know, the pretty one!?" Vern then knocks the lamp into Ernest's head, knocking him down. Those same television advertisements also were featured on channels in the [[St. Louis, Missouri|St. Louis]] area for [[Laclede Gas Company]] during the mid-1980s and in the Metro Detroit area for Michigan Consolidated Gas Company. Another TV ad for Laclede Gas featured Ernest saying, "Heat pump, schmeat pump."{{Citation needed|date=September 2010}} 

Varney also appeared in several Braum's Ice Cream and Dairy Stores commercials throughout the 1980s. These aired on Oklahoma television. He made commercials for car dealerships across the country, most notably [[Cerritos Auto Square]] in [[Cerritos, California]], Tysons Toyota in [[Tysons Corner, Virginia]], and Audubon Chrysler in [[Henderson, Kentucky]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.ew.com/ew/article/0,,317162,00.html|work=Entertainment Weekly|first=Kathy|last=Kalafut|title=Hey, Vern, I'm a Star!!|date=April 13, 1990}}&lt;/ref&gt; 

Varney portrayed Ernest in a series of commercials for [[Convenient Food Mart]] during the 1980s. In 1982, Varney co-hosted the syndicated ''[[Pop! Goes the Country]]'' with singer [[Tom T. Hall]]. The show had just had a major overhaul and ended shortly afterward. He also portrayed "Auntie Nelda", in numerous commercials long before he resurrected the character for the movies. Dressed in drag and appears to be a senior citizen, the commercials gave off the tone of a motherly lady encouraging one to do what was right (in this case, buy whatever product was being promoted). This character, along with the "Ernest" character, ran for a couple of years in [[Mississippi]] and [[Louisiana]] in commercials for Leadco Aluminum Siding.&lt;ref&gt;{{YouTube|qhwKqq0j1S8|Auntie Nelda}}&lt;/ref&gt;

During the 1990s, Varney reprised his role as Ernest for [[Blake's Lotaburger]], a fast food chain in [[New Mexico]]. In these commercials, Ernest typically would be trying to get into Vern's house to see what food Vern was eating. After a lengthy description of whatever tasty morsel Vern had, Ernest would get locked out but would continue to shout from outside.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|title=Guess Who's Coming to Breakfast, Lunch and Dinner—Hey, Vern! It's Your Old Pal Jim Varney!|work=People|url=http://www.people.com/people/archive/article/0,,20092335,00.html|accessdate=October 6, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Ernest's popularity===
[[File:Jim Varney (handprints in cement).jpg|left|thumb|250px|Jim Varney's handprints, displayed at Disney]]
Varney's character [[Ernest P. Worrell|Ernest]] proved so popular that it was spun off into a TV series, ''[[Hey Vern, It's Ernest!]]'' (1988) and a series of movies in the 1980s and 1990s.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|title= The Character Curse: Actor, Role Seen As One|work=Orlando Sentinel|url=http://articles.orlandosentinel.com/1991-10-27/entertainment/9110251024_1_varney-ernest-p-batman|accessdate=October 6, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|title= Jim Varney Hopes Cards And Letters Keep Pouring in to Save Poor Ernest|work=Chicago Tribune|date=July 8, 1989|url=http://articles.chicagotribune.com/1989-07-08/entertainment/8902150724_1_jim-varney-ernest-vern|accessdate=October 6, 2010|first=Stephanie|last=Dubois}}&lt;/ref&gt;

''[[Ernest Goes to Camp]]'' (1987) was a huge hit, grossing $23.5&amp;nbsp;million at the U.S. box office, on a $3&amp;nbsp;million production budget, and staying in the Box Office Top 5 for its first three weeks of release. Though the film saw Varney nominated for the now-defunct [[Razzie Award for Worst New Star]], only one year later Varney earned the [[Daytime Emmy Award for Outstanding Performer in Children's Programming#Outstanding Performer in a Children's Series|Daytime Emmy Award for Outstanding Performer in a Children's Series]] for ''Hey Vern, It's Ernest!''{{cn|date=February 2018}}

The canon of theatrically released Ernest films also includes ''[[Ernest Saves Christmas]]'' (1988), ''[[Ernest Goes to Jail]]'' (1990), ''[[Ernest Scared Stupid]]'' (1991) and ''[[Ernest Rides Again]]'' (1993). After the financial failure of ''Ernest Rides Again'', all further films were released [[direct-to-video]]: ''[[Ernest Goes to School]]'' (1994), ''[[Slam Dunk Ernest]]'' (1995), ''[[Ernest Goes to Africa]]'' (1997) and ''[[Ernest in the Army]]'' (1998). 

The [[Walt Disney World|Walt Disney World Resort]]'s [[Epcot]] theme park featured Ernest. Epcot's [[Cranium Command]] attraction used the Ernest character in its pre-show as an example of a "lovable, but not the brightest person on the planet" type of person. And in addition to his ''Ernest Goes to...'' series, he starred as Ernest in several smaller movies for [[John R. Cherry III]], such as ''[[Knowhutimean? Hey Vern, It's My Family Album]]''; ''[[Dr. Otto and the Riddle of the Gloom Beam]]''; and the direct-to-video feature ''Your World as I See It'', all of which showcased his great facility with assuming a wide variety of characters and accents.{{cn|date=February 2018}}

''The Ernest Film Festival'' (a.k.a. Greatest Hits Volume 1) was released on V.H.S. in 1986. ''Greatest Hits Volume 2'' was released in 1992. [[Mill Creek Entertainment]] released these classic television commercials on DVD box sets October 31, 2006. [[Image Entertainment]] re-released them on June 5, 2012, as part of the DVD set ''Ernest's Wacky Adventures: Volume 1''.{{cn|date=February 2018}}

===Other roles===
{{Unreferenced section|date=September 2010}}
Varney had an established acting career before his fame as Ernest. In 1976, Varney was a regular cast member of the television show ''Johnny Cash and Friends''. He also played a recurring guest on the faux late-night talk show ''[[Fernwood 2 Night]]''. From 1977 to 1979, Varney was cast as Seaman "Doom &amp; Gloom" Broom in the television version of ''[[Operation Petticoat#1977 television series|Operation Petticoat]]''. Just prior to his stint as Ernest, he was a cast member on the notorious television flop ''[[Pink Lady (TV series)|Pink Lady and Jeff]]''.

From 1983 to 1984, Varney played heartthrob [[Chad Everett]]'s younger brother Evan Earp in the comedy-drama, high-action television series, ''[[The Rousters]]'', created by [[Stephen J. Cannell]], about the descendants of [[Wyatt Earp]], a family of bounty hunters/carnival bouncers. As Evan Earp, Varney played a con man/mechanical-inventor "genius," constantly getting himself into comedic trouble, with those around him ready to lynch him. Although the series was promising, the show failed after its first season because it was poorly slotted (four episodes every few months) against the number-one prime-time television series for the past six years, ''[[The Love Boat]]''.

Varney can be seen in [[Hank Williams Jr.]]'s video for "[[All My Rowdy Friends Are Coming Over Tonight]]", where he is briefly shown casually riding a bull being pulled on a rope by a young lady, and later in a swimming pool with two young ladies.

In 1985, Varney co-hosted [[HBO]]'s New Year's Eve special, along with [[Johnny Cash]] and [[Kris Kristofferson]]. Varney also starred as Jed Clampett in the 1993 production of ''[[The Beverly Hillbillies (film)|The Beverly Hillbillies]]'' and played Rex, a carnival worker/associate of [[Dennis Quaid]] in ''[[Wilder Napalm]]''. The latter story is about two pyrokinetic brothers, played by Quaid and [[Arliss Howard]], and as the accident-prone entertainer/watch guard (aka "safety guy/human torch") Rudy James in the movie ''[[Snowboard Academy]]''. He later played a small role in the 1995 action film ''[[The Expert (1995 film)|The Expert]]'' as a weapons dealer named Snake.

Varney also lent his voice to [[List of Toy Story characters#Slinky Dog|Slinky Dog]] in [[The Walt Disney Company|Disney]]/[[Pixar]]'s ''[[Toy Story]]'' and ''[[Toy Story 2]]'' in the [[Toy Story (franchise)|Toy Story series]] (Varney was replaced by [[Blake Clark]] in ''[[Toy Story 3]]'' due to his death in 2000). Varney played numerous other characters, including "Cookie" Farnsworth, from ''[[Atlantis: The Lost Empire]]'', released the year after his death ([[Steve Barr (actor)|Steve Barr]] replaced Varney for the sequel ''[[Atlantis: Milo's Return]]''), the [[carny]] character Cooter in the "[[Bart Carny]]" episode of ''[[The Simpsons]]'', the character Walt Evergreen in the ''[[Duckman]]'' episode "You've Come a Wrong Way, Baby", Prince Carlos Charmaine (a royal suitor Jackie dates) for a few episodes of the final season of the 1990s television series ''[[Roseanne]]'', and Lothar Zogg in the 1998 film ''[[3 Ninjas: High Noon at Mega Mountain]]'', also starring [[Hulk Hogan]] and [[Loni Anderson]].

Varney had a brief role as an incestuous, abusive father in an independent film, ''100 Proof'', for which he received good reviews from critics. He also played a rebel in the [[midnight movie]] ''Existo'', as well as an old mariner in a low-budget horror film, ''Blood, Friends, and Money''. During the filming of ''[[Treehouse Hostage]]'', he played an escaped convict held hostage and tormented by some 5th graders in a treehouse.

One of Varney's final films was [[Billy Bob Thornton]]'s ''[[Daddy and Them]]'', where he played Uncle Hazel, who had been arrested for murder. Co-stars included [[Kelly Preston]] and [[Andy Griffith]]. Another final guest appearance was the Bibleman Genesis Series ''Bibleman Jr. Volume 1 &amp; 2'' as himself. Varney starred in three videos, ''The Misadventures of Bubba'', ''The Misadventures of Bubba II'', and ''Bubba Goes Hunting'', in which he played himself and taught young kids important safety rules about hunting and guns. He illustrated the rules with the help of his bumbling and accident-prone cousin Bubba (also played by Varney) and Bubba's imaginary hunting pal, Billy Bob. The videos were distributed as part of a membership pack from Buckmasters' Young Bucks Club.

According to an interview, one of his final projects was writing a screenplay about the legendary [[Hatfield–McCoy feud|feud between the Hatfields and the McCoys]], stating that his grandfather hunted squirrel with the McCoys.

==Personal life==
Varney was married twice, first to Jacqueline Drew (1977–1983) and then to Jane Varney (1988–1991). Both marriages ended in divorce, although he remained friends with his ex-wife Jane until his death; she became Varney's spokeswoman and accompanied him in Pixar's 1999 film ''Toy Story 2''. Both unions were childless.

On December 6, 2013, Varney's nephew Justin Lloyd published a comprehensive biography about his uncle titled ''The Importance of Being Ernest: The Life of Actor Jim Varney (Stuff that Vern doesn't even know)''.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last=Lloyd|first=Justin|title=The Importance of Being Ernest: The Life of Actor Jim Varney|publisher=CreateSpace|ISBN=978-1-4927-4631-7|url=http://importanceofbeingernest.com/|deadurl=yes|archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20141217132952/http://importanceofbeingernest.com/|archivedate=December 17, 2014}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Illness and death==
During the filming of ''[[Treehouse Hostage]]'' in August 1998,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|title=The Importance of Being Ernest|last=Keel|first=Beverly|work=Nashville Scene|date=November 15, 1999|url=http://www.weeklywire.com/ww/11-15-99/nash_cover.html|accessdate=June 2, 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt; Varney started developing a bad cough, and was diagnosed with [[lung cancer]]. The disease slowly became worse, yet Varney continued to film movies. 

Varney finally returned to Tennessee, where he went through chemotherapy in the hope he could beat the disease. However, it failed, and he died on February 10, 2000, at his home in [[White House, Tennessee]], a city north of [[Nashville, Tennessee|Nashville]], at the age of 50. He was buried in [[Lexington Cemetery]] in Lexington, Kentucky.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|title=Actor Jim "Ernest" Varney dies at 50 |work=Salon |date= |url=http://www.salon.com/people/obit/2000/02/10/ernest/print.html |accessdate=October 6, 2010 |deadurl=yes |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20100918031619/http://www.salon.com/people/obit/2000/02/10/ernest/print.html |archivedate=September 18, 2010 |df= }}&lt;/ref&gt; Disney's ''[[Atlantis: The Lost Empire]]'', which was released a year after his death, was his final role. The film was dedicated to his memory.

== Filmography ==
===Film===
{|   class="wikitable shortable" style="font-size: 95%;"
|-   align="center"
! style="background: #B0C4DE;" | Year
! style="background: #B0C4DE;" | Title
! style="background: #B0C4DE;" | Role
! style="background: #B0C4DE;" | Notes
|-
|1982
| ''Spittin' Image''
| Sheriff
|
|-
| 1983
| ''[[Knowhutimean? Hey Vern, It's My Family Album]]''
| [[Ernest P. Worrell]] / Davy Worrell &amp; Company / Ace Worrell / Lloyd Worrell / Billy Boogie Worrell / Rhetch Worrell / Pop Worrell
|
|-
| rowspan=2|1986
| ''Ernest's Greatest Hits Volume 1'' (''The Ernest Film Festival'')
| Ernest P. Worrell
|
|-
| ''[[Dr. Otto and the Riddle of the Gloom Beam]]''
| Dr. Otto / Ernest P. Worrell / Rudd Hardtact / Laughin' Jack / Guy Dandy / Auntie Nelda
|
|-
| rowspan=2|1987
| ''[[Ernest Goes to Camp]]''
| Ernest P. Worrell
|
|-
| ''Hey Vern, Win $10,000...Or Just Count on Having Fun!''
| Ernest P. Worrell
|
|-
| 1988
|''[[Ernest Saves Christmas]]''
|  Ernest P. Worrell / Aster Clement / The Governor's Student / Auntie Nelda / Mrs. Brock / Marty's Mother / The Snake Guy
|
|-
| 1989
| ''[[Fast Food (film)|Fast Food]]''
| Wrangler Bob Bundy
|
|-
| 1990
|''[[Ernest Goes to Jail]]''
| Ernest P. Worrell / Felix Nash / Auntie Nelda
|
|-
| 1991
| ''[[Ernest Scared Stupid]]''
| Ernest P. Worrell / Phineas Worrell / Auntie Nelda / Various Relatives
|
|-
| 1992
| ''Ernest's Greatest Hits Volume 2''
| Ernest P. Worrell
|
|-
| rowspan=3|1993
| ''[[Wilder Napalm]]''
| Rex
|
|-
|''[[The Beverly Hillbillies (film)|The Beverly Hillbillies]]''
| Jed Clampett
|
|-
|''[[Ernest Rides Again]]''
| rowspan=2 | Ernest P. Worrell
|
|-
| 1994
| ''[[Ernest Goes to School]]''
|
|-
| rowspan=4|1995
| ''[[The Expert (1995 film)|The Expert]]''
| Snake
|
|-
| ''[[Slam Dunk Ernest]]''
| Ernest P. Worrell
|
|-
| ''[[Toy Story]]''
| [[List of Toy Story characters#Slinky Dog|Slinky Dog]]
| Voice
|-
| ''Bubba Goes Hunting''
| Bubba
|
|-
| 1996
|''[[Snowboard Academy]]''
| Rudy James
|
|-
| rowspan=4|1997
| ''[[Ernest Goes to Africa]]''
| Ernest P. Worrell / Hey You, the Hindu / Auntie Nelda / African Woman Dancer
|
|-
| ''[[100 Proof (film)|100 Proof]]''
| Rae's Father
|
|-
| ''Blood, Friends and Money''
| The Old Mariner
|
|-
| ''[[Annabelle's Wish]]''
| Mr. Gus Holder
| Voice
|-
| rowspan=2|1998
| ''[[Ernest in the Army]]''
| Pvt./Capt. Ernest P. Worrell / Operation Sandtrap Arab
|
|-
| ''[[3 Ninjas: High Noon at Mega Mountain]]''
| Lothar Zogg
|
|-
| rowspan=3|1999
| ''Existo''
| Marcel Horowitz
|
|-
| ''[[Treehouse Hostage]]''
| Carl Banks
|
|-
| ''[[Toy Story 2]]''
| [[List of Toy Story characters#Slinky Dog|Slinky Dog]]
| Voice
|-
| rowspan=2|2001
| ''[[Atlantis: The Lost Empire]]''
| Jebidiah 'Cookie' Farnsworth
| Voice
|-
| ''[[Daddy and Them]]''
| Hazel Montgomery
| (final film role)
|}

=== Television ===
{|   class="wikitable" style="font-size: 95%;"
|-   align="center"
! style="background: #B0C4DE;"   | Year
! style="background: #B0C4DE;"   | Title
! style="background: #B0C4DE;"   | Role
! style="background: #B0C4DE;"   | Notes
|-
| 1976
| ''[[Dinah!]]''
| Himself
| 1 episode
|-
| rowspan=2|1977
| ''[[Operation Petticoat]]''
| Doom &amp; Gloom Broom
|
|-
|''[[Fernwood 2 Night]]''
| Virgil Simms
| Episode: "Ethnic  Myths"&lt;br /&gt;Episode: "Getting the Most from Your Warranty"&lt;br /&gt;Episode: "#1.46"&lt;br /&gt;Episode: "Battery Powered Car"
|-
|  rowspan=3|1978
| ''[[America 2-Night]]''
| Virgil Simms
| Episode: "Daredevil Virgil Simms"&lt;br /&gt;Episode: "Falafel-on-a-Stick"&lt;br /&gt;Episode: "The UBS Story"
|-
|''[[Operation Petticoat#1977 television series|Operation Petticoat]]''
| Seaman 'Doom &amp; Gloom' Broom
| 32 episodes
|-
|''[[Alice (TV series)|Alice]]''
| Milo Skinner
| Episode: "Better Never Than Later"
|-
| 1979
|''Alan King's Third Annual Final Warning!''
| Various
|
|-
| 1980
|''[[Pink Lady (TV series)|Pink Lady]]''
| Various
| All 6 episodes
|-
| 1982–83
| ''[[Pop! Goes the Country]]''
| Bobby Burbank / 'Shotglass' The Bartender / Bunny The Barmaid 
| Unknown episodes
|-
| rowspan=2|1983
| ''The Rousters''
| Evan Earp
| TV series pilot film
|-
| ''[[The Rousters]]''
| Evan Earp
| All 13 episodes
|-
|1988
|''[[Hey Vern, It's Ernest!]]''
|  [[Ernest P. Worrell]] / Various
|
|-
|1988–89
|''[[Happy New Year, America]]''
|[[Ernest P. Worrell]] / Correspondent
| Live New Year's Eve special
|-
| 1989
| ''Ernest Goes to Splash Mountain''
|  [[Ernest P. Worrell]]
|
|-
| rowspan=2|1990
| ''[[Walt Disney anthology television series|Disneyland]]''
|  [[Ernest P. Worrell]] / Ernest's Father
| Episode: "Disneyland's 35th Anniversary Celebration"
|-
| ''Disneyland's 35th Anniversary Celebration''
| [[Ernest P. Worrell]]
|
|-
| 1994
| ''XXX's &amp; OOO's''
|
| Cameo
|-
| 1996
|''[[Roseanne]]''
| Prince Carlos
| Episode: "[[List of Roseanne episodes#Season 9 (1996−1997)|Someday My Prince Will Come]]"&lt;br /&gt;Episode: "[[List of Roseanne episodes#Season 9 (1996−1997)|Home Is Where the Afghan Is]]"
|-
|1997
| ''[[Duckman|Duckman: Private Dick/Family Man]]''
| Walt Evergreen
| Voice only&lt;br /&gt;Episode: "[[List of Duckman episodes#Season 4: 1997|You've Come a Wrong Way, Baby]]"
|-
| 1998
|''[[Hercules: The Animated Series]]''
| King Ephialtes
| Voice only&lt;br /&gt;Episode "Hercules and the Dance Muse"
|-
| 1998
|''[[The Simpsons]]''
| Cooder
| Voice only&lt;br /&gt;Episode: "[[Bart Carny]]"
|}

=== Video games ===
{|   class="wikitable" style="font-size: 95%;"
|-   align="center"
! style="background: #B0C4DE;"   | Year
! style="background: #B0C4DE;"   | Title
! style="background: #B0C4DE;"   | Role
! style="background: #B0C4DE;"   | Notes
|-
| 1996
| ''[[Disney's Activity Center|Toy Story: Activity Center]]''
| rowspan=4 | [[List of Toy Story characters#Slinky Dog|Slinky Dog]]
| rowspan=5 | Voice only
|-
| 1996 
|  ''[[Disney's Animated Storybook|Animated Storybook: Toy Story]]'' 
|- 
| 1999
| ''[[Disney's Activity Center|Toy Story 2: Activity Center]]''
|-
| 1999
|''[[Toy Story 2: Buzz Lightyear to the Rescue]]''
|-
| 2000
| ''[[Atlantis: The Lost Empire#Video games|Atlantis: The Lost Empire]]''
| Cookie
|}

== References ==
{{reflist|2}}

== External links ==
* {{Find a Grave|8459}}
* {{IMDb name|0001815}}
* {{tcmdb name|id=197475|name=Jim Varney}}
* {{AllMovie name|115186}}

{{Authority control}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Varney, Jim}}
[[Category:1949 births]]
[[Category:2000 deaths]]
[[Category:20th-century American male actors]]
[[Category:20th-century American writers]]
[[Category:Actors from Lexington, Kentucky]]
[[Category:American male comedians]]
[[Category:American comedians]]
[[Category:American male film actors]]
[[Category:American male television actors]]
[[Category:American stand-up comedians]]
[[Category:American male video game actors]]
[[Category:American male voice actors]]
[[Category:American male writers]]
[[Category:Burials in Kentucky]]
[[Category:Deaths from cancer in Tennessee]]
[[Category:Deaths from lung cancer]]
[[Category:Male actors from Kentucky]]
[[Category:Murray State University alumni]]
[[Category:People from White House, Tennessee]]
[[Category:Writers from Lexington, Kentucky]]
[[Category:20th-century male writers]]</text>
      <sha1>9tgppp8mrx2vt25il6km7rergogb0i4</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
