<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10.xsd" version="0.10" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <dbname>enwiki</dbname>
    <base>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.32.0-wmf.16</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="118" case="first-letter">Draft</namespace>
      <namespace key="119" case="first-letter">Draft talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2300" case="first-letter">Gadget</namespace>
      <namespace key="2301" case="first-letter">Gadget talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2302" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition</namespace>
      <namespace key="2303" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Joey Diaz</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>6149955</id>
    <revision>
      <id>855176619</id>
      <parentid>854133105</parentid>
      <timestamp>2018-08-16T13:09:29Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>TheMagikBOT</username>
        <id>24649005</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor/>
      <comment>Added page protection template where none existed</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="23648">{{pp|small=yes}} 
{{Infobox person
| name         = Joey Diaz
| image        = Joey Diaz.jpg
| caption      = Diaz in March 2015
| birth_date   = {{birth date and age|1963|02|19}}
| birth_name   = Jose Antonio Diaz
| birth_place  = [[Havana]], Cuba
| years_active = 1991–present
| occupation   = Comedian, actor, podcaster
| other_names  = Coco, Joey Karate
}}
'''Jose Antonio "Joey" "CoCo" Diaz''' (born February 19, 1963) is a [[Cuban-Americans|Cuban-American]] standup comedian, actor and podcast host. Born in Cuba and raised in [[North Bergen, New Jersey]], Diaz began his stand-up career in 1991. He had roles in the television series ''[[My Name is Earl]]'' and the films ''[[The Longest Yard (2005 film)|The Longest Yard]]'' and ''[[Taxi (2004 film)|Taxi]]''. Since 2012, Diaz has hosted the podcast, ''The Church of What's Happening Now'', is a regular guest on ''[[The Joe Rogan Experience]]'', and produced an autobiographical documentary.

==Early life==
Joey Diaz was born in [[Havana, Cuba]] as an only child. In the 1970s, his family had relocated to the United States and settled in [[North Bergen, New Jersey]].&lt;ref name=HudReporter4.21.03&gt;{{cite web|url=http://hudsonreporter.com/view/full_story/2389493/article-Cuban-comedian--NB-native-making-strides-as-comic-actor-Film-role-in--You-Got-Nothin--will-be-shown-at-Hoboken-Film-Festival?instance=search_results|title=NB native Diaz making strides as comic actor film role in 'You Got Nothin' will be shown at Hoboken Film Festival|work=The Hudson Reporter|first=Jim|last=Hague|date=April 21, 2003|accessdate=March 31, 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt; His mother ran a bar and a successful [[numbers game]] operation. He was raised Catholic as a youngster and enjoyed learning stories about [[Francis of Assisi]] and [[St. Michael]].&lt;ref name=CantonRepository&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.cantonrep.com/special/20170105/kidnapping-to-comedy-joey-coco-diaz-finds-his-way|title=Kidnapping to comedy: Joey 'Coco' Diaz finds his way|work=[[The Repository]]|first=B.J.|last=Lisko|date=January 5, 2017|accessdate=April 23, 2018}}&lt;/ref&gt; Diaz attended McKinley School and then [[North Bergen High School]],&lt;ref name=HudReporter4.21.03/&gt; where he won awards for performing arts.&lt;ref name=HudReporter11.29.09&gt;{{cite web|url=http://hudsonreporter.com/view/full_story/4926885/article--The-Dog-that-Saved-Christmas-NB-native-stars-in-TV-movie--talks-about-comedy-and-missing-Hudson-County-food-?instance=search_results|title='The Dog that Saved Christmas'|work=The Hudson Reporter|first=Tricia|last=Tirella|date=November 29, 2009|accessdate=March 31, 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt; He graduated in 1982.&lt;ref name=HudReporter4.21.03/&gt;&lt;ref name=HudReporter9.30.07&gt;{{cite web|url=http://hudsonreporter.com/view/full_story/2413612/article-NB-comedian-lands-role-on--My-Name-IS-Earl--Diaz-has-recurring-spot-on-award-winning-NBC-sitcom?instance=search_results|title=NB comedian lands role on 'My Name IS Earl' Diaz has recurring spot on award-winning NBC sitcom|work=The Hudson Reporter|first=Jim|last=Hague|date=September 30, 2007|accessdate=March 31, 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Diaz suffered loss in his family early on. He lost his father when he was three, and found his mother dead on the floor in his home at 16.&lt;ref name="HotOnes"&gt;{{cite web |last1=Diaz |first1=Joey |title=Joey "CoCo" Diaz Breaks Out the Blue Cheese While Eating Spicy Wings |url=https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=e226MZIXJ5E&amp;feature=youtu.be&amp;t=12m27s|publisher=First We Feast |website=YouTube|date=January 26, 2017 |accessdate=July 25, 2018 |ref=HotOnes}}&lt;/ref&gt; He was taken in by four families around North Bergen during his teenage years, and credits about twenty people who helped him, but his reckless nature and tendency to get into trouble caused him to move from one home to another.&lt;ref name=HudReporter10.2.11/&gt; During this time, Diaz began taking drugs and committing crimes.&lt;ref name=CantonRepository/&gt; Diaz explains that his peers' sense of humor greatly influenced his comedy career,&lt;ref name=HudReporter10.2.11/&gt; and used lines from his teacher at McKinley School in his act. Diaz was also influenced by albums by [[Richard Pryor]]. Diaz wished to become a [[bookmaker]] initially, but changed his mind when he realized that it was not an honest way of making a living.&lt;ref name=HudReporter4.21.03/&gt;

In 1982, Diaz moved to [[Colorado]]. However, his growing homesickness led to his return to New Jersey initially for his birthday in 1984, but he stayed there for eighteen months. He later called this time as "the worst 18 months of my life" and "the biggest mistake of my life", as his cocaine abuse worsened.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|first=Giorgio|last=Mustica|url=http://www.theaquarian.com/2014/03/05/an-interview-with-joey-coco-diaz-in-the-name-of-science/|title=An Interview with Joey "CoCo" Diaz: In The Name Of Science|date=March 5, 2014|work=The Aquarian Weekly|accessdate=April 1, 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Career==
===Stand-up comedy===
In June 1985, Diaz left New Jersey for good and returned to Colorado to study economics at the [[University of Colorado at Boulder]]. He did not enjoy his time there, and quit before taking up work selling roofing which earned him money, but he remained unhappy.&lt;ref name=HudReporter4.21.03/&gt; Developments in his life were interrupted by a stint in prison in 1988, following his arrest for kidnapping and aggravated robbery.&lt;ref name=HudReporter10.2.11&gt;{{Cite news|url=http://hudsonreporter.com/view/full_story/15853263/article-From-North-Bergen-to-prison-to-Hollywood-Documentary-will-standup-comedian%E2%80%99s-humble-roots-|title=From North Bergen to prison to Hollywood|last=LaMarca|first=Stephen|date=October 2, 2011|work=The Hudson Reporter|accessdate=January 28, 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt; During his time in prison, Diaz would perform stand-up routines for his fellow inmates during the weekly film screening event when the projector broke. It took Diaz a further three years to try stand-up, despite being often told of his talent, and later called his entry into the line of work as "the last resort" as he had many other jobs in the past.&lt;ref name=CantonRepository/&gt; After seeing the 1988 film  ''[[Punchline (film)|Punchline]]'', Diaz responded to an advertisement for a $37 stand-up comedy course in the ''Rocky Mountain Post'', and developed a [[blue comedy]] act. Before he did his first standup routine, he worked as a doorman at Wit's End.&lt;ref name=HowComedyWorks&gt;{{cite web|url=http://comedyworks.libsyn.com/episode-30-joey-diaz|title=How Comedy Works with Wende Curtis and Rick Kerns - Episode 30: Joey Diaz|date=September 2, 2016|publisher=Libsyn|accessdate=April 2, 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Diaz performed his first routine on June 18, 1991&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=By-zQN2g0DE|title=Joe Rogan Experience #598 - Joey "CoCo" Diaz|at=1:54:00|date=January 12, 2015|accessdate=April 3, 2017|via=YouTube}}&lt;/ref&gt; at the [[Comedy Works]] in Denver at a show headlined by Matt Woods. In April 1992, prior to his opening spot for Troy Baxley in [[Boulder, Colorado]], Diaz took cocaine before going on stage and had a set that he described as "a disaster". He then ceased to take the substance before a performance. After developing his act, Diaz entered the Beck's Amateur Comedy Competition and won. He initially lost another competition until the winner was caught [[joke thievery|stealing jokes]] made famous by [[Jerry Seinfeld]] and Diaz was declared the winner. Diaz claimed Comedy Works manager Wende Curtis promised him a flight to Los Angeles for a showcase spot at [[The Comedy Store]] for owner [[Mitzi Shore]], but never received either.&lt;ref name=HowComedyWorks/&gt; Diaz went on to participate in a similar contest in [[Seattle]], [[Washington (state)|Washington]], and finished sixth out of 40.&lt;ref name=HudReporter4.21.03/&gt; In 1994, Diaz returned to the Comedy Works and found Curtis had started a developmental program for comics which he joined. The process involved group writing sessions at Wood's home followed by sets in the club the same evening. At one point, Curtis banned Diaz from the Comedy Works before it was lifted after they met years later.&lt;ref name=HowComedyWorks/&gt;

In 1995, Diaz left Colorado for [[Los Angeles]], California to try and make it as a successful stand-up comic. Had he failed, and after an incident with his ex-wife's boyfriend which almost landed him in prison (by a miracle, nothing came of the incident), in which he slapped him for calling Joey racial slurs in front of Joey's daughter, he was set on returning to Colorado and send jokes to [[Jay Leno]] via fax machine from prison.&lt;ref name=HowComedyWorks/&gt; He used his divorce from his first wife, and the loss of contact with their daughter in the process, as a motivation so he "could come back and make her proud".&lt;ref name=CantonRepository/&gt; In the following years, he worked on his act in local and national venues as a supporting act for other comedians. Around 1997, Diaz first met his longtime friend [[Joe Rogan]], who had Diaz open for him on his stand-up tours.{{citation needed|date=April 2018}}

On November 4, 2007, Diaz appeared in North Bergen to help raise money for North Bergen High School's basketball team uniforms.&lt;ref name=HudReporter9.30.07/&gt;

In April 2012, Diaz supported his ''Where I Got My Balls From'' documentary with the release of his stand-up special, ''It's Either You or the Priest''. It went to number one on the ''[[Billboard (magazine)|Billboard]]'' comedy charts in the UK and Canada, and number one on [[iTunes]].&lt;ref name=HudReporter5.10.12&gt;{{cite web|url=http://hudsonreporter.com/view/full_story/18523193/article-Brazen-comic-North-Bergen-resident-creates-documentary--comedy-CD-?instance=search_results|title=Brazen comic|work=The Hudson Reporter|first=Vanessa|last=Cruz|date=May 10, 2012|accessdate=April 1, 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In December 2016, Diaz put out his first one-hour comedy special, ''Sociably Unacceptable'', through the on-demand subscription services [[Seeso]] and [[Comedy Dynamics]].&lt;ref name=CantonRepository/&gt;

===Film and television===
In 1998, Diaz received a contract to star in a [[television pilot]], playing a bartender in a series titled ''Bronx County'', after a talent scout at [[CBS]] saw him perform comedy in Seattle. The offer was a total surprise to Diaz, who initially did not believe him until he saw the talent scout possess tickets to have him fly to Los Angeles for the shoot. The series was not picked up, but the opportunity led to more work for Diaz, including an offer in his first feature film, a referee in ''[[BASEketball]]'' (1998), and a part in the television series ''[[NYPD Blue]]''. In 2000, Diaz was featured in ''You Got Nothin''' (2003), an independent film. Parts of ''[[Analyze That]]'' (2002), which starred Diaz, were filmed in Hudson County, New Jersey. He said, "That was big for me, able to come home to film".&lt;ref name=CantonRepository/&gt;

Diaz's profile increased with subsequent roles in ''[[Law &amp; Order]]'' and his first major feature films, ''[[Spider-Man 2]]'' (2004)&lt;ref name=HudReporter10.2.11/&gt; and ''[[Taxi (2004 film)|Taxi]]'' (2004).&lt;ref name=HudReporter9.30.07/&gt; This was followed by a role in ''[[The Longest Yard (2005 film)|The Longest Yard]]'' (2005) as an unlawful union organizer, for which Diaz took several longtime friends to the premiere screening as they helped him face adversity in life.&lt;ref name=CantonRepository/&gt;&lt;ref name=HudReporter9.30.07/&gt;&lt;ref name=HudReporter10.2.11/&gt;&lt;ref name=hudson-20050607/&gt; Diaz secured the role after he learned a remake of the original was in production, and had lunch with [[Chris Rock]] and [[Adam Sandler]], during which Rock said he could land Diaz an audition. Diaz proceeded to assemble an audition tape: "I went out and got a football jersey two sizes too small, pants two sizes two small with my butt hanging out. I got kids' football shoulder pads and ran around the field with a cigar in my mouth". Three days after submitting the tape, Diaz landed the role; the producers liked the name Big Tony Tedesco, which Diaz named himself on the tape, and wrote it into the script.&lt;ref name=hudson-20040911&gt;{{cite web|url=http://hudsonreporter.com/view/full_story/2400244/article-NB-comedian-gets-big-break-in--Longest-Yard--Diaz-in-remake-of-classic-football-prison-movie-with-Burt-Reynolds?instance=search_results|title=NB comedian gets big break in 'Longest Yard' Diaz in remake of classic football prison movie with Burt Reynolds|work=The Hudson Reporter|first=Jim|last=Hague|date=September 11, 2004|accessdate=March 31, 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt; Originally Diaz had a mere three lines, but his tape got his part extended.&lt;ref name=hudson-20050607&gt;{{cite web|url=http://hudsonreporter.com/view/full_story/2405004/article-Tackling-the--Longest-Yard--North-Bergen-native-Diaz-enjoys-prominent-role-in-remake-starring-Sandler--Rock--Reynolds?instance=search_results|title=Tackling the 'Longest Yard' North Bergen native Diaz enjoys prominent role in remake starring Sandler, Rock, Reynolds|work=The Hudson Reporter|first=Jim|last=Hague|date=June 7, 2005|accessdate=March 31, 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In 2005, Diaz expressed his wish to continue as a [[character actor]], saying: "It's like a dream come true for me. ... I got my call and I have to make the most of it". Around this time prepared his one-man comedy show ''Larceny &amp; Laughter'', which featured stories while growing up in North Bergen.&lt;ref name=hudson-20050607/&gt;

In 2007, Diaz appeared in four episodes of the television series ''[[My Name is Earl]]'' as Joey the Candy Bar Criminal. The show's producers wished to hire actors to play prisoners, and called Diaz after they saw him in ''The Longest Yard''. That year, he had a stint as the host of humorous promotions for the [[Ultimate Fighting Championship]] as Joey Karate, giving karate instructions and comical predictions for upcoming fights.&lt;ref name=HudReporter9.30.07/&gt; Diaz regards his role in the 2009 television film ''[[The Dog Who Saved Christmas]]'' as a point of pride, as it allowed children in North Bergen to see him act. At the time of filming, Diaz weighed 390 lbs. By late 2009, he slimmed down to 295 lbs.&lt;ref name=HudReporter11.29.09/&gt;

In 2011 Diaz appeared in "Scarlet Ribbons", an episode of ''[[The Mentalist]]'' and the film ''[[Bucky Larson: Born to Be a Star]]''.&lt;ref name=HudReporter10.2.11/&gt;

Around 2011, Diaz raised $1400 from fans on Twitter and Facebook to finance a documentary about his upbringing in North Bergen, chronicling his life and how he was influenced by the various people who took care of him following his parents' death. Diaz pitched in $2,600 to complete it and by mid-2012, ''Where I Got My Balls From'' was produced with his podcast co-host and producer Lee Syatt as director, who shot six hours of footage in total. Diaz made the film in tribute to those who helped him.&lt;ref name=HudReporter10.2.11/&gt;&lt;ref name=HudReporter5.10.12/&gt;

In 2013, Diaz secured a role in ''[[Grudge Match (film)|Grudge Match]]'' where he is seen alongside [[Robert De Niro]] as his coach. Diaz took his fifth grade teacher to the premiere.&lt;ref name=CantonRepository/&gt;

Diaz appeared in Season 2 Episode 12 of ''[[Maron (TV series)|Maron]]''.

In 2017, Diaz started work on a presentation based on one of his cats for [[Animal Planet]].&lt;ref name=CantonRepository/&gt;

===Podcast===
In 2009, Diaz was introduced to comedian [[Felicia Michaels]], who encouraged him to co-host a new comedy podcast,&lt;ref name=HowComedyWorks/&gt; ''Beauty and Da Beast'' launched in August 2010.  In one early episode, Diaz recalled a story about setting a prostitute's wig on fire when he was young.  The weekend after it aired, more people were turning up at Diaz's stand-up shows.&lt;ref name=CantonRepository/&gt;&lt;ref name=HudReporter9.30.07/&gt;&lt;ref name=HowComedyWorks/&gt;&lt;ref name=badb&gt;{{cite web|url=http://badbpodcast.libsyn.com/|title=Beauty and Da Beast Podcast w/ Joey Diaz and Felicia Michaels|publisher=Libsyn|accessdate=April 1, 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt; The podcast ended in November 2012 after 113 episodes.&lt;ref name=badb/&gt;

On September 2, 2012, Diaz launched his own audio and video podcast, ''The Church of What's Happening Now''. The podcast features co-host and producer Lee Syatt; as of August 2018, the podcast has over 600 episodes.&lt;ref name=CantonRepository/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://thechurchofwhatshappeningnow.libsyn.com/|title=The Church of What's Happening Now: With Joey Coco Diaz|publisher=Libsyn|accessdate=August 1, 2018}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Personal life==
In 1991, Diaz divorced his first wife, during which he lost a relationship with their daughter.&lt;ref name=CantonRepository/&gt; On November 25, 2009, he married his second wife, Terrie Clark of [[Nashville, Tennessee]].&lt;ref name=HudReporter11.29.09/&gt;

In 2007, Diaz ended his longtime cocaine abuse, after one of his cats ingested the substance and died. He later said, "It has to do with your peace of mind. For some people, it takes 10 years to acquire. It took me 30."&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.reviewjournal.com/columns-blogs/doug-elfman/drugs-prison-comedy-hollywood-vegas-one-man-s-life-so-far|title=Drugs, prison, comedy, Hollywood, Vegas — one man's life so far|first=Doulg|last=Elfman|date=July 17, 2014|work=[[Las Vegas Review Journal]]|accessdate=April 1, 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Diaz is [[Catholic]] and practices [[Santeria]].&lt;ref&gt;[https://m.youtube.com/watch?v=8jar5l-_820 "Joey Diaz - A Santeria Prediction - This Is Not Happening - Uncensored"]. [[Comedy Central]], [[YouTube]], May 31, 2016, 1:24 mark.&lt;/ref&gt;

== Filmography ==
===Film===
{{div col|colwidth=30em}}
*''[[BASEketball]]'' (1998) – Referee
*''You Got Nothin''' (2002) – Charlie
*[[American Gun (2002 film)|American Gun]] (2002) – Gun Smuggler
*''Another Bobby O'Hara Story...'' (2002) – Tommy Brando
*''[[Analyze That]]'' (2002) – Ducks
*"The Mezzos" (short) (2003) – Joey Mezzo
*''[[Dickie Roberts: Former Child Star]]'' (2003) – Emmanuel's Entourage
*''[[Back by Midnight]]'' (2004) – Jojo (as Joey 'Coco' Diaz)
*''[[Spider-Man 2]]'' (2004) – Train Passenger (as Joey Coco Diaz)
*''[[Taxi (2004 film)|Taxi]]'' (2004) – Freddy (as Joey Coco Diaz)
*''The Mafia Type'' (2004) – Big Al
*''Endings'' (2005)
*''Break a Leg'' (2005) – Large Producer
*''Accidentally on Purpose'' (2005) – Geraldo
*''[[The Longest Yard (2005 film)|The Longest Yard]]'' (2005) – Anthony "Big Tony" Cobianco
*''[[A Fine Line]]'' (2006) – Bruno Scalise
*''[[18 Fingers of Death!]]'' (2006) – Sammy Delassandro
*''[[Smiley Face (film)|Smiley Face]]'' (2007) – Security Guard
*''White Pants'' (video short) (2007) – Coach Larkin
*''[[The Dark Knight (film)|The Dark Knight]]'' (2008) – Restaurant owner (special features)
*''Boiler Maker'' (video) (2008) – Enzo
*''Redemption'' (short film) (2009) – Ritchie
*''The Deported'' (2009) – Sheriff
*''Stacy's Mom'' (video) (2010) – Frankie the Teach (as Joey 'Coco' Diaz)
*''The Russian'' (short film) (2010) – Frank
*''Stonerville'' (video) (2011) – Johnny Scarano
*''[[My Dog's Christmas Miracle]]'' (2010) – TSA Officer
*''[[Bucky Larson: Born to Be a Star]]'' (2011) – German Guy / Distributor
*''[[Grudge Match (film)|Grudge Match]]'' (2013) – Mikey (as Joey Coco Diaz)
*''[[Rules Don't Apply]]'' (2016) – Mobster
*''[[The Bronx Bull (film)|The Bronx Bull]]'' (2016) – Mickey
{{div col end}}

===Television===
{{div col|colwidth=30em}}
*''[[Mad TV]]'' (2001) – "Big Pussy" in [[The Sopranos]] parody
*''[[The Jamie Kennedy Experiment]]'' (2002) – Pizza Deliver Bodyguard (as Joey 'Coco' Diaz)
*''[[NYPD Blue]]''
**"Death by Cycle" (2002) – Manny Mankiewicz
**"Women vs. Men" (2002) – Goon
*''[[Karen Sisco]]'' 
**"Dear Derwood..." (2003) – Paulie
*''[[ER (TV series)|ER]]''
**"The Greater Good" (2003) – Grocery Store Clerk
*''[[Cold Case]]''
**"Disco Inferno (2004) – Ken Mazzacone (as Joey 'Coco' Diaz)
*''[[Law &amp; Order: Special Victims Unit]]''
**"Criminal" (2004) – Elijah Coney
*''[[How I Met Your Mother]]''
**"[[Where Were We? (How I Met Your Mother)|Where Were We?]]" (2006) – Angry New Yorker
*''[[Everybody Hates Chris]]''
**"Everybody Hates Promises" (2006) – Restaurant owner
*''[[Murder 101 (TV film series)|Murder 101]]: College Can Be Murder'' (2007) – Herbie Saxe
*''Alive N' Kickin''' (TV movie) (2007) – Joey
*''[[My Name Is Earl]]'' (2007) – Joey the Prisoner (as Joey 'Coco' Diaz)
**"Our Other Cops Is On!: Part 1" (2007)
**"Our Other Cops Is On!: Part 2" (2007)
**"My Name Is Inmate #28301-016: Part 1" (2007)
*''[[Frank TV]]'' (2007) "Ballpark Frank" (2007) – Defendant
*''One Hogan Place'' (TV movie) (2008) – Vinnie Books
*''[[Wizards of Waverly Place]]''
**"The Supernatural" (2008) – Newsstand Guy (as Joey 'Coco' Diaz)
*''My Life at 26'' (TV movie) (2008) –. Paxon
*''[[The Dog Who Saved Christmas]]'' (2009) – Stewey McMann (as Joey "Coco" Diaz)
*''[[The Dog Who Saved Christmas Vacation]]'' (2010) – Stewey McMann
*''The Dog Who Saved Halloween'' (2011) – Stewey McMann
*''[[Kickin' It]]''
**"We Are Family" (2012) – Meatball King (as Joey 'Coco' Diaz)
*''The Dog Who Saved The Hollidays'' (2012) – Stewey McMann
*''[[Brooklyn Nine-Nine]]'' (2013) – Sal (as Joey 'Coco' Diaz) 
*''The Dog Who Saved Easter'' (2014) – Stewey McMann
*''[[TripTank]]'' (2014) – Catman
**"Game Over"
**"Ahhh, Serenity"
*''[[Maron (TV series)|Maron]]'' (2014–2016) – Bobby Mendez
**"The Joke" (2014)
**"Philippe" (2016)
*''The Dog Who Saved Summer'' (2015) – Stewey McMann
*''[[I'm Dying Up Here]]'' (2018) – Taffy
{{div col end}}

===Video games===
*''[[Mafia III]]'' (2016) – Roman "The Butcher" Barbieri (voice) (as Joey Coco Diaz)

===Comedy releases===
*''Live at the 3 Clubs in Hollywood'' (2011)
*''It's Either You or the Priest'' (2012)
*''Testicle Testaments 1: The Worst &amp; Best Day of My Life'' (2012)
*''Testicle Testaments 2: Crime Stories'' (2012)
*''Testicle Testaments 3: The Person Who Made Me a Man'' (2012)
*''The Blue Album'' (2013)
*''Testicle Testaments 4: How I Got Into Comedy'' (2013)
*''Testicle Testaments 5: Crimes Against Myself'' (2013)
*''You Can't Eat Pussy with Asthma'' (2013)
*''Savage Dad'' (2015)
*''Socially Unacceptable'' (2016)

===Writer===
*''1st Amendment Stand Up (Episode: "Joey Diaz/Melanie Comarcho/Lavell Crawford") (2007)
*''[[Black Entertainment Television|BET]]'s '[[ComicView]]'' (Episode: "ComicView: New Orleans Party Gras") (2000)

===Self===
*''BET's Comicview'' "ComicView: New Orleans Party Gras" (2000) – Himself – Comedian (as Coco)
*''The History of Choking'' (2002) – Himself
*''National Lampoon Live: New Faces''
*''Inside Joke'' (2004) – Himself
*''1st Amendment Stand Up'' (2007) – Himself – Comedian (Episode: "Joey Diaz/Melanie Comarcho/Lavell Crawford") 
*''The Payaso Comedy Slam''  (2007) – Himself
*''[[Inside MMA]]''  (2008) – Guest&lt;ref&gt;{{cite video|date=April 30, 2008|publisher=[[YouTube]]|title=HDNet presents Inside MMA with Toby TigerHeart Grear|url=https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=MM4xHjQVKg8}}&lt;/ref&gt; (Episode: "Episode #2.17")
*''Where I Got My Balls From'' (2012) – Himself

==References==
{{Reflist|30em}}

==External links==
*{{IMDb name|0224995}}
* {{Official website|http://www.joeydiaz.net/}}

{{Use dmy dates|date=June 2011}}

{{authority control}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Diaz, Joey}}
[[Category:1963 births]]
[[Category:American male film actors]]
[[Category:American comedians]]
[[Category:American male comedians]]
[[Category:American people of Cuban descent]]
[[Category:American podcasters]]
[[Category:Cuban comedians]]
[[Category:Cuban emigrants to the United States]]
[[Category:Cuban male comedians]]
[[Category:Living people]]
[[Category:People from North Bergen, New Jersey]]</text>
      <sha1>g1efh447xkibsfc5agxyr7d8rv69458</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
