<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10.xsd" version="0.10" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <dbname>enwiki</dbname>
    <base>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.32.0-wmf.16</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="118" case="first-letter">Draft</namespace>
      <namespace key="119" case="first-letter">Draft talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2300" case="first-letter">Gadget</namespace>
      <namespace key="2301" case="first-letter">Gadget talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2302" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition</namespace>
      <namespace key="2303" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Larry Fine</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>589925</id>
    <revision>
      <id>856144692</id>
      <parentid>856140872</parentid>
      <timestamp>2018-08-23T05:28:43Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Ewulp</username>
        <id>998182</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>rv, not a defining characteristic</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="20626">{{Use mdy dates|date=June 2012}}
{{about|the actor|the American technician and author|Larry Fine (pianos)}}

{{Infobox person
| name             = Larry Fine
| image            = File:LFine1936 color.jpg
| caption          = Fine in the 1936 film ''[[Disorder in the Court]]''
| birth_name       = Louis Feinberg
| birth_date       = {{Birth date|1902|10|5}}
| birth_place      = [[Philadelphia]], [[Pennsylvania]], U.S.
| death_date       = {{Death date and age|1975|1|24|1902|10|5}}
| death_place      = [[Woodland Hills, Los Angeles]], [[California]], U.S.
| resting_place    = [[Forest Lawn Memorial Park, Glendale|Forest Lawn Memorial Park]]
| years_active     = 1923–1970
| occupation       = Actor, comedian, musician, boxer
| spouse           = {{marriage|Mabel Fine&lt;br&gt;|1926|1967|reason=her death}}
| children         = 2
| other_names      =
| website          =  
}}

'''Louis Feinberg''' (October 5, 1902 – January 24, 1975), known professionally as '''Larry Fine''', was an American [[actor]], [[comedian]], [[violin]]ist and [[boxer]], who is best known as a member of the comedy act [[The Three Stooges]].&lt;ref name=obit/&gt;

==Early life==
Fine was born to a [[Russian Jewish]] family at 3rd and [[South Street (Philadelphia)|South Street]] in [[Philadelphia]], [[Pennsylvania]] on October 5, 1902.&lt;ref&gt;Pennsylvania, Philadelphia City Births, 1860-1906, Familysearch.org&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[[A&amp;E Network|A&amp;E]] television show ''[[Biography (TV series)|Biography]]''&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://southstreet.com/index.php?option=com_mtree&amp;task=viewlink&amp;link_id=317&amp;Itemid=12 South Street Headhouse District]&lt;/ref&gt; His father, Joseph Feinberg, and mother, Fanny Lieberman, owned a watch repair and jewelry shop.

In his early childhood, Fine's arm was accidentally burned with [[hydrochloric acid|acid]].  His father used the acid to test jewelry for its gold content. On one occasion, the young Fine mistook the acid for a beverage and raised the bottle to his lips.  Before he could drink any, his father knocked the bottle from Fine's hand, splashing Fine's forearm with acid and causing extensive damage to it.

His parents later gave Fine [[violin]] lessons to help strengthen the damaged muscles in his forearm. He became so proficient on the violin that his parents wanted to send him to a European [[music conservatory]].  However, that plan was thwarted by the outbreak of [[World War I]]. Fine later played the violin in the Stooge films.  In scenes where all three Stooges are playing fiddles, only Larry is actually playing, while the other two are [[mime artist|miming]].

To further strengthen his damaged arm, Fine took up boxing in his teens, winning one professional bout. His father, opposed to Larry's fighting in public, put an end to his brief career as a [[boxing|boxer]].{{Ref|1}}

==Acting career==
===Vaudeville===
At an early age, Fine started performing as a violinist in [[vaudeville]]. In March 1928, while starring as the [[master of ceremonies]] at Chicago's [[Uptown, Chicago|Rainbo Gardens]], Fine met [[Shemp Howard]] and [[Ted Healy]].  At the time, Healy and Howard were performing in the [[The Shubert Organization|Shubert Brothers']] ''[[A Night in Spain]]''. Since Howard was leaving the play for a few months, they asked him to be a replacement 'stooge'.  Fine joined Ted's other stooges, Bobby Pinkus and Sam 'Moody' Braun.  Howard returned in September 1928 to finish ''Spain's'' national tour.

In early 1929, Healy signed a contract to perform in the Shuberts' new revue ''A Night in Venice''.  Healy brought Fine, Shemp Howard, and [[Moe Howard]] together for the first time as a trio.  "Moe, Larry, and Shemp", with [[Fred Sanborn]], appeared in ''Venice'' from 1929 through March 1930.  Fine, Shemp Howard and Moe Howard toured as "Ted Healy &amp; His Racketeers" that spring and summer, and then went to [[Hollywood]] in the summer to film [[20th Century Fox|Fox Studio's]] ''[[Soup to Nuts]]'' (1930).

Fine and the Howard brothers broke up with Healy after ''Soup to Nuts'' and toured as "Howard, Fine, and Howard: Three Lost Soles" from the fall of 1930 to the summer of 1932.  In July 1932, Fine and Moe Howard teamed up with Healy again, adding [[Curly Howard]] to the group. The new lineup premiered at Cleveland's RKO Palace Theatre on August 27, 1932. Shemp Howard split off to pursue a solo career, appearing in Shemp Howard shorts as well as playing numerous supporting roles in feature films starring major comedians such as [[Roscoe Arbuckle]], [[W.C. Fields]], and [[Abbott and Costello]], as well as other mainstream performers.

===Larry's hair===
Fine was easily recognized in the Stooge features by his hairdo, bald on top with lots of thick, bushy, curly red hair around the sides and back; Moe called him "[[Porcupine]]".  Fine's trademark bushy hair had its origin, according to rumor, from his first meeting with Healy. Fine had just wet his hair in a [[sink|basin]], and it dried oddly as they talked. Healy encouraged Fine to keep the zany hairstyle.  On a 1973 TV interview on ''[[The Mike Douglas Show]]'', Moe Howard recounted:
{{bquote|"So Healy said 'Would you like to be one of the stooges and make three instead of two?' And Larry said 'Yes, I would love that.' Healy said, 'I'll give you ninety bucks a week.' 'Fine.' He also said, 'I'll give you an extra ten dollars a week if you throw that fiddle away.'"}}  This is presumed to be a fictionalized account, as Moe Howard wasn't present for that moment in March 1928, having "retired" from show business in July 1925 to go into real estate with his mother. He did not return to performing and Ted's act until December 1928.  Fine's backstage visitors that day were Ted Healy, Shemp Howard, and Bobby Pinkus.

===Three Stooges features===
Beginning in 1932, the Three Stooges made 206 short films and several features, their most prolific period starring Fine, Moe Howard and Curly Howard. However, their career with Healy was marked by disputes over pay, film contracts, and Healy's drinking and verbal abuse. Fine and the Howard brothers finally left Healy for good in 1934.&lt;ref name=Scrapbookrev&gt;{{cite book| last = Maurer| first = Joan Howard| authorlink = Joan Howard Maurer|author2=Jeff Lenburg |author3=Greg Lenburg | title = The Three Stooges Scrapbook| publisher = Citadel Press| origyear = 1982 |year=2012|edition=revised| location = | pages = | doi =| id = | isbn = 978-1-61374-074-3 | url =http://a.co/cYoBoxO}}&lt;/ref&gt;

[[File:Malice in the Palace.JPG|thumb|left|270px|Larry Fine (right) in 1949's ''[[Malice in the Palace]]'' with [[Moe Howard]] and [[Shemp Howard]].]]

In films from the Curly era, the Larry character did more reacting than acting, staying in the background and serving as the voice of reason in contrast to the zany antics of Moe and Curly. He was a [[surrealistic]] foil and the middle ground between Moe's gruffly "bossy", and Curly's childish personae. Like the other Stooges, Larry was often on the receiving end of Moe's abuse. His reasonableness was the perfect foil to Moe's brusque bluntness and Curly or Shemp's boyish immaturity, but Larry would sometimes propose something impossible or illogical and be quickly put down by Moe, both verbally and physically, who would often react by pulling a handful of hair out of Larry's head.&lt;ref name=Scrapbookrev/&gt; Film critic [[Leonard Maltin]] commented in 1978 that "Larry is the least distinctive character of the trio, but he adds a pleasing touch by siding with either Moe or Curly, depending on the situation, thereby enabling him to show moments of lucidity as well as lunacy."&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book | last = Maltin | first = Leonard | authorlink = Leonard Maltin | author2= | author3= | title = The Great Movie Comedians: From Charlie Chaplin to Woody Allen | publisher = CreateSpace Independent Publishing Platform | origyear = 1978 |year=2015 | edition=revised | location = | pages = | doi = | id = | isbn = 978-1-51432-494-3 | url = http://amzn.com/1613740743}}&lt;/ref&gt;

After Curly suffered a debilitating stroke in May 1946, Shemp replaced him in the act. The Shemp era marked a period of increased onscreen presence for Larry, who had been relegated to a background role during the Curly era. Upon Shemp's return, he was allotted equal onscreen time, even becoming the focus of several films, in particular ''[[Fuelin' Around]]'' (1949) and ''[[He Cooked His Goose]]'' (1952).&lt;ref name="Okuda"&gt;{{cite book| last = Okuda| first = Ted | authorlink = Ted Okuda|author2=Watz, Edward | title = The Columbia Comedy Shorts| publisher = McFarland &amp; Company, Inc., Publishers| year = 1986| location = | pages =60–102| id = | isbn = 0-89950-181-8}}&lt;/ref&gt;

On November 22, 1955, Shemp died of a heart attack. [[Joe Palma]] played a [[Fake Shemp|fake Shemp]] role in three previously contracted Stooges shorts, then [[Joe Besser]] succeeded him as the third Stooge. [[Joe DeRita]] replaced Besser in 1958 when the team was fired from Columbia Pictures.

In the earliest Stooge films, the Larry character frequently indulged in utterly nutty behavior. Fine would liven up a scene with a random improvised remark or ridiculous action. In the hospital spoof ''[[Men in Black (1934 film)|Men in Black]]'' (1934), Larry, dressed as a surgeon and wielding a large kitchen knife, chortles: "Let's pluck him... and see if he's ripe!" In ''[[Disorder in the Court]]'' (1936), a tense courtroom scene is interrupted by Larry breaking into a wild [[Tarzan yell]]. Of course, after each of his outbursts, Moe would gruffly put him down. According to Fine's brother, Fine developed a [[callus]] on one side of his face from being slapped innumerable times by Moe.&lt;ref name=Scrapbookrev/&gt;

The Larry character's on-screen goofiness has been described as an extension of Fine's own relaxed personality. Director [[Charles Lamont]] recalled: "Larry was a nut. He was the kind of guy who always said anything. He was a yapper."&lt;ref name=Scrapbookrev/&gt; Writer-director [[Edward Bernds]] remembered that Fine's suggestions for the scripts were often "flaky", but occasionally contained a good comic idea.&lt;ref name=Scrapbookrev/&gt;

The Three Stooges became a big hit on television in 1959, when [[Columbia Pictures]] released a batch of the trio's films, whose popularity brought them to a new audience and revitalized their careers.&lt;ref name=Scrapbookrev/&gt;

==Personal life==
{{tone|section|date=August 2017}}
[[File:Three Stooges 1937.jpg|right|thumb|Larry Fine, Curly Howard and Moe Howard in 1937]]

Offstage, Larry was a social butterfly. He liked a good time and surrounded himself with friends. He and his wife, Mabel Haney, loved to party, and every Christmas served lavish midnight meals. Some of his friends called him a "yes man" since he was always so agreeable, no matter what the circumstances.&lt;ref name=Scrapbookrev/&gt;

Larry's devil-may-care personality carried over to the world of finance. He was a terrible businessman and spent his money as soon as he earned it. He had a significant [[gambling addiction]], leading him to gamble away all the money he had on him either at [[racetracks]] or high-stakes [[gin rummy]] card games. In an interview, Fine even admitted that he often gave money to actors and friends who needed help and never asked to be repaid. As [[Joe Besser]] and director [[Edward Bernds]] recall, because of his constant and free spending and gambling, Larry was almost forced into [[bankruptcy]] when Columbia stopped filming new Three Stooges films in December 1957.&lt;ref name=Scrapbookrev/&gt;

Because of his profligate ways and Mabel's dislike for housekeeping, Larry and his family lived in hotels—first in the President Hotel in [[Atlantic City, New Jersey]], where his daughter Phyllis was raised, then the [[Knickerbocker Hotel (Los Angeles)|Knickerbocker Hotel]] in Hollywood. He did not own a house until the late 1940s, when he purchased one in the [[Los Feliz, Los Angeles, California|Los Feliz]] area of Los Angeles, California.&lt;ref name = "Stooge Bio"/&gt;

On May 30, 1967, Mabel died of a sudden [[heart attack]] at age 63.&lt;ref name="Stooge Bio"&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.threestooges.com/bios/bios.php?intStoogeID=2|title=Stooge Bios - Larry Fine|publisher=threestooges.com|deadurl=yes|archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20120729073719/http://www.threestooges.com/bios/bios.php?intStoogeID=2|archivedate=July 29, 2012|df=mdy-all}}&lt;/ref&gt; Larry was on the road and about to take the stage for a live show at [[Rocky Point Amusement Park]] in [[Warwick, Rhode Island]] when he heard the news.&lt;ref&gt;''You Must Be This Tall: The Story of Rocky Point Park.'' [[Midway Pictures]].&lt;/ref&gt; He immediately flew home to California, leaving the other two Stooges to improvise their remaining shows at the park.&lt;ref name=Scrapbookrev/&gt;

Mabel's death came nearly six years after the death of their only son, John, in a car crash on November 17, 1961, at age 24.&lt;ref name = "Stooge Bio"/&gt; Their only daughter, Phyllis, died of cancer on April 3, 1989, at 60.&lt;ref name=Scrapbookrev/&gt;

Fine is sometimes erroneously reported to be the father of sportscaster [[Warner Wolf]], who is in fact the son of Jack Wolf, one of several other "stooges" who played in [[Ted Healy]]'s [[vaudeville]] act at one time or another. Fine is the father-in-law of actor and Los Angeles television personality [[Don Lamond]], best known for hosting the Stooges shorts on [[KTTV]] for many years.

==Final acting years and death==
[[File:larryfinegrave.jpg|thumb| Larry Fine's [[gravesite]] at the [[Forest Lawn Memorial Park, Glendale|Forest Lawn Memorial Park Cemetery]] in [[Glendale, California]].]]
In 1965, Fine, Moe Howard, and Joe DeRita started a new TV comedy show entitled ''[[The New 3 Stooges]]'', a mixture of live and animated segments. While the show produced good ratings, the men were too old by this point to do [[slapstick]] comedy well.  Fine began showing signs of mental impairment, such as frequent trouble delivering his lines properly.

A few years later, the men started working ''[[Kook's Tour]]'', a new TV series. On January 9, 1970, Fine suffered a debilitating [[stroke]] that paralyzed the left side of his body. This event marked the end of his performing career.&lt;ref name=StrokeOfLuck/&gt;

Fine eventually moved to the [[Motion Picture &amp; Television Country House and Hospital|Motion Picture Country House]], an industry retirement community in [[Woodland Hills, Los Angeles, California|Woodland Hills]], where he spent his remaining years, and used a [[wheelchair]] during the last five.&lt;ref name=obit&gt;{{cite news |author=Louis Calta  |title=Larry Fine of Three Stooges, Frizzy‐Haired Comic, Is Dead |url=https://www.nytimes.com/1975/01/25/archives/larry-fine-of-three-stooges-frizzyhaired-comic-is-dead.html |quote= |newspaper=[[New York Times]] |date=January 25, 1975 }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=Scrapbookrev/&gt;&lt;ref name=StrokeOfLuck/&gt; Even in his paralyzed state, Fine did what he could to entertain the other patients. Fine also completed his "as told to" autobiography ''Stroke of Luck'',&lt;ref name=StrokeOfLuck&gt;Larry Fine, as told to James Carone - ''Stroke of Luck'', Siena Publishing, Hollywood, 1973.&lt;/ref&gt; Fine received visits from his old partner Moe Howard.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |first=Pat |last=Brady |title=Recovering From Stroke: It's Easy Life for the Stooge |work=Los Angeles Times, Valley Edition, Part XI, |page=6 |date=October 28, 1973}}&lt;/ref&gt; Fine remained accessible to Stooge fans, regularly hosting them despite his disability. When asked if spending his life as a Stooge was enjoyable, he would comment "it wasn't fun: it was work — but it paid off good, so I enjoyed it."&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book| last = Davis| first = Lon &amp; Debra| title = Stooges Among Us | publisher = BearManor Media| year = 2008 | origyear = | location = Albany, Georgia | pages = 117 | url = http://www.bearmanormedia.com/stooges-among-us-hardcover-edition-edited-by-lon-and-debra-davis?search=hardcover | isbn = 1-59393-300-2}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Like [[Curly Howard]], Fine suffered several additional strokes before his death on January 24, 1975, at the nursing home in Woodland Hills, at age 72.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |first=Dorothy |last=Townsend |title=Larry Fine of 3 Stooges Dies After Stroke at 73 |work=Los Angeles Times, Part I, |page=3 |date=January 24, 1975}}&lt;/ref&gt; He was interred with his wife, Mabel, and son, John in a crypt at [[Glendale, California|Glendale's]] [[Forest Lawn Memorial Park, Glendale|Forest Lawn Memorial Park Cemetery]] in the Freedom Mausoleum, Sanctuary of Liberation.&lt;ref name=FindAGrave&gt;{{Find a Grave|338|accessdate=2015-12-09}}&lt;/ref&gt; Fellow Stooge [[Joe Besser]] is interred in a grave a short distance away from the Freedom Mausoleum.&lt;ref&gt;[https://www.findagrave.com/memorial/1554 "Joe Besser". Find a Grave.] Retrieved 2015-12-09&lt;/ref&gt; [[Moe Howard]] died four months after him.

==Filmography==
{{Main article|The Three Stooges filmography}}

==Legacy==
[[File: Sing a Song of Six Pants (1947) 2.jpg|thumb|right|300px|Moe Howard, his brother Shemp Howard, and Larry Fine in 1947's ''[[Sing a Song of Six Pants]]''.]]

* The Three Stooges have a star on the [[Hollywood Walk of Fame]] in honor of their contributions to the motion-pictures industry at 1560 Vine Street in Hollywood, dedicated on August 30, 1983, with ex-stooge [[Joe Besser]] in attendance.
* In the 2000 made-for-TV movie, Larry Fine was played by [[Evan Handler]].
* In a 2004 ''[[The New Yorker|New Yorker]]'' feature on the [[Farrelly brothers|Farrelly Brothers's]] attempt to write a script for a new Three Stooges movie, [[Peter Farrelly]] offered his theory of Stooge appreciation: “Growing up, first you watched Curly, then Moe, and then your eyes got to Larry. He’s the reactor, the most vulnerable. Five to fourteen, Curly; fourteen to twenty-one, Moe. Anyone out of college, if you’re not looking at Larry you don’t have a good brain.”
* A large mural of Larry Fine appears on a wall at the busy intersection of 3rd and South Streets, near his birthplace in [[Philadelphia]]. The effort to create a mural on that site began when a local weekly newspaper suggested that the city should somehow honor him. Dedicated on October 26, 1999, with Fine's sister in attendance, that mural showed Larry with a peculiar look on his face. In May 2006, a similar mural showing Larry with a more animated expression and playing the violin was painted over the original mural. This mural stands over Jon's Bar and Grill with a sign reading "Birthplace of Larry Fine."
* On October 15, 2009, the Associated Alumni of [[Central High School (Philadelphia, Pennsylvania)|Central High School]] in [[Philadelphia]] inducted Fine into that school's Hall of Fame, even though he never graduated. A member of the Central Alumni Hall of Fame Committee pointed out, "Many people are not even aware that Mr. Fine was a Philadelphian and that is a part of what we’re trying to do."
* In the 2012 [[Farrelly brothers]]' film ''[[The Three Stooges (2012 film)|The Three Stooges]]'', Larry is portrayed by [[Sean Hayes (actor)|Sean Hayes]] of ''[[Will &amp; Grace]]'' fame. Young Larry is portrayed by Lance Chantiles-Wertz.

==References==
{{reflist}}

==Further reading==
* ''Stroke of Luck''; by James Carone, as told by Larry Fine (Siena Publishing, Hollywood, 1973.)
* ''Larry, the Stooge in the Middle''; by Morris Feinberg with G. P. Skratz (Last Gasp, San Francisco, 2001.) {{ISBN|0-86719-324-7}}
* ''One Fine Stooge: A Frizzy Life in Pictures''; by Steve Cox and Jim Terry, (Cumberland House Publishing, 2006.)

==External links==
* {{iMDb name|4310}}
* {{tcmdb name|id=61879|name=Larry Fine}}
* {{IBDB name}}
* [http://www.ThreeStooges.com Larry Fine at The Three Stooges Official Website]
* [http://www.larryfine.com/ Larry Fine Webpage]
* {{findagrave|338}}

{{ThreeStooges}}

{{Authority control}}

{{DEFAULTSORT: Fine, Larry}}
[[Category: 1902 births]]
[[Category: 1975 deaths]]
[[Category: 20th-century American male actors]]
[[Category: American male comedians]]
[[Category: American gin players]]
[[Category: Jewish American comedians]]
[[Category: American male stage actors]]
[[Category: American people of Russian-Jewish descent]]
[[Category: American male television actors]]
[[Category: American male voice actors]]
[[Category: American male boxers]]
[[Category: Burials at Forest Lawn Memorial Park (Glendale)]]
[[Category: Central High School (Philadelphia) alumni]]
[[Category: Deaths from neurological disease]]
[[Category: Jewish American male actors]]
[[Category: Male actors from Philadelphia]]
[[Category: The Three Stooges members]]
[[Category: Vaudeville performers]]
[[Category: American male comedy actors]]</text>
      <sha1>flpkfdow4xudje5g0ngutsizr3tsd09</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
