<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10.xsd" version="0.10" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <dbname>enwiki</dbname>
    <base>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.32.0-wmf.16</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="118" case="first-letter">Draft</namespace>
      <namespace key="119" case="first-letter">Draft talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2300" case="first-letter">Gadget</namespace>
      <namespace key="2301" case="first-letter">Gadget talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2302" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition</namespace>
      <namespace key="2303" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Mack Sennett</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>18824</id>
    <revision>
      <id>851404466</id>
      <parentid>851402494</parentid>
      <timestamp>2018-07-22T02:06:21Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>MarnetteD</username>
        <id>220924</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>rvt changes made w/o explanation or sourcing</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="19616">{{more citations needed|date=February 2018}}
{{Infobox person
| name = Mack Sennett
| image = Mack Sennett 1916.jpg
| birth_name = Michael Sinnott
| birth_date = {{Birth date|1880|01|17|mf=y}}
| birth_place = [[Richmond, Quebec]], Canada
| death_date = {{Death date and age|1960|11|05|1880|01|17|mf=y}}
| death_place = [[Woodland Hills, California]], U.S.
| years_active = 1908–1949
| occupation = Actor, director, producer, screenwriter, presenter, composer, cinematographer
}}
'''Mack Sennett''' (born '''Michael Sinnott'''; January 17, 1880 &amp;ndash; November 5, 1960) was an American film director and producer, known as the King of Comedy.

Born in Canada, he started in films in the Biograph company of New York, he opened Keystone Studios in Edendale, California in 1912. It was the first fully enclosed film stage, and Sennett became famous as the originator of slapstick routines such as pie-throwing and car-chases, as seen in the Keystone Cops films. He also produced short features that displayed his Bathing Beauties, many of whom went on to develop successful acting careers.
 
Sennett’s work in sound-movies was less successful and he was bankrupted in 1933. He was presented with an honorary Academy Award for his contribution to film comedy.

==Early life==
Born Michael Sinnott in Richmond [[Danville, Quebec|Ste-Bibiane Parish, Quebec]], Canada, he was the son of [[Irish Catholic]] John Sinnott and Catherine Foy, married 1879 in Tingwick St-Patrice Parish, Québec.&lt;ref name="Spokane Daily Chronicle - March 25th 1932"&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://news.google.com/newspapers?nid=1338&amp;dat=19320325&amp;id=ZoUSAAAAIBAJ&amp;sjid=3fQDAAAAIBAJ&amp;pg=2954,5607197|title=Give Citizenship to Mack Sennett|accessdate=2010-04-23}}&lt;/ref&gt; The newlyweds moved the same year to Richmond, where John Sinnott was hired as a laborer. By 1883, when Michael's brother George was born, John Sinnott was working in Richmond as an innkeeper; he worked as an innkeeper for many years afterward. John Sinnott and Catherine Foy had all their children and raised their family in Richmond, then a small [[Eastern Townships]] village. At that time, Michael's grandparents were living in Danville, Québec. Michael Sinnott moved to [[Connecticut]] when he was 17 years old.

He lived for a while in [[Northampton, Massachusetts]], where, according to his autobiography, Sennett first got the idea to become an opera singer after seeing a [[vaudeville]] show. He claimed that the most respected lawyer in town, Northampton mayor (and future [[President of the United States]]) [[Calvin Coolidge]], as well as Sennett's own mother, tried to talk him out of his musical ambitions.&lt;ref&gt;King of Comedy by Mack Sennett, 1954&lt;/ref&gt;
 
In New York City, Sennett became an [[actor]], [[singer]], [[dancer]], [[clown]], [[set designer]], and [[Film director|director]] for [[American Mutoscope and Biograph Company|Biograph]]. A major distinction in his acting career, often overlooked, is the fact that Sennett played [[Sherlock Holmes]] 11 times, albeit as a parody, between 1911 and 1913.{{Citation needed|date=January 2010}}

==Keystone Studios==
[[Image:Mack Sennett Studios 1917.jpg|thumb|right|300px|Mack Sennett Studios, ''circa'' 1917]]

With financial backing from Adam Kessel and Charles O. Bauman of the [[New York Motion Picture Company]], Michael "Mack" Sennett founded [[Keystone Studios]] in [[Edendale, Los Angeles, California|Edendale, California]] in 1912 (which is now a part of [[Echo Park, California|Echo Park]]). The original main building which was the first totally enclosed film stage and studio ever constructed, is still there today. Many important actors cemented their film careers with Sennett, including [[Marie Dressler]], [[Mabel Normand]], [[Charles Chaplin]], [[Harry Langdon]], [[Roscoe Arbuckle]], [[Harold Lloyd]], [[Raymond Griffith]], [[Gloria Swanson]], [[Ford Sterling]], [[Andy Clyde]], [[Chester Conklin]], [[Polly Moran]], [[Louise Fazenda]], [[The Keystone Cops]], [[Bing Crosby]], and [[W. C. Fields]].

Mack Sennett's [[slapstick]] comedies were noted for their wild car chases and [[custard pie]] warfare, especially in the ''Keystone Cops ''series. Additionally, Sennett's first female comedian was Mabel Normand, who became a major star under his direction and with whom he embarked on a tumultuous romantic relationship. Sennett also developed the ''Kid Comedies'', a forerunner of the ''[[Our Gang]]'' films, and in a short time, his name became synonymous with screen comedy which were called "flickers" at the time. In 1915, Keystone Studios became an autonomous production unit of the ambitious [[Triangle Film Corporation]], as Sennett joined forces with [[D. W. Griffith]] and [[Thomas H. Ince|Thomas Ince]], both powerful figures in the film industry.{{Citation needed|date=January 2010}}

== Sennett Bathing Beauties ==

[[File:MackSennetBathingBeauties.JPG|right|thumb|Sennett Bathing Beauties]]

[[File:Billy Bevan (1).jpg|right|thumb|Actor [[Billy Bevan]] flanked by four bathing beauties, 1920s]]

Also beginning in 1915,&lt;ref&gt;"Splashes of Fun and Beauty" by Hilde d'Haeyere, collected in ''Slapstick Comedy'' by Rob King, &lt;!--publisher, place, &amp; year? Is King writer or editor?--&gt; p.205.&lt;/ref&gt; Sennett assembled a bevy of women known as the Sennett Bathing Beauties to appear in provocative bathing costumes in comedy short subjects, in promotional material, and in promotional events such as [[Venice Beach]] beauty contests.

Two of those often named as Bathing Beauties do not belong on the list: Mabel Normand and Gloria Swanson. Normand was a featured player, and her 1912 8-minute film ''[[The Water Nymph]]'' may have been the direct inspiration for the Bathing Beauties.&lt;ref&gt;Balshofer, Fred J. &amp; Miller, Arthur C. ''One reel a week'',&lt;!--publisher, place, &amp; year?--&gt; p.81.&lt;/ref&gt; Although Gloria Swanson worked for Sennett in 1916 and was photographed in a bathing suit, she was also a star and "vehemently denied" being one of the bathing beauties.&lt;ref&gt;Jeanine Basinger, Jeanine. ''Silent Stars'', &lt;!--publisher, place, &amp; year?--&gt; p.205.&lt;/ref&gt;

Not individually featured or named, many of these young women ascended to significant careers of their own. They included [[Juanita Hansen]], [[Claire Anderson]], [[Marie Prevost]], [[Phyllis Haver]], and [[Carole Lombard]]. In the 1920s, Sennett's Bathing Beauties remained popular enough to provoke imitators such as the [[Christie Studios]]' Bathing Beauties (counting [[Raquel Torres]] and [[Laura La Plante]] as alumnae&lt;ref&gt;Lowe, Denise. ''An encyclopedic dictionary of women in early American films, 1895-1930'', &lt;!--publisher, place, &amp; year?--&gt; p.308.&lt;/ref&gt;) and [[20th Century Fox#Fox Film Corporation|Fox Film Corporation]]'s "Sunshine Girls" (counting [[Janet Gaynor]] as an alumna).&lt;ref&gt;King, Rob. ''The fun factory: the Keystone Film Company and the emergence of mass culture'', &lt;!--publisher, place, &amp; year?--&gt; p.211.&lt;/ref&gt; The Sennett Bathing Beauties continued to appear through 1928.

== Independent production ==

In 1917, Sennett gave up the Keystone trademark and organized his own company, Mack Sennett Comedies Corporation. (Sennett's bosses retained the Keystone trademark and produced a cheap series of comedy shorts that were "Keystones" in name only: they were unsuccessful, and Sennett had no connection with them.) Sennett went on to produce more ambitious comedy short films and a few feature-length films.{{Citation needed|date=January 2010}}
During the 1920s, his short subjects were in much demand, featuring stars such as [[Billy Bevan]], [[Andy Clyde]], Harry Gribbon, [[Vernon Dent]], [[Alice Day]], Ralph Graves, Charlie Murray, and [[Harry Langdon]]. He produced several features with his brightest stars such as [[Ben Turpin]] and Mabel Normand.

Many of Sennett's films of the early 1920s were inherited by [[Warner Bros. Studio]]. Warner Bros. merged with the original distributor, First National, and added music and commentary to several of these short subjects. Unfortunately, many of the films of this period were destroyed due to inadequate storage. As a result, many of Sennett's films from his most productive and creative period no longer exist.{{Citation needed|date=January 2010}}

==Move to Pathé Exchange==

In the mid-1920s, Sennett moved to [[Pathé Exchange]] distribution. Pathé had a huge market share, but made bad corporate decisions, such as attempting to sell too many comedies at once (including those of Sennett's main competitor, [[Hal Roach]]). In 1927, [[Paramount Pictures|Paramount]] and [[MGM]], which were Hollywood's two top studios at the time, took note of the profits being made by smaller companies such as [[Pathé Exchange]] and [[Educational Pictures]]. So, Paramount and MGM decided to resume the production and distribution of short subjects. Hal Roach signed with MGM, but Mack Sennett remained with Pathé Exchange even during hard times, which were brought on by the competition. Hundreds of other independent exhibitors and movie houses of this period had switched from Pathe′ to the new MGM or Paramount films and short subjects.{{Citation needed|date=January 2010}}

==Experiments, awards, and bankruptcy==
[[File:Mabel's Dramatic Career 1913.jpeg|thumb|right|300px|Movie theatre audience members Roscoe Arbuckle and Mack Sennett square off while watching [[Mabel Normand]] onscreen in ''[[Mabel's Dramatic Career]]'' (1913)]]
[[File:The Fatal Mallet.jpg|right|thumb|Mabel Normand, Mack Sennett, and Charles Chaplin in ''[[The Fatal Mallet]]'' (1914)]]
[[File:Love, Speed and Thrills - Walter Wright - 1915, Keystone Film - EYE FLM39508 - OB 685625.webm|thumb|Silent film ''Love, Speed and Thrills'' (1915) directed by [[Walter Wright (director)|Walter Wright]] and produced by Mack Sennett, running time: 14:12, is a chase film in which a man (named Walrus) kidnaps the wife of his benefactor, but the so-called "Keystone Cops" are also chasing down Walrus.]]
Sennett made a reasonably smooth transition to sound films, releasing them through Earle Hammons's Educational Pictures. Sennett occasionally experimented with color. Plus, he was the first to get a talkie short subject on the market in 1928. In 1932, he was nominated for the [[Academy Award for Live Action Short Film]] in the comedy division for producing ''[[The Loud Mouth]]'' (with Matt McHugh, in the sports-heckler role later taken in [[Columbia Pictures]] remakes by [[Charley Chase]] and [[Shemp Howard]]). Sennett also won an Academy Award in the novelty division for his film ''[[Wrestling Swordfish]]'' also in 1932.&lt;ref name=oscars/&gt; On March 25, 1932, he became a United States citizen.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |author= |title=Mack Sennett is Naturalized |url=https://query.nytimes.com/gst/abstract.html?res=9C0CEEDD163EE633A25755C2A9659C946394D6CF&amp;legacy=true |quote= |newspaper=[[The New York Times]] |date=March 26, 1932 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

Sennett often clung to outmoded techniques, making his early-1930s films seem dated and quaint. This doomed his attempt to re-enter the feature-film market with ''Hypnotized'' (starring [[blackface]] comedians [[Moran and Mack]], "The Two Black Crows"). However, Sennett enjoyed great success with short comedies starring [[Bing Crosby]], which were more than likely instrumental in Sennett's product being picked up by a major studio, [[Paramount Pictures]]. [[W. C. Fields]] conceived and starred in four famous Sennett-Paramount comedies. Fields himself recalled that he "made seven comedies for the Irishman", his original deal called for one film and an option for six more, but ultimately only four were made.

Sennett's studio did not survive the [[Great Depression]]. His partnership with Paramount lasted only one year and he was forced into bankruptcy in November 1933.

On January 12, 1934, Sennett was injured in an automobile accident that killed [[Charles Mack (blackface performer)|blackface performer Charles Mack]] in [[Mesa, Arizona]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |author= |agency=[[Associated Press]] |title=Mack, Comedian, Killed In Crash. Moran, His Partner in Blackface Skits, Escapes Injury in Arizona Mishap |url=https://query.nytimes.com/gst/abstract.html?res=9907E6D91439E33ABC4A52DFB766838F629EDE |quote=... injured Mack Sennett, former producer of 'Bathing Beauty' film comedies. |newspaper=[[The New York Times]] |date=January 12, 1934 |accessdate=2015-03-22 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

His last work, in 1935, was as a producer-director for Educational Pictures, in which he directed [[Buster Keaton]] in ''[[The Timid Young Man]]'' and [[Joan Davis]] in ''[[Way Up Thar]]''. (The 1935 [[Vitaphone]] short subject ''[[Keystone Hotel (film)|Keystone Hotel]]'' is not a Sennett production, although it featured several alumni from the Mack Sennett Studios. Actually, Sennett was not involved in the making of this film.)

Mack Sennett went into semiretirement at the age of 55, having produced more than 1,000 silent films and several dozen [[talkies]] during a 25-year career. His studio property was purchased by [[Mascot Pictures]] (later part of [[Republic Pictures]]), and many of his former staffers found work at [[Columbia Pictures]].

In March 1938, Sennett was presented with an honorary [[Academy Award]]: "for his lasting contribution to the comedy technique of the screen, the basic principles of which are as important today as when they were first put into practice, the Academy presents a Special Award to that master of fun, discoverer of stars, sympathetic, kindly, understanding comedy genius - Mack Sennett."&lt;ref name=oscars&gt;[http://www.oscars.org/research-preservation/resources-databases/index.html Academy Awards Database] at [[Academy of Motion Picture Arts and Sciences]]&lt;/ref&gt;

==Later projects==
Rumors abounded that Sennett would be returning to film production (a 1938 publicity release indicated that he would be working with [[Stan Laurel]] of [[Laurel and Hardy]]), but apart from Sennett reissuing a couple of his Bing Crosby two-reelers to theaters, nothing happened. Sennett did appear in front of the camera, however, in ''[[Hollywood Cavalcade]]'' (1939), itself a thinly disguised version of the Mack Sennett-Mabel Normand romance. In 1949, he provided film footage for and also appeared in the first full-length comedy compilation called ''Down Memory Lane'' (1949), which was written and narrated by [[Steve Allen]]. Sennett was profiled in the television series ''[[This is Your Life]]'' in 1954.&lt;ref&gt;{{IMDb title|id=0721407|title=This Is Your Life, broadcast March 10, 1954.}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Thomas, Bob (1954). "Sennett Takes Sentimental Journey in Past at Reunion". ''Panama City News'', March 12, 1954. Retrieved from [http://looking-for-mabel.webs.com/sennettobelisk.htm Looking for Mabel Normand] on 2012-02-03.&lt;/ref&gt; and made a cameo appearance (for $1,000) in ''[[Abbott and Costello Meet the Keystone Kops]]'' (1955). His last contribution worth noting was to the NBC radio program ''Biography in Sound'' relating memories of working with W.C. Fields, which was broadcast February 28, 1956.

==Death==
Mack Sennett died on November 5, 1960, in [[Woodland Hills, California]], aged 80.&lt;ref name=obit&gt;{{cite news |author= |title=Mack Sennett, 76, Film Pioneer Who Developed Slapstick, Dies. Keystone Kops, Custard Pies and Bathing Beauties Were Symbols of His Movies |url=https://query.nytimes.com/gst/abstract.html?res=9F07EED81E31E633A25755C0A9679D946191D6CF&amp;legacy=true |quote= |newspaper=[[The New York Times]] |date=November 6, 1960 }}&lt;/ref&gt; He was interred in the [[Holy Cross Cemetery, Culver City|Holy Cross Cemetery]] in [[Culver City, California]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |author= |title=Sennett Buried in Hollywood |url=https://query.nytimes.com/gst/abstract.html?res=9901E5D91F31EF3ABC4C51DFB767838B679EDE&amp;legacy=true |quote= |newspaper=[[The New York Times]] |date=November 24, 1960 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Filmography==
{{main|Mack Sennett filmography}}

==Tributes==
For his contribution to the motion picture industry, Sennett honored with a star on the [[Hollywood Walk of Fame]] at 6712 [[Hollywood Boulevard]]. He was also inducted into [[Canada's Walk of Fame]] in 2014.

==Keystone legacy==

A line in a [[Henry Kuttner]] science-fiction short story "Piggy Bank" reads, "Within seconds the scene resembled a Mack Sennett pie-throwing comedy."&lt;ref&gt;''A Treasury of Great Science Fiction, vol. 2'', [[Anthony Boucher]] (ed.) Doubleday &amp; Co., 1959.&lt;/ref&gt;

In ''[[A Story of Water]]'', a 1961 short film by [[Jean-Luc Godard]] and [[François Truffaut]], the directors dedicate the film to Mack Sennett.

[[Henry Mancini]]'s score for the 1963 film ''[[The Pink Panther (1963 film)|The Pink Panther]]'', the original entry in the series, contains a segment called "Shades of Sennett". It is played on a silent film era style "[[barrel house]]" piano, and accompanies a climactic scene in which the incompetent police detective [[Inspector Clouseau]] is involved in a multi-vehicle chase with the antagonists.

In 1974, [[Michael Stewart (playwright)|Michael Stewart]] and [[Jerry Herman]] wrote the musical ''[[Mack &amp; Mabel]]'', chronicling the romance between Sennett and Mabel Normand.

Sennett also was a leading character in ''[[The Biograph Girl]]'', a 1980 musical about the silent-film era.

[[Peter Lovesey]]'s 1983 novel ''Keystone'' is a [[whodunnit]] set in the Keystone Studios and involving (among others), Mack Sennett, Mabel Normand, Roscoe Arbuckle, and the Keystone Cops.

[[Dan Aykroyd]] portrayed Mack Sennett in the 1992 movie ''[[Chaplin (film)|Chaplin]]''. [[Marisa Tomei]] played Mabel Normand and [[Robert Downey, Jr.]] starred as Charlie Chaplin.

Joseph Beattie and Andrea Deck portrayed Mack Sennett and Mabel Normand, respectively, in episode eight of series two of ITV's ''[[Mr. Selfridge]]''.

==See also==
*[[Canadian pioneers in early Hollywood]]

==References==
{{reflist|30em}}

==Further reading==
* Lahue, Kalton (1971); ''Mack Sennett's Keystone: The man, the myth and the comedies''; New York: Barnes; {{ISBN|978-0-498-07461-5}}

==External links==
{{Commons category}}
*{{Internet Archive author |sname=Mack Sennett |sopt=t}}
*{{IMDb name|784407|Mack Sennett}}
*{{Find a Grave|942}}
*[http://www.virtual-history.com/movie/person/1789/mack-sennett Mack Sennett] at Virtual History
*[http://catalog.oscars.org/vwebv/holdingsInfo?bibId=69727 Mack Sennett papers], Margaret Herrick Library, Academy of Motion Picture Arts and Sciences

{{Academy Honorary Award}}
{{Portal bar|Biography|Silent film|Film}}

{{Authority control}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Sennett, Mack}}
[[Category:1880 births]]
[[Category:1960 deaths]]
[[Category:Male actors from Massachusetts]]
[[Category:Academy Honorary Award recipients]]
[[Category:American male comedians]]
[[Category:American comedians]]
[[Category:American male film actors]]
[[Category:American male silent film actors]]
[[Category:Anglophone Quebec people]]
[[Category:Burials at Holy Cross Cemetery, Culver City]]
[[Category:Canadian emigrants to the United States]]
[[Category:Canadian film directors]]
[[Category:Canadian film producers]]
[[Category:Canadian male silent film actors]]
[[Category:Canadian male comedians]]
[[Category:American people of Irish descent]]
[[Category:Canadian people of Irish descent]]
[[Category:People from Estrie]]
[[Category:People from Northampton, Massachusetts]]
[[Category:Producers of Live Action Short Film Academy Award winners]]
[[Category:Slapstick comedians]]
[[Category:Silent film directors]]
[[Category:20th-century American male actors]]
[[Category:20th-century Canadian male actors]]
[[Category:Articles containing video clips]]
[[Category:American film production company founders]]</text>
      <sha1>esf1lpmr9l7hsoh7rvwqk93js4t8dmr</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
