<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10.xsd" version="0.10" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <dbname>enwiki</dbname>
    <base>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.32.0-wmf.16</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="118" case="first-letter">Draft</namespace>
      <namespace key="119" case="first-letter">Draft talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2300" case="first-letter">Gadget</namespace>
      <namespace key="2301" case="first-letter">Gadget talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2302" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition</namespace>
      <namespace key="2303" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Mario Barth</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>27997937</id>
    <revision>
      <id>833656488</id>
      <parentid>718501992</parentid>
      <timestamp>2018-04-01T20:19:19Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Ira Leviton</username>
        <id>25046916</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor/>
      <comment>Fixed a typo and combined a duplicate reference.</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="7088">{{multiple issues|
{{no footnotes|date=April 2014}}
{{BLP sources|date=March 2014}}
{{Use dmy dates|date=September 2013}}
{{Expand German|date=July 2010|Mario Barth}}
}}
{{Infobox person
|name        = Mario Barth
|image       = 2234Mario Barth 2.JPG
|caption     =
|birth_date  = {{birth date and age|1972|11|01|df=yes}}
|birth_place = [[Berlin]]-[[Mariendorf]], [[Germany]]
|net worth   = 70 Million Euros&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=News.de: Mario Barth witzelt sich reich: 70 Millionen Euro auf dem Konto|url=http://www.news.de/tv/855606734/stefan-raab-guenther-jauch-thomas-gottschalk-vermoegen-so-reich-sind-deutschlands-tv-moderatoren-bohlen-barth/2/}}&lt;/ref&gt;
|website     = [http://www.mariobarth.de/ Official website]
}}
'''Mario Barth''' (born 1 November 1972&lt;ref name="Barth Official"&gt;{{cite web|title=Mario Barth - Official Website - Biography|url=http://www.mario-barth.de/biografie}}&lt;/ref&gt; in Berlin) is a [[Germany|German]] [[comedian]] who mainly deals with the interactions between men and women.

==Life==
Barth was one out of six children born to a family in Berlin-Mariendorf. Raised [[Catholic]], he served as an altar boy in his youth, and his parents sent him to a private Catholic school. Barth completed an apprenticeship as a telecommunications electrician at [[Siemens]] in Berlin. Thereafter, in 1995, he started studying to become an actor.&lt;ref name="Barth Official" /&gt;

During several comedy-workshops, such as the Comedy School in Cologne, he met other actors and comedians, including [[Diether Krebs]], Anka Zink, and [[Thomas Hermanns]]. He gained experience by performing on TV shows such as NightWash and Quatsch Comedy Club. Since the beginning of 2001 he has been on the road with his stage show, ''Männer sind Schweine, Frauen aber auch!'' (translated as "Men are pigs, but women are too"). In 2003, Barth had his comedy breakthrough with ''"Männer sind Schweine, Frauen aber auch!"''.&lt;ref name="Barth Official" /&gt;  In the same year, he developed his own comedy question-program called ''Keine Ahnung?'' ("No Clue"), with its second season broadcast in 2005. In 2004, Barth published a ''"dictionary for men to understand women"'' called ''"Deutsch-Frau, Frau-Deutsch"''.&lt;ref name="Barth Official" /&gt; Barth's dictionary sold out within the first days of its publication and so far 2&lt;ref name="Barth Official" /&gt; million dictionaries have been sold. The dictionary was also sold internationally in various countries such as South Korea, the Netherlands, the Czech Republic, Japan and Poland.&lt;ref name="Barth Official" /&gt; Barth has been an occasional guest in the comedy show ''[[Schillerstraße]]'', where his roles included, among other things, a heating engineer, an exterminator, a master potter and a funeral director. He also took part in the RTL show, ''Typisch Frau – Typisch Mann'', from its inception.

On 28 October 2005, his Live-DVD, ''Männer sind Schweine, Frauen aber auch!'', was published after being recorded on 24 and 25 June in Berlin. The DVD reached the number 3 position on the German album-charts, and has reached platinum status for selling over two million times.  The following year, on 16 February, Barth started his new program, ''Männer sind primitiv, aber glücklich!'' ("Men are primitive, but happy!"), which received the German Comedy Award in the category best live-comedy, in October 2006. RTL broadcast, on 1 and 8 December 2006, the program ''Mario Sucht das Paradies Aus'', where Barth travelled around Dubai, as a cowboy in Texas, as a fireman in Dallas, as a pilot (à la Top Gun),  as well as in Hollywood with Ralf Möller. Beginning on 30 November 2007, RTL has shown the ten-part, new entertainment program,  ''Mario Barth Präsentiert''.

On 12 July 2008 Barth established a new world record in the category, "live-comedy with the largest audience", as he performed in front of 70,000 people at [[Olympic Stadium]] in Berlin, breaking the previous record of 15,900 comedy-visitors held by the American comedian [[Chris Rock]] at a show in London. With this performance Barth also published his single, "Mensch Berlin", which he recorded with Paul Kuhn. In September 2008 the DVD ''Die Weltrekord-Show: Männer sind primitiv aber glücklich!'' was published, which included the whole performance at Olympic Stadium. Mario Barth was selected out of 100 candidates as the "most embarrassing man" of Berlin by the Berlin journal, ''Tip'', at the end of 2008.

In 2009 Mario Barth produced his own first movie, the comedy ''Männersache'', where he eleborated on the relationship between man and woman, similar to his comedy routines.  The audio book ''Männersache'' came out in April of the same year. On 2 May 2009 Barth started up his new stage program entitled ''Männer sind peinlich, Frauen manchmal auch!''. In September 2009 the matching live CD was released. Since 2009, he has hosted the comedy-show ''Willkommen bei Mario Barth'' on RTL. In March 2010 the CD compilation ''Die Trilogie'' was released, which included live on-stage performances of his programs ''Männer sind Schweine, Frauen aber auch!'', ''Männer sind primitiv, aber glücklich!'', as well as ''Männer sind peinlich, Frauen manchmal auch!'' ("Men are embarrissing, but women sometimes too!").

In September 2010, the DVD of his on stage performances ''Männer sind peinlich, Frauen manchmal auch!'' was published.  Later that year, in December, Barth registered the quotation, "Nichts reimt sich auf Uschi", as a protected expression, although this quotation was used by Oliver Kalkhofe and Dietmar Wischmeyer, as presenters of the show ''Frühstyxradio'' at Radio FFN. A T-shirt producer, who had printed this quote on T-shirts, was officially warned by Barth's attorneys to desist using the quote, with a claim value of 100,000 €. Barth lives in both Berlin and Düsseldorf, where his entertainment company is located.

In 2014, Barth established a new world record: Barth managed to increase the record he had set in 2008 as the German comedian in the category "live-comedy with the largest audience" with an audience of "116,498". Guinness World Records judge Eva Norris had observed the world record attempt.&lt;ref name=GWR&gt;{{cite web|title=Guinness World Records: Mario Barth|url=http://www.guinnessworldrecords.de/news/2014/6/mario-barth-holt-den-zuschauer-weltrekord!-57989?fb_comment_id=948558995170368_1032397386786528}}&lt;/ref&gt; This is Barth's third world record; apart from the two audience records, Barth also hold the world record for the longest DVD ending which lasted 40 minutes and 38 seconds and which can be found on Barth's DVD ''Mario Barth: Die Weltrekord-Show''.&lt;ref name=GWR/&gt;

==References==
{{reflist}}

==External links==
* [http://www.mariobarth.de/ Official website] {{de icon}}
* [http://musicline.de/de/chartverfolgung_summary/artist/Barth%2CMario?sort=entry&amp;type=longplay German Album Charts]
* {{IMDb name|1496122|Mario Barth}}

{{Authority control}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Barth, Mario}}
[[Category:1972 births]]
[[Category:Living people]]
[[Category:People from Berlin]]
[[Category:German male comedians]]</text>
      <sha1>gowasxm7t3kj4qkz2ob8r9fff877gmm</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
