<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10.xsd" version="0.10" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <dbname>enwiki</dbname>
    <base>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.32.0-wmf.16</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="118" case="first-letter">Draft</namespace>
      <namespace key="119" case="first-letter">Draft talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2300" case="first-letter">Gadget</namespace>
      <namespace key="2301" case="first-letter">Gadget talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2302" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition</namespace>
      <namespace key="2303" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Mike Warnke</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>1430865</id>
    <revision>
      <id>843845147</id>
      <parentid>843845140</parentid>
      <timestamp>2018-05-31T20:57:42Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Discospinster</username>
        <id>82432</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>Adding {{pp-vandalism}} ([[WP:TW|TW]])</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="25609">{{pp-vandalism|expiry=20:57, 31 May 2019|small=yes}}
 
{{Use mdy dates|date=March 2014}}
{{Infobox person
| name                      = Mike Warnke
| image                     = Mike Warnke December 2001.jpg
| image_size                = 200px
| alt                       = 
| caption                   = in December 2001
| birth_name                = Michael Alfred Warnke
| birth_date                = {{birth date and age|1946|11|19|mf=yes}}
| birth_place               = [[Evansville, Indiana]], U.S.
| death_date                = 
| death_place               = 
| death_cause               = 
| resting_place             = 
| nationality               = American
| education                 = [[Rim of the World High School]]
| alma_mater                = [[San Bernardino Valley College]]
| occupation                = [[Christianity|Christian]] [[Evangelism|Evangelist]] and [[comedian]]
| known_for                 = Discredited "expert" on [[Satanism]], [[Christian comedy]]
| spouse                    = {{marriage|Sue Studer|1967|1975|reason=divorced}}&lt;br&gt;{{marriage|Carolyn Alberty|1975|1979|reason=divorced}}&lt;br&gt;{{marriage|Rose Hall|1980|1991|reason=divorced}}&lt;br&gt;{{marriage|Susan Patton|1991|}}
| children                  = 2
| website                   = {{URL|http://www.mikewarnke.org/}} 
}}

'''Michael Alfred "Mike" Warnke''' (born November 19, 1946) is an American [[Christianity|Christian]] [[Evangelism|evangelist]] and [[comedian]]. With the success of his books and recordings, Warnke became one of evangelical Christianity's best-known experts on the subject of [[Satanism]] during the 1980s, before his claims of having been a Satanist high priest were discredited in 1991 by the Christian magazine, ''[[Cornerstone (magazine)|Cornerstone]]''.

==Early life==
Mike Warnke was born in 1946 to parents Alfred "Al" Warnke and Louise Warnke. When he was five years old, the Warnke family moved to [[Manchester, Tennessee]] where his father opened a [[truck stop]]. In 1955, Warnke's mother was killed in a car accident. In 1958 his father died, leaving Warnke an [[orphan]]. After the death of his father, Warnke was taken to live with two of his aunts in [[Sparta, Tennessee]], and from there to his father's half-sister and her husband in [[San Bernardino County, California|San Bernardino]], [[California]]. In June 1965, Warnke graduated from [[Rim of the World High School]] in [[Lake Arrowhead, California|Lake Arrowhead]]. That September, he enrolled at [[San Bernardino Valley College]] but withdrew after one semester, whereupon by his account, Warnke began his tenure as a Satanist. On June 2, 1966, Warnke enlisted in the [[United States Navy]]. After graduating from boot-camp on August 22, 1966, Warnke's assigned [[military occupational specialty]] was as a hospital [[corpsman]].&lt;ref name=cornerstone-expose&gt;{{cite journal|url =http://www.cornerstonemag.com/features/iss098/sellingsatan.htm |title = Selling Satan |work = Cornerstone |issue=98 |year=1992 |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20110629063019/http://www.cornerstonemag.com/features/iss098/sellingsatan.htm |archivedate=2011-06-29}}&lt;/ref&gt;

According to the account of his life in the ''Satan Seller'', Warnke [[Conversion to Christianity|converted to Christianity]] during navy [[recruit training|boot camp]].&lt;ref name=cornerstone-expose/&gt; However, high-school acquaintance Charlotte Tweeten has stated she recalls him proclaiming faith in [[Christ]] in the year prior to his navy enlistment in 1966.&lt;ref name=cornerstone-expose/&gt; Warnke also wrote that he began dating fellow Rim of the World High School alumna, Sue Studer, during this time period. This has been disproven, however, and Warnke was actually engaged to Lois Eckenrod at this time.&lt;ref name=cornerstone-expose/&gt; In 1967, Warnke completed naval [[corpsman]] training, returned to [[San Diego]], and married Studer.  Together, they had two children.&lt;ref name=warnke-response&gt;{{cite web |url = http://www.cornerstonemag.com/features/iss098/warnke_response/csr0009a.htm |date=1992-07-15 |title = Warnke's statement in response to Cornerstone's claims |work = Cornerstone |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20110629063109/http://www.cornerstonemag.com/features/iss098/warnke_response/csr0009a.htm |archivedate=2011-06-29}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In 1969, Warnke was deployed to [[Vietnam War|Vietnam]] for a six-month tour of duty.&lt;ref name=cornerstone-vietnam&gt;''Cornerstone'', issue 98: "Records show Warnke was in Vietnam for only six months"&lt;/ref&gt;  Having been wounded in battle during those six months, Warnke was awarded the [[Purple Heart]]. Warnke's own written accounts differ on the number of times he sustained injuries during his time in Vietnam. In ''The Satan Seller'', Warnke says he was wounded twice, while in his second book, ''Hitchhiking on Hope Street'', he states he was wounded five times. Despite these wounds received during his tour of duty as a hospital corpsman, second class,  Warnke's various accounts have him spending much time detained, allegedly killing a man in battle, and surviving being shot several times, including once by an arrow. Warnke says it was the latter wound for which he was awarded the Purple Heart.&lt;ref&gt;''Hey Doc'' recording. Word Records&lt;/ref&gt; Warnke returned to the United States in 1970.&lt;ref name=cornerstone-expose/&gt;

While still serving in the navy, Warnke teamed up with San Diego [[Evangelism|evangelist]] [[Morris Cerullo]] and was touted for his "Satanist experience". Warnke and Cerullo toured the country participating in charismatic [[revival meeting]]s. Cerullo wanted to write a book about youth occultism, and assigned the writing task to David Balsiger with help from Warnke. In early 1972, Warnke requested and received an early discharge from the navy as a [[conscientious objector]] so that he could work full-time in the ministry. Warnke then left Cerullo's ministry to start his own, forbidding Cerullo to use any of his material. It was at this time that Warnke and Balsiger went on to write the book that would make Warnke famous.&lt;ref name=cornerstone-expose/&gt;

==Rise to fame==

===''The Satan Seller''===
In 1972, Warnke's book ''The Satan Seller'' was released. Written by Warnke, with help from Balsiger and [[Les Jones (author)|Les Jones]], the book tells of Warnke being orphaned as a child and his introduction into Satanism. Further detailed is Warnke's participation in sexual orgies, alcoholism, and drug dealing; his rise in the ranks of Satanism to the level of "high priest"; presiding over Satanic rituals including magical spells, summoning demons, ritual sex including a ritual kidnap and rape; the attempt on his life &amp;mdash; a [[heroin]] [[overdose]] &amp;mdash; that left him angry and disillusioned; his heroism in [[Vietnam]]; and how he found Jesus and came home as an evangelist. The story ends with Warnke living happily in California with wife Sue Studer. In fewer than three months after the release, ''The Satan Seller'' had become a religious best-seller.&lt;ref name=cornerstone-expose/&gt;

The book launched Warnke into stardom within [[Evangelicalism|evangelical]] Christian communities. He became a popular speaker at Christian meeting places such as [[Melodyland]] in [[Anaheim, California|Anaheim]], [[California]]. In 1974, Warnke moved his family to attend Trinity Bible College in [[Tulsa, Oklahoma|Tulsa]], [[Oklahoma]], as a nine-month preparation for ministry. It was here, while among other [[Charismatic movement|charismatic]] Christians and recent converts preparing for a life of ministry, that Warnke met Carolyn Alberty and the two began a sexual affair.&lt;ref name=cornerstone-expose/&gt;&lt;!-- LEAVE CITATION IN--&gt; Warnke also met Elijah Coady, an [[episcopi vagantes|independent, schismatic bishop]] of the Syro-Chaldean Church, also known as the [[Assyrian Church of the East]] or the Nestorian church. Coady [[ordained]] Warnke as a [[deacon]]. Upon graduation, Warnke was again ordained, and Warnke moved with his family to [[Denver, Colorado|Denver]], [[Colorado]].&lt;ref name=cornerstone-expose/&gt;

===Recordings and wives===
In November 1975 at an [[Indiana]] [[coffeehouse]], Warnke's talk about his conversion from Satanism to Christianity was incidentally recorded. This recording became Warnke's first [[album]], ''Alive'', which was soon widely played on [[Christian radio]].{{Citation needed|date=March 2007}} Later that same year, despite interventions from pastors and other acclaimed ministers, Warnke left his wife for Alberty and filed for divorce. The divorce was finalized in December 1975 and four months later, Warnke married Alberty.&lt;ref name=cornerstone-expose/&gt;

Warnke's popularity earned him the cover of the September 1976 issue of the Christian magazine, ''Harmony''. In 1977, Warnke released his second album, ''Jester In The King's Court''. In 1978, Warnke recounted his Vietnam experiences on his third album, ''Hey, Doc!''. His albums became "the most popular [[Christian comedy]] albums ever produced".&lt;ref name=ccm&gt;As quoted in ''Cornerstone'' issue 98: {{Cite news |title = When Mike Warnke Speaks, the World Listens! |periodical = Contemporary Christian Music |date = 1979-02-26 |postscript = &lt;!--None--&gt;}}&lt;/ref&gt; During a tour to [[Hazard, Kentucky|Hazard]], [[Kentucky]], Warnke met Rose Hall, a thrice-divorced mother of three children. At this time, Warnke began courting Hall while still married to his second wife. Warnke's second marriage came to an end when, as Alberty stated in an interview,&lt;ref name=cornerstone-expose/&gt;&lt;!-- DO NOT REMOVE CITATION--&gt; "[Warnke] threw me into a wall and split my head open. He said, 'If you go to a local hospital and tell them what your name is, I'll kill you.'" Alberty fled to Florida. By November 1979, their divorce was final, and Warnke moved to Hall's farm in Kentucky. On January 2, 1980, Warnke and Hall were married.&lt;ref name=cornerstone-expose/&gt;

Warnke and his label, [[Word Records]], feuded over an album which he eventually produced and distributed on his own, ''A Christian's Perspective on Halloween '' (1979). Word Records and Warnke reconciled by 1981,{{Citation needed|date=March 2007}} resulting in ''Coming Home'' (1981), and now including wife Rose, ''Higher Education'' (1982) and ''Growing Up'' (1983). Then under Word's [[DaySpring Records|Dayspring]] label, he released (solo) ''Stuff Happens'' (1985), ''Good News Tonight'' (1986), ''One In A Million'' (1988), ''Live ... Totally Weird'' (1989).&lt;ref name=album-list&gt;[http://ccmdiscography.150m.com/W-WebSite.html The Exhaustive Christian Music Discography: W] {{webarchive |url=https://web.archive.org/web/20070314025935/http://ccmdiscography.150m.com/W-WebSite.html |date=March 14, 2007 }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=sweet-music-list&gt;{{cite web |author=Sweet-Music.com |url=http://www.sweet-music.com/WW.html |title=W - Complete Alphabetical Christian Music catalogue listing: Sweet Christian Music - Celebrating Our 10th Year Shipping WorldWide! |publisher=Sweet-music.com |date=2011-09-28 |accessdate=2011-11-14 |deadurl=yes |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20110930192642/http://www.sweet-music.com/WW.html |archivedate=September 30, 2011 |df=mdy-all }}&lt;/ref&gt; Warnke also made a VHS home video, ''Do You Hear Me?'' (1989).

During the 1980s, Warnke's ministry prospered, as Warnke and his new wife toured and performed together, raising millions of dollars for their ministry. Contributions to the ministry were over $1 million in 1985, and over $2 million each year from 1987 through 1990.&lt;ref name=cornerstone-expose/&gt;&lt;!--facts checked; Cornerstone obtained HOCCK filings and cited them in article {{Citation needed|date=March 2007}}--&gt; As the Warnkes' popularity waxed, their personal relationship waned. In 1984, Warnke's wife wrote, "Satan provided a woman to fill the gap in Michael's life."&lt;ref name="great-pretender"&gt;As cited by ''Cornerstone'' expose: {{cite book |author = Rose Hall Warnke |author2=Joan Hake Robie |isbn = 0-914984-03-9 | title = The Great Pretender |location= Lancaster, PA |publisher = Starburst Publishers | year = 1985}}&lt;/ref&gt; The Warnkes separated in 1989 and later divorced in 1991. Six weeks after the divorce was finalized, Warnke married [[Rim of the World High School]] alumna Susan Patton.&lt;ref name=cornerstone-expose/&gt;

===Extravagant claims===
In 1982, Warnke began to exaggerate his achievements. During the 1980s, Warnke's claims of academic degrees increased from two [[Bachelor's degree]]s to two [[Master's Degree]]s to a [[Doctorate of Philosophy]].&lt;!--As stated on Higher Education {{Citation needed|date=March 2007}} --&gt; In ''The Satan Seller'', Warnke says he was wounded twice while in Vietnam. In ''Hitchhiking on Hope Street'', he said he had been wounded five times.&lt;ref name=cornerstone-expose/&gt; Warnke followed up his interest in the [[Syro-Chaldean]] tradition and his 1970s ordination as a deacon with a 1983 ordination by independent bishop Richard Morrill, lately of the Byzantine Catholic Church, Inc. This ordination allowed Warnke to call himself bishop.&lt;ref name=cornerstone-expose/&gt;

===National exposure===
On May 16, 1985, Warnke appeared in a prime-time news report about [[Satanism]] on [[American Broadcasting Company|ABC]]'s ''[[20/20 (US television series)|20/20]]''. In the show's episode titled "The Devil Worshippers", Warnke was included in a number of segments where he discussed the implements and clothing used in Satanic ceremonies, a scar allegedly indicating where he was repeatedly cut so that his blood could be used in Satanic ceremonies, and what drew him to Satanism.&lt;ref name="ABC"&gt;{{cite news |title = The Devil Worshippers |work = |publisher = ABC News 20/20 transcript, show #521 |date = May 16, 1985}}&lt;/ref&gt; After Warnke's appearance on ''20/20'', he was frequently cited as an expert on the [[occult]] by Christian radio host [[Bob Larson]] and the [[Chick Publications]] stable of authors.

==Investigation and debunking==
In 1991, ''[[Cornerstone (magazine)|Cornerstone]]'' magazine launched an investigation into Warnke's life and testimony. The previous year, Cornerstone had debunked [[Laurel Rose Willson|Lauren Stratford]]'s story that had been recounted in ''[[Satan's Underground]]''. Stratford claimed her deep involvement in Satanism led her to partake in a ritual in which her own child was [[human sacrifice|sacrificed]]. After the exposé showed Stratford's alleged child had never existed, Cornerstone journalists Mike Hertenstein and Jon Trott investigated Warnke and his life.

The ''Cornerstone'' investigation spanned from interviews with over 100 of Warnke's personal friends and acquaintances to his ministry's tax receipts. The investigation revealed a number of inaccuracies and evidence of [[fraud]] and [[deceit]] in Warnke's accounts. During the course of ''Cornerstone'''s investigation, pictures of Warnke taken during the time he was alleged to be a Satanist priest were discovered. Rather than showing an emaciated drug-addict sporting long fingernails and waist-length hair, the pictures showed Warnke as a typical 'square' of the mid-1960s. The investigation also revealed Warnke's claims that he and [[Charles Manson]] had attended a Satanic ritual to be false; Manson was in federal prison at the time, having no known ties to Satanic churches.

The investigation further uncovered that before joining the Navy, Warnke had been involved with the college Christian ministry [[Campus Crusade for Christ]]. The investigation also revealed the unflattering circumstances surrounding Warnke's multiple marriages, affairs, and divorces. Most critically, however, the investigation showed how Warnke could not have done the many things he claimed to have taken part in throughout the nine months he claimed to be a Satanist - including his claims to be a drug-addicted dealer or a Satanic high priest.&lt;ref name=cornerstone-dates&gt;{{cite journal|url = http://www.cornerstonemag.com/features/iss098/dates.htm |title = Why the Dates Don't Work (sidebar) |work = Cornerstone |issue=98 |year=1992 |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20110629063030/http://www.cornerstonemag.com/features/iss098/dates.htm |archivedate=2011-06-29}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Before publishing the article, ''Cornerstone'' contacted Warnke for an interview, but he and ''Cornerstone'' could not agree to the terms of an interview.&lt;ref name=warnke-response/&gt;&lt;ref name=cornerstone-update/&gt; In June 1992, at the annual [[CBA (Christian trade association)|Christian Booksellers Association]] convention, ''Cornerstone'' revealed its story.

==Aftermath==
Warnke sent a response to ''Cornerstone'',&lt;ref name=warnke-response/&gt; published in July, insisting he told the truth, stating:
{{blockquote|I stand by my testimony of being delivered and set free by the power of Jesus Christ after being a Satanic high priest exactly as published in my book, ''The Satan Seller''.... some information was purposefully changed to protect the privacy of certain individuals and to prevent readers from using the book as a guide for occultism and Satanic purposes. But, as we stated in the front of the book, 'The events are absolutely as described.'}} Despite these assertions, Warnke did not provide the name of a single Satanist but used invectives against ex-wife Carolyn.&lt;ref name=warnke-response/&gt; In the ensuing months, Warnke conceded parts of the allegations, telling ''Christianity Today'' that there had been only 13 members of his coven, not 1,500 as originally claimed, and that of those 13, the whereabouts of five were unknown to him, while the other eight had since died.&lt;ref name="lied"&gt;Jay Grelen. "Christian comedian says he lied about coven", ''[[Lexington Herald-Leader]]'', November 3, 1992, page B1.&lt;/ref&gt;

Public response was varied but was nevertheless overwhelmingly against Warnke.&lt;ref name=cornerstone-update&gt;{{cite journal|url = http://www.cornerstonemag.com/features/iss099/warnke_update.htm |title = Warnke Update |issue=99 |work = Cornerstone |year=1992 |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20110629063024/http://www.cornerstonemag.com/features/iss099/warnke_update.htm |archivedate=2011-06-29}}&lt;/ref&gt; Initially, Word Records stated that they would stand by their artist. However, further investigations by local Kentucky reporters at the ''[[Lexington Herald-Leader]]'' revealed that Warnke's ministry had engaged in financial misdeeds and that "Mike, his ex-wife Rose, and her brother Neale [Hall] received a total of $809,680 in salary at a time when the ministry newsletter claimed donations were down and more funds were needed."&lt;ref name=cornerstone-update/&gt; One week later, Word Records dropped Warnke from its label. Finally, on September 30, 1992, fewer than 100 days after the investigation was made public, Warnke Ministries closed its doors.&lt;ref name="grelen"&gt;Jay Grelen. "Christian comedian set to close doors of troubled ministry", ''[[Lexington Herald-Leader]]'' (KY), September 30, 1992, page C13.&lt;/ref&gt;

In the spring of 1993, Warnke submitted to the authority of an assembly of ministers "acting as elders", acknowledging his "ungodliness", his "multiple divorces", his "failure as husband, father, and friend", and of "embellishment and exaggeration ... in an attempt ... to entertain", and offering to pay [[back taxes]] to the federal government. The group recommended specific changes to the ministry, including a [[salary cap]] and accountability reports.&lt;ref name="okla2000"&gt;Tamie Ross. "Laughs stopped for Christian comic: Mike Warnke offers fans new outlook after ministry's crash", ''The Daily Oklahoman'', September 30, 2000, page 1B&lt;/ref&gt; Nonetheless, he continued to "stand by [his] testimony of former Satanic involvement"&lt;ref name=warnke-apology&gt;Warnke's [http://www.mikewarnke.org/packet22.html 1993 statement of apology and repentance] {{webarchive|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20060504182948/http://www.mikewarnke.org/packet22.html |date=May 4, 2006 }}&lt;/ref&gt; stating in a 2000 interview with the ''[[Daily Oklahoman]]'', "Exaggeration did creep into some of my stories, but my testimony is still my testimony."&lt;ref name="okla2000"/&gt;&lt;ref name="modesto"&gt;"Local notes - Controversial comedian", ''[[The Modesto Bee]]'' (CA), February 2, 2002, page G1: ''"Mike Warnke, a popular 1970s Christian comedian later accused of fabricating claims about his Satanist past, will speak at Pentecostal Church of God Friday through February 10. ... It is unlikely he will talk about his colorful past, said Hughson Pastor Roy Little. Warnke speaks these days about his current Christian faith."''&lt;/ref&gt; As of 2006, a letter posted on Warnke's web site indicated the group had released him as having met their accountability requirements.&lt;ref name="rancho"&gt;Monique H. Henderson. "Spotlight: Christian comedian Mike Warnke comes to Rancho Mirage: his humor is in the past", ''[[The Press-Enterprise]]'' ([[Riverside, CA]]), October 3, 2007, page B2.&lt;/ref&gt;

In 1997, Warnke suffered a [[myocardial infarction|heart attack]].{{Citation needed|date=March 2007}} In 2000, he began attempting a [[wiktionary:comeback|comeback]], limited to small churches in Kentucky.{{Citation needed|date=March 2007}} In 2002, he published ''Friendly Fire: A Recovery Guide for Believers Battered by Religion'' ({{ISBN|0-7684-2124-1}}), an account of what he perceived as his unfair treatment by fellow Christians in the wake of the ''Cornerstone'' exposé.&lt;ref name="rancho"/&gt; &lt;!-- (Website no longer mentions his satanic notoriety: 2007-03-22) As of December 2006, his [http://www.mikewarnke.org/default.asp?startpage=bios.asp website biography] claimed that he is a former Satanic high priest. --&gt; By 2004, he was making occasional performing appearances at churches around the country, often referred to simply as "Christian comedian Mike Warnke",&lt;ref name="mo-07"&gt;"This week" (local events column), ''Springfield News-Leader'' (MO), September 15, 2007, page 2C: ''"Shoal Creek Revival Church ... Christian comedian Mike Warnke 7 p.m. today and 10 a.m. and 6 p.m. Sunday."''&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="reiter"&gt;Carol Reiter. "Around Town: Walk for health care" (local events column), ''The Merced Sun-Star'' (CA), April 14, 2007: ''"Calvary Temple Worship Center, ... will present Mike Warnke ... . Warnke will share his life experiences from more than 35 years in World Wide Ministry."''&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="oklahoman"&gt;"Access religion" (local events column), ''[[The Oklahoman]]'' ([[Oklahoma City, OK]]), August 19, 2006, page 2E: "First Assembly of God of Guthrie, Christian comedian Mike Warnke ... ."&lt;/ref&gt; and sometimes as a former Satanic priest&lt;ref name="exhippie"&gt;Staff reports. "Ex-hippie employs comedy to spread God's word", ''[[El Paso Times]]'' (TX), October 15, 2004, page 1D: ''"According to his Web site, Warnke was a satanic high priest..."...&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="stpete"&gt;"Religion calendar", ''[[St. Petersburg Times]]'' (FL), October 21, 2006, PASCO TIMES section, page 5.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="hale"&gt;Barbara Hale. "Around town: Mike Warnke entertains", ''The Merced Sun-Star'' (CA), August 3, 2006, page 2: ''"A man who has spent 34 years ministering to the lost and brokenhearted is coming to Merced to share his comedic style that gains the attention of listeners. The speaker is Mike Warnke, an ex-satanist high priest, hippie, drug addict, pusher and Naval hospital corpsman attached to a U.S. Marine Corps unit in Vietnam. ..."''&lt;/ref&gt; although some mentions in the news referred to the ''Cornerstone'' exposé.&lt;ref name="rancho"/&gt;

==See also==
{{Portal|United States Navy}}
* [[Tony Anthony (evangelist)|Tony Anthony]] - a British evangelist whose claims were exposed as false
* [[Ergun Caner]] - Former college President who made similar claims that he was an Islamic terrorist that have been disputed 
* [[Laurel Rose Willson|Lauren Stratford]] - an American whose claims to have been brought up as a baby breeder in a Satanic cult were exposed as false
* [[John Todd (conspiracy theorist)|John Todd]] - an American who claimed to have been a Satanic high priest before his conversion to Christianity
* ''[[Michelle Remembers]]'' - a discredited memoir detailing Satanic ritual abuse by Canadian psychiatrist [[Lawrence Pazder]] and his patient and later wife, Michelle Smith

==References==
{{Reflist|2}}

==Further reading==
*Mike Hertenstein, Jon Trott: ''Selling Satan: The Tragic History of Mike Warnke'' ({{ISBN|0-940895-07-2}}), Cornerstone Press 1993. An expanded, book-length version of the ''Cornerstone'' exposé by the original journalists.

==External links==
{{wikiquote}}
*[http://www.mikewarnke.org/ Mike Warnke and Celebrations of Hope], official website
*{{webarchive |url=https://web.archive.org/web/20110604055445/http://www.cornerstonemag.com/features/iss098/warnke_index.htm |date=June 4, 2011 |title=The Cornerstone series on Mike Warnke }} by Mike Hertenstein and Jon Trott

{{Satanic ritual abuse}}

{{Authority control}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Warnke, Mike}}
[[Category:1946 births]]
[[Category:20th-century hoaxes]]
[[Category:American autobiographers]]
[[Category:American evangelicals]]
[[Category:American male comedians]]
[[Category:American military personnel of the Vietnam War]]
[[Category:Evangelicalism]]
[[Category:Hoaxes in the United States]]
[[Category:Impostors]]
[[Category:Living people]]
[[Category:Nestorians]]
[[Category:People from Manchester, Tennessee]]
[[Category:Writers from Evansville, Indiana]]
[[Category:People from Kentucky]]
[[Category:People from San Bernardino, California]]
[[Category:Religious scandals]]
[[Category:United States Navy sailors]]
[[Category:Satanic ritual abuse in the United States]]
[[Category:Comedians from California]]</text>
      <sha1>9b6b2og7a4cqjs1xp8wnwzg01dv06qs</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
