<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10.xsd" version="0.10" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <dbname>enwiki</dbname>
    <base>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.32.0-wmf.16</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="118" case="first-letter">Draft</namespace>
      <namespace key="119" case="first-letter">Draft talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2300" case="first-letter">Gadget</namespace>
      <namespace key="2301" case="first-letter">Gadget talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2302" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition</namespace>
      <namespace key="2303" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Moe Howard</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>465838</id>
    <revision>
      <id>856173108</id>
      <parentid>856144661</parentid>
      <timestamp>2018-08-23T10:57:54Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <ip>103.60.201.120</ip>
      </contributor>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="23595">{{Infobox person
| name             = Moe Howard
| image            = File:Moe Howard 1937 (cropped).jpg
| image_size       = 
| caption          = Moe Howard in 1937
| birth_name       = Moses Harry Horwitz
| birth_date       = {{Birth date|1897|6|19}}
| birth_place      = [[Bensonhurst, Brooklyn]], New York, U.S.
| death_date       = {{death date and age|1975|5|4|1897|6|19}}
| death_place      = [[Los Angeles]], California, U.S.
| resting_place    = [[Hillside Memorial Park Cemetery]]
| years_active     = 1909–1975
| height         = {{height|ft=5|in=3.5}}
| occupation       = Actor, comedian
| spouse           = {{marriage|Helen Schonberger&lt;br&gt;|1925|1975|end=his death}}
| other_names      = Harry Howard
| website          = 
| baptised = 
| relatives = [[Curly Howard]] &lt;small&gt;(brother)&lt;/small&gt;&lt;br&gt;[[Shemp Howard]] &lt;small&gt;(brother)&lt;/small&gt;
| children = 2, including [[Joan Howard Maurer]]
}}
'''Moses Harry Horwitz''' (June 19, 1897 – May 4, 1975), known professionally as '''Moe Howard''', was an American [[actor]] and [[comedian]] best known as the ''[[de facto]]'' leader of [[the Three Stooges]], the farce comedy team who starred in motion pictures and television for four decades. That group originally started out as [[Ted Healy|Ted Healy and His Stooges]], an act that toured the vaudeville circuit. Moe's distinctive hairstyle came about when he was a boy and cut off his curls with a pair of scissors, producing a ragged shape approximating a [[bowl cut]].

==Early life==
Howard was born as Moses Harry Horwitz on June 19, 1897, in the [[Brooklyn, New York City]] neighborhood of [[Bensonhurst, Brooklyn|Bensonhurst]] to Solomon Horwitz and Jennie Gorovitz, the fourth-born of five brothers of [[Lithuanian Jewish]] ancestry. He was named Moe when he was younger and later called himself Harry. Howard's parents and brothers, Benjamin and Irving, were not involved in show business, but his older brother [[Shemp Howard]], younger brother [[Curly Howard]], and he all eventually became known as members of [[the Three Stooges]]. He loved to read as his older brother Jack recalled: "I had many [[Horatio Alger, Jr.|Horatio Alger]] books, and it was Moe's greatest pleasure to read them. They started his imaginative mind working and gave him ideas by the dozen. I think they were instrumental in putting thoughts into his head to become a person of good character and to become successful." This helped him in his acting career in later years, such as in memorizing his lines quickly and easily.

Howard's "bowl cut" hairstyle became his trademark, despite his mother initially refusing to cut his hair in childhood, letting it grow to shoulder length. He secretly cut his hair in his backyard shed, after being frequently teased in school.  During one appearance on the [[Mike Douglas]] show in the 1970s, he stated that "I used to fight my way to school, in school, and back home from school."&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=Ecd9dPO8BhE|title=Moe Howard on The Mike Douglas Show. Part 3|first=|last=Jimymac|date=20 August 2007|publisher=|accessdate=9 February 2018|via=YouTube}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Howard began to develop an interest in acting to the point where his grades worsened and began to play [[truancy|hookey]] from school. He said, "I used to stand outside the theater knowing the truant officer was looking for me. I would stand there 'til someone came along, and then ask them to buy my ticket. It was necessary for an adult to accompany a juvenile into the theater. When I succeeded I'd give him my ten cents—that's all it cost—and I'd go up to the top of the balcony where I'd put my chin on the rail and watch, spellbound, from the first act to the last. I would usually select the actor I liked the most and follow his performance throughout the play."&lt;ref name=HowardBook&gt;{{cite book| last = Howard| first = Moe| authorlink = Moe Howard|title = [[Moe Howard and the Three Stooges]]| publisher = Broadway Publishing| origyear = 1977|edition=revised|year=1979|isbn = 978-0-8065-0723-1}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Despite his waning attendance, Howard graduated from P.S. 163 in Brooklyn, but dropped out of [[Erasmus Hall High School]] after only two months, ending his formal education. He took an electric shop course for his parents' wishes, but quit after a few months to pursue a career in show business.&lt;ref name=HowardBook/&gt;

Howard started off running unpaid errands at the [[Vitagraph Studios]] in [[Midwood, Brooklyn]], and was rewarded at first with bit parts in movies in production there, until a 1910 fire destroyed the films done there, and with it, most of Howard's work. Already in 1909, he had met a young man named Ernest Lea Nash (later known as [[Ted Healy]]), who was later to provide a significant boost for his career aspirations. In 1912, they both held a summer job working in [[Annette Kellerman]]'s aquatic act as diving "girls".&lt;ref name=HowardBook/&gt;

==Career==
===Before Stooges (to 1930) ===

Howard continued his attempts at gaining show business experience by singing in a bar with his older brother Shemp until their father put a stop to it, and in 1914, by joining a performing [[minstrel show]] troupe on a [[Mississippi River]] showboat for the next two summers. In 1921, he joined Ted Healy in a vaudeville routine. In 1923, Moe saw Shemp in the audience during a theater performance and yelled at him from the stage. Shemp responded by heckling Moe, and the two brothers' amusing bickering during the performance resulted in Healy immediately hiring Shemp Howard as a permanent part of the act.

Moe retired in June 1925 after his marriage to Helen Schonberger and went into real estate with his mother.  Meanwhile, Healy's act with frequent stooge Shemp Howard went on to national fame in the Shubert Brothers' ''A Night in Spain'' (Jan. 1927 – Nov. 1928), which had a successful Broadway run, as well as a national tour.  During ''A Night in Spain'', and the end of a 4-month run in Chicago, Illinois,  Healy recruited vaudeville violinist [[Larry Fine]] to join the troupe in March 1928.

After the show ended in late November, Healy signed for the Shuberts' new revue ''A Night in Venice'' and recruited Moe Howard out of retirement to rejoin the act in December 1928. In rehearsals in early 1929, Howard, Larry Fine, and Shemp Howard came together for the first time as a trio.  When ''A Night in Venice'' closed in March 1930, Healy and the trio toured for a while as "Ted Healy and His Racketeers" (later changed to Ted Healy and His Stooges).&lt;ref name=HowardBook/&gt;
[[File: Three Stooges 1937.jpg|right|thumb|Larry Fine, Curly Howard, and Moe Howard in 1937]]

===Ted Healy and His Stooges===
Ted Healy and His Stooges were on the verge of hitting the big time and made their first movie, ''[[Soup to Nuts]]'' (1930)—featuring Healy and his four Stooges:  Moe (billed as "Harry Howard"), Shemp, Larry, and [[Fred Sanborn]] (Sanborn had been with Healy's troupe since January 1929, as one of the stooges in "A Night in Venice")—for Fox Films (later [[20th Century Fox]]). A disagreement with Healy led Moe, Larry, and Shemp to strike out on their own as "Howard, Fine, and Howard," and on August 28, 1930, they premiered that act at L.A.'s Paramount Theatre.  Joining the RKO vaudeville circuit, they toured for almost two years, eventually dubbing themselves as "Three Lost Souls" and taking on Jack Walsh as their straight man.&lt;ref&gt;Cox, Steve and Terry, Jim (2005). ''One Fine Stooge: Larry Fine's Frizzy Life in Pictures''. Nashville: Cumberland House. p. 25. {{ISBN|1581823630}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In July 1932, Moe, Larry, and Shemp were approached by Healy to rejoin him for the new Shubert Broadway revue ''Passing Show of 1932'', and the three accepted the offer. On August 16, 1932, during ''Passing'' rehearsals in New York, Ted walked out on the Shuberts over a contract dispute. On August 19, 1932, Shemp gave his notice having not seen eye-to-eye with the hard-drinking and sometimes belligerent Healy and decided to remain with ''Passing'' which closed in September after pan reviews of its first roadshow performances in Detroit and Cincinnati. Shemp landed at Vitaphone Studios in Brooklyn in May 1933, where he stayed for almost four years.

On August 20, the day after Shemp's departure, Moe suggested adding his youngest brother Jerome ("Babe" to Moe and Shemp) to the act; contrary to some sources, no search for a replacement was conducted. Healy originally passed on Jerry, but Jerry was so eager to join the act that he shaved off his luxuriant auburn mustache and hair and ran on stage during Healy's routine. That finally got Healy to hire Jerry, who took the stage name Curly.&lt;ref name=HowardBook/&gt; The new lineup of Moe, Larry, and Curly premiered with Ted on stage at Cleveland's [[Keith-Albee-Orpheum|RKO Palace]] on August 27, 1932.  Early 1933 during appearances in Los Angeles, Healy and the Stooges were hired by [[Metro-Goldwyn-Mayer]] as "nut" comics to liven up feature films and short subjects with their antics.

===Post-Healy – to 1940===

After a number of appearances in MGM films, Healy was being groomed as a solo character comedian. With Healy pursuing his own career in 1934, his Stooges (now renamed the Three Stooges) signed with [[Columbia Pictures]], where they stayed until December 1957, making 190 comedy shorts.&lt;ref name=HowardBook/&gt;

With Healy's departure, Moe Howard assumed Healy's prior role as the aggressive, take-charge leader of the Three Stooges: a short-tempered bully, prone to slapstick violence against the other two Stooges. Despite his outwardly rather cruel demeanor towards his pals, Moe was also very loyal and protective of the other Stooges on film, keeping them from harm, and should it befall them, doing whatever it took to save them.

He emphasized in his 1977 book that the ill-tempered aspects of his on-screen persona did not reflect his real personality. He also boasted of being a shrewd businessman by wisely investing the money made from his film career, but the Stooges received no subsequent royalties (i.e., residuals) from any of their many shorts; they were paid a flat amount for each one, and Columbia owned the rights (and profits) thereafter.&lt;ref name=HowardBook/&gt; However, according to Larry Fine in the 1970s, Columbia allowed the Stooges to do live tours when they were not filming in exchange for half-salary during those months. Fine indicated that the profits from the tours substantially increased their yearly take.

Columbia released its first Three Stooges short, ''[[Woman Haters]]'' (1934), where their stooge characters were not quite fully formed. It was not a Stooge comedy in the classic sense, but rather a romantic farce; Columbia was then making a series of two-reel "Musical Novelties" with the dialogue spoken in rhyme, and the Stooges were recruited to support comedian [[Marjorie White]]. Only after the Stooges became established as short-subject stars were the main titles changed to give the Stooges top billing. The version seen on TV and video today is this reissue print.&lt;ref name=HowardBook/&gt;

Their next film, ''[[Punch Drunks]]'' (1934), was the only short film written entirely by the Three Stooges, with Curly as a reluctant boxer who goes ballistic every time he hears "[[Pop Goes the Weasel]]". Their next short, ''[[Men in Black (1934 film)|Men in Black]]'' (also 1934), a parody of the contemporary hospital drama ''[[Men in White (1934 film)|Men in White]]'', was their first and only film to be nominated for an [[Academy Award]] (with the classic catchphrases "Calling Dr. Howard, Dr. Fine, Dr. Howard" followed by their reiterated unison declaration as young doctors, "For Duty and Humanity!!"). They continued making short films at a steady pace of eight per year, such as ''[[Three Little Pigskins]]'' (also 1934) with a young [[Lucille Ball]], ''[[Pop Goes the Easel]]'' (1935), and ''[[Hoi Polloi (1935 film)|Hoi Polloi]]'' (also 1935), in which two professors make a bet trying to turn the Three Stooges into gentlemen.&lt;ref name=HowardBook/&gt;

===1940s===

In the 1940s the Three Stooges became topical, making several anti-Nazi short films, including ''[[You Nazty Spy!]]'' (1940) Moe's favorite Three Stooges film, ''[[I'll Never Heil Again]]'' (1941), and ''[[They Stooge to Conga]]'' (1943). Moe's impersonation of [[Adolf Hitler]] highlighted these shorts, the first of which preceded [[Charlie Chaplin]]'s film satire ''[[The Great Dictator]]'' by months.&lt;ref name=HowardBook/&gt;

On May 6, 1946, during the filming of ''[[Half-Wits Holiday]]'' (1947), brother Curly suffered a [[stroke]]. He had already suffered a series of them prior to the filming of ''[[Beer Barrel Polecats]]'' (1946) and was replaced by Shemp who agreed to return to the group, but only until Curly would be well enough to rejoin. Although Curly recovered enough to appear in ''[[Hold That Lion! (1947 film)|Hold That Lion!]]'' (1947) in a cameo appearance (the only Three Stooges film to contain all three Howard brothers; Moe, Curly, and Shemp), he soon suffered a second series of strokes which led to his death at age 48 on January 18, 1952.&lt;ref name=HowardBook/&gt;

After Shemp rejoined the act, Moe, Shemp, and Larry shot a television pilot for ABC called ''[[Jerks of All Trades]]'' (1949), apparently intended to lead to a weekly sitcom series on the premise that the Stooges would try a different job or business every week, hoping that eventually one of their attempts would be successful. Anything they tried turned out to be a fiasco, which was the source of the comedy. The pilot took a single day to film and was never aired. It was actually a kinescope film of a three-camera television production, most likely to replicate a proposed live broadcast.

[[File:Malice in the Palace.JPG|thumb|right|Moe Howard (left) in ''[[Malice in the Palace]]'' (1949) with [[Shemp Howard]] and [[Larry Fine]]]]

B.B. Kahane, Columbia Pictures' vice president of business affairs, stopped the show from being broadcast. Kahane warned the Stooges that a contract stipulation restricted them from performing in a TV series that might compete with their two-reel comedies. Columbia further threatened to cancel the boys' contract and take them to court if they tried to sell the series. To avert a legal hassle, the pilot was shelved and the project abandoned. The kinescope film is now in the public domain and widely available.

===1950s===

The Three Stooges' series of shorts continued to be popular through the 1950s; Shemp co-starred in 73 comedies. The Stooges also co-starred in a [[George O'Brien (actor)|George O'Brien]] Western, ''[[Gold Raiders]]'' (1951). Moe also co-produced occasional Western and musical films in the 1950s.

On November 22, 1955, Shemp died of a [[myocardial infarction|heart attack]] at age 60, necessitating the need for another Stooge. Producer [[Jules White]] used old footage of Shemp to complete four more films, with Columbia regular [[Joe Palma]] filling in for Shemp (thus creating the [[Fake Shemp]] phenomenon), until Columbia head Harry Cohn hired [[Joe Besser]] in 1956. According to Moe's autobiography, Howard wanted a "two-stooge" act, and it was Cohn's idea, not Howard's, to replace Shemp as part of the act.

The Stooges replaced Shemp with Besser, already an established Columbia comedy shorts star in his own right and frequent movie supporting player. Joe, Larry, and Moe filmed 16 shorts through December 1957. Shortly before Cohn's death in February 1958, the making of short subjects came to an end. Keeping himself busy, Moe was hired by Harry Romm as associate producer. According to Moe, stories (and later, scenes in a 2000 made-for-TV biopic) that he was forced to take a job as a [[gofer]] at Columbia are completely false.&lt;ref name=HowardBook/&gt;

===Television and the advent of Curly Joe===

Fortunately for the Stooges, Columbia sold the Three Stooges' library of short films to television under the [[Screen Gems]] name. With this, the Three Stooges quickly gained a new audience of young fans. Ever the businessman, Moe Howard put together a new Stooges act, with [[American burlesque|burlesque]] and screen comic [[Curly Joe DeRita|Joe DeRita]] (dubbed "Curly Joe" because of his vague resemblance to Curly Howard and to differentiate him from Joe Besser) as the new "third Stooge". DeRita, like both Shemp Howard and Joe Besser, had also starred in a series of his own comedy shorts.

The revitalized trio starred in six feature-length movies: ''[[Have Rocket, Will Travel]]'' (1959); ''[[Snow White and the Three Stooges]]'' (1961), ''[[The Three Stooges Meet Hercules]]'' and ''[[The Three Stooges in Orbit]]'' (1962), ''[[The Three Stooges Go Around the World in a Daze]]'' (1963), and ''[[The Outlaws Is Coming]]'' (1965).&lt;ref name=HowardBook/&gt;

Howard, Larry, and Curly Joe continued to make live appearances, many notable "guest appearances", particularly in ''[[It's a Mad, Mad, Mad, Mad World]]'' (1963) as three firemen who appear for only a few seconds, and a longer appearance in ''[[4 for Texas]]'' (also 1963) starring [[Frank Sinatra]] and [[Dean Martin]]. The men tried their hand at a children's cartoon show titled ''[[The New Three Stooges]]'', with the cartoons sandwiched between live-action segments of the Stooges filmed in color.

During this period, Moe and the Stooges appeared on numerous television shows, including ''[[The Steve Allen Show]]'', ''[[Here's Hollywood]]'', ''[[Masquerade Party]]'',  ''[[The Ed Sullivan Show]]'', ''[[Danny Thomas Meets The Comics]]'', ''[[The Joey Bishop Show (talk show)|The Joey Bishop Show]]'',&lt;ref&gt;Lenburg, Jeff, Joan Howard Maurer, and Greg Lenburg (2012).[https://books.google.com/books?id=VY_j1vzWnasC&amp;pg=PA202&amp;dq=joey+bishop+moe+howard&amp;hl=en&amp;sa=X&amp;ved=0ahUKEwiymMqXy-rQAhUGNiYKHZnhCxoQ6AEIGjAA#v=onepage&amp;q= ''The Three Stooges Scrapbook'']. Chicago, Ill: Chicago Review Press. p. 202. {{ISBN|9781613740743}}.&lt;/ref&gt; ''[[Off To See The Wizard]]'', and ''[[Truth or Consequences]]'', but by the late 1960s, they were all at an age where they could no longer risk serious injury while performing slapstick comedy.

===Later years===

[[File:oldmoe75.jpeg|thumb|right|Moe Howard in February 1975, three months before his death]]

The men were paid residuals for their later efforts and continued to receive the bulk of the profits from sales of Stooges merchandise.{{Citation needed|date=April 2012}}  Moe sold [[real estate]] when his show-business life slowed down, although he still did minor solo roles and walk-on bits in movies, such as ''[[Don't Worry, We'll Think of a Title]]'' (1966) and ''Doctor Death: Seeker of Souls'' (1973), as well as several appearances on ''[[The Mike Douglas Show]]'' in the 1970s.

In one of Douglas' episodes, Moe, his hair in a style popular at the time, made a surprise appearance during an interview of the writer of a "where-are-they-now" book. When the audience was given the chance to ask the writer about famous people, Howard asked, "Whatever happened to the Three Stooges?" Finally recognized by Douglas, he then combed his hair into his trademark style.{{episode needed|date=April 2012}}

The Stooges attempted to make a final film in 1969, ''[[Kook's Tour]]'', which was essentially a documentary of Howard, Larry, and Curly Joe out of character, touring the US, and meeting with fans, but production abruptly halted when on January 9, 1970, Larry suffered a major stroke during filming, paralyzing the left side of his body. He died on January 24, 1975, at age 72. Enough footage of Larry was shot so that ''Kook's Tour'' was eventually released in a 52-minute version to home video. After Fine's stroke, Howard asked longtime Three Stooges supporting actor [[Emil Sitka]] to replace Larry, but this final lineup never shot any material.

==Personal life==
On June 7, 1925, Moe Howard married Helen Schonberger, a cousin of [[Harry Houdini]]. The next year, Schonberger persuaded Howard to retire since she was pregnant. Howard attempted to earn a living in a succession of "normal" jobs, none of which was very successful, and he soon returned to working with Ted Healy.&lt;ref name=HowardBook/&gt;

Howard and Schonberger had two children, [[Joan Howard Maurer|Joan Howard]] (born 1927) and Paul Howard&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.caricaturesbypaul.com/ "Caricatures by Paul"] - website&lt;/ref&gt; (born 1935).

==Filmography==
{{Main article|The Three Stooges filmography}}

==Death and legacy==
[[File: Moe Howard Grave.JPG|thumb|200px|right|Crypt of Moe Howard, at Hillside Memorial Park]]
Howard died of [[lung cancer]] at age 77 on May 4, 1975, at [[Cedars-Sinai Medical Center]] in Los Angeles, where he had been admitted a week earlier in April, just over three months after [[Larry Fine]]'s death, and more than a month before his 78th birthday. He was a heavy smoker for much of his adult life.&lt;ref name=HowardBook/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |first=Rick |last=Greene |title=I Stooged to Conquer: The Forthcoming Autobiography of Moe Howard  |work=Three Stooges Fan Club Journal |date=Spring 1975 | url = http://threestooges.net/journal.php?action=view&amp;id=1}}&lt;/ref&gt; He was interred in an outdoor crypt at [[Culver City, California|Culver City's]] [[Hillside Memorial Park Cemetery]]. His wife Helen Schonberger died of a heart attack later that year on October 31, 1975, at age 75 and was interred in the crypt next to him on the right. At the time of his death, Howard was working on his autobiography titled ''I Stooged to Conquer''. It was released in 1977 as ''[[Moe Howard and the Three Stooges]]''.

Howard and the Three Stooges received a Star on the [[Hollywood Walk of Fame]] on August 30, 1983, at 1560 Vine Street.

Howard was portrayed by [[Paul Ben-Victor]] in ''The Three Stooges'', a 2000 made-for-TV biopic that focused on the trio's years in show business and their off-screen lives. In the 2012 [[Farrelly brothers]]' film ''[[The Three Stooges (2012 film)|The Three Stooges]]'', [[Chris Diamantopoulos]] portrays Howard. [[Skyler Gisondo]] portrays Young Howard.

==References==
{{reflist}}

==Further reading==
* ''Stroke of Luck''; by James Carone, as told by Larry Fine (Siena Publishing, Hollywood, 1973.)

==External links==
{{Portal|Biography}}
* [http://www.mypalmoe.com/ My Pal Moe by Bob Bernet] (featuring letters and rare photos of Moe Howard at home)
* {{IMDb name|2935}}
* {{tcmdb name|id=89660|name=Moe Howard}}
* {{IBDB name}}
* {{Find a Grave|512}}
* [http://otrrlibrary.org/OTRRLib/Library%20Files/W%20Series/Whatever%20Became%20Of/Whatever%20Became%20Of%2071-06-29%20The%20Three%20Stooges.mp3 Moe Howard audio interview with Richard Lamparski]
* [http://rerunit.com/index.html?video=howard1 Moe Howard Audio Interview]

{{ThreeStooges}}

{{Authority control}}
{{commonscat|Moe Howard}}

{{DEFAULTSORT: Howard, Moe}}
[[Category:1897 births]]
[[Category:1975 deaths]]
[[Category: Male actors from New York City]]
[[Category: Jewish American comedians]]
[[Category: American male film actors]]
[[Category: American male television actors]]
[[Category: American male stage actors]]
[[Category: People from Bensonhurst, Brooklyn]]
[[Category: American male comedians]]
[[Category: American comedians]]
[[Category: Jewish American male actors]]
[[Category: American people of Lithuanian-Jewish descent]]
[[Category: Deaths from lung cancer]]
[[Category: Vaudeville performers]]
[[Category: Deaths from cancer in California]]
[[Category: Burials at Hillside Memorial Park Cemetery]]
[[Category:20th-century American male actors]]
[[Category: The Three Stooges members]]
[[Category: American male comedy actors]]</text>
      <sha1>6z6jbr2hpdr7p2897h8chibts0mxxjt</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
