<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10.xsd" version="0.10" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <dbname>enwiki</dbname>
    <base>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.32.0-wmf.16</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="118" case="first-letter">Draft</namespace>
      <namespace key="119" case="first-letter">Draft talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2300" case="first-letter">Gadget</namespace>
      <namespace key="2301" case="first-letter">Gadget talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2302" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition</namespace>
      <namespace key="2303" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Mort Sahl</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>599356</id>
    <revision>
      <id>849357672</id>
      <parentid>847964602</parentid>
      <timestamp>2018-07-08T12:42:17Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <ip>73.18.120.241</ip>
      </contributor>
      <comment>/* Other */</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="33048">{{Infobox comedian
| name         = Mort Sahl
| image        = Mort Sahl -1.jpg 
| imagesize    = 
| caption      = Sahl in 1960
| alt          = 
| pseudonym    =
| birth_name   = Morton Lyon Sahl
| birth_date   = {{Birth date and age|1927|05|11|mf=y}}
| birth_place  = [[Montreal]], [[Quebec]], Canada
| medium       = [[Stand up comedian|Stand-up]], [[television]]
| nationality  = [[Americans|American]]
| alma_mater   = [[University of Southern California]]
| active       = 1950–present
| genre        = [[political satire]], [[Improvisational comedy]]
| subject      = [[American politics]], [[Culture of the United States|American culture]]
| influences   = [[Will Rogers]], [[Henry Morgan (comedian)|Henry Morgan]], [[H. L. Mencken]]
| influenced   = [[George Carlin]], [[Jon Stewart]], [[Dick Gregory]], [[Lenny Bruce]], [[Woody Allen]], [[Jay Leno]], [[Bill Maher]]
| spouse       = {{unbulleted list|{{marriage|Sue Babior|1955|1958|end=divorced}}|{{marriage|[[China Lee]]|1967|1991|end=divorced}}|{{marriage|Kenslea Sahl|1997}}}}
| website      = {{URL|mortsahlofficial.com|Mort Sahl website}}
}}

'''Morton Lyon''' "'''Mort'''" '''Sahl''' (born May 11, 1927) is a [[Canadians|Canadian]]-born American stand-up comedian, actor and social [[satirist]], considered the first modern stand-up comedian since [[Will Rogers]].&lt;ref name=Weide/&gt;&lt;ref name=Time/&gt; Sahl pioneered a style of social satire which pokes fun at political and current event topics using improvised monologues and only a newspaper as a prop.

Sahl spent his early years in Los Angeles and moved to the San Francisco Bay Area where he made his professional stage debut at the [[hungry i]] nightclub in 1953. His popularity grew quickly, and after a year at the club he traveled the country doing shows at established nightclubs, theaters and college campuses. In 1960 he became the first comedian to have a cover story written about him by ''Time'' magazine. He appeared on various television shows, played a number of film roles, and performed a one-man show on Broadway.

Television host [[Steve Allen]] claimed that Sahl was "the only real political philosopher we have in modern comedy." His social satire performances broke new ground in live entertainment, as a stand-up comic talking about the real world of politics at that time was considered "revolutionary." It inspired many later comics to become stage comedians, including [[Lenny Bruce]], [[Jonathan Winters]], [[George Carlin]] and [[Woody Allen]]. Allen credits Sahl's new style of humor with "opening up vistas for people like me."&lt;ref name=Nachman/&gt;{{rp|545}}

Numerous politicians became his fans, with [[John F. Kennedy]] asking him to write his jokes for campaign speeches. After Kennedy's assassination in 1963, however, Sahl became obsessed with what he saw as the [[Warren Report]]'s inaccuracy and conclusions, and spoke about it often during his shows. This alienated much of his audience and led to a decline in his popularity for the remainder of the 1960s. By the 1970s, however, his shows and popularity staged a partial comeback which continues to the present.&lt;ref name=Hopper&gt;[http://news.nationalpost.com/arts/weekend-post/mort-sahl-invented-stand-up-comedy-so-whats-he-doing-at-a-community-theatre-in-northern-california "Mort Sahl invented stand-up comedy — so what’s he doing at a community theatre in Northern California?"], ''National Post'', May 25, 2015&lt;/ref&gt; A biography of Sahl, ''Last Man Standing'', by [[James Curtis (biographer)|James Curtis]], was released in 2017.&lt;ref name=bio&gt;[http://www.ocregister.com/2017/06/02/comedian-mort-sahl-and-biographer-james-curtis-talk-about-last-man-standing-the-story-of-sahls-fearless-funny-life/ "Comedian Mort Sahl and biographer James Curtis talk about ‘Last Man Standing,’ the story of Sahl’s fearless, funny life"], ''Orange County Register'', June 2, 2017&lt;/ref&gt;

==Early life==
Sahl was born on May 11, 1927 in Montreal, Quebec, Canada,&lt;ref name=master/&gt; the only child of Jewish parents.&lt;ref name=Nachman&gt;{{cite book|last1=Nachman|first1=Gerald|author-link1=Gerald Nachman (journalist)|title=Seriously Funny |script-title=The Rebel Comedians of the 1950s and 1960s|url=http://geraldnachman.com/about.html|location=New York|publisher=Pantheon Books|publication-date=2003|page=659|isbn=9780375410307|oclc=50339527}}&lt;/ref&gt; His father, Harry Sahl, came from an immigrant family on New York's Lower East Side, and hoped to become a Broadway playwright. He met his wife when she responded to an advertisement he took out in a poetry magazine. Unable to break into the writing field they moved to Canada where he owned a tobacco store in Montreal.&lt;ref name=Time&gt;''Time'' magazine, August 15, 1960, pp. 44-48&lt;/ref&gt;

The family later relocated to [[Los Angeles|Los Angeles, California]] where his father, unable to become a Hollywood writer, worked as a clerk and court reporter for the FBI. Sahl notes, "My dad was disappointed in his dreams and he distrusted that world for me."&lt;ref name=Nachman/&gt;{{rp|55}} Sahl went to [[Belmont High School (Los Angeles, California)|Belmont High School]] in Los Angeles where he wrote for the school's newspaper. Actor [[Richard Crenna]] was a classmate.&lt;ref name=Nachman/&gt;{{rp|55}}

When the U.S. entered World War II after Pearl Harbor, Sahl, then fourteen, joined the school's [[Reserve Officers' Training Corps]] (ROTC). He won a medal for marksmanship and an [[American Legion]] Americanism award.&lt;ref name=Nachman/&gt;{{rp|55}} Wanting to express his patriotism, he wore his ROTC uniform to school and in public&lt;ref name=Time/&gt; and, when he turned fifteen, he dropped out of high school to join the Army by lying about his age.&lt;ref name=Nachman/&gt;{{rp|55}} His mother tracked him down and brought him back home two weeks later after she revealed his true age.&lt;ref name=Nachman/&gt;{{rp|55}}

Upon graduating from high school, his father tried to get him into West Point and had received his Congressman's help.&lt;ref name=Time/&gt; But Sahl had by then already enlisted in the [[United States Air Force]]. He was later stationed in [[Alaska]] with the 93rd Air Depot Group. In the military, however, he resisted the discipline and authoritarian control it had over his life. He expressed his nonconformity by growing a beard and refusing to wear a cap as required. He also wrote articles for a small newspaper criticizing the military, which resulted in his being penalized with three months of [[KP duty]].&lt;ref name=Time/&gt;

He was discharged in 1947 and enrolled in [[Compton College]], followed by the [[University of Southern California]]. He received a B.S. degree in 1950 with majors in [[traffic engineering (transportation)|traffic engineering]] and [[city management]].&lt;ref name=Time/&gt;&lt;ref name=master/&gt; He continued with the masters program but dropped out to become an actor and playwright.&lt;ref name=Time/&gt;

==Career==

===Breaking into comedy===
Between 1950 and 1953 he tried to get jobs as a stand-up comedian in about 30 nightclubs throughout Los Angeles, but with no success. NBC, where he once auditioned, told him he would never succeed as a comedian.&lt;ref name=Time/&gt; He even offered to perform free during intermissions for the chance to show his talent. He recalls that period: "Despite all the folklore about the faith of friends in the struggling young artist, my friends constantly discouraged me."&lt;ref name=Nachman/&gt;{{rp|56}} He and a friend then rented an old theater, which they called Theater X, for "experimental," and he began writing and staging one-act plays. One of his plays was titled "Nobody Trusted the Truth."&lt;ref name=Time/&gt; But unable to attract a large enough audience, they eventually closed the theater.

For income, Sahl began doing odd jobs and writing. He worked as a used car salesman and a messenger, and wrote an unpublished novel and short stories. He went to New York hoping to sell his plays, but only managed to earn about eighteen dollars a week. He recalls, "I couldn't get a thing going. I was working on a novel, I was out of work, and I was out of gas."&lt;ref name=Nachman/&gt; As a result, he decided to try something different, by performing his plays as monologues. He felt it would be easier to do his monologue on stage instead of trying to sell it to others.&lt;ref name=Nachman/&gt;{{rp|56}} "I knew that if I was going to get anything done, I'd have to do it myself," he says.&lt;ref name=Nachman/&gt;{{rp|56}} He returned to Los Angeles where he appeared at some clubs but his new style of monologue comedy received little attention.

In 1953 he began dating Sue Babior. When she moved to Berkeley to study at the [[University of California, Berkeley|University of California]], Sahl hitchhiked there to be with her. He spent his time auditing classes and hanging out at local coffee houses. For income he wrote for a few avant-garde publications. He slept in the back seat of a friend's car since Babior was living with roommates. "Things were simple then," he says. "All we had to worry about was the destiny of man."&lt;ref name=Playboy&gt;''Playboy'' magazine, February, 1969&lt;/ref&gt; He felt at home in the [[San Francisco Bay Area]], commenting, "I was born in San Francisco." The three years he lived in Berkeley were a valuable experience, he said.&lt;ref name=Nachman/&gt;{{rp|57}}

He sought out any clubs where he could perform as a stand-up, and Babior suggested he audition for the [[hungry i]], a nightclub in [[San Francisco]].&lt;ref name=master/&gt; Its owner, [[Enrico Banducci]], took an immediate liking to Sahl's comedy style and offered him a job at $75 a week, which became his first steady job as a stand-up comedian.&lt;ref name=Time/&gt;

Word about Sahl's satirical comedy acts spread quickly. He received good reviews from influential newspaper columnist, [[Herb Caen]], which gave him instant credibility: "I don't know where Mr. Sahl came from but I'm glad he's here," he wrote after watching his show.&lt;ref name=Nachman/&gt;{{rp|62}} Caen began inviting his own friends, such as film comedians [[Danny Kaye]] and [[Eddie Cantor]], to watch Sahl's performances.&lt;ref name=Nachman/&gt;{{rp|62}} Cantor took him "under his wing" and gave him suggestions.&lt;ref name=Nachman/&gt;{{rp|71}}By the end of his first year at the hungry i, Sahl was earning $3,000 a week and performing to packed houses. "I'd be washing cars if it weren't for Enrico," he said later in his career, appreciating that Banducci was the first club owner to give him the chance to perform as a stand-up comedian.&lt;ref name=Nachman/&gt;{{rp|62}}

===Nightclub shows and national acclaim===
After a year at the hungry i, Sahl began appearing at clubs throughout the country, including the [[The Black Orchid (nightclub)|Black Orchid]] and [[Mister Kelly's]] in Chicago, the Crescendo in Los Angeles, and the [[Village Vanguard]] and
the [[Blue Angel nightclub (New York)|Blue Angel]] in New York City.&lt;ref&gt;Hashagen, Paul. ''Fire Department, City of New York'', Turner Publishing (2002) p. 148&lt;/ref&gt; Many of the clubs had never before had a stand-up comedian perform, which required Sahl to break in as a new kind of act. "I had to build up my own network of places to play," he says.&lt;ref name=Nachman/&gt;{{rp|68}}

{{quote box||align=right|width=25em|bgcolor = LightCyan|quote=He was the best thing I ever saw. There was a need for revolution, everybody was ready for revolution, but some guy had to come along who could perform the revolution and be great. Mort was the one. He was the tip of the iceberg. Underneath were all the other people who came along: Lenny Bruce, Nichols &amp; May, all the Second City. Mort was the vanguard of the group.|source= — '''Woody Allen'''&lt;ref name=Nesteroff&gt;Nesteroff, Kliph. ''The Comedians'', Grove Press (2015)&lt;/ref&gt;{{rp|160}}}}

Numerous celebrities dropped by to see his shows after they heard about the "new phenomenon," referring to Sahl's unique style of comedy. [[Woody Allen]], who saw his show at the Blue Angel in 1954, commented that "he was suddenly this great genius that appeared who revolutionized the medium."&lt;ref name=Nachman/&gt;{{rp|68}} British comedy actor [[John Cleese]] became immediately interested in Sahl's radical style of humor, and accorded to him the same level of respect that the Beatles once reserved for Elvis Presley.&lt;ref name=Hopper/&gt;

[[file:Mort Sahl Ed Sullivan 1960.JPG|thumb|left|On the [[Ed Sullivan show]] in 1960]]
Television host [[Steve Allen]], who originated the [[Tonight Starring Steve Allen|''Tonight Show'']], said he was "struck by how amateur he seemed," but added that the observation was not meant as a criticism, but as a "compliment". He noted that all the previous successful comics dressed formally, were glib and well-rehearsed, and were always in control of their audiences.&lt;ref name=Nachman/&gt;{{rp|63}} Allen said that Sahl's "very un-show business manner was one of the things I liked when I first saw him work."&lt;ref name=Nachman/&gt;{{rp|63}}

Sahl dressed casually, with no tie and usually wearing his trademark V-neck campus-style sweater. His stage presence was seen as being "candid and cool, the antithesis of the slick comic," states theater critic [[Gerald Nachman (journalist)|Gerald Nachman]].&lt;ref name=Nachman/&gt;{{rp|50}} And although Sahl acquired a reputation for being an intellectual comedian, it was an image he disliked and disagreed with: "It was absurd. I was barely a C student," he said.&lt;ref name=Nachman/&gt;{{rp|67}} His naturalness on stage was partly due to his preferring improvisation over carefully rehearsed monologues. Sahl explained:

{{quote|I never found you could write the act. You can't rehearse the audience's responses. You adjust to them every night. I come in with only an outline. You've got to have a spirit of adventure. I follow my instincts and the audience is my jury.&lt;ref name=Nachman/&gt;{{rp|64}}}}

His casual style of stand-up, where he seemed to be one-on-one with his audience, influenced new comedians, including [[Lenny Bruce]] and [[Dick Gregory]]. Sahl was the least controversial, however, because he dressed and looked "collegiate" and focused on politics, while Bruce confronted sexual and language conventions and Gregory focused on the civil rights movement. After seeing Mort Sahl on stage, [[Woody Allen]], whose writings were often about his personal life, decided to give it a try: "I'd never had the nerve to talk about it before. Then Mort Sahl came along with a whole new style of humor, opening up vistas for people like me."&lt;ref name=Nachman/&gt;{{rp|545}}

Commenting about Sahl's monologues, Nachman describes him as a "gifted narrator, so good at taking you along on his travels that you didn't quite realize until the show was over that you had been on a labyrinthine journey."&lt;ref name=Nachman/&gt;{{rp|64}} The speed with which Sahl gave his monologues was also notable. British film critic [[Penelope Gilliatt]] recalls how Sahl's improvisation "goes on a breakneck stammering loop and you think it will never make the circle. It always does." For her it was like watching a circus act: "He freewheels a bike on a high wire tightrope with his brain racing and his hands off the handlebars."&lt;ref name=Nachman/&gt;{{rp|65}}

Sahl's popularity "mushroomed like an Atomic cloud during the 50's," says filmmaker [[Robert B. Weide]], adding, "Simply put, Mort Sahl reinvented stand-up comedy."&lt;ref name=Weide/&gt; ''Time'' magazine in 1960 published a cover story about him and his rise to fame, in which they described him as "the best of the New Comedians [and] the first notable American political satirist since [[Will Rogers]]."&lt;ref name=Time/&gt; Along with his nightclub performances, he appeared in some films and on television shows, including his network debut on ''[[The NBC Comedy Hour]]'' in May 1956.&lt;ref&gt;[https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=FoEUZMSTYjo "The Big Party" (1959, NBC)] (on YouTube.com); accessed February 14, 2015.&lt;/ref&gt;

His audience had also widened to include not only students and a "hip" public, but now even noted politicians sought out his shows. Some became friends, such as presidential candidate [[John F. Kennedy]], who asked him to prepare a bank of political jokes he could use at public functions.&lt;ref name=Time/&gt; Kennedy liked his style of political satire and what he described as Sahl's "relentless pursuit of everybody."&lt;ref name=Time/&gt; [[Adlai Stevenson II|Adlai Stevenson]] and [[Hubert Humphrey]] were fans, Humphrey stating that "whenever there is a political bloat, Mort sticks a pin in it."&lt;ref name=Time/&gt;

They valued the fact that he stayed current and took material from major newspapers and magazines. He kept his material fresh, wrote few notes, and entertained his audiences by presenting otherwise serious news with his brand of humor.&lt;ref name=Time/&gt; He was not fond of television news, however, which he blamed in 1960 for "spoon-feeding" the public, and was therefore responsible for the "corruption and ignorance that may sink this country."&lt;ref name=Time/&gt;

As a result of Sahl's popularity, besides getting on the cover of ''Time'', he also became the first comedian to make a record album, the first to do college concerts and was the first comedian to win a Grammy.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.goldstar.com/events/san-francisco-ca/mort-sahl-and-dick-gregory "Legendary Comedians Mort Sahl and Dick Gregory at the Rrazz Room"], ''Goldstar''&lt;/ref&gt;

===Declining career from mid 1960s===
Following [[John F. Kennedy assassination|Kennedy's assassination]] in 1963, Sahl's interest in who was responsible was so great that he became a [[Sheriff|deputized member]] of New Orleans District Attorney [[Jim Garrison]]'s team to investigate the assassination.&lt;ref name=master/&gt; As a result, Sahl's comedy would often reflect his politics and included readings and commentary about the [[Warren Commission]] Report, of which he consistently disputed the accuracy.&lt;ref&gt;[https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=yL6bo3DxwOw&amp;t=28m58s "Mors Sahl Live in New York City"], January 17, 1992&lt;/ref&gt; He alienated much of his audience, was effectively [[blacklisting|blacklisted]] and more of his planned shows were cancelled. His income dropped from $1 million to $19,000 by 1964.{{citation needed|date=February 2016}} According to Nachman, the excessive focus on the Kennedy assassination details was Sahl's undoing and wrecked his career. Sahl later admitted that "there's never been anything that had a stronger impact on my life than this issue," but added that he nonetheless "thought it was a wonderful quest."&lt;ref name=Playboy/&gt;

===Partial comeback in the 1970s to the present===
{{quote box||align=right|width=30em|bgcolor = Cornsilk|quote=Mort Sahl has charted one of the most precipitous courses in American entertainment for last thirty years and has gone from celebrity to internal exile. There was no precedent for what he did. There were no prototypes. He's a genuinely self-created man and a true existential in that sense. Once he passes from the scene, people will begin to lionize him and call him the great American and take to heart all the things he said.|source= — ''Los Angeles Times'', 1983&lt;ref name=Nachman/&gt;{{rp|54}}}}

By the 1970s the rising tide of [[counterculture]] eventually fueled Sahl's partial comeback as a veteran comedian, and he was included along with the new comedians breaking into the field, such as [[George Carlin]], [[Lily Tomlin]] and [[Richard Pryor]].&lt;ref name=Nachman/&gt;{{rp|89}} In the 1980s he headlined for Banducci's new clubs in San Francisco. In the late 1980s he was trying to write screenplays, besides doing sporadic shows around the country. In 1987 he had a successful multiweek run in Australia.&lt;ref&gt;[http://articles.latimes.com/1987-03-21/entertainment/ca-4466_1_mort-sahl "L.A. To Get Another Taste Of The Biting Wit Of Mort Sahl"], ''Los Angeles Times'', March 21, 1987.&lt;/ref&gt;

In 1988 Sahl was back in New York and performed a one-man Off-Broadway show, ''Mort Sahl's America'', which, despite getting good reviews from critics was not a box office success. The ''New York Times'' stated, "History has returned Mort Sahl to the spotlight when he is most needed. His style has an intuitive spontaneity. His presence is tonic."&lt;ref name=Nachman/&gt;{{rp|92}} Robert Weide produced a biographical documentary, ''Mort Sahl: The Loyal Opposition'', which ran  on PBS in 1989.&lt;ref name=Weide&gt;[http://duckprods.com/projects/mortsahl/index.html ''''Mort Sahl: The Loyal Opposition''], Whyaduck Productions, March 2, 2012.&lt;/ref&gt;

However, the level of success he once had now eluded him. One ''Los Angeles Times'' critic wrote, "Sahl is a man with a country but not a stage."&lt;ref name=Nachman/&gt;{{rp|96}} A number of television specials gave him a venue to perform in front of live audiences. The Monitor Channel broadcast a series of eight shows called ''Mort Sahl Live'' beginning in November 1991.&lt;ref&gt;[https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=JnHUStTmm3A "Mort Sahl Live #1 Atlantic City 11/16/91"], The Monitor Channel, November 16, 1991&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=l3YlYRkR6I4 "Mort Sahl Live #2 Anaheim 2/21/91"], The Monitor Channel, December 12, 1991.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;!--Note: these are fair use videos uploaded by their producer, Bob Burns--&gt;

From the 1990s on he has performed, but less often and mostly in theaters and college auditoriums.&lt;ref&gt;[http://articles.latimes.com/1992-10-22/news/ol-977_1_mort-sahl "BARK AND BITE : For Nearly Four Decades, Mort Sahl Has Been the Voice of Social Satire; Don't Expect Him to Back Off Now"], ''Los Angeles Times'', October 22, 1992&lt;/ref&gt; When [[Woody Allen]] saw him perform in 2001 at one of his rare New York club appearances, Allen told him, "this is crazy—you should be working all the time."&lt;ref name=Nachman/&gt;{{rp|96}} Allen then called his manager [[Jack Rollins (producer)|Jack Rollins]]: "Listen, this guy is hilarious. We gotta bring him to New York."&lt;ref name=Nachman/&gt;{{rp|96}} Sahl then did shows at [[Joe's Pub]] in Manhattan to standing-room only audiences.&lt;ref name=Nachman/&gt;{{rp|97}}

Sahl is #40 on [[Comedy Central]]'s list of the 100 greatest stand-up comedians of all time, ranked between [[Billy Crystal]] and [[Jon Stewart]].&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite episode | title = Comedy Central's 100 Greatest Stand-Ups of All Time | url = http://www.comedycentral.com/tv_shows/100greatest/list.jhtml | access-date = 21 September 2016 | series = Comedy Central Presents | network = Comedy Central | date = 17 April 2004 | deadurl = yes | archiveurl = https://web.archive.org/web/20040605175309/http://www.comedycentral.com/tv_shows/100greatest/list.jhtml | archivedate = 5 June 2004 | df =  }}&lt;/ref&gt; In 2003 he received the Fifth Annual [[Alan King (comedian)|Alan King]] Award in American Jewish Humor from the [[National Foundation for Jewish Culture]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.avclub.com/article/mort-sahl-13850 "Mort Sahl"], ''A.V. Club, January 7, 2004.&lt;/ref&gt;

In 2011, the Library of Congress placed his 1955 recording, ''At Sunset'', on the [[National Recording Registry]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.loc.gov/rr/record/nrpb/registry/essays/Mort%20Sahl%20At%20Sunset%20--%20laptop%20version5.pdf|title=Mort Sahl at Sunset (1955)|first=Daniel|last=Blazek|work=[[National Recording Registry]]|publisher=[[Library of Congress]]|year=2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Satire comedy style===
Sahl's humor is based on current events, especially politics, which led [[Milton Berle]] to describe him as "one of the greatest political satirists of all time."&lt;ref name=Hopper/&gt; His trademark persona is to enter the stage with a newspaper in hand, casually dressed in a [[V-neck sweater]]. He would often recite some news stories combined with satire.&lt;ref name=master&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.pbs.org/wnet/americanmasters/episodes/mort-sahl/about-mort-sahl/694|title=About Mort Sahl|quote=In his trademark V-neck sweater, with the day's newspaper tucked under his arm, Mort Sahl has satirized—and entertained—presidents from Eisenhower to Clinton.|date=March 19, 2006|work=[[American Masters]]}}&lt;/ref&gt; He was dubbed "[[Will Rogers]] with fangs" by Time magazine in 1960.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal| url=http://content.time.com/time/magazine/article/0,9171,826502,00.html|title=Comedians: Will Rogers with Fangs|journal=[[Time (magazine)|Time]]|date=July 25, 1960|issn=0040-781X}}&lt;/ref&gt;

He would discuss people or events almost as if he were reporting them for the first time, and would digress into related stories or his own experiences. TV executive [[Roger Ailes]] said he saw him read the paper one day and after a few hours Sahl got up onstage with an entire evening's worth of new material. "With no writers, he just did what he had seen in the afternoon paper. He was a genius."&lt;ref name=Nachman/&gt;{{rp|52}}

Sahl's presentation of news commentary as a form of social satire created a wide assortment of celebrity and political fans, including [[Adlai Stevenson II|Adlai Stevenson]], [[Marlene Dietrich]], [[S.J. Perelman]], [[Saul Bellow]] and [[Leonard Bernstein]]. [[Arthur M. Schlesinger, Jr.]] said his popularity was due to the public's "yearning for youth, irreverence, trenchancy, satire, [and] a clean break with the past."&lt;ref name=Nachman/&gt;{{rp|71}} And [[Steve Allen]] introduced him on one of his shows as being "the only real [[political philosopher]] we have in modern comedy."&lt;ref&gt;{{cite av media|url=https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=NrSfyzuXS2M|title=MORT SAHL DISCUSSES LENNY BRUCE|date=23 October 2010|accessdate=February 6, 2016|via=YouTube}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Combined with his improvisational skill, Sahl's naturalness was also considered unique for a stage performer. [[Woody Allen]] notes that other comics were jealous of Sahl's stage persona and did not understand how he could perform by simply talking to the audience.&lt;ref name=Nachman/&gt;{{rp|52}} Nachman states that the "mere idea of a stand-up comic talking about the real world was in itself revolutionary...[and] the comedians who followed him—[[Lenny Bruce]], [[Woody Allen]], [[Dick Gregory]], [[Phyllis Diller]], [[Shelley Berman]], [[Jonathan Winters]]—were cast in a familiar nightclub mold."&lt;ref name=Nachman/&gt;{{rp|51}}

==Marriages==
Sahl has been married three times:
He married Susan J. Babior in 1955; they divorced in 1958.

In 1967 he married actress and model [[China Lee]] and they divorced in 1991.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.marinij.com/general-news/20100809/mort-sahl-improvising-a-new-life|title=Mort Sahl: Improvising a new life|first=Paul|last=Liberatore|newspaper=[[Marin Independent Journal]]|date=August 9, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; They had one son, Mort Sahl Jr., who died in 1996, aged 19, from an unknown drug-related reaction.&lt;ref name=Nachman/&gt;{{rp|92}}&lt;ref&gt;[http://cache2.asset-cache.net/gc/155509152-comedian-mort-shal-wife-china-lee-and-son-gettyimages.jpg?v=1&amp;c=IWSAsset&amp;k=2&amp;d=GkZZ8bf5zL1ZiijUmxa7QS89yH3F74QS1cV5r7dZrrdcHpyxry5VcU7uPbxS8SMk%2BNDm2XT%2BIEaK%2FMPgfdHLZA%3D%3D] Comedian Mort Sahl, wife China Lee and son Mort Sahl Jr. at Le Palmier Restaurant in New York City.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=https://variety.com/1996/voices/columns/copperfield-act-could-blow-away-auds-1117862937|title=Copperfield Act Could Blow Away Auds|first=Army|last=Archerd|authorlink=Army Archerd|quote=Mort Sahl, "picking up the pieces" since the March 27 death of his son, Mort Jr., returns to the stage, with a four-week stand at the Tiffany, starting July 17.|date=June 21, 1996|work=[[Variety (magazine)|Variety]]|issn=0042-2738}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In 1997 he married Kenslea Ann Motter; they divorced around 2009.&lt;ref name=Lion&gt;Nachman, Gerald. [http://spectator.org/articles/37853/comedys-lion-winter "COMEDY’S LION IN WINTER"], ''The American Spectator'', April 2011.&lt;/ref&gt; He regrets their separation, saying "I'm sorry I divorced Kenslea; I'm still in love with my wife. If you love a woman it'll make her a better woman."&lt;ref name=Lion/&gt;

==Other==
In 1976, Sahl wrote an autobiography called ''Heartland''. In June 2007 a number of star comedians including George Carlin and Jonathan Winters, gave Sahl an 80th birthday tribute.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.mortsahlofficial.com/honors.html Mort Sahl Acclaim], Mortsahlofficial.com; accessed February 14, 2016.&lt;/ref&gt;

Sahl does not drink, smoke, use drugs or use swear words, on or off stage.&lt;ref name=Nachman/&gt;{{rp|92}} In 2008, Sahl moved from Los Angeles to Mill Valley, a suburb of San Francisco, where he became friends with comedian [[Robin Williams]] who lived nearby. Sahl works every Thursday night with his take-no-prisoners approach, taking questions from the live audience and from Periscope/Twitter.&lt;ref&gt;[https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=hOwSO7uN4sg "Mort Sahl Tells Of Time Robin Williams Was His One Fan"], August 15, 2014.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.people.com/article/robin-williams-inside-his-last-days "Inside Robin Williams's Last Days"], People.com. August 14, 2014.&lt;/ref&gt;

==Discography==
*''At Sunset'', [[Fantasy Records]] (recorded 1955, released 1958)
*''The Future Lies Ahead'', [[Verve Records]] (1958)
*''Mort Sahl: 1960 or Look Forward In Anger'', Verve Records MG V-15004 (1959)
*''At the Hungry I'', Verve Records (1960)
*''The Next President'', Verve Records (1960)
*''A Way of Life'', Verve Records (1960)
*''The New Frontier'', [[Reprise Records]] (1961)
*''On Relationships'', Reprise Records (1961)
*''Great Moments of Comedy with Mort Sahl'' Verve Records (1965)
*''Anyway...Onward'', [[Mercury Records]] (1967)
*''"Sing a Song of Watergate... Apocryphal of Lie!"'', [[GNP Crescendo Records]] (1973)
*''Mort Sahl's America'', Dove Audio (1996)

==Selected filmography==
*''[[In Love and War (1958 film)|In Love and War]]'' (1958) as Danny Krieger
*''[[Richard Diamond, Private Detective]]'' (CBS-TV 1959) as Himself
*''[[All the Young Men]]'' (1960) as Cpl. Crane
*''[[Johnny Cool]]'' (1963) as Ben Morrow
*''[[Doctor, You've Got to Be Kidding!]]'' (1967) as Dan Ruskin
*''[[Don't Make Waves]]'' (1967) as Sam Lingonberry
*''[[hungry i]] reunion'' (1981) as Himself, documentary
*''[[Inside the Third Reich (film)|Inside the Third Reich]]'' (1982) (TV) as [[Werner Finck]]
*''[[Nothing Lasts Forever (film)|Nothing Lasts Forever]]'' (1984) as Uncle Mort
*''[[Jonathan Winters]]: On the Ledge'' (1987) as Himself, TV Special
*''Mort Sahl: The Loyal Opposition'' (1989) as Himself, [[American Masters]] documentary
*''[[Jewish humour|The World of Jewish Humor]]'' (1990) as Himself, documentary
*''Looking for [[Lenny Bruce|Lenny]]'' (2011) as Himself, documentary
*''When Comedy Went to School'' (2013) as Himself, documentary
*''[[Max Rose]]'' (2016) as Jack

==Bibliography==
* Curtis, James; ''Last Man Standing: Mort Sahl and the Birth of Modern Comedy'', Univ. Press of Mississippi (2017) {{isbn|1496809289}}&lt;ref name=bio/&gt;
* {{cite book |last=Sahl |first=Mort |title=Heartland |publisher=[[Harcourt Brace Jovanovich]] |location=San Diego, CA |year=1976 |isbn=978-0151398201}}

==Notes==
{{Reflist|30em}}

==References==
* {{cite book|last=Epstein |first=Lawrence J. |authorlink=Lawrence J. Epstein |title=The Haunted Smile:The Story of Jewish Comedians in America |publisher=Public Affairs |location=New York, NY |year=2001 |isbn=1-8916-2071-1}}
* {{cite book |last1= Nachman |first1=Gerald |author-link1= Gerald Nachman (journalist) |title=Seriously Funny |script-title=The Rebel Comedians of the 1950s and 1960s|url=http://geraldnachman.com/about.html |access-date= |location=New York, NY |publisher=Pantheon Books |publication-date=2003 |page= |pages=659 |isbn=  9780375410307 &lt;!-- 0375410309 --&gt; |oclc=50339527  |trans-title= |author-mask1= |date= |year= |orig-year= |editor1-last= |editor1-first= |editor1-link= |editor1-mask= |display-editors= |type= |language= |edition= |quote= |postscript= |ref= }}
* {{cite book|last=Smith |first=Ronald L. |title=Who's Who in Comedy: Comedians, Comics, and Clowns From Vaudeville to Today's Stand-ups |publisher=Facts on File |location=New York, NY |year=1992 |isbn=0-81602-338-7}}

==External links==
{{Wikiquote}}
{{Portal|Biography|Canada|Los Angeles|California|New York City|Film|Television|Comedy|Politics|United States Air Force|Judaism}}
*{{Official website}}
*[http://mortsahl.com/ Mort Sahl fan site]
*{{Allmusic |class=artist |id=mort-sahl-mn0001253710}}
*{{Discogs artist}}
*{{IMDb name|0756340}}
*[http://thankyouoneandall.co.uk/letters/sahl.htm The Future Lies Behind! Thank you Mort Sahl...for telling it like it was]

{{Authority control}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Sahl, Mort}}
[[Category:1927 births]]
[[Category:Belmont High School (Los Angeles, California) alumni]]
[[Category:American Jews]]
[[Category:American stand-up comedians]]
[[Category:American satirists]]
[[Category:American social commentators]]
[[Category:Canadian stand-up comedians]]
[[Category:Counterculture of the 1960s]]
[[Category:Jewish American male actors]]
[[Category:Jewish Canadian comedians]]
[[Category:Living people]]
[[Category:People from Montreal]]
[[Category:Researchers of the assassination of John F. Kennedy]]
[[Category:United States Air Force airmen]]
[[Category:University of Southern California alumni]]
[[Category:Jewish American comedians]]
[[Category:Anglophone Quebec people]]
[[Category:Canadian expatriate actors in the United States]]</text>
      <sha1>tfs398fxstkjmnik43cfqpgcb7t41yq</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
