<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10.xsd" version="0.10" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <dbname>enwiki</dbname>
    <base>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.32.0-wmf.16</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="118" case="first-letter">Draft</namespace>
      <namespace key="119" case="first-letter">Draft talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2300" case="first-letter">Gadget</namespace>
      <namespace key="2301" case="first-letter">Gadget talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2302" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition</namespace>
      <namespace key="2303" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Pert Kelton</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>3643711</id>
    <revision>
      <id>855124206</id>
      <parentid>855122402</parentid>
      <timestamp>2018-08-16T03:27:27Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <ip>69.181.23.220</ip>
      </contributor>
      <comment>Sadakichi Hartmann , Warner-Kelton Hotel, 6326 Lexington Ave, Los Angeles, California</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="23635">{{Infobox person
| name          = Pert Kelton
| image         = Pert Kelton 1942.JPG
| imagesize     = 220px
| caption       = Kelton in 1942.
| birth_date    = {{birth date|1907|10|14|mf=y}}
| birth_place   = [[Great Falls, Montana]], U.S.
| death_date    = {{death date and age|1968|10|30|1907|10|14|mf=y}}
| death_place   = [[Ridgewood, New Jersey]], U.S.
| spouse        = Ralph Bell (?&amp;ndash;1968) 2 children
| children      = Brian Bell and Stephen Bell
| yearsactive   = 1910&amp;ndash;1968 
}}

'''Pert L. Kelton''' (October 14, 1907&lt;ref name="Kelton.org"&gt;{{cite news |title=The Story of Pert Kelton |url=http://www.kelton.org/notables/pert.html |publisher=Edward F. Kelton |year=2002 |deadurl=yes |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20060501065447/http://www.kelton.org/notables/pert.html |archivedate=2006-05-01 |df= }}&lt;/ref&gt; &amp;ndash; October 30, 1968) was an American stage, movie, radio and television actress.&lt;ref&gt;Obituary ''[[Variety Obituaries|Variety]]'', November 6, 1968, page 71.&lt;/ref&gt; She was the first actress who played [[The Honeymooners#Alice Kramden|Alice Kramden]] in ''[[The Honeymooners]]'' with [[Jackie Gleason]] and earlier, during the 1930s, was a prominent [[comedy|comedic]] supporting and leading actress in [[Hollywood]] films such as ''[[Bed of Roses (1933 film)|Bed of Roses]]'' and ''[[The Bowery (1933 film)|The Bowery]]''. She performed in a dozen Broadway productions between 1925 and 1968. However, her career was interrupted in the 1950s as a result of [[Hollywood blacklist|blacklisting]],&lt;ref name=kelton2&gt;{{cite book|last=Cullen|first=Frank|author2=Florence Hackman|author3=Donald McNeilly|title=Vaudeville, Old and New|publisher=Routledge|year=206|location=New York|pages=629–630|isbn=978-0-415-93853-2|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=XFnfnKg6BcAC&amp;pg=PA629&amp;lpg=PA629&amp;dq=pert+kelton+great+falls&amp;source=bl&amp;ots=5unFuNzbC3&amp;sig=NGLaIJ8ge5ftMiiDOSZx-HfrREU&amp;hl=en&amp;ei=43xdTqS4Aom2sQKgh8wp&amp;sa=X&amp;oi=book_result&amp;ct=result&amp;resnum=10&amp;ved=0CDsQ6AEwCQ#v=onepage&amp;q=pert%20kelton%20great%20falls&amp;f=false}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=NYTobit/&gt; leading to her departure from ''The Honeymooners''.

==Early life==
Pert L. Kelton was born in 1907 in Great Falls, Montana. Her mother, Sue Kelton, was a native of [[Canada]]; her father, Edward Kelton, a native of [[California]].&lt;ref&gt;[https://www.familysearch.org/ark:/61903/1:1:KSQX-P2K "New York State Census, 1925".] New York State Archives, Albany, New York. [[FamilySearch]]. Retrieved September 8, 2017.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="1930 Census"&gt;[https://www.familysearch.org/ark:/61903/3:1:33SQ-GR4X-WSF?i=44&amp;cc=1810731 "The Fifteenth Census of the United States: 1930"], enumeration date April 14, 1930, District 55, Warner-Kelton Hotel, 6326 Lexington Avenue, Los Angeles City, Los Angeles County, California. Bureau of the Census, United States Department of Commerce and Labor, Washington, D.C. FamilySearch. Retrieved August 31, 2017.&lt;/ref&gt; Both of her parents were traveling song-and-dance performers in [[vaudeville]]; and her aunt, Jane Kelton, was also a professional actress in the late 1800s and early 1900s .  In fact, it was her Aunt Jane who is credited with giving Pert her unusual name. According to Kelton family history, Jane suggested the name to Pert's mother while reminiscing about her career and describing her favorite theatrical role, that of the character "Pert Barlow" in a play called ''Checkers''.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.playbill.com/playbillpagegallery/inside-playbill?asset=00000150-aea5-d936-a7fd-eef542a50008&amp;type=InsidePlaybill&amp;slide=10 "Who's Who in the Cast: Pert Kelton",] ''[[Playbill]]'', March 1958, a cast profile included in preview for ''The Music Man'', which premiered at the Majestic Theatre, New York, N.Y., December 19, 1957. Retrieved September 1, 2017.&lt;/ref&gt; Pert therefore, even from infancy, seemed destined to be an entertainer, and she quickly became one. In 1910, while accompanying her parents and sister on an overseas tour of shows, she debuted on stage at the age of three in [[Cape Town, South Africa]].&lt;ref name="Playbill Miracle"&gt;[http://www.playbill.com/playbillpagegallery/inside-playbill?asset=00000150-aea8-d936-a7fd-eefc3a280001&amp;type=InsidePlaybill&amp;slide=5 "Inside the Playbill: Minor Miracle - Opening Night at the Henry Miller's Theatre",] ''Playbill'', October 7, 1965; "Who's Who in the Cast", p. 34. Retrieved September 3, 2017.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=rs&gt;DeLong, Thomas A. (1996). ''Radio Stars: An Illustrated Biographical Dictionary of 953 Performers, 1920 through 1960''. McFarland &amp; Company, Inc, p. 149. {{ISBN|978-0-7864-2834-2}}.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="ose"&gt;{{cite news|last1=Hall|first1=Leonard|title=Pert Kelton -- A New Tale For the Cinderella Book|url=https://www.newspapers.com/clip/5707887/the_ogden_standardexaminer/|work=The Ogden Standard Examiner|agency=Newspaper Enterprise Association|date=February 20, 1928|location=Utah, Ogden|page=7}}&lt;/ref&gt; Upon her return to the United States with her family, Pert was enrolled in private schools for her early formal education and for extensive training in dance, voice, and drama. By age 12, after appearing for a while with her parents as "The Three Keltons", she began appearing as a solo act or "single" in vaudeville; and by age 17 she was performing on [[Broadway theatre|Broadway]], initially as a cast member in [[Jerome Kern]]'s 1925 musical comedy ''[[Sunny (musical)|Sunny]]'', starring [[Marilyn Miller]].&lt;ref name=ose/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.playbill.com/playbillpagegallery/inside-playbill?asset=00000150-aea5-d936-a7fd-eef542b20000&amp;type=InsidePlaybill&amp;slide=2 "Inside the Playbill: Come Blow Your Horn—Opening Night at the Brooks Atkinson Theatre"], profile of Pert Kelton in ''Playbill'', February 1961. Premiere of ''Come Blow Your Horn'', Brooks Atkinson Theatre, New York, New York. Retrieved September 4, 2017.&lt;/ref&gt;

==Films==
Pert and her parents had moved to California to work in [[Hollywood]] films by the latter half of 1927.&lt;ref name=ose/&gt; Her first credited movie role there was as the character Rosie in [[First National Pictures]]' 1929 release ''[[Sally (1929 film)|Sally]]'', a production based on the Broadway hit by the same name. With regard to the Kelton family's living arrangements in this period, the [[1930 United States Census |federal census]] of 1930 documents that Pert was residing in Los Angeles at the "Warner-Kelton Hotel",&lt;ref name="1930 Census"/&gt; later called the ''Hotel Brevoort (and Tropical Gardens)''&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.google.com/maps/place/6326+Lexington+Ave,+Los+Angeles,+CA+90038/@34.0923165,-118.3274688,93a,35y,180h/data=!3m1!1e3!4m5!3m4!1s0x80c2bf341741d81d:0x2802da3652cdad39!8m2!3d34.0923922!4d-118.3276112?hl=en|title=6326 Lexington Ave|author=|date=|website=google.com/maps|accessdate=15 August 2018}}&lt;/ref&gt; and sharing room 666&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20130801102646/http://allanellenberger.com/elizabeth-shorts-hollywood/|title=HOLLYWOODLAND » Elizabeth Short’s Hollywood…|author=Allan Ellenberger|date=29 July 2008|archivedate=1 August 2013|website=allanellenberger.com|via=archive.org|accessdate=15 August 2018}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20130731010854/https://martinturnbull.com/hollywood-places/|title=Hollywood Places|author=Martin Turnbull|date=31 July 2013|website=martinturnbull.com|via=archive.org|accessdate=15 August 2018}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;!-- https://martinturnbull.com/timeline-3/ --&gt; That same census identifies all three of the Keltons as employed actors in "motion pictures".&lt;ref name="1930 Census"/&gt;

Pert was a young comedienne in A-list movies during the 1930s, often portraying the leading lady's wisecracking friend. She had a memorable turn in 1933 as dance hall singer "Trixie" in ''[[The Bowery (1933 film)|The Bowery]]'' alongside [[Wallace Beery]], [[George Raft]], [[Jackie Cooper]], and [[Fay Wray]]. Directed by [[Raoul Walsh]], the film is based on the story of [[Steve Brodie (bridge jumper)|Steve Brodie]], the first man who reportedly jumped off the [[Brooklyn Bridge]] in 1886 and lived to brag about it. Kelton at one point in the film sings to a rowdy, appreciative crowd in an energetic [[Dive bar|dive]], using a curious New York accent to good comedic effect, with Beery and Raft arguing afterwards over her attentions.

In [[Gregory LaCava]]'s 1933 pre-Code comedy ''[[Bed of Roses (1933 film)|Bed of Roses]]'', Kelton plays Minnie, a witty prostitute who is a partner in crime with Lorry, portrayed by [[Constance Bennett]]. The two women in the plot are fond of getting admiring men helplessly drunk before robbing them, at least until getting caught and tossed back into jail. Kelton has all the best lines, surprisingly wicked and amusing observations that would never be allowed in an American film after the Hollywood [[Production Code]] was adopted. The movie remains realistic in terms of the interactions of the characters and features an early turn by [[Joel McCrea]] as the [[leading man]], a small boat skipper who pulls Bennett from the river after she dives into the water to escape capture. 

Kelton for the remainder of the 1930s performed in over 20 more feature films and [[Film short|short]]s.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.afi.com/members/catalog/SearchResult.aspx?s=&amp;retailCheck=&amp;Type=PN&amp;CatID=DATABIN_CAST&amp;ID=123589&amp;AN_ID=&amp;searchedFor=Pert_Kelton_ "Pert Kelton"], filmography, [[American Film Institute]] (AFI), Los Angeles, California. Retrieved September 1, 2017.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="IMDb"&gt;[https://www.imdb.com/name/nm0447125/?ref_=fn_al_nm_1 "Pert Kelton"], filmography, [[Internet Movie Database]] (IMDb), a subsidiary of [[Amazon.com|Amazon]], Seattle, Washington. Retrieved September 1, 2017.&lt;/ref&gt; After her appearance in the 1939 film ''Whispering Enemies'', she redirected her career, returning again to theatre and to performing increasingly on radio and later on the rapidly expanding medium of television. She did not return to the "big screen" until 1962, when she was cast as Mrs. Paroo in ''[[The Music Man (1962 film)|The Music Man]].''

==Radio and return to New York==
By April 1940, Pert had left California and was living in New York City again, sharing a $65-per-month apartment in [[Manhattan]] on West 55th Street with three other women, two of whom were employed as dancers in the theatre and the other roommate was working as a secretary.&lt;ref name="1940 Census"&gt;[https://www.familysearch.org/ark:/61903/3:1:3QSQ-G9MY-RFQL?cc=2000219 "The Sixteenth Census of the United States: 1940"], enumeration date April 23, 1940, Manhattan Borough, New York County, New York. FamilySearch. Retrieved September 6, 2017.&lt;/ref&gt; A federal census taker canvassing Manhattan that year concisely identified Kelton in his [[Census|enumeration]] ledger as "Actress, Theatre &amp; Movies" and recorded her given age as only 28, although in the spring of 1940 Pert was actually 32 years old.&lt;ref name="1940 Census"/&gt; If not a mistake in documentation, it is possible that Kelton herself, feeling the pressures to maintain a youthful profile within the image-conscious realm of entertainment, "shaved" a few years off her age when answering census questions at that time. Her documented lack of consistent employment during the previous year may be indicative too of the professional pressures she was experiencing after her film career in Hollywood began to wane in the late 1930s. According to the United States Census of 1940, Kelton was employed for only six weeks during the entire year of 1939, a total time of employment far less than the weeks worked by her roommates over the same period.&lt;ref name="1940 Census"/&gt;

Once Kelton had resettled in New York during the early 1940s, she began to work in theatre again, and she became a familiar voice on radio as well, performing on programs such as ''[[Easy Aces]]'', ''It's Always Albert'', ''The Stu Erwin Show'', and on the 1941 soap opera ''We Are Always Young''. Later, In 1949, she did the voices of five different radio characters on ''[[Texaco Star Theater|The Milton Berle Show]]''. She was also a regular cast member of ''The [[Henry Morgan (comedian)|Henry Morgan]] Show''; and in the early 1950s, she performed the role of the tart maid in the [[Monty Woolley]] vehicle ''The Magnificent Montague''.

== Television ==
Kelton appeared in ''[[Henry Morgan's Great Talent Hunt]]'', first aired January 26, 1951, hosted by [[Henry Morgan (comedian)|Henry Morgan]], and with [[Kaye Ballard]], [[Art Carney]], and [[Arnold Stang]].

Kelton was the original Alice Kramden in ''[[The Honeymooners]]'' comedy sketches on the [[DuMont Television Network]]'s ''[[Cavalcade of Stars]]''. These sketches formed the eventual basis for the 1955 [[CBS Television]] sitcom ''The Honeymooners''. [[Jackie Gleason]] starred as her husband Ralph Kramden, and Art Carney as their upstairs neighbor Ed Norton. [[Elaine Stritch]] played Trixie, the burlesque dancer wife of Norton, for one sketch before being replaced by [[Joyce Randolph]].

Kelton appeared in the original sketches, generally running about 10 to 20 minutes, shorter than the later one-season half-hour series episodes and 1960s hour-long musical versions. However, she was abruptly dropped from her role as a result of blacklisting and was replaced by [[Audrey Meadows]]; rather than acknowledge that she was being blacklisted, her producers explained that her departure was based on alleged heart problems. In his book ''The Forgotten Network'', David Weinstein says Kelton remained on ''Cavalcade of Stars'' through the final season of the series (1951-1952), and suggests that it may have been because Jackie Gleason had resisted attempts at having her dropped.

[[File:Pert Kelton Phil Silvers 1963.jpg|thumb|275px|Kelton performing with [[Phil Silvers]] in a 1963 CBS comedy special]]

In the 1960s, Kelton was invited back to Gleason's CBS show to play Alice's mother in an episode of the hour-long musical version of ''The Honeymooners'' (also known as ''The Color Honeymooners''), with [[Sheila MacRae]] as a fetching young Alice. By this time, the original age discrepancies were reversed, with Ralph married to a much younger Alice than himself. Gleason had been one of big-name celebrities who sought to end the widespread [[paranoia]] and hysteria being caused by the blacklist, as many others in the entertainment industry had also rejected the [[Red Scare]] of the 1950s.

In 1963 Kelton appeared on ''[[The Twilight Zone]]'', playing the overbearing mother of [[Robert Duvall]] in the episode "[[Miniature (The Twilight Zone)|Miniature]]." The next year she guest-starred on the popular family [[Situation comedy|sitcom]] ''My Three Sons'' starring [[Fred MacMurray]] as Steve Douglas and [[William Frawley]] as Bub O'Casey.  In that series' episode "Stage Door Bub", Kelton portrays Thelma Wilson, a veteran itinerant stage actress who longs for a settled domestic life but soon realizes that lifestyle is actually ill-suited for her personality.&lt;ref&gt;[https://www.imdb.com/title/tt0655092/ "Stage Door Bub",]] ''My Three Sons'', S04E24, originally broadcast February 27, 1964. [[Internet Movie Database]] (IMDb), a subsidiary of [[Amazon.com|Amazon]], Seattle, Washington. Retrieved August 30, 2017.&lt;/ref&gt;  In her last years, Kelton was also strongly identified with [[Spic and Span]] because of her televised commercials on behalf of that cleaning product.

== Broadway ==

In her 1925 Broadway debut in ''[[Sunny (musical)|Sunny]]'', Kelton had played the character Magnolia and performed a song with the same title as the play. Years later, she was twice nominated for Tony Awards: in 1960, as Best Supporting or Featured Actress (Musical) for [[Frank Loesser]]'s ''[[Greenwillow]]''; and in 1967-1968, as Best Supporting or Featured Actress (Dramatic) for ''Spofford''. Her most memorable Broadway role, however, was her portrayal of the impatient Mrs. Paroo, the Irish mother of the town librarian Marian Paroo ([[Barbara Cook]]), in [[Meredith Willson]]'s ''[[The Music Man]]'', which premiered at the [[Majestic Theatre (Broadway)|Majestic Theatre]] in New York in December 1957. She reprised her Broadway character in the film adaptation of ''[[The Music Man (1962 film)|The Music Man]]'' in 1962.

== Hotel owner ==
Pert Kelton was part owner of the Warner-Kelton Hotel, built in the late 1920s, at 6326 Lexington Avenue in Los Angeles, Pert and her parents resided in the hotel during the late 1920s until at least 1930.&lt;ref name="1930 Census"/&gt;. (A February 20, 1928, article in the ''[[Standard-Examiner]]'' ([[Ogden, Utah]]) incorrectly identifies the hotel as the ''Walton''-Kelton Hotel.)&lt;ref name=ose/&gt; The hotel catered to actors, poets and musicians such as [[Cary Grant]], [[Orry Kelly]], [[Rodgers and Hart]] and [[Monroe Salisbury]], [[Sadakichi Hartmann]],&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.oac.cdlib.org/findaid/ark:/13030/tf7s2007q4/dsc/|title=Sadakichi Hartmann Papers|website=Online Archive of California}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[The Great Dictator#Other cast|Esther Michelson]],&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.imdb.com/name/nm0585116/|title=Esther Michelson|author=|date=|website=IMDb|accessdate=15 August 2018}}&lt;/ref&gt; 
Clara Bow's stepmother, Mary Lorraine Tui (Tui Lorraine)&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.imdb.com/name/nm0100680/|title=Tui Bow|author=|date=|website=IMDb|accessdate=15 August 2018}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=mm3gQqcl20UC&amp;pg=PA140&amp;lpg=PA140&amp;dq=Kelton|title=Clara Bow: Runnin' Wild|first=David|last=Stenn|date=13 March 2000|publisher=Cooper Square Press|accessdate=15 August 2018|via=Google Books}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.newspapers.com/newspage/19714301/|title=|author=|date=|website=Jefferson City Post-Tribune from Jefferson City, Missouri on July 29, 1929 · Page 10|quote=...Gets Divorce From Clara Bow's Daddy. She no longer is Clara Bow's stepmother. Tui Lorraine Bow...|via=newspapers.com|accessdate=15 August 2018}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Graham Bicknell. ''Woman’s Day'' – 31 May 1993 (Page 114)&lt;/ref&gt;
and later, [[Elizabeth Short]].&lt;ref&gt;http://movielanddirectory.com/tour-location.cfm?location=43323&lt;/ref&gt;  The building had a small outdoor theatre, in a garden to the south, along with a wishing well that may have inspired the song "[[There's a Small Hotel]]" from the musical ''[[On Your Toes]]'' (1936). It also housed a [[speakeasy]] in the basement. A sign above the hotel entrance reads "Joyously Enter Here". It later was the home of the ''California Television Society''.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.earlytelevision.org/california_television_society.html&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;http://articles.latimes.com/1985-11-10/magazine/tm-3424_1_teen-age-girl/2&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;https://apps.usfa.fema.gov/hotel/main/resultsDetail?propertyID=49558&lt;/ref&gt;

==Personal life and death==
When away from rehearsing and performing, Kelton enjoyed art as a pastime and became a "passionate" painter.&lt;ref name="Spofford"&gt;[http://www.playbill.com/playbillpagegallery/inside-playbill?asset=00000150-aea3-d936-a7fd-eef7d7fd0001&amp;type=InsidePlaybill&amp;slide=5 "Who's Who in the Cast"] for the Broadway play ''Spofford'' at the ANTA Theatre, New York, New York, premiered December 14, 1967; ''[[Playbill]]'', December 1967, page 36.  Retrieved September 4, 2017.&lt;/ref&gt; Pert was married only once, to actor-director Ralph S. Bell with whom she had two sons, Brian and Stephen.&lt;ref name="Spofford"/&gt; The couple remained together until her death. 

A resident of [[Washington Township, Bergen County, New Jersey]], Kelton died of a [[heart attack]] on October 30, 1968, at age 61 while swimming at the [[YMCA]] in [[Ridgewood, New Jersey]].&lt;ref name=NYTobit&gt;Staff. [https://query.nytimes.com/gst/abstract.html?res=9E00E7DF1630E034BC4950DFB6678383679EDE&amp;legacy=true "Pert Kelton, Versatile Character Actress, Dead; Made Broadway Debut in '25 in the Musical ''Sunny'' Played Gleason's TV Wife Also on Radio Show"], ''[[The New York Times]]'', October 31, 1968. Accessed November 17, 2017. "Washington Township, N. J., Oct. 30-Pert Kelton, the character actress, was stricken, apparently with a heart attack, while swimming this morning at the Young Men's-Young Women's Hebrew Association in Ridgewood. She was pronounced dead at Valley Hospital. She was 61 years old and lived here with her husband, Ralph Bell, at 112 President Road."&lt;/ref&gt; Her body was cremated, and her ashes were given to family members.&lt;ref&gt;"Cinnamonntoast4" (2002). [https://www.findagrave.com/cgi-bin/fg.cgi?page=gr&amp;GRid=6595758 "Pert Kelton"], online memorial 6595758 with biographical profile and images originally created July 10, 2002. [[Find a Grave]], a subsidiary of [[Ancestry.com]], Lehi, Utah.  Retrieved September 8, 2017.&lt;/ref&gt; Her husband Ralph, who lived another three decades, remarried and died in August 1998.&lt;ref&gt;[https://www.nytimes.com/1998/08/12/classified/paid-notice-deaths-bell-ralph-s.html "Paid Notice: Deaths BELL, RALPH S."], obituary, ''The New York Times'', August 12, 1998. Retrieved September 8, 2017.&lt;/ref&gt;

==Filmography==

{{col-begin}}{{col-break}}
'''Features'''
*''[[Sally (1929 film)|Sally]]'' ([[1929 in film|1929]])
*''[[Hot Curves]]'' ([[1930 in film|1930]])
*''[[Bed of Roses (1933 film)|Bed of Roses]]'' ([[1933 in film|1933]])
*''[[The Bowery (1933 film)|The Bowery]]'' (1933)
*''[[The Meanest Gal in Town]]'' ([[1934 in film|1934]])
*''[[Sing and Like It]]'' (1934)
*''[[Bachelor Bait]]'' (1934)
*''[[Pursued (1934 film)|Pursued]]'' (1934)
*''[[Lightning Strikes Twice (1934 film)|Lightning Strikes Twice]]'' (1934)
*''[[Hooray for Love (film)|Hooray for Love]]'' ([[1935 in film|1935]])
*''[[Mary Burns, Fugitive]]'' (1935)
*''[[Annie Oakley (1935 film)|Annie Oakley]]'' (1935)
*''[[Kelly the Second]]'' ([[1936 in film|1936]])
*''[[Sitting on the Moon]]'' (1936)
*''[[Cain and Mabel]]'' (1936)
*''[[Laughing at Trouble]]'' (1936)
*''[[Women of Glamour]]'' ([[1937 in film|1937]])
*''[[The Hit Parade (film)|The Hit Parade]]'' (1937)
{{col-break|gap=4em}}
*''[[Meet the Boyfriend]]'' (1937)
*''[[You Can't Take It With You (film)|You Can't Take It with You]]'' ([[1938 in film|1938]])
*''[[Slander House]]'' (1938)
*''[[Rhythm of the Saddle]]'' (1938)
*''Whispering Enemies'' ([[1939 in film|1939]])
*''[[The Music Man (1962 film)|The Music Man]]'' ([[1962 in film|1962]])
*''[[Love and Kisses (film)|Love and Kisses]]'' ([[1965 in film|1965]])
*''[[The Comic]]'' ([[1969 in film|1969]])

'''Short Subjects:'''
*''Their Wives' Vacation'' ([[1930 in film|1930]])
*''Next Door Neighbors'' ([[1931 in film|1931]])
*''The Albany Branch'' (1931)
*''Signing 'em Up'' ([[1933 in film|1933]])
*''Screen Snapshots Series 14, No. 8'' ([[1935 in film|1935]])
*''A Night at the Biltmore Bowl'' (1935)
*''Pan Handlers'' ([[1936 in film|1936]])
*''Cinema Circus'' ([[1937 in film|1937]])
{{col-end}}

== See also ==
{{Portal|Biography}}
* [[Pitts and Todd]]

==References==
{{reflist}}
{{refimprove|date=October 2013}}

==External links==
{{Commons category}}
*{{IMDb name|0447125}}
*{{Amg name|37593}}
*{{Find a Grave|6595758}}
*{{IBDB name}}
*{{iobdb name|43409}}
*[http://www.tvguide.com/celebrities/pert-kelton/169805 Pert Kelton] at TVGuide.com
*[https://web.archive.org/web/20060501065447/http://www.kelton.org/notables/pert.html Kelton Family history]

{{Authority control}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Kelton, Pert}}
[[Category:1907 births]]
[[Category:1968 deaths]]
[[Category:American film actresses]]
[[Category:American radio actresses]]
[[Category:American television actresses]]
[[Category:Hollywood blacklist]]
[[Category:People from Great Falls, Montana]]
[[Category:People from Washington Township, Bergen County, New Jersey]]
[[Category:Vaudeville performers]]
[[Category:20th-century American actresses]]
[[Category:Actresses from Montana]]</text>
      <sha1>dx2i1gn7eggxdpj0rk6pcpbdwu0b01i</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
