<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10.xsd" version="0.10" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <dbname>enwiki</dbname>
    <base>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.32.0-wmf.16</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="118" case="first-letter">Draft</namespace>
      <namespace key="119" case="first-letter">Draft talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2300" case="first-letter">Gadget</namespace>
      <namespace key="2301" case="first-letter">Gadget talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2302" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition</namespace>
      <namespace key="2303" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Peter Cook</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>23547</id>
    <revision>
      <id>854635576</id>
      <parentid>854635356</parentid>
      <timestamp>2018-08-12T19:42:18Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Matuko</username>
        <id>298951</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>Re-added citation</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="41778">{{Other people|Peter Cook}}
{{Use British English|date=January 2014}}
{{Use dmy dates|date=January 2014}}
{{Infobox person
| name         = Peter Cook
| image        = File:Peter Cook Dudley Moore Kraft Music Hall.jpg
| imagesize    = 
| caption      = Cook on ''[[Kraft Music Hall]]'', 1969
| birth_date   = {{Birth date|1937|11|17|df=y}}
| birth_place  = [[Torquay]], [[Devon]], England
| death_date   = {{Death date and age|1995|1|9|1937|11|17|df=y}}
| death_place  = [[Hampstead]], London, England
| occupation   = Actor, satirist, writer, comedian
| years_active = 1958–1995
| spouse       = {{marriage|Wendy Snowden|1963|1971|reason=divorced}}&lt;br&gt;{{marriage|[[Judy Huxtable]]|1973|1989|reason=divorced}}&lt;br&gt;{{marriage|Lin Chong|1989|1995|reason=his death}}
| website      = 
}}

'''Peter Edward Cook''' (17 November 1937 – 9 January 1995) was an English actor, [[satirist]], writer and comedian. Cook is widely regarded as the leading light of the British [[satire boom]] of the 1960s. He was closely associated with the [[anti-establishment]] comedy that emerged in the United Kingdom and United States in the late 1950s.

Called "the father of modern satire" by ''[[The Guardian]]'', in 2005, Cook was ranked number one in the ''Comedians' Comedian'', a poll of more than 300 comics, comedy writers, producers, and directors throughout the English-speaking world.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|title=Peter Cook the funniest|url=http://www.theage.com.au/news/People/Peter-Cook-the-funniest/2005/01/03/1104601276619.html |work=The Age |location=Australia|date=3 January 2005}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|title=Cook tops poll of comedy greats|url=https://www.theguardian.com/uk/2005/jan/02/arts.artsnews |work=The Guardian|date=2 January 2005}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Early life==
Cook was born at his parents' house, "Shearbridge", in Middle Warberry Road, [[Torquay]], [[Devon]]. He was the only son and eldest of the three children of Alexander Edward "Alec" Cook (1906–1984), a colonial [[Civil service|civil servant]] (serving as [[political officer (British Empire)|political officer]] and later [[district officer]] in Nigeria, then as [[financial secretary]] to the colony of Gibraltar, followed by a return to Nigeria as [[Permanent Secretary]] of the Eastern Region, based at [[Enugu]])&lt;ref&gt;Peter Cook: A Biography, Harry Thompson, Sceptre, 1998, p. 5, 21&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;https://www.independent.co.uk/news/people/profiles/remembering-peter-cook-family-and-friends-including-keith-richards-ronnie-wood-and-bruce-forsyth-9952941.html&lt;/ref&gt;, and his wife Ethel Catherine Margaret (1908–1994), daughter of solicitor Charles Mayo.&lt;ref&gt;Peter Cook: A Biography, Harry Thompson, Sceptre, 1998, p. 3&lt;/ref&gt; Cook's grandfather, Edward Arthur Cook (1869-1914), had also been a colonial civil servant, traffic manager for the [[Federated Malay States Railway]] in [[Kuala Lumpur]], [[British Malaya|Malaya]]; stress leading up to an interview regarding promotion led him to commit suicide. His wife, Minnie Jane (1869-1957; daughter of Thomas Wreford, of [[Thelbridge]] and [[Witheridge]], Devon, and of [[Stratford-upon-Avon]], of a prominent Devonshire family traced back to 1440),&lt;ref&gt;Records and Pedigree of the Wreford Family, George Wreford, second edition, 1909&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;A Genealogical and Heraldic Dictionary of the Commoners of Great Britain and Ireland, ed. John Burke, 1838, vol. IV, p. 454&lt;/ref&gt;, kept this fact secret; Peter Cook only discovered the truth when later researching his family.&lt;ref&gt;Peter Cook: A Biography, Harry Thompson, Sceptre, 1998, pp. 1-2&lt;/ref&gt;

Cook was educated at [[Radley College]] and [[Pembroke College, Cambridge]], where he studied French and German. As a student, Cook initially intended to become a career [[diplomat]] like his father, but Britain "had run out of colonies", as he put it.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last1=Paxman|first1=Jeremy|authorlink=Jeremy Paxman|title=Empire|date=2012|publisher=Penguin|isbn=9780670919598|url=https://books.google.co.uk/books?id=tQpOOnImnd4C&amp;pg=PT340}}&lt;/ref&gt; Although politically largely apathetic, particularly in later life when he displayed a deep distrust of politicians of all hues, he did join the [[Cambridge University Liberal Club]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://keynessociety.wordpress.com/about-the-keynes-society/ |title=About us " Keynes Society |publisher=Keynessociety.wordpress.com |accessdate=15 May 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; At Pembroke Cook performed and wrote comedy sketches as a member of the Cambridge [[Footlights|Footlights Club]], of which he became president in 1960. His hero was fellow Footlights writer and Cambridge magazine writer [[David Nobbs]].&lt;ref&gt;I Didn't Get Where I am Today by David Nobbs 9780099421641&lt;/ref&gt;

Whilst still at university, Cook wrote for [[Kenneth Williams]], providing several sketches for Williams' hit [[West End theatre|West End]] comedy revue ''[[Pieces of Eight (1959 revue)|Pieces of Eight]]'' and much of the follow-up, ''[[One Over the Eight]]'', before finding prominence in his own right in a four-man group satirical stage show, ''[[Beyond the Fringe]]'', with [[Jonathan Miller]], [[Alan Bennett]] and [[Dudley Moore]].&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news|url=https://www.britannica.com/biography/Peter-Cook|title=Peter Edward Cook {{!}} British entertainer|work=Encyclopedia Britannica|access-date=2017-10-17|language=en}}&lt;/ref&gt;

''Beyond the Fringe'' became a great success in London after being first performed at the [[Edinburgh Festival]] and included Cook impersonating the [[Prime Minister of the United Kingdom|prime minister]], [[Harold Macmillan]]. This was one of the first occasions satirical political mimicry had been attempted in live theatre and it shocked audiences. During one performance, Macmillan was in the theatre and Cook departed from his script and attacked him verbally.&lt;ref&gt;Cook as Macmillan: "there's nothing I like better than to wander over to a theatre and sit there listening to a group of sappy, urgent, vibrant young satirists with a stupid great grin spread all over my silly face", ''Tragically I Was an Only Twin'', p. 51.&lt;/ref&gt;

==Career==

===1960s===
[[File:Peter Cook Beyond the Fringe 1962.JPG|thumb|upright|Cook in the revue ''[[Beyond the Fringe]]'']]

In 1961, Cook opened [[The Establishment (club)|The Establishment]], a club at 18 Greek Street in [[Soho]] in [[central London]], presenting fellow comedians in a nightclub setting, including American [[Lenny Bruce]]. Cook said it was a satirical venue modelled on "those wonderful Berlin cabarets ... which did so much to stop the rise of Hitler and prevent the outbreak of the Second World War";&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.smh.com.au/articles/2003/02/28/1046407753895.html |title=Tom Lehrer interview |publisher=Smh.com.au |date=1 March 2003 |accessdate=16 September 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt; as a members-only venue it was outside the [[Lord Chamberlain's Office|censorship restrictions]]. The Establishment's regular cabaret performers were [[Eleanor Bron]], [[John Bird (actor)|John Bird]] and [[John Fortune]].&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news|url=https://www.newyorker.com/magazine/1995/01/23/bedazzled|title=BEDAZZLED|work=The New Yorker|access-date=2018-08-12|language=en-US}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Cook befriended and supported Australian comedian and actor [[Barry Humphries]], who began his British solo career at the club. Humphries said in his autobiography, ''My Life As Me'', that he found Cook's lack of interest in art and literature off-putting. Dudley Moore's jazz trio played in the basement of the club during the early 1960s.

In 1962, the [[BBC]] commissioned a pilot for a television series of satirical sketches based on the Establishment Club, but it was not immediately picked up and Cook went to [[New York City]] for a year to perform ''Beyond The Fringe'' on Broadway. When he returned, the pilot had been refashioned as ''[[That Was the Week That Was]]'' and had made a star of [[David Frost]], something Cook resented. 

The 1960s [[satire boom]] was coming to an end and Cook said: "England was about to sink giggling into the sea".&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|url=https://books.google.com/books?ei=4yE3UtuvCIKthQfny4CgAw&amp;id=cBs-AQAAIAAJ&amp;dq=sea+under+the+own+giggling+%22peter+cook%22+-wikipedia&amp;q=sink+giggling#search_anchor |title=The Spectator, Volume 211 |year=1963|accessdate=16 September 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt; He complained that Frost's success was based on copying Cook's own stage persona and Cook dubbed him "the bubonic plagiarist",&lt;ref name="Hattenstone"&gt;Simon Hattenstone [https://www.theguardian.com/theguardian/2011/jul/02/david-frost-interview-frost-nixon "The Saturday interview: David Frost"], ''The Guardian'', 2 July 2011&lt;/ref&gt; and said that his only regret in life, according to [[Alan Bennett]], had been saving Frost from drowning. This incident occurred in the summer of 1963, when the rivalry between the two men was at its height. Cook had realised that Frost's potential drowning would have looked deliberate if he had not been rescued.&lt;ref&gt;Humphrey Carpenter ''That Was Satire That Was: The Satire Boom of the 1960s'', London: Victor Gollancz, 2000, pp. 270–71.&lt;/ref&gt;

Around this time, Cook provided financial backing for the satirical magazine ''[[Private Eye]]'', supporting it through difficult periods, particularly in [[libel]] trials. Cook invested his own money and solicited investment from his friends. For a time, the magazine was produced from the premises of the Establishment Club. In 1963, Cook married Wendy Snowden; the couple had two daughters, Lucy and Daisy, but the marriage ended in 1970.

Cook's first regular television spot was on [[Granada Television]]'s ''Braden Beat'' with [[Bernard Braden]], where he featured his most enduring character: the static, dour and monotonal [[E. L. Wisty]], whom Cook had conceived for Radley College's Marionette Society.

[[File:Dudley Moore Peter Cook Kraft Music Hall.JPG|thumb|left|upright|Cook and Dudley Moore in London for the US television programme, ''[[Kraft Music Hall]]'']]

Cook's [[Double act|comedy partnership]] with Dudley Moore led to ''[[Not Only... But Also]]''. This was originally intended by the BBC as a vehicle for Moore's music, but Moore invited Cook to write sketches and appear with him. Using few props, they created dry, absurd television that proved hugely popular and lasted for three series between 1965 and 1970. Cook played characters such as [[Sir Arthur Streeb-Greebling]] and the two men created their [[Pete and Dud]] alter egos. Other sketches included "Superthunderstingcar", a parody of the [[Gerry Anderson]] marionette TV shows, and Cook's pastiche of 1960s trendy arts documentaries – satirised in a parodic segment on [[Greta Garbo]].

When Cook learned a few years later that the videotapes of the series were to be [[Wiping|wiped]], a common practice at the time, he offered to buy the recordings from the BBC but was refused because of copyright issues. He suggested he could purchase new tapes so that the BBC would have no need to erase the originals, but this was also turned down. Of the original 22 programmes, only eight still survive complete. A compilation of six half-hour programmes, ''The Best of What's Left of Not Only...But Also'' was shown on television and has been released on both VHS and DVD.

With ''[[The Wrong Box]]'' (1966) and ''[[Bedazzled (1967 film)|Bedazzled]]'' (1967) Cook and Moore began to act in films together. Directed by [[Stanley Donen]], the underlying story of ''Bedazzled'' is credited to Cook and Moore and its screenplay to Cook. A comic parody of [[Faust]], it stars Cook as George Spigott (the [[Devil]]) who tempts Stanley Moon (Moore), a frustrated, short-order chef, with the promise of gaining his heart's desire – the unattainable beauty and waitress at his cafe, Margaret Spencer ([[Eleanor Bron]]) – in exchange for his soul, but repeatedly tricks him. The film features cameo appearances by [[Barry Humphries]] as Envy and [[Raquel Welch]] as Lust. Moore composed the soundtrack music and co-wrote (with Cook) the songs performed in the film. His jazz trio backed Cook on the theme, a parodic anti-love song, which Cook delivered in a deadpan monotone and included his familiar put-down, "you fill me with inertia."

In 1968, Cook and Moore briefly switched to [[Associated TeleVision|ATV]] for four one-hour programmes titled ''[[Goodbye Again (TV)|Goodbye Again]]'', based on the Pete and Dud characters. Cook's increasing alcoholism led him to become reliant on cue cards and the show was not a popular success, owing in part to the publication of the ITV [[listings magazine]], ''[[TV Times]]'', being suspended because of a strike. [[John Cleese]] was a cast member.

===1970s===
[[File:Good Evening Dudley Moore Peter Cook 1975.JPG|thumb|Cook (right) and [[Dudley Moore|Moore]] performing in the revue ''Good Evening'' on Broadway]]
In 1970, Cook took over a project initiated by David Frost for a satirical film about an opinion pollster who rises to become President of Great Britain. Under Cook's guidance, the character became modelled on Frost. The film, ''[[The Rise and Rise of Michael Rimmer]]'', was not a success, although the cast contained notable names (including appearances from [[Monty Python|Monty Python's]] [[John Cleese]] and [[Graham Chapman]], who co-wrote the film).

Cook became a favourite of the chat show circuit but his own effort at hosting one for the BBC in 1971, ''Where Do I Sit?'', was said by the critics to have been a disappointment. He was replaced after only two episodes by [[Michael Parkinson]], the start of Parkinson's career as a chat show host. Parkinson later asked Cook what his ambitions were, Cook replied jocularly "[...] in fact, my ambition is to shut you up altogether you see!"&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=_0_xbprZFD0 |title=Peter Cook on "Parkinson" – Part 2 |publisher=YouTube |accessdate=16 September 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Cook and Moore fashioned sketches from ''Not Only....But Also'' and ''Goodbye Again'' with new material into the stage revue called ''Behind the Fridge''. This show toured Australia in 1972 before transferring to New York City in 1973, re-titled as ''Good Evening''. Cook frequently appeared on and off stage the worse for drink. Nonetheless, the show proved very popular and it won [[Tony Award|Tony]] and [[Grammy Award]]s. When it finished, Moore stayed in the United States to pursue his film acting ambitions in Hollywood. Cook returned to Britain and in 1973 married the actress and model [[Judy Huxtable]].

Later, the more risqué humour of Pete and Dud went farther on [[gramophone record|long-playing records]] as "[[Derek and Clive]]". The first recording was initiated by Cook to alleviate boredom during the Broadway run of ''Good Evening'' and used material conceived years before for the two characters but considered too outrageous. One of these audio recordings was also filmed and tensions between the duo are seen to rise. [[Chris Blackwell]] circulated [[Bootleg recording|bootleg]] copies to friends in the music business. The popularity of the recording convinced Cook to release it commercially, although Moore was initially reluctant, fearing that his rising fame as a Hollywood star would be undermined. Two further ''Derek and Clive'' albums were released, the last accompanied by a film.

Cook and Moore hosted ''[[Saturday Night Live]]'' on 24 January 1976 during the show's first season. They did a number of their classic stage routines, including "[[One Leg Too Few]]" and "Frog and Peach" among others, in addition to participating in some skits with the show's ensemble cast.

In 1978, Cook appeared on the British music series ''[[Revolver (TV series)|Revolver]]'' as the manager of a ballroom where emerging punk and new wave acts played. For some groups, these were their first appearances on television. Cook's acerbic commentary was a distinctive aspect of the programme.

In 1979, Cook recorded comedy-segments as B-sides to the [[Sparks (band)|Sparks]] 12-inch singles "Number One in Heaven" and "Tryouts for the Human Race". The main songwriter [[Ron Mael]] often began with a banal situation in his lyrics, and then went at surreal tangents in the style of Cook and [[S. J. Perelman]].

===''Consequences'' album===
Cook played multiple roles on the 1977 [[concept album]] ''[[Consequences (Godley &amp; Creme album)|Consequences]]'', written and produced by former [[10cc]] members [[Kevin Godley]] and [[Lol Creme]]. A mixture of spoken comedy and [[progressive rock]] with an environmental subtext, ''Consequences'' started as a single that Godley and Creme planned to make to demonstrate their invention, an electric guitar effect called [[the Gizmo]], which they developed in 10cc. The project grew into a triple LP boxed set. The comedy sections were originally intended to be performed by a cast including [[Spike Milligan]] and [[Peter Ustinov]], but Godley and Creme eventually settled on Cook once they realised he could perform most parts himself.

The storyline centres on the impending divorce of ineffectual Englishman Walter Stapleton (Cook) and his French wife Lulu ([[Judy Huxtable]]). While meeting their lawyers – the bibulous Mr. Haig and overbearing Mr. Pepperman (both played by Cook) – the encroaching global catastrophe interrupts proceedings with bizarre and mysterious happenings, which seem to centre on Mr. Blint (Cook), a musician and composer living in the flat below Haig's office, to which it is connected by a large hole in the floor.

Although it has since developed a cult following due to Cook's presence, ''Consequences'' was released as [[Punk rock|punk]] was sweeping the UK and proved a resounding commercial failure, savaged by critics who found the music self-indulgent. The script and story have evident connections to Cook's own life – his then wife Judy Huxtable plays Walter's wife. Cook's struggles with alcohol are mirrored in Haig's drinking, and there is a parallel between the fictional divorce of Walter and Lulu and Cook's own divorce from his first wife. The voice and accent Cook used for the character of Stapleton are similar to those of Cook's ''[[Beyond the Fringe]]'' colleague, Alan Bennett, and a book on Cook's comedy, ''How Very Interesting'', speculates that the characters Cook plays in ''Consequences'' are caricatures of the four ''Beyond The Fringe'' cast members – the alcoholic Haig represents Cook, the tremulous Stapleton is Bennett, the parodically Jewish Pepperman is Miller, and the pianist Blint represents Moore.&lt;ref&gt;Peter Gordon, Dan Kieran Paul Hamilton (eds) – ''How Very Interesting: Peter Cook's Universe and All That Surrounds It'' (Matrix Media Services, 2006)&lt;/ref&gt;

===Amnesty International performances===
Cook appeared at the first three fund-raising galas staged by humourists [[John Cleese]] and [[Martin Lewis (humorist)|Martin Lewis]] on behalf of [[Amnesty International]]. The benefits were dubbed ''[[The Secret Policeman's Balls]]'' though it wasn't until the third show in 1979 that the title was used. He performed on all three nights of the first show in April 1976, ''[[A Poke in the Eye (With a Sharp Stick)]]'', as an individual performer and as a member of the cast of ''Beyond the Fringe'', which reunited for the first time since the 1960s. He also appeared in a [[Monty Python]] sketch, taking the place of [[Eric Idle]]. Cook was on the cast album of the show and in the film, ''[[Pleasure at Her Majesty's]]''. He was in the second Amnesty gala in May 1977, ''An Evening Without Sir Bernard Miles''. It was retitled ''The Mermaid Frolics'' for the cast album and TV special. Cook performed monologues and skits with [[Terry Jones]].

In June 1979, Cook performed all four nights of ''[[The Secret Policeman's Ball (1979)|The Secret Policeman's Ball]]'' – teaming with [[John Cleese]]. Cook performed a couple of solo pieces and a sketch with [[Eleanor Bron]]. He also led the ensemble in the finale – the "End of the World" sketch from ''Beyond The Fringe''.

In response to a barb in ''[[The Daily Telegraph]]'' that the show was recycled material, Cook wrote a satire of the summing-up by [[Mr Justice Cantley]] in the trial of former Liberal Party leader [[Jeremy Thorpe]], a summary now widely thought to show bias in favour of Thorpe. Cook performed it that same night (Friday 29 June – the third of the four nights) and the following night. The nine-minute opus, "Entirely a Matter for You", is considered by many fans and critics to be one of the finest works of Cook's career. Cook and show producer [[Martin Lewis (humorist)|Martin Lewis]] brought out an album on [[Virgin Records]] entitled ''Here Comes the Judge: Live'' of the live performance together with three studio tracks that further lampooned the Thorpe trial.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.phespirit.info/pictures/heroes/p008_info.htm |title=Peter Cook |publisher=Phespirit.info |accessdate=25 July 2009 |deadurl=yes |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20100113163211/http://www.phespirit.info/pictures/heroes/p008_info.htm |archivedate=13 January 2010 |df=dmy-all }}&lt;/ref&gt;

Although unable to take part in the 1981 gala, Cook supplied the narration over the animated opening title sequence of the 1982 film of the show. With Lewis, he wrote and voiced radio commercials to advertise the film in the UK. He also hosted a spoof film awards ceremony that was part of the world première of the film in London in March 1982.

Following Cook's 1987 stage reunion with Moore for the annual American benefit for the homeless, ''[[Comic Relief USA|Comic Relief]]'' (not related to the UK ''[[Comic Relief]]'' benefits), Cook repeated the reunion for a British audience by performing with Moore at the 1989 Amnesty benefit ''The Secret Policeman's Biggest Ball''.

===1980s===
In 1980, partly spurred by Moore's growing film star status, Cook moved to Hollywood and appeared as an uptight English butler to a wealthy American woman in a short-lived United States television sitcom, ''[[The Two of Us (1981 TV series)|The Two of Us]]'', also making cameo appearances in a couple of undistinguished films. In 1980, Cook starred in the [[LWT]] special ''Peter Cook &amp; Co.'' The show included comedy sketches, including a ''[[Tales of the Unexpected (TV series)|Tales of the Unexpected]]'' parody "Tales of the Much As We Expected." This involved Cook as [[Roald Dahl]], explaining his name had been Ronald before he dropped the "n." The cast included John Cleese, [[Rowan Atkinson]], [[Beryl Reid]], [[Paula Wilcox]] and [[Terry Jones]].

In 1983 Cook played the role of [[Richard III of England|Richard III]] in the first episode of ''[[The Black Adder|Blackadder]]'', "[[The Foretelling]]," which parodies [[Laurence Olivier]]'s portrayal. He narrated the short film "Diplomatix" by Norwegian comedy trio [[Trond Kirkvaag|Kirkvaag]], [[Knut Lystad|Lystad]] and [[Lars Mjøen|Mjøen]], which won the "Special Prize of the City of Montreux" at the Montreux Comedy Festival in 1985. In 1986 he partnered [[Joan Rivers]] on her UK talk show. He appeared as Mr Jolly in 1987 in ''[[The Comic Strip Presents]]''' episode "[[Mr. Jolly Lives Next Door]]," playing an assassin who covers the sound of his murders by playing [[Tom Jones (singer)|Tom Jones]] records. That same year, Cook made a big splash on American shores when he appeared in ''[[The Princess Bride (film)|The Princess Bride]]'' as the "Impressive Clergyman" who officiates the wedding ceremony between Buttercup and Prince Humperdinck, uttering the now famous line "Mawage!" Also that year he spent time working with [[Martin Lewis (humorist)|Martin Lewis]] on a political satire about the [[U.S. presidential election, 1988|1988 US presidential elections]] for [[HBO]], but the script went unproduced. Lewis suggested Cook team with Moore for the US ''[[Comic Relief]]'' telethon for the homeless. The duo reunited and performed their "One Leg Too Few" sketch.

In 1988, Cook appeared as a contestant on the improvisation comedy show ''[[Whose Line Is It Anyway? (UK TV series)|Whose Line Is It Anyway?]]'' Cook was declared the winner, his prize being to read the credits in the style of a New York cab driver – a character he had portrayed in ''Peter Cook &amp; Co.''

Cook occasionally called in to [[Clive Bull]]'s night-time phone-in radio show on [[LBC]] in London. Using the name "Sven from Swiss Cottage," he mused on love, loneliness and herrings in a mock Norwegian accent. Jokes included Sven's attempts to find his estranged wife, in which he often claimed to be telephoning the show from all over the world, and his hatred of the Norwegian obsession with fish. While Bull was clearly aware that Sven was fictional he did not learn of his real identity until later.

===Revival===
In late 1989, Cook married for the third time, to [[Malaysia]]n-born property developer Chiew Lin Chong (1945–2016) in [[Torbay]], [[Devon]]. She provided him with some stability in his personal life and he reduced his drinking, to the extent that for a time he was [[Teetotalism|teetotal]]. He lived alone in a small 18th-century house in Perrins Walk,&lt;!-- 51.554931, -0.178945 --&gt; [[Hampstead]], while his wife kept her own property only 100 yards away.

Cook returned to the BBC as Sir Arthur Streeb-Greebling for an appearance with [[Ludovic Kennedy]] in ''A Life in Pieces''. The 12 interviews saw Sir Arthur recount his life based on the [[Twelve Days of Christmas]]. Unscripted interviews with Cook as Streeb-Greebling and satirist [[Chris Morris (satirist)|Chris Morris]] were recorded in late 1993 and broadcast as ''[[Why Bother? (radio show)|Why Bother?]]'' on [[BBC Radio 3]]. Morris described them:{{quote|It was a very different style of improvisation from what I'd been used to, working with people like [[Steve Coogan]], [[Doon Mackichan]] and [[Rebecca Front]], because those ''[[On the Hour]]'' and ''[[The Day Today]]'' things were about trying to establish a character within a situation, and Peter Cook was really doing 'knight's move' and 'double knight's move' thinking to construct jokes or ridiculous scenes flipping back on themselves, and it was amazing. I mean, I held out no great hopes that he wouldn't be a boozy old sack of lard with his hair falling out and scarcely able to get a sentence out, because he hadn't given much evidence that that wouldn't be the case. But, in fact, he stumbled in with a Safeways bag full of Kestrel lager and loads of fags and then proceeded to skip about mentally with the agility of a grasshopper. Really quite extraordinary.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://stabbers.truth.posiweb.net/stabbers/html/spiggott/morris.htm |title=The Establishment – The Spiggott – Chris Morris Interview |publisher=Stabbers.truth.posiweb.net |accessdate=25 July 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt;}}

On 17 December 1993, Cook appeared on ''[[Clive Anderson|Clive Anderson Talks Back]]'' as four characters – biscuit tester and alien abductee Norman House, football manager and motivational speaker Alan Latchley, judge Sir James Beauchamp and rock legend Eric Daley. The following day he appeared on [[BBC Two|BBC2]] performing links for ''[[Arena (UK TV series)|Arena]]'''s "Radio Night". He also appeared, on 26 December, in the 1993 Christmas special of ''[[One Foot in the Grave]]'' ("One Foot in the Algarve"), playing a muckraking [[paparazzi|tabloid photographer]]. Before the end of the next year his mother died, and a grief-stricken Cook returned to heavy drinking. He made his last TV appearance on the show ''[[Pebble Mill at One]]'' in November 1994.

==Personal life and death==
Cook was married three times; he was first married to Wendy Showden in 1963, they divorced on 1971 after eight years of marriage.&lt;ref&gt;https://www.theguardian.com/uk/2002/dec/08/arts.books&lt;/ref&gt; Cook then married his second wife, actress [[Judy Huxtable]] in 1973, they divorced in 1989 after sixteen years of marriage.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.theguardian.com/uk/2002/dec/08/arts.books|title=Wife's grief for wasted genius of Peter Cook|first1=Vanessa|last1=Thorpe|first2=|last2=arts|first3=media|last3=correspondent|date=8 December 2002|publisher=|accessdate=26 October 2017|via=www.theguardian.com}}&lt;/ref&gt; He then married his third and final wife Lin Chong in 1989, they remained married until his death in 1995.&lt;ref&gt;https://www.chortle.co.uk/news/2016/11/30/26338/peter_cooks_widow_lin_dies_at_71&lt;/ref&gt; Chong died at the age of 71 in November 2016.&lt;ref&gt;https://www.chortle.co.uk/news/2016/11/30/26338/peter_cooks_widow_lin_dies_at_71&lt;/ref&gt;

Cook died from a [[gastrointestinal bleeding|gastrointestinal hemorrhage]]&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Wife's grief for wasted genius of Peter Cook|url=https://www.theguardian.com/uk/2002/dec/08/arts.books}}&lt;/ref&gt; on 9 January 1995, aged 57. His body was cremated at [[Golders Green Crematorium]] and his ashes were buried in an unmarked plot behind [[St John-at-Hampstead]], not far from his home in Perrins Walk.

Dudley Moore attended Cook's memorial service at St John-at-Hampstead on 1 May 1995.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.independent.co.uk/news/goodbyee-dud-bids-poignant-farewell-to-his-partner-pete-1617816.html|title=Goodbyee . . . Dud bids poignant farewell to his partner Pete|date=2 May 1995|publisher=|accessdate=12 October 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt; He and [[Martin Lewis (humorist)|Martin Lewis]] presented a two-night memorial for Cook at [[The Improv]] in Los Angeles, on 15 and 16 November 1995, to mark what would have been Cook's 58th birthday.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.dailyllama.com/news/1995/llama014.html|title=Daily Llama – NEWS 1995_12_21 – Celebration Recently Held to Honor Deceased Peter Cook|website=www.dailyllama.com|accessdate=12 October 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Legacy==
[[File:Peter Cook (3985376490).jpg|thumb|right|Cook's [[Blue plaque|green plaque]] in [[Westminster]], [[London]]]]

Cook is widely acknowledged as a strong influence on the many British comedians who followed him from the amateur dramatic clubs of British universities to the [[Edinburgh Festival Fringe]], and then to radio and television. On his death some critics choose to see Cook's life as tragic, insofar as the brilliance of his youth had not been sustained in his later years. However, Cook himself always maintained he had no ambitions at all for sustained success. He assessed happiness by his friendships and his enjoyment of life. [[Eric Idle]] and [[Stephen Fry]] said Cook had not wasted his talent but rather that the newspapers had tried to waste him.{{citation needed|date=May 2017}}

Several friends honoured him with a dedication in the closing credits of ''[[Fierce Creatures]]'' (1997), a comedy film written by [[John Cleese]] about a zoo in peril of being closed. It starred Cleese, [[Jamie Lee Curtis]], [[Kevin Kline]] and [[Michael Palin]]. The dedication displays photos and the lifespan dates of Cook and of British naturalist and humourist [[Gerald Durrell]].

In 1999 the [[minor planet]] [[20468 Petercook]], in the main asteroid belt, was named after Cook.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|author=Alan Chamberlin |url=http://ssd.jpl.nasa.gov/sbdb.cgi?sstr=20468 |title=Minor planet "20468 Petercook" at NASA website |publisher=Ssd.jpl.nasa.gov |accessdate=15 May 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Channel 4 broadcast ''[[Not Only But Always]]'', a television film dramatising the relationship between Cook and Moore, with [[Rhys Ifans]] portraying Cook. At the [[2005 Edinburgh Festival Fringe]] a play, ''[[Pete and Dud: Come Again]]'' written by [[Chris Bartlett (writer)|Chris Bartlett]] and [[Nick Awde]], examined the relationship from Moore's view. The play was transferred to London's West End at The Venue in 2006 and toured the UK the following year. [[Tom Goodman-Hill]] starred as Cook and [[Kevin Bishop]] as Moore in the West End.

A green plaque was unveiled by the [[Westminster City Council]] and the Heritage Foundation at the site of the Establishment Club on 15 February 2009 after an online campaign by satirist / event Organiser Mark Biddiss, who also organised "The World's 1st Peter Cook is dead Birthday Party/Long overdue Public Wake" at the site of the Establishment Club to promote the plaque, which featured a live reworking of 'Derek &amp; Clive' material titled "Derek &amp; Clive are Alive again".&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.theheritagefoundation.info/petercook.html|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20100225144043/http://www.theheritagefoundation.info/petercook.html|dead-url=yes|archive-date=25 February 2010|title=Peter Cook Blue Plaque Unveiling|work=The Heritage Foundation|accessdate=27 March 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt;

A historic blue plaque was unveiled by the Torbay Civic Society on 17 November 2014 at Cook's place of birth, "Shearbridge",  Middle Warberry Road, Torquay, with his widow Lin and other members of the family in attendance. A further blue plaque was commissioned and erected at the home of Torquay United, Plainmoor, Torquay, in 2015.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.torquayheraldexpress.co.uk/Comedian-Peter-Cook-honoured-blue-plaque/story-24545932-detail/story.htm{{dead link|date=April 2017 |bot=InternetArchiveBot |fix-attempted=yes }}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Filmography==
*''[[Bachelor of Hearts]]'' (1958) – Pedestrian in Street (uncredited)
*''[[Ten Thousand Talents]]'' Short Film (1960) (voice)
*''[[What's Going on Here]]'' TV Movie (1963) 
*''[[The Wrong Box]]'' (1966) – Morris Finsbury
*''[[Alice in Wonderland (1966 TV play)|Alice in Wonderland]]'' (1966) – Mad Hatter
*''[[Bedazzled (1967 film)|Bedazzled]]'' (1967) – George Spiggott / The Devil
*''[[A Dandy in Aspic]]'' (1968) – Prentiss
*''[[Monte Carlo or Bust!]]'' (released in the US as ''Those Daring Young Men in Their Jaunty Jalopies'') (1969) – Maj. Digby Dawlish
*''[[The Bed Sitting Room (film)|The Bed Sitting Room]]'' (1969) – Inspector
*''[[The Rise and Rise of Michael Rimmer]]'' (1970) – Michael Rimmer
*''[[Behind the Fridge]]'' TV Movie (1971) – Various Characters
*''[[An Apple a Day]]'' TV Movie (1971) – Mr Elwood Sr.
*''[[The Adventures of Barry McKenzie]]'' (1972) – Dominic
*''Saturday Night at the Baths'' (1975) – Himself – in theater audience (uncredited)
*''[[Find the Lady (1976 film)|Find the Lady]]'' (1976) – Lewenhak
*''[[Eric Sykes Shows a Few of Our Favourite Things]]'' TV Movie (1977) – Stagehand
*''[[The Hound of the Baskervilles (1978 film)|The Hound of the Baskervilles]]'' (1978) – Sherlock Holmes
*''[[Derek and Clive Get the Horn]]'' (1979) – Clive
*''[[Peter Cook &amp; Co]]'' TV Movie (1980) – Various Characters
*''[[Yellowbeard]]'' (1983) – Lord Percy Lambourn
*''[[Supergirl (1984 film)|Supergirl]]'' (1984) – [[Nigel]]
*''[[Kenny Everett's Christmas Carol]]'' TV Movie (1985) – Ghost of Christmas Yet To Come
*''The Myth'' (1986) – Himself
*''[[The Princess Bride (film)|The Princess Bride]]'' (1987) – The Impressive Clergyman
*''[[Whoops Apocalypse (film)|Whoops Apocalypse]]'' (1988) – Sir Mortimer Chris
*''[[Without a Clue]]'' (1988) – Norman Greenhough
*''[[Getting It Right (film)|Getting It Right]]'' (1989) – Mr. Adrian
*''[[Jake's Journey]]'' TV Movie (1988) – King
*''[[Great Balls of Fire! (film)|Great Balls of Fire!]]'' (1989) – First English Reporter
*''[[The Craig Ferguson Story]]'' TV Movie (1991) – Fergus Ferguson 
*''[[One Foot in the Algarve]]'' (1993 film) – Martin Trout
*''[[Black Beauty (1994 film)|Black Beauty]]'' (1994) – Lord Wexmire (final film role)
*''[[Peter Cook Talks Golf Balls]]'' (Video 1994) – Plays 4 characters Alec Dunroonie / Dr Dieter Liedbetter / Major Titherly Glibble / Bill Rossi

==TV Series==
*''[[Chronicle (UK TV series)]]'' TV Series (1964) – (1 episode)
*''[[A Series of Bird's]]'' TV Series (1967) – (1 episode)
*''[[Not Only... But Also]]'' TV Series (1965–1970)  Various Characters (22 episodes)
*''[[Not Only But Also. Peter Cook and Dudley Moore in Australia]]'' TV Mini Series (1971) 
*''[[Thirty-Minute Theatre]]'' (1972) – Peter Trilby (1 episode)
*''[[The Two of Us (1981 TV series)|The Two of Us]]'' TV Series 1981 – 1982) – Robert Brentwood (20 episodes)
*''[[The Black Adder]]'' TV Series (1983) Richard III (1 episode)
*''[[Diplomatix]]'' TV Short (1985) – Narrator  (voice)
*''[[The Comic Strip Presents...]]'' (1988) – Mr Jolly (1 episode)
*''[[The Best of... What's Left of... Not Only... But Also]]'' (1990) – Pete / Himself / other characters (1 episode)
*''[[A Life in Pieces]]'' (TV Series Short 1990) – Sir Arthur Streeb-Greebling (12 episodes)
*''[[Roger Mellie: The Man on the Telly]]'' (1991) – Roger Mellie (voice) 
*''[[Gone to Seed]]'' (1992) – Wesley Willis – (6 episodes)
*''[[Arena]]'' (1993) – (documentary) (2 episodes)

''[[Amnesty International]] Performances:''

*''[[Pleasure at Her Majesty's]]'' (1976)
*''[[The Secret Policeman's Ball#1977 - The Mermaid Frolics|The Mermaid Frolics]]'' (1977)
*''[[The Secret Policeman's Ball (1979)|The Secret Policeman's Ball]]'' (1979)
*''The Secret Policeman's Private Parts'' (1981)
*''The Best of Amnesty: Featuring the Stars of Monty Python'' (1999)

==Discography==
[[UK Singles Chart|UK]] chart singles:
*"The Ballad of Spotty Muldoon" (1965)
*"Goodbye-ee" (1965) (both with Dudley Moore)&lt;ref name="British Hit Singles &amp; Albums"&gt;{{cite book
| first= David
| last= Roberts
| year= 2006
| title= [[British Hit Singles &amp; Albums]]
| edition= 19th
| publisher= Guinness World Records Limited
| location= London
| isbn= 1-904994-10-5
| page= 119}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Albums:
* ''[[Bridge on the River Wye]]'' (1962)
* ''[[The Misty Mr. Wisty]]'' (1965) Decca LK 4722
* ''[[Derek and Clive (Live)]]'' (with Dudley Moore) (1976)
* ''[[Derek and Clive Come Again]]'' (with Dudley Moore) (1977)
* ''[[Derek and Clive Ad Nauseam]]'' (with Dudley Moore) (1978)

==References==
{{Reflist|30em}}

==Further reading==
*{{cite book | author=Harry Thompson | title=Peter Cook: A Biography| publisher=Hodder &amp; Stoughton | year=1998 | isbn= 0-340-64969-0 }}
*{{cite book | author=John Lawton | title=1963: 500 Days | publisher=Hodder &amp; Stoughton | year=1992 | isbn= 0340508469 }}
*{{cite book | author=Peter Cook and Dudley Moore | title=Dud and Pete: The Dagenham Dialogues | publisher=Methuen | year=2003 | isbn=978-0-413-77347-0 }}
*{{cite book | author=Robert Hewison | title=Footlights!: A Hundred Years of Cambridge Comedy| publisher=Methuen London Ltd | year=1983 | isbn= 0-413-51150-2 }}
*{{cite book | author=Roger Wilmut | title=From Fringe to Flying Circus: Celebrating a Unique Generation of Comedy 1960–1980 | publisher=Eyre Methuen Ltd | year=1980 | isbn=0-413-46950-6 }}
*{{cite book | author=Peter Cook Appreciation Society | title=How Very Interesting!: Peter Cook's Universe And All That Surrounds It | publisher=Snowbooks | year=2006 | isbn=1-905005-23-7 }}
*{{cite book | author=Alexander Games| title=Pete &amp; Dud: An Illustrated Biography| publisher=Andre Deutsch| year=1999 | isbn=0-233-99642-7 }}
*{{cite book | author=Wendy Cook | title=So Farewell Then: The Biography of Peter Cook| publisher=HarperCollins Entertainment | year=2006 | isbn= 0-00-722893-7 }}
*{{cite book | author=Lin Cook | title=Something Like Fire: Peter Cook Remembered | publisher=Arrow Books | year=2003 | isbn=0-09-946035-1 }}
*{{cite book | author=Chris Bartlett and Nick Awde | title=Pete and Dud: Come Again|publisher=Methuen Drama | year=2006 | isbn=0-413-77602-6 }}
*{{cite book | author=William Cook (editor)| title=Tragically I Was an Only Twin: The Complete Peter Cook| publisher=Century and St. Martin's Press |orig-year=First published 2002|location=United Kingdom | isbn=978-0-312-31891-8 }}
*{{cite book | author=Judy Cook with Angela Levin| title=Loving Peter: My Life with Peter Cook and Dudley Moore| publisher=Piatkus | year=2008 | isbn=978-0-7499-0966-6 }}
*Richard Mills, (2010). Pop half-cocked: a history of "Revolver". In Inglis, Ian, (ed). Popular Music and Television in Britain. Ashgate, Farnham, pp. 149 - 160. {{ISBN|9780754668640}}

*{{cite book | author=William Cook | title=One Leg Too Few: The Adventures of Peter Cook and Dudley Moore | publisher=Arrow | year=2014 | isbn=978-0099559924 }}

==External links==
{{commons category|Peter Cook (actor)}}
{{Wikiquote}}
*{{IMDb name|00177228}}
*[http://stabbers.truth.posiweb.net/stabbers/index.htm The Establishment]
*[http://www.bobclaster.com Lengthy 1988 KCRW radio interview in 3 parts "Bob Claster's Funny Stuff" including many excerpts.]
*[http://www.suppertime.co.uk/blint/ Mr Blint's Attic]
*[https://web.archive.org/web/20110606125944/http://larvatus.livejournal.com/66328.html Tribute to Peter Cook, with texts and commentary]
*[http://www.lunaestas.com/petercook/ Good Evening], a Peter Cook Fansite incl. Gallery
*[http://www.bbc.co.uk/comedy/guide/articles/n/notonlybutalso_7774870.shtml The BBC Guide to Comedy: Not Only...But Also]
*[http://missing-episodes.com/ Missing-Episodes.com]
*[http://mm.iit.uni-miskolc.hu/Lart/monty/oneleg.html One Leg Too Few], script for one of Cook and Moore's most famous and oft-performed sketches.

{{Private Eye}}
{{Grammy Award for Best Spoken Word Album 1970s}}
{{Authority control}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Cook, Peter}}
[[Category:20th-century English male actors]]
[[Category:1937 births]]
[[Category:1995 deaths]]
[[Category:Alumni of Pembroke College, Cambridge]]
[[Category:Comedians from Devon]]
[[Category:Deaths from liver disease]]
[[Category:English male comedians]]
[[Category:English male film actors]]
[[Category:English male television actors]]
[[Category:English satirists]]
[[Category:English television writers]]
[[Category:Grammy Award winners]]
[[Category:Male actors from Devon]]
[[Category:People educated at Radley College]]
[[Category:People from Torquay]]
[[Category:Private Eye contributors]]
[[Category:English male writers]]
[[Category:Male screenwriters]]
[[Category:English social commentators]]
[[Category:Decca Records artists]]</text>
      <sha1>25ajm7susqq5u598754y23i0rihjwx4</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
