<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10.xsd" version="0.10" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <dbname>enwiki</dbname>
    <base>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.32.0-wmf.16</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="118" case="first-letter">Draft</namespace>
      <namespace key="119" case="first-letter">Draft talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2300" case="first-letter">Gadget</namespace>
      <namespace key="2301" case="first-letter">Gadget talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2302" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition</namespace>
      <namespace key="2303" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Sugar Sammy</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>11866022</id>
    <revision>
      <id>855106851</id>
      <parentid>854818130</parentid>
      <timestamp>2018-08-16T00:27:23Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Bus stop</username>
        <id>2299668</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>/* Appearances */ not sure if this is right but it is my best guess at what is supposed to be there</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="32542">{{Use mdy dates|date=January 2014}}
{{Infobox comedian
| name = Sugar Sammy
| image = 
| imagesize = 300px
| birth_name = Samir Khullar
| birth_place = [[Montreal]], [[Quebec]], Canada
| birth_date = {{Birth date and age|1976|2|29|mf=yes}}
| genre = [[Observational comedy]], [[improvisational comedy]]
| subject = [[race (classification of human beings)|Race]], sex, [[popular culture|pop culture]]
| influences = [[Dave Chappelle]], [[Eddie Murphy]], [[Chris Rock]], [[Don Rickles]]&lt;ref name="AXP" /&gt;
| medium            = Comedy, television
| nationality    =  [[Canadian]]
| website = [http://www.sugarsammy.com/ www.sugarsammy.com]
}}

'''Samir Khullar''', better known as '''Sugar Sammy''', is a Canadian comedian, actor, writer and producer from [[Montreal]], Quebec, Canada. His comedy routines are delivered in a mixture of  fluent English, French, [[Punjabi language|Punjabi]] and [[Hindi]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.straight.com/article-126902/slick-savvy-stand-up-sugar-sammy-takes-on-the-world|title=Slick, savvy stand-up Sugar Sammy takes on the world|last=MacPherson|date=January 3, 2008|first=Guy|publisher=Straight.com|accessdate=}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Early life==
Samir Khullar was born February 29, 1976 and raised in the Côte-des-Neiges neighbourhood of Montreal, Quebec; he worked in his parents;' convenience store.&lt;ref name="nytimes.com"&gt;https://www.nytimes.com/2018/08/11/world/americas/quebec-sugar-sammy-comedian.html&lt;/ref&gt; At the age of eight he saw [[Eddie Murphy]]'s 1983 comedy special ''[[Eddie Murphy Delirious|Delirious]]'',&lt;ref name="SAP"&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.southasianpost.com/portal2/c1ee8c44187ff6c001188199dc0800ca_Sugar_Sammy_returns_at_Lafflines.do.html |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20080319001122/http://www.southasianpost.com/portal2/c1ee8c44187ff6c001188199dc0800ca_Sugar_Sammy_returns_at_Lafflines.do.html |archivedate=March 19, 2008|title=Sugar Sammy returns for encore performance|last=Durai|date=March 6, 2008|first=Melvin|publisher=South Asian Post|accessdate=}}&lt;/ref&gt; and credits the experience as being a defining moment in his life. From then on, he knew what he wanted to do.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=https://www.theglobeandmail.com/servlet/story/RTGAM.20090204.wsammy0205/BNStory/Entertainment |title=How sweet it is for Sugar Sammy |last=Posner |first=Michael |publisher=The Globe and Mail |accessdate= |location=Toronto |deadurl=yes |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20090208144329/http://www.theglobeandmail.com/servlet/story/RTGAM.20090204.wsammy0205/BNStory/Entertainment |archivedate=February 8, 2009 }}&lt;/ref&gt; Khullar also names [[Martin Lawrence]], [[Chris Rock]] and [[Dave Chappelle]] as comedic influences.

After early stage experiences in high school ''École Secondaire La Voie'', Khullar attended [[Marianopolis College]] while occasionally performing at open-mic nights at the Comedy Works and the Comedy Zone.&lt;ref name="SAP" /&gt; Continuing to work for recognition on the comedy circuit, he attended [[McGill University]] in cultural studies while working as a nightclub promoter. There he received what would later become his stage name, after letting many women into parties for free.&lt;ref name="AXP"&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.asiaxpress.com/Articles/2010/mar/sugar-sammy/1.html|title=Face2Face with Sugar Sammy|last=Nguyen|first=Joe|date=March 11, 2010|publisher=AsiaXpress.com|accessdate=March 15, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Subjects==
Khullar blends polished material with improvisational comedy and interacts with audience members sitting near the stage.&lt;ref name="SAP" /&gt; ''The Hollywood Reporter'' selected him as one of their "Ten Comics to Watch".&lt;ref name="hollywoodreporter.com"&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.hollywoodreporter.com/news/sugar-sammy-signs-gersh-89217|title=Sugar Sammy signs with Gersh|author=AP|work=The Hollywood Reporter|accessdate=February 2, 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Appearances==

Khullar has performed on TV several times since 2004. He appeared at the [[Just For Laughs|Just For Laughs Festival]] seven years in a row and was the first comedian ever to perform in the English, French, and Hindi Toronto editions of the Festival.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://mtv.in.com/blogs/parent/just-in/sugar-sammy-putting-the-ha-in-haha-50194562.html|title=Sugar Sammy: Putting the HA in HAHA!|work=http://www.mtvindia.com/|accessdate=February 2, 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt; He has also appeared at the Sydney Comedy Festival, the Cape Town Comedy Festival, and was invited to the inaugural Johannesburg Comedy Festival in 2009.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://represent.co.za/jozi-comedy-festival/|title=Jozi Comedy Festival|publisher=|accessdate=February 2, 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt;

On August 21, 2006, Khullar opened for [[Dave Chappelle]] at Toronto's Massey Hall.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.nowtoronto.com/news/story.cfm?content=161846|title=Q&amp;A : Sugar Sammy|work=NOW Magazine|accessdate=February 2, 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt; In 2006, he taped his ''Comedy Now!'' special, which aired in Canada on the Comedy Network, CTV and A. It also aired on Comedy Central in the United States.

On one of the most electric nights of the 2016 edition of [[Just For Laughs Festival]], Sugar Sammy capped off his 420-show tour with one last performance of his hit show You’re Gonna Rire in front of crowd of 115,000 in Montreal.  This is how he marked his 8th presence at the festival. In July 2017, the hometown boy made his triumphant return to the Just For Laughs Festival to host 2 evenings of Sugar Sammy's International Gala.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://montrealgazette.com/entertainment/just-for-laughs-now-a-hit-in-france-sugar-sammy-is-back-briefly}}&lt;/ref&gt; In hosting a Just For Laughs gala, Sugar Sammy joined legends and comedy stars such as [[Don Rickles]], [[Steve Martin]], [[Tina Fey]], [[Jimmy Fallon]], [[Bill Maher]] and [[Bill Burr]]. Fresh from hosting two critically acclaimed sold-out Galas at the 35th edition of the Montreal International [[Just For Laughs Festival|Just For Laughs Comedy Festival]],&lt;ref&gt;http://montrealgazette.com/entertainment/sugar-sammy-heads-just-for-laughs-comedy-tour-in-october&lt;/ref&gt; Sugar Sammy went on to host the 17th edition of the Just For Laughs Canadian Comedy Tour annual comedy tour in the autumn of 2017.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.y108.ca/events/115584&lt;/ref&gt;

==International career==

Sugar Sammy has toured in the United States, Canada, France, Belgium, Switzerland, England, Australia, Germany, Ireland, the [[Netherlands]], Hong Kong, [[Thailand]], [[the Philippines]], China, [[India]], [[Bahrain]], [[Jordan]], [[Qatar]], [[Egypt]], [[Kuwait]], [[Abu Dhabi]], [[Lebanon]], Singapore, [[Malaysia]], [[Saudi Arabia]], [[Bahrain]], [[Northern Ireland]], [[Dubai]], [[Haiti]]&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.alarabiya.net/articles/2009/02/16/66594.html|work=Al Arabiya|title=Stand-up comedy takes the Arab world by storm|publisher=AlArabiya.net/English |first=Courtney |last=Radsch |date=February 16, 2009|accessdate=February 16, 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[New Zealand]] and South Africa, where his one-man show sold 15,000 tickets.&lt;ref&gt;http://web2.hahaha.com/microsite/SugarSammy/SugarSammy&lt;/ref&gt;

In the summer of 2009, [[The Gersh Agency]] signed Sugar Sammy following a strong showing at the [[Just For Laughs Festival]].&lt;ref name="hollywoodreporter.com"/&gt;

He is the first artist chosen by Comedy Central India to tour their country, visiting Mumbai, Bangalore and Delhi in March 2013 with his English/Hindi/Punjabi comedy show.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.newindianexpress.com/cities/bangalore/article1498351.ece|title=Tickling your funny bone|work=The New Indian Express|accessdate=February 2, 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Sugar Sammy's international TV credits include his own one-hour TV special on Showtime Arabia entitled, ''Sugar Sammy Live in Dubai'', which aired in 14 countries;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.meetup.com/losangeles-indians/events/16585321/|title=The Laugh Factory: Monrok, Sugar Sammy, Rajiv Satyal &amp; other Comics!!|work=Meetup|accessdate=February 2, 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt; headlining two TV shows for Showtime, ''Minority Rules'' and ''Friday Night Live''; and appearances on [[Canadian Broadcasting Corporation|CBC]], Comedy Now on [[CTV Television Network|CTV]], [[The Comedy Network]] (Canada), [[The Comedy Channel]] (Australia), and Dutch TV.

Since 2016, Sugar Sammy has been performing his ever-growing, one-man show in France, where GC magazine published a piece saying the funniest man in France is Quebecois.&lt;ref name="nytimes.com"/&gt; He has been touring the country as well as performing 3 nights a week at the Alhambra Theatre in Paris. He has added dates until December 2018. He has just been named one of the judges on "La France a un Incroyable Talent", the French equivalent of "America's Got Talent", reaching 3.5 - 4 million viewers a week.&lt;ref name="montrealgazette.com"&gt;https://montrealgazette.com/opinion/columnists/bill-brownstein-sugar-sammy-making-big-waves-on-other-continents&lt;/ref&gt;

In Spring/Summer 2017, Sugar Sammy toured the U.S.A. performing 40 shows in 7 American cities, including New York, San Jose, Seattle, Atlanta, Austin, Naples and Dallas.&lt;ref&gt;http://montrealgazette.com/entertainment/local-arts/sugar-sammy-set-to-launch-u-s-comedy-tour&lt;/ref&gt;

In July 2018, between his runs in France, Sugar Sammy set off for Malaysia, where he performed two nights of tapings for Comedy Central: Stand-Up Asia!. The tapings will air in 18 Asian countries on Aug. 14. Following the tapings, he took of for Singapore to perform his one-man show.&lt;ref name="montrealgazette.com"/&gt;

==Francophone career==
In 2007 Sugar Sammy appeared in Quebec's ''Le Show Raisonnable'', and in 2009 performed in the French edition of the Just for Laughs Festival. His point of view concerning Quebec politics and culture from the perspective of a minority earned him a standing ovation and "The Revelation of the Year" award. In 2010 he made headlines again by presenting an award alongside Quebec political leader [[Pauline Marois]]. He teased her incessantly about sovereignty and the language debate.

Sugar Sammy wanted a stronger presence in Quebec. His bilingual show ''You’re Gonna Rire'' became his first tour of Quebec in 2012.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.myvirtualpaper.com/doc/lpa-magazine/lpa_web/2011052001/32.html#32|title=La Presse Affaires Magazine - 0032|work=Virtual Paper|accessdate=February 2, 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In May 2013, Sugar Sammy became the first anglophone comedian to win at Quebec's prestigious Olivier comedy awards. He won the Olivier for Best Show (voted by the industry, for ''En français svp!'') and the Olivier for Comedian of the Year (voted by the public).&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://montreal.ctvnews.ca/sugar-sammy-picked-as-quebec-s-comedian-of-the-year-1.1279035|title=Sugar Sammy picked as Quebec's comedian of the year|work=Montreal|accessdate=February 2, 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt;  In 2014, he once again won the Olivier for Comedian of the Year at the 16th annual gala, and Apple chose him to perform in their TV ads in French Canada. In May 2015, he was nominated again, for a third year in a row, for the Olivier for Comedian of the Year.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.montrealgazette.com/entertainment/Sugar+Sammy+repeats+Olivier+year+winner/9828824/story.html&lt;/ref&gt;

During December 2014, he ran a billboard ad in the Montreal Metro stating that "For Christmas, I'd like a complaint from the [[Office québécois de la langue française|Office de la langue française]]", in reference to the Quebec government organization that forces businesses to run ads in French. After a complaint was received, the English text was blacked out and replaced by "Pour Noel, j'ai eu une plainte de l'Office de la langue française" ("For Christmas, I got a complaint from the Office de la langue française"). This marketing campaign, designed by Sid Lee, garnered much attention from Quebec media and was the center of heated debates between different linguistic communities in the province.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://bryo.ca/fr/sugar-sammy-tensions-langues-publicite-metro/|title=L'humoriste Sugar Sammy se moque des tensions linguistiques dans une nouvelle publicité - Bryo|work=Bryo|accessdate=February 2, 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Montreal comedian Sugar Sammy’s bilingual show, in the four and a half years since its debut, became a hit with little precedent, the most successful solo comedy show Montreal has ever seen, and one that catapulted its creator from merely being a successful comic to becoming a bonafide star. Through his comedy, his charisma and his evident sense of gratitude at the support he received from fans and the media for an ambitious concept that, if executed even a little bit off-key, could have become a far more polarizing endeavour, it quickly become clear this was one of those rare confluences of ideal messenger, ideal message and ideal time.&lt;ref&gt;http://montrealgazette.com/opinion/columnists/boshra-sugar-sammy-youre-gonna-rire&lt;/ref&gt; In July 2016, after setting records in the Province of Quebec- he is the comedian who's sold the most tickets to a debut one-man show in Quebec history, Sugar Sammy announced that, as the curtain comes down on all the You’re Gonna Rire madness, he’ll be heading to France in an effort to conquer that particular market.&lt;ref&gt;http://ici.radio-canada.ca/nouvelles/arts_et_spectacles/2016/07/28/005-sugar-sammy-festival-juste-pour-rire-dernier-spectacle.shtml&lt;/ref&gt;

In fall 2016, Sugar Sammy sets off for Paris and launches a new show geared specifically for a French audience. His show opened March 1, 2017 at l’Européen, in Paris. New to the French scene, Sugar Sammy quickly became one of the best selling shows in Paris.&lt;ref name="parismatch.com"&gt;http://www.parismatch.com/Culture/Spectacles/Les-impros-delirantes-de-Sugar-Sammy-1227107&lt;/ref&gt; Sugar Sammy received the top critic score, the 3Ts from Télérama.&lt;ref name="telerama.fr"&gt;http://www.telerama.fr/sortir/sugar-sammy-comment-la-star-de-l-humour-quebecois-a-conquis-la-france,156672.php&lt;/ref&gt; More shows were added in Paris until the end of December 2017. In 2018, Sugar Sammy has added more dates in the City of Lights and is also be touring the rest of France, Belgium and Switzerland.

M6 network just announced that Sugar Sammy will be one of the judges for season 13 of 'La France a un incroyable talent', the French equivalent of 'America’s Got Talent', reaching 3.5 to 4 million weekly viewers.&lt;ref name="montrealgazette.com"/&gt;

== One-man shows ==

===''Down With the Brown''===

After traveling across the globe to perform in many comedy festivals and clubs, Sugar Sammy hit the road again in 2007 to present around the world his first one-man show "Down with the Brown". He tackled everything from life in [[Quebec]] to his take on sex and race from the perspective of an Indo-Canadian. His debut comedy album followed, ''Down With the Brown''. It was released on January 15, 2008 and coincided with a Canadian tour.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.straight.com/arts/slick-savvy-stand-sugar-sammy-takes-world|title=Slick, savvy stand-up Sugar Sammy takes on the world|work=The Georgia Straight - Vancouver News and Entertainment Weekly|accessdate=February 2, 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===''Live in Concert''===
After setting attendance records around the world for sold-out shows in four languages- English, French, Punjabi and Hindi, Sugar Sammy brings the house down across Canada during February–March 2009 with his show ''Live in Concert''. He drew on everything from arranged marriages in his own Indian ancestry to his view on deviant sex, drugs and modern-day relationships. The tour ended in Montreal in March 2009. He then released the DVD ''Sugar Sammy Live in Concert: Direct from Montreal'', which was the number-one best-selling comedy DVD on Amazon.ca for five straight weeks.

=== ''You're Gonna Rire'', bilingual show, and ''En Français SVP'', French-only show  ===
In an unprecedented experiment, Sugar Sammy's ''You're Gonna Rire'' is the first large-scale Anglo-Franco comedy show in the country.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.montrealgazette.com/sports/Review+Success+doesn+breed+safety+Sugar+Sammy/6230972/story.html#ixzz1viiyiiJe&lt;/ref&gt; In 2011, he created a show in a language called Franglais, an ode to the common Montreal experience of switching between English and French throughout the day.&lt;ref&gt;http://montreal.openfile.ca/blog/curator-blog/curated-news/2012/sugar-sammys-youre-gonna-rire-makes-some-columnists-pleure&lt;/ref&gt; It was described as "50.5 per cent English, 49.5 per cent French" as a reference to the 1995 referendum results. Initially conceived as a single night at the 1,300-seat Olympia theater, tickets sold so fast that it extended to 45 performances,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://fullcomment.nationalpost.com/2012/03/01/sugar-sammy/|title=Sugar Sammy’s ‘franglais’ show has Quebecers laughing in both languages: Graeme Hamilton: - National Post|author=Graeme Hamilton|date=March 2, 2012|work=National Post|accessdate=February 2, 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt; with a total of 53,000 tickets sold by April 2013.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news| url=https://www.theglobeandmail.com/news/arts/theatre/sugar-sammy-unites-many-solitudes-with-laughter/article2358197/print/ | location=Toronto | work=The Globe and Mail | title=Sugar Sammy unites many solitudes with laughter | date=September 10, 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In 2012, the bilingual show was also transformed into a fully French-language show entitled ''En Français S.V.P.'' ("In French, Please").

Sugar Sammy continued to perform both shows in Montreal, and the French show throughout the province of Quebec. His ranked as the 30th largest-grossing tour in North America according to ''Pollstar magazine'' in May 2013.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.journaldemontreal.com/2013/05/01/sugar-sammy-et-marie-mai-dans-le-top-50|title=Sugar Sammy et Marie-Mai dans le Top-50|author=Véronique Harvey|work=Le Journal de Montréal|accessdate=February 2, 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt; Two years later, the combined shows had sold over 230,000 tickets, with over 100 sold-out shows performed at the Olympia theatre in Montreal alone.&lt;ref&gt;http://fr.canoe.ca/divertissement/tele-medias/nouvelles/2014/05/02/21644916-qmi.html&lt;/ref&gt;

In May 2014, ''[[Billboard magazine|Billboard]]'' magazine named Sugar Sammy the top-selling Canadian tour of the 12 months ending April 12, 2014.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.billboard.com/articles/news/6077513/sugar-sammy-video-interview-canada-comedian|title=Sugar Sammy Video Interview: Canada's Hot Comedian - Billboard|work=Billboard|accessdate=February 2, 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt; By the end of the year, he became Admission.com’s overall Best Selling Show of 2014, with over 300,000 tickets sold.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.admission.com/artist/sugar-sammy-billets/360293?language=en-us&amp;camefrom=DSP_Admission_WEB_SPOT_SugarSammy&amp;tm_link=tm_homeA_2_f4&amp;tm_link=tm_homeA_2_f2}}&lt;/ref&gt;

On July 28, 2016 Sugar Sammy headlined his last You’re Gonna Rire show in front of a record-breaking crowd of 115 000 people at the Place des Festivals in Montreal, a free outdoor gig that was part of the [[Just for Laughs|Just For Laughs Festival]].  Before the Grande Finale, Sugar Sammy had performed his bilingual show and the all-French version En français svp! 420 times, and sold 371,509 tickets.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://montrealgazette.com/entertainment/sugar-sammy-performs-youre-gonna-rire-for-the-last-time-in-montreal}}&lt;/ref&gt;

=== ''Sugar Sammy'' (France)  ===

Sugar Sammy developed and tested his show "Les préliminaires" at Le Point Virgule in Paris, from September 2016 through December 2016. Sugar Sammy then moved his tried and tested show to a larger venue in Paris, l'Européen, and performed his new French show, titled "Sugar Sammy", four nights a week from March 1, 2017 until April 29, 2017.&lt;ref&gt;http://ici.radio-canada.ca/nouvelle/1002823/sugar-sammy-prend-du-galon-en-france&lt;/ref&gt; A pure "American stand-up" style show, with just a microphone and no censorship. Sugar Sammy expresses his point of view as a world-travelled Canadian, now living in Paris. Previously unknown in France, Sugar Sammy's show at l'Européen quickly became one of the top selling shows in Paris. After rave reviews from critics&lt;ref name="telerama.fr"/&gt; and by popular demand, Sugar Sammy announced 25 more shows in Paris, set to perform between November 9, 2017 and December 31, 2017 at l'Alhambra, moving from a 350 seat theatre, to a 600 seat theatre.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.lapresse.ca/arts/spectacles-et-theatre/humour-et-varietes/201705/05/01-5095107-le-tour-du-monde-de-sugar-sammy.php&lt;/ref&gt;

After selling over 25,000 tickets and presenting over 134 performances in France, Sugar Sammy was dubbed the “Best of 2017” by Paris Match magazine, who referred to his show as “grand art”.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.envedette.ca/stars/sugar-sammy-encense-par-le-paris-match-1.3531612&lt;/ref&gt; Thanks to the success of his first run, Sugar Sammy is set to continue his residency at the Alhambra Theatre until December 2018, he will also be touring the rest of France, Belgium and Switzerland.

French Media Quotes:

QUOTIDIEN: “Le new king of comedy.”&lt;ref&gt;https://ici.radio-canada.ca/nouvelle/1022708/sugar-sammy-invite-a-la-populaire-emission-de-yann-barthes-en-france&lt;/ref&gt;
TÉLÉRAMA: “Virtuose de la punchline, du rythme et de l’impro.”&lt;ref&gt;http://sortir.telerama.fr/evenements/spectacles/sugar-sammy,214553.php&lt;/ref&gt;
PARIS MATCH: “Il est étonnant en scène, constamment en hors-piste, allant chercher les spectateurs sur les terrains les plus dangereux. Du grand art.”&lt;ref name="parismatch.com"/&gt; 
GQ France: “Le plus drôle des Français est Québécois.”&lt;ref&gt;https://www.gqmagazine.fr/club-gq/pop-culture/concours/le-plus-drole-des-francais-est-quebecois/551&lt;/ref&gt; 
C À VOUS: “Il a un sens de l’improvisation, c’est comme une conversation à 100 à l’heure avec le public.”&lt;ref&gt;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=4Gx29lGZFes&lt;/ref&gt; 
KONBINI: “Il débarque sur scène avec une aisance et un franc-parler dévastateur.”&lt;ref&gt;http://www.konbini.com/fr/entertainment-2/10-spectacles-au-mois-decembre/&lt;/ref&gt;

==''Ces gars-là'' TV series==
In February 2014, Sugar Sammy and French-speaking comedian Simon-Olivier Fecteau launched the  ten-episode series ''Ces gars-là'' on Quebec’s French V network. A buddy comedy à la ''Wedding Crashers'' and ''Swingers'', the show stars the two comedians, is directed by Fecteau, and is written by the two principals and India Desjardins. Inspired by the lives of the two writer-comedians, the series follows their searches for love, their relationships with their families and how they deal with the rules of their own friendship. Unusually, Sammy's English-speaking fans have followed him to a show on a French channel.&lt;ref&gt;{url=http://m.torontosun.com/2014/05/03/sugar-sammy-crosses-canadas-two-solitudes | location=Toronto |date= May 3, 2014}&lt;/ref&gt; The successful series was &lt;ref&gt;{url=http://vtele.ca/v/communiques/l-emission-ces-gars-la-depasse-largement-les-attentes_432.php}&lt;/ref&gt; prolonged into a second season.&lt;ref&gt;{url=http://vtele.ca/v/communiques/une-deuxieme-saison-pour-ces-gars-la_443.php}&lt;/ref&gt;

As the show wrapped its second season in April 2015, it was renewed for a third.&lt;ref&gt;{url=http://www.tvqc.com/2015/04/ces-gars-la-v-confirme-la-saison-3/}&lt;/ref&gt;

== HBO Canada special ==

Sugar Sammy’s biggest TV credit is his 72-minute [[HBO Canada]] special which became one of the network's highest rated TV specials and a first for any Canadian. The special was eventually acquired by [[Air Canada]] and was aired on all international and domestic flights.&lt;ref&gt;http://blog.aeroplan.com/aeroplan-members/member-profile-sugar-sammy/&lt;/ref&gt; Due to popular demand, the special was eventually released on DVD, where it went straight to # 1 on the stand-up comedy best-sellers list on Amazon Canada.

==Accomplishments==

* Voted by the readers of the ''[[Montreal Mirror]]'' "funniest comedian" for three years in a row
* Winner of the 2009 COCA (Canadian Organization for College Activities) Award for Best Comedian
* Voted by the readers of the ''Montreal Mirror'' as one of the top ten "most desirable men"
* [[HBO]] special premiered on June 14, 2009 across Canada and ran continuously throughout summer
* Named one of the top 25 "Sexy and Successful" Indian artists by ''Anokhi Magazine''
* Rumour's Restaurant &amp; Comedy Club in Winnipeg named a sandwich in Sugar's honour, The Sugar Sammy Sammie (Butter Chicken on a Bun)&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.winnipegsun.com/entertainment/2009/12/16/12181386.html |title= Dining at Rumor's? Take my advice – please! |publisher=''Winnipeg Sun'' |date=December 16, 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* Nominated for Best Male Stand-up at the 2009 Canadian Comedy Awards
* Nominated for the category of Favorite Comedian by Masala! Mehndi! Masti!
* Recipient of the 2009 ''La Revelation de [[Juste Pour Rire]]'' (the 2009 French discovery of The [[Just For Laughs]] Festival )
* Named one of the Top Ten Rising Comedy Talents on the planet by ''The Hollywood Reporter''
* Awarded the 2010 COCA awards
* Ranked No. 58 in the annual list of the Top 100 Men of 2009 by ''Divine'' magazine
* Featured in the 27th edition of the ''Juste le meilleur des galas 2009'' DVD; a greatest hits compilations by the French version of the prestigious [[Just For Laughs]] Comedy Festival
*Nominated in the categories 'Discovery of the Year' and 'Best Comedic Act' for his routine ''les Quebecquois'' for the 12th annual  Le Gala Les Olivier, a ceremony which honors Quebec's top comedians.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.apih.ca/index.php?option=com_content&amp;view=category&amp;id=17&amp;Itemid=86|title=APIH|publisher=|accessdate=February 2, 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* Recipient of the 2010 Prix québécois de la citoyenneté, which honors individuals, enterprises and organizations for their commitmment and contribution to making Quebec a more pluralistic and inclusive society&lt;ref&gt;http://www.micc.gouv.qc.ca/fr/presse/phototheque/pqc2010.html&lt;/ref&gt;
*Recipient of the 2010 ' Le Prix Umayyad'ambassadeur et rayonnement' presented by the Societe des Grands Citoyens for his contribution as an international ambassador for Canada&lt;ref&gt;http://www.lelezard.com/communique-282802.html&lt;/ref&gt;
* The first Canadian to have a special on HBO Canada, which became one of the top-rated specials on that channel
* Sugar Sammy's HBO special is the #1 bestselling DVD on Amazon.ca
* Air Canada picked up Sugar Sammy's HBO special, airing it on all domestic and international Air Canada flights
* Sugar Sammy's stand-up videos have had over three million views on YouTube.{{Citation needed|reason=does this account for duplicate videos? Source needed |date=February 2014}}
* Has multiple international TV specials and appearances including in Canada, Dubai, Australia and the Netherlands
* First comedian to perform at Just for Laughs in English, French, Hindi and Punjabi&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.comedyworksmontreal.com/index.php?option=com_content&amp;view=article&amp;id=61:sugar-sammy&amp;catid=1&amp;Itemid=2|title=Sugar Sammy|author=Chris|publisher=|accessdate=February 2, 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* Performed at Just for Laughs 7 years in a row since 2004

== Awards ==
{| class="wikitable"
|-
! Year
! Award
! Category
! Result
|-
| rowspan="8" | 2009
| COCA (Canadian Organization for College Activities)
| Best Comedian 2009
| {{won}}
|-
| [[Montreal Mirror]]
| top ten "most desirable man"
| {{won}}
|-
| ''Anokhi Magazine''
| top 25 "Sexy and Successful" Indian artists
| {{won}}
|-
| [[Canadian Comedy Awards]]
| Best Male Stand-up
| {{nom}}
|-
| Masala! Mehndi! Masti!
| Favorite Comedian
| {{nom}}
|-
| The [[Just For Laughs Festival]]
| The 2009 French discovery of The [[Just For Laughs Festival]]
| {{won}}
|-
| ''[[The Hollywood Reporter]]''
| Ten Rising Comedy Talents From Around
| {{won}}
|-
| ''Divine'' magazine
| [[Ranked#58 in the annual list of the Top 100 Men of 2009]]
| {{won}}
|-
| rowspan="7" | 2010
| Le Gala Les Olivier
| Discovery of the Year
| {{nom}}
|-
| Le Gala Les Olivier
| Best Comedic Act
| {{nom}}
|-
| Ministère de l'Immigration et des Communautés culturelles
| Prix québécois de la citoyenneté
| {{won}}
|-
| Societe des Grands Citoyens
| Le Prix Umayyad'ambassadeur et rayonnement
| {{won}}
|-
|  COCA ( Canadian Organization for College Activities)
| Best Comedian 2010
| {{won}}
|-
| ''[[Montreal Mirror]]''
| Best Comedian 2010
| {{won}}
|-
| Canadian Comedy Awards
| Best Television Performance
| {{nom}}
|-
| 2011
| ''[[Montreal Mirror]]''
| Best Montreal Comedian 2011
| {{won}}
|-
| rowspan="4" | 2013
| Gala Les Olivier
| Olivier de l'année
| {{won}}
|-
| Gala Les Olivier
| Spectacle de l'année
| {{won}}
|-
| Gala Les Olivier
| Auteur de l'année
| {{nom}}
|-
| ADISQ
| Spectacle de l'année - Humour : En français s.v.p.!
| {{nom}}
|-
| rowspan="3" | 2014
| Gala Les Olivier
| Olivier de l'année
| {{won}}
|-
| Canadian Comedy Awards
| Canadian Comedy Person of the year
| {{nom}}
|-
| Prix Gémeaux
| Meilleurs textes - comédie (Ces gars-là)
| {{nom}}
|-
| rowspan="4" | 2015
| Gala Les Olivier
| Olivier de l'année
| {{nom}}
|-
| Gala Les Olivier
| Comédie à la télévision (Ces gars-là)
| {{nom}}
|-
| Gala Artis
| Best actor in a comedy series
| {{nom}}
|-
| Prix Gémeaux
| Meilleur texte - Comédie (Ces gars-là)
| {{nom}}
|-
| rowspan="4" | 2016
| Gala Artis
| Best actor in a comedy series
| {{nom}}
|-

|}

== Créa ==

The 2012 Grand Prix Créa,&lt;ref&gt;[http://concourscrea.com/resultats/2012/resultats/ 2012 Grand Prix Créa]&lt;/ref&gt; which recognizes Quebec's best advertisement of the year, has been awarded to the Sid Lee agency for [[Vidéotron]]'s English-language Prank Calls campaign featuring Sugar Sammy. Sugar Sammy also won the best actor award for his performance.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://strategyonline.ca/2012/03/30/videotron-and-sid-lee-win-grand-prix-crea/}}&lt;/ref&gt; The campaign aimed at showing its customer-service employees' patience and efficiency, while also mentioning the company's various services. In each spot, Sammy called Videotron's customer service with a bizarre problem designed to test the employees' abilities while highlighting a particular aspect of Vidéotron's services. "The writing and direction are perfect," the jury explained. "Because Sugar Sammy delivers the goods so masterfully, viewers understand everything and laugh a lot.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.newswire.ca/en/story/947159/the-2012-grand-prix-crea-is-awarded-to-videotron-and-sid-lee-for-the-prank-calls-campaign|title=Éditions Infopresse - The 2012 Grand Prix Créa is awarded to Vidéotron and Sid Lee for the Prank Calls campaign!|publisher=|accessdate=February 2, 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt;" According to Claude Foisy, Vice President, Brand Management, of Videotron. "These are actual calls answered by real employees, who demonstrate their dedication to their mission of providing their customers with the best possible experience".&lt;ref name="corpo.videotron.com"&gt;{{cite web|url=http://corpo.videotron.com/site/salle-presse/view.form?id=512|title=Press Releases|publisher=|accessdate=February 2, 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In 2015, Sugar Sammy won big again at Quebec’s CREA Awards, with five CREA Awards.&lt;ref&gt;[http://concours.infopresse.com/crea/resultats Concours Infopresse: Résultats &amp; archives]&lt;/ref&gt; These include the Grand Prix Campagne Intégrée, one of the night’s most prestigious awards. Other awards included Indoor Billboards (Sugargate), TV spot (TV campaign Offrez Sugar Sammy) and Radio Campaign (Sugar Sammy). The campaign was produced again in collaboration with Montreal advertising agency Sid Lee. The campaign to promote comedy shows ''You’re Gonna Rire'' and ''En français SVP!'', featuring comedian Sugar Sammy, highlighted what he does best: making fun of life in Montreal.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://globalnews.ca/news/1944873/comedian-sugar-sammys-metro-ads-win-big-at-quebecs-crea-awards/}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==References==
{{Reflist}}

==External links==
* [http://www.sugarsammy.com Official Site]
* [http://www.facebook.com/pages/SUGAR-SAMMY/16876285974 Official Facebook Fanpage]
* [https://twitter.com/sugarsammyk Twitter]
* [https://www.youtube.com/sugarsammy Official Youtube Channel]
* [http://www.myspace.com/sugarsammy MySpace Page]
* {{IMDb name|2252692}}

{{authority control}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Sammy, Sugar}}
[[Category:Anglophone Quebec people]]
[[Category:Canadian stand-up comedians]]
[[Category:Canadian people of Indian descent]]
[[Category:Living people]]
[[Category:People from Côte-des-Neiges–Notre-Dame-de-Grâce]]
[[Category:Quebec comedians]]
[[Category:Male actors from Montreal]]
[[Category:People from Hampstead, Quebec]]
[[Category:1976 births]]</text>
      <sha1>jdsarkor7vkkgdjmqcvxzp0vddrcr3b</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
