<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10.xsd" version="0.10" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <dbname>enwiki</dbname>
    <base>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.32.0-wmf.16</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="118" case="first-letter">Draft</namespace>
      <namespace key="119" case="first-letter">Draft talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2300" case="first-letter">Gadget</namespace>
      <namespace key="2301" case="first-letter">Gadget talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2302" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition</namespace>
      <namespace key="2303" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Ted Healy</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>396962</id>
    <revision>
      <id>855463433</id>
      <parentid>855463368</parentid>
      <timestamp>2018-08-18T13:47:50Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>NICHOLAS NEEDLEHAM</username>
        <id>33907110</id>
      </contributor>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="26471">{{Infobox person
| name                      = Ted Healy
| image                     = Ted Healy in The Casino Murder Case trailer.jpg
| alt                       = 
| caption                   = Healy in the trailer for ''[[The Casino Murder Case]]'' (1935)
| birth_name                = Ernest Lea Nash
| birth_date                = {{birth date|1896|10|01|mf=y}}
| birth_place               = [[Kaufman, Texas]], U.S.
| death_date                = {{death date and age|1937|12|21|1896|10|01|mf=yes}}
| death_place               = [[Los Angeles]], California, U.S.
| resting_place             = [[Calvary Cemetery, East Los Angeles]]
| nationality               = American
| occupation                = Comedian, actor
| years_active              = 1912—1937
| spouse                    = {{marriage|Betty Brown&lt;br&gt;|1922|1932|end=div}}&lt;br /&gt;{{marriage|Betty Hickman&lt;br&gt;|1936|1937|end=his death}}
| children                  = 1
}}

'''Ted Healy''' (born '''Ernest Lea Nash''', October 1, 1896&amp;nbsp;– December 21, 1937) was an American [[vaudeville]] performer, [[comedian]], and [[actor]]. Though he is chiefly remembered as the creator of [[the Three Stooges]] and the style of [[slapstick comedy]] that they later made famous, he had a successful stage and film career of his own, and was cited as a formative influence by several later comedy stars. His sister was [[Marcia Healy]] who costarred with the Three Stooges as well in ''[[The Sitter Downers]]''.

== Early life ==
Sources conflict on Healy's precise birth name and birthplace, but according to baptism records, he was born Ernest (or Earnest) Lea Nash on October 1, 1896, in [[Kaufman, Texas]].&lt;ref name="cass1"&gt;{{cite book|last=Cassara|first=Bill|title=Nobody's Stooge: Ted Healy|year=2014|publisher=BearManor Media|isbn=1593937687}}&lt;/ref&gt; He attended Holy Innocents School in Houston before the family moved to New York in 1908. While in New York, he attended high school at [[De La Salle Institute (New York)|De La Salle Institute]]. Nash initially intended to follow in the footsteps of his father and pursue a career as a high-powered business executive but eventually decided on the stage.&lt;ref name=scrap&gt;{{cite book| last = Maurer |first = Joan Howard| authorlink = Joan Howard Maurer |author2=Jeff Lenburg |author3=Greg Lenburg | title = The Three Stooges Scrapbook | publisher = Chicago Review Press| year = 2012 | location = Chicago, Illinois | pages = 2–9 | url = http://www.chicagoreviewpress.com/three-stooges-scrapbook--the-products-9781613740743.php?page_id=21 |  doi =| isbn = 978-1-6137-4074-3}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Show business career==
Nash made his first foray into show business in 1912 at the age of 15. His childhood friend [[Moe Howard|Moses Horwitz]] (later known as Moe Howard) and he joined the [[Annette Kellerman]] Diving Girls, a [[vaudeville]] act that included four boys. The act ended quickly after an accident on stage, and Nash and Howard went their separate ways. Nash developed a vaudeville act and adopted the stage name Ted Healy.

Healy's act was a hit, and he soon expanded his role as a comedian and [[master of ceremonies]]. In the 1920s, he was the highest-paid performer in vaudeville, making $9000 a week.  He added performers to his stage show, including his new wife, Betty Brown (Betty Braun), and his German shepherd dog.&lt;ref name="tmg1"&gt;{{cite news|url=https://news.google.com/newspapers?id=wHwuAAAAIBAJ&amp;sjid=3YsFAAAAIBAJ&amp;dq=ted%20healy%20dog&amp;pg=6766%2C4045414|title=Princess Bill is Rich in Comedy|last=staff|date=September 30, 1924|work=The Montreal Gazette|accessdate=27 August 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The Healys' revue toured, listed on the marquee as ''[[Syncopated Toes]]'', and when some of his acrobats quit in late 1923, Moe Howard answered the advertisement for replacements. Since Howard was not an acrobat, Healy cast his old friend as a [[wikt:stooge|stooge]] (a purported member of the audience who is picked, ostensibly at random, to come onstage). In the routine, Howard's appearance would end with Healy losing his trousers.

=== Ted Healy and his Southern Gentlemen ===
Howard's brother [[Shemp Howard|Shemp]] joined the act as a heckler in early 1924, but both Howards temporarily retired from show business by mid-1925.  Ted and Betty were hired in June 1925 to star in the Broadway revue ''[[Earl Carroll Vanities of 1925]].''  Ted brought some of the routines he developed with the Howard brothers, using three comics under contract to Carroll, [[Dave Chasen]], [[Kenneth Lackey]], and [[Lou Warren]].  After a contract dispute whereby it was determined that Carroll was in the wrong, Ted and Betty left "Vanities" in October 1925 with Lou Warren and relaunched their "Syncopated Toes" revue, now retitled ''[[Fun in the Healy Manner]]''.  By January 1926 Shemp Howard had returned, and they successfully toured the country through the summer of 1926.  Ted and Betty received another Broadway opportunity, this time from the Shubert Brothers, who hired them for ''[[The Passing Show of 1926]]'', with Ted bringing Shemp and Lou along.  "Passing" only enjoyed a preview tour and did not open on Broadway, but the Shuberts and Healy retooled the show into the successful ''[[A Night in Spain]]'', with Phil Baker joining the Healys as its stars.  For "Spain," Ted now utilized four stooges in some scenes, Shemp, Lou Warren, brother-in-law Sam "Moody" Braun, and Dick Hakins.  Arriving on Broadway in May 1927 after four months of successful previews, Hakins fell ill and was replaced by comedy/specialty dancer [[Bobby Pinkus]].  In November 1927, "Spain" began a national tour with four months at Chicago's 4 Cohans Grand Opera House.  [[Larry Fine (actor)|Larry Fine]], who had been working as the lead performer and house M.C. at Chicago's Rainbo Gardens nightclub and restaurant, was added to Healy's group of comics in late March 1928.

The Shuberts hired Ted to star in their new show ''[[A Night in Venice (musical)|A Night in Venice]]'', with Moe Howard returning to show biz and joining Ted at his home in Connecticut to develop some comedy bits for the revue, which began rehearsals in January 1929.  Shemp Howard also came back, but Larry Fine was in Atlantic City with his wife, waiting for the birth of his daughter.  Healy hired comedy xylophonist [[Fred Sanborn]] as a third comic in Fine's place.  Circa mid-February, Larry contacted Healy and was welcomed to join the "Venice" cast.

During the run of ''[[A Night in Spain]],'' Ted and Betty also performed a song-and-dance stage act in nightclubs and other theaters after the evening curtain went down on "Spain."  But the Healys split in 1928, and Ted came up with the idea to spotlight his stooges in a new act, with the emphasis on comedy and slapstick humor.  Concurrent with their performances in "Venice," Healy booked himself and his troupe in additional shows as "Ted Healy &amp; His Southern Gentlemen" and later as "Ted Healy &amp; His Racketeers."  ''[[A Night in Venice (musical)|A Night in Venice]]'' had a shortened road tour after Broadway and closed in March 1930, largely owing to the economic impact of the Depression.

Fox Films hired Healy to costar in the film ''[[Soup to Nuts]]'' (filmed in July 1930), and Ted brought Moe, Shemp, Larry, and Fred Sanborn with him. In late August 1930, the Stooges and Healy parted ways after a dispute over a movie contract. Sanborn began a solo career, and the remaining trio began performing on their own, using such monikers as "The Three Lost Soles" and "Howard, Fine, and Howard", and often incorporated material from previous Healy shows. Healy attempted to sue the Stooges for using his material, but the copyright was held by the [[Shubert Theatre Corporation]], for which the routines had been produced, and the Stooges had the Shuberts' permission to use it.

Healy hired replacement stooges, consisting of Eddie Moran (soon replaced by Richard "Dick" Hakins), Jack Wolf (father of sportscaster [[Warner Wolf]]), and [[Paul Garner|Paul "Mousie" Garner]], in early 1931.  This group appeared in two Broadway plays, with Healy co-starring in ''[[The Gang's All Here (musical)|The Gang's All Here]]'' and ''[[Billy Rose's Crazy Quilt]]''. Moe, Larry, and Shemp rejoined Healy's act in late July 1932, but Shemp left on August 19 to pursue a solo career and was replaced by his younger brother, Jerry Howard, renamed [[Curly Howard]]. The switch from Shemp to Curly happened very quickly, and on August 27, 1932, only eight days after Shemp departed, "Ted Healy with Howard, Fine &amp; Howard" premiered Curly at the RKO Palace in Cleveland OH.  The new lineup's personal appearances headlined many of the prime nightclubs and movie palaces nationally for the next several months.  In late spring 1933 Ted was contracted by MGM, and the act once more headed to Hollywood, this time to stay.  Over the next year, Ted's comedy team appeared in several MGM shorts, and even supported stars like Clark Gable and Joan Crawford in features like ''[[Dancing Lady]]''.  On his own, Healy was given major roles in MGM features like ''[[Bombshell (film)|Bombshell]]'' with Jean Harlow and ''[[Operator 13]]'' with Marion Davies and Gary Cooper. In March 1934, Fine and the Howards permanently and amicably parted professional ways with Ted Healy and began working at Columbia Studios as "The Three Stooges."

=== After the Stooges ===
[[File:Ted Healy Fiesta.jpg|thumb|right|200px|Healy in the color short ''[[La Fiesta de Santa Barbara]]'' (1935), one of the earliest examples of the full-color [[Technicolor]] film process]] Healy appeared in a succession of films for [[MGM]] from 1934 to 1937 and was also loaned to [[20th Century Fox]] and [[Warner Bros.]] for films by those companies, playing both dramatic and comedic roles. One of his films, ''[[Mad Holiday]]'' (1936), featured stooge Dick Hakins as his sidekick. In ''[[San Francisco (1936 film)|San Francisco]]'' (1936), a new lineup of "stooges" consisting of Jimmy Brewster, Red Pearson, and Sammy Glasser (Sammy Wolfe) filmed a scene with Healy, but it was omitted from the final release; a few production stills of them exist. Also, in the Technicolor short subject ''[[La Fiesta de Santa Barbara]] (1935)'', Jimmy Brewster briefly appears to 'stooge' with Healy. During this period, Healy took to wearing a [[toupée]] in public.&lt;ref name=scrap/&gt; His last film, ''[[Hollywood Hotel (film)|Hollywood Hotel]]'' (1937), was released a few days after he died.

==Personal life==
Healy's first wife was dancer and singer Betty Brown (born Elizabeth Braun), whom he married in 1922,&lt;ref name="rochester"&gt;{{cite news|url=https://news.google.com/newspapers?id=nVJZAAAAIBAJ&amp;sjid=SUgNAAAAIBAJ&amp;pg=4124,2670799&amp;dq=ted+healy+nash&amp;hl=en|title=Mrs. Ted Healy Seeks Decree|date=January 27, 1932|work=Rochester Evening Journal|page=4|accessdate=May 15, 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt; one week after they met.&lt;ref name="pp25"&gt;{{cite news|url=https://news.google.com/newspapers?id=gngrAAAAIBAJ&amp;sjid=DEoEAAAAIBAJ&amp;dq=betty%20healy&amp;pg=7268%2C991094|title=Betty Healy's Fairy Tale Rivals Cinderella Legend|last=staff|date=May 11, 1925|work=The Pittsburgh Press|accessdate=27 August 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt; The couple worked together in vaudeville, then divorced in 1932&lt;ref name="re1"&gt;{{cite news|url=https://news.google.com/newspapers?id=CuUxAAAAIBAJ&amp;sjid=zuIFAAAAIBAJ&amp;dq=betty%20healy%20divorce&amp;pg=5268%2C3139209|title=California Girl Bride of Healy Comedian|last=staff|date=May 14, 1936|work=Reading Eagle|accessdate=27 August 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt; after Brown sued heiress [[Barclay Harding Warburton I|Mary Brown Warburton]] for "alienation of her husband's affections".&lt;ref name="mj1"&gt;{{cite news|url=https://news.google.com/newspapers?id=_6tQAAAAIBAJ&amp;sjid=LyIEAAAAIBAJ&amp;dq=betty%20healy%20sues&amp;pg=4236%2C5712741|title=Comedian's Wife Suing Heiress|last=staff|date=January 28, 1932|work=The Milwaukee Journal|accessdate=27 August 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Healy's second marriage was to UCLA coed Betty Hickman. After introducing himself, Healy proposed immediately, and the couple became engaged the following day.&lt;ref name="mg1"&gt;{{cite book|last1=Garner|first1=Paul|last2=Kissane|first2=Sharon|title=Mousie Garner: autobiography of a vaudeville stooge|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=Vy41mDPFqYQC&amp;pg=PA72&amp;lpg=PA73&amp;dq=Ted+Healy|accessdate=August 27, 2015|date=January 1999|publisher=Mcfarland &amp; Co Inc|isbn=978-0-7864-0581-7|page=72}}&lt;/ref&gt; They were married in [[Yuma, Arizona]], on May 15, 1936, after a midnight elopement by plane.&lt;ref name="ei1"&gt;{{cite news|url=https://news.google.com/newspapers?id=cJULAAAAIBAJ&amp;sjid=mFUDAAAAIBAJ&amp;dq=ted%20healy%20betty%20hickman&amp;pg=5620%2C302548|title=Ted Healy Wed After Elopement by Plane|last=staff|date=May 15, 1936|work=The Evening Independent|accessdate=27 August 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt; Hickman was granted a divorce on October 7, 1936, which was nullified after a reconciliation.&lt;ref name="ms2"&gt;{{cite news|url=https://news.google.com/newspapers?id=RENQAAAAIBAJ&amp;sjid=HQ0EAAAAIBAJ&amp;dq=ted%20healy%20hickman&amp;pg=3013%2C1368878|title=Ted Healy's Wife Granted Divorce|last=staff|date=October 8, 1936|work=The Milwaukee Sentinel|accessdate=27 August 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt; Their son, John Jacob, was born on December 17, 1937, four days before Healy's death.&lt;ref name="sdc1"&gt;{{cite news|url=https://news.google.com/newspapers?id=WSNZAAAAIBAJ&amp;sjid=HPUDAAAAIBAJ&amp;pg=7183,7136922&amp;dq=ted+healy+john&amp;hl=en|title=Dead Comedian's Son 10 Days Old|date=December 29, 1937|work=Spokane Daily Chronicle|page=21|accessdate=May 15, 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt;

== Death ==
Healy died on December 21, 1937, at the age of 41, after an evening of celebration at the [[Trocadero (Los Angeles)|Trocadero]] nightclub on the [[Sunset Strip]] in Los Angeles.  He was reportedly celebrating the birth of his son, an event he had eagerly anticipated according to Moe Howard. "He was nuts about kids," wrote Howard.  "He used to visit our homes and envied the fact that we were all married and had children. Healy always loved kids and often gave Christmas parties for underprivileged youngsters and spent hundreds of dollars on toys."&lt;ref name=scrap/&gt;

The circumstances surrounding his death remain a matter of some controversy.&lt;ref name="nyt2"&gt;{{cite news|url=https://query.nytimes.com/gst/abstract.html?res=9C05EED9113DE23ABC4A51DFB467838C629EDE|title=Ted Healy Dies. Autopsy Ordered. Rumors of Cafe Fight Add Some Mystery to Passing of Actor in California Home|date=December 22, 1937|work=New York Times|accessdate=11 July 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt; An MGM spokesman initially announced the cause as a [[myocardial infarction|heart attack]],&lt;ref name="evening"/&gt;&lt;ref name="pec1"&gt;{{cite news|url=https://news.google.com/newspapers?id=gaBaAAAAIBAJ&amp;sjid=SE8DAAAAIBAJ&amp;pg=4452,4227661&amp;dq=ted+healy&amp;hl=en|title=Police Drop Healy Probe|last=staff|date=December 22, 1937|work=Prescott Evening Courier|page=1|accessdate=May 15, 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt; but the presence of recent wounds&amp;mdash;a cut over his right eye and a "discolored" left eye&amp;mdash;combined with reports of an altercation at the Trocadero gave rise to speculation that he died as a result of those injuries.&lt;ref name="evening"/&gt; 

Healy's friend writer Henry Taylor told Moe Howard that the fight was preceded by an argument between Healy and three men whom he identified as "college fellows".&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book| last = Maurer |first = Joan Howard| authorlink = Joan Howard Maurer |author2=Jeff Lenburg |author3=Greg Lenburg | title = The Three Stooges Scrapbook | publisher = Chicago Review Press| year = 2012 | location = Chicago, Illinois | pages = 8 | url = http://www.chicagoreviewpress.com/three-stooges-scrapbook--the-products-9781613740743.php?page_id=21 |  doi =| isbn = 978-1-6137-4074-3}}&lt;/ref&gt; The younger men allegedly knocked Healy to the ground and kicked him in the head, ribs, and abdomen.  The wrestler [[Man Mountain Dean]] reported that he was standing in front of the Plaza Hotel in Hollywood at 2:30 a.m. when Healy emerged, bleeding, from a taxi.  He related an "incoherent story" of being attacked at the Trocadero but could not identify his assailant.&lt;ref name="pp37"&gt;{{cite news|url=https://news.google.com/newspapers?id=RiEbAAAAIBAJ&amp;sjid=MUwEAAAAIBAJ&amp;dq=wrestler%20ted%20healy&amp;pg=2012%2C1634943|title=Foul Play Ruled Out In Ted Healy's Death|last=staff|date=December 22, 1937|work=The Pittsburgh Press|page=2|accessdate=May 15, 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt;  Dean contacted a physician, Sydney Weinberg, who treated Healy at the hotel.&lt;ref name="evening"/&gt;  Another friend, [[Joe Frisco]], then drove him to his home.&lt;ref name="howard"&gt;{{cite book|last1=Howard|first1=Moe|last2=Howard Maurer|first2=Joan|title=I Stooged to Conquer: The Autobiography of the Leader of the Three Stooges|url=http://www.chicagoreviewpress.com/i-stooged-to-conquer-products-9781613747667.php?page_id=21|year=2013|publisher=Chicago Review Press|isbn=978-1-6137-4766-7|page=42}}&lt;/ref&gt;  Wyantt LaMont, Healy's personal physician, was summoned to the home the following morning when Healy began experiencing convulsions.&lt;ref name="cass1"/&gt;  Despite the efforts of LaMont and a cardiologist, John Ruddock, Healy died later that day.  Because of the circumstances, LaMont refused to sign Healy's death certificate.&lt;ref name="evening"&gt;{{cite news|url=https://news.google.com/newspapers?id=zfVPAAAAIBAJ&amp;sjid=NlUDAAAAIBAJ&amp;dq=ted%20healy%20fight&amp;pg=6348%2C5904368|title=Police Probe Death of Ted Healy, Motion Picture Star|date=December 22, 1937|work=The Evening Independent|page=1|accessdate=May 15, 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt;  

A later source alleged that the three assailants were not college boys but rather actor [[Wallace Beery]], producer [[Albert R. Broccoli]], and Broccoli's cousin, agent/producer [[Pat DiCicco]].&lt;ref name="fleming"&gt;{{cite book|last=Fleming|first=E.J.|title=The Fixers: Eddie Mannix, Howard Strickling, and the MGM Publicity Machine|year=2004|publisher=McFarland|isbn=978-0-7864-2027-8|pages=174–177}}&lt;/ref&gt; While  no documentation is seen in contemporaneous news reports that either Beery or DiCicco was present, Broccoli admitted that he was indeed involved in a fist fight with Healy at the Trocadero.&lt;ref name="odc1"&gt;{{cite news|url=https://news.google.com/newspapers?id=oQNLAAAAIBAJ&amp;sjid=QyINAAAAIBAJ&amp;dq=ted%20healy%20fight&amp;pg=3659%2C3275705|title=Wealthy Sportsman Confesses Fight with Ted Healy|last=staff|date=December 23, 1937|work=The Oxnard Daily Courier|page=1|accessdate=May 15, 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt;  He later modified his story, stating that a heavily intoxicated Healy had picked a fight with him and the two had briefly scuffled and then shook hands and parted ways.&lt;ref name="cass1"/&gt; In other reports, Broccoli admitted to pushing Healy, but not striking him.&lt;ref name=lewiston&gt;{{cite news|url=https://news.google.com/newspapers?id=zZk0AAAAIBAJ&amp;sjid=0GkFAAAAIBAJ&amp;dq=albert%20broccoli%20ted%20healy&amp;pg=759%2C6895564|title=Ted Healy Died of Toxic Nephritis|date=December 23, 1937|work=Lewiston Evening Journal|page=8|accessdate=May 15, 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt; 

Following an autopsy, the Los Angeles county coroner reported that Healy died of acute toxic [[nephritis]] secondary to acute and chronic [[alcoholism]]. Police closed their investigation, as no indication in the report was given that his death was caused by physical assault.&lt;ref name=lewiston /&gt;

Healy was a prolific spender; despite a weekly salary of $1,700 ({{inflation|US|1700|1937|fmt=eq}}), he died in debt.&lt;ref name="cass1"/&gt; He indulged in numerous personal luxuries and paid his assistant performers' salaries out of his own pocket.  He was also financially generous to friends when they were out of work; for example, while unemployed, Frisco lived at an expensive hotel on Healy's tab.&lt;ref name="cass1"/&gt; Betty was left responsible for a multitude of liabilities, including hospital bills related to the birth of her son and Healy's medical care.&lt;ref name="cullen"&gt;{{cite book|last=Cullen|first=Frank|title=Vaudeville, Old and New: An Encyclopedia of Variety Performers in America|page=495|volume=1|date=October 9, 2006|publisher=Routledge|isbn=978-0415938532}}&lt;/ref&gt; She remained hospitalized for some time after Healy died, leaving their house unattended; as a result, it was burglarized and looted of everything of value.&lt;ref name="cass1"/&gt;

A trust fund was organized by friends and colleagues to provide financial support for Betty and her child.  A fundraiser was also held, including a $10-per-plate dinner (about $170 in 2017) and an auction of the [[Hollywood Hotel]]'s ledger with hundreds of famous signatures, but Betty later asserted that she had never received any proceeds from the fundraiser.&lt;ref name="cass1"/&gt;

Ted Healy is interred at [[Calvary Cemetery, East Los Angeles|Calvary Cemetery]] in [[Los Angeles, California]], along with his mother and sister.

==Legacy==
In the decades that followed, many comedy stars, including [[Milton Berle]], [[Bob Hope]], and [[Red Skelton]], cited Healy as a mentor and significant influence on their careers.&lt;ref name="eo1"&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.empireonline.com/features/the-three-stooges|title=The Tragic And Twisted Tale Of The Three Stooges|last=Braund|first=Simon|year=2012|work=EmpireOnline|accessdate=1 September 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt; "Back in 1925, Ted Healy took me aside and gave me some wonderful advice," Berle told [[Walter Winchell]], in 1955. "'Milton, always play to the public. Never mind playing to the theatrical crowd. Don't try to impress the trumpet player in the pit. Entertain the people and you'll get rich and famous.'"&lt;ref name="dbnj1"&gt;{{cite news|url=https://news.google.com/newspapersid=DYoeAAAAIBAJ&amp;sjid=fcsEAAAAIBAJ&amp;pg=2361,2120766&amp;dq=ted+healy+interview&amp;hl=en%20Daytona%20Beach%20Morning%20Journal%209/17/55|title=Editorial|last=Winchell|first=Walter|date=September 17, 1955|work=The Daytona Beach News-Journal|page=4|accessdate=1 September 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[Alex Gard]]'s [[caricature]] of Healy was the first of several hundred displayed at [[Sardi's]] restaurant in [[New York City]]'s [[Theater District]].&lt;ref name="tnypl1"&gt;{{cite web|url=http://archives.nypl.org/the/21510/pdf|title=Sardi's (Restaurant) caricatures 1927-1952?|publisher=[[The New York Public Library]]|last=Hunter|first=Rick|accessdate=2 July 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Filmography==
{| class="wikitable sortable"
|-
! Year
! Title
! Role
! class="unsortable" | Notes
|-
| 1926
| ''Wise Guys Prefer Brunettes''
| Napoleon Fizz 
| Short film
|-
| 1930
| ''[[Soup to Nuts]]''
| Ted "Teddy" 
| 
|-
| 1931
| ''A Night in Venice'' 
| 
| Short film
|-
| 1933
| ''[[Nertsery Rhymes]]'' 
| Papa
| Short film&lt;br /&gt;Story
|-
| 1933
| ''Stop, Sadie, Stop''
| Ted
| Short film. A [[lost film]]
|-
| 1933
| ''[[Beer and Pretzels]]''
| Ted Healy
| Short film&lt;br /&gt;Writer
|-
| 1933
| ''[[Hello Pop!]]''
| Father
| Short film&lt;br /&gt;Writer
|-
| 1933
| ''Stage Mother''
| Ralph Martin 
| 
|-
| 1933
| ''[[Bombshell (film)|Bombshell]]''
| Junior Burns 
| 
|-
| 1933
| ''[[Plane Nuts]]''
| Ted Healy
| Short film&lt;br /&gt;Writer
|-
| 1933
| ''[[Meet the Baron]]''
| Head Janitor 
| 
|-
| 1933
| ''[[Dancing Lady]]''
| Steve - Patch's Assistant 
|
|-
| 1933
| ''[[Myrt and Marge (film)|Myrt and Marge]]''
| Mullins 
| 
|-
| 1934
| ''[[Fugitive Lovers]]''
| Hector Withington, Jr. 
| 
|-
| 1934
| ''Lazy River''
| William "Gabby" Stone 
| 
|-
| 1934
| ''[[The Big Idea (1934 film)|The Big Idea]]''
| Ted Healy, Scenario Company President 
| Short film&lt;br /&gt;Writer
|-
| 1934
| ''[[Hollywood Party (1934 film)|Hollywood Party]]''
| Reporter
| Uncredited; last film with the Stooges
|-
| 1934
| ''[[Operator 13]]''
| Doctor Hitchcock 
| 
|-
| 1934
| ''[[Paris Interlude]]''
| Jimmy
|
|-
| 1934
| ''[[Death on the Diamond]]''
| Terry "Crawfish" O'Toole
| 
|-
| 1934
| ''[[The Band Plays On (film)|The Band Plays On]]''
| Joe 
| 
|-
| 1934
| ''[[Forsaking All Others]]''
| 
| Scenes deleted
|-
| 1935
| ''[[The Winning Ticket]]''
| Eddie Dugan 
| 
|-
| 1935
| ''[[The Casino Murder Case (film)|The Casino Murder Case]]''
| Sergeant Heath
|
|-
| 1935
| ''[[Reckless (1935 film)|Reckless]]''
| Smiley 
| 
|-
| 1935
| ''[[Murder in the Fleet]]''
| Gabby O'Neill
|
|-
| 1935
| ''[[La Fiesta de Santa Barbara]]''
| Himself
| Color short film
|-
| 1935
| ''[[Mad Love (1935 film)|Mad Love]]''
| Reagan 
| 
|-
| 1935
| ''[[Here Comes the Band (film)|Here Comes the Band]]''
| Happy
| 
|-
| 1935
| ''[[It's in the Air (1935 film)|It's in the Air]]''
| Clip McGurk 
|
|-
| 1936
| ''[[Speed (1936 film)|Speed]]''
| Clarence Maxmillian "Gadget" Haggerty 
|
|-
| 1936
| ''[[San Francisco (1936 film)|San Francisco]]''
| Mat 
|
|-
| 1936
| ''[[Sing, Baby, Sing]]''
| Al Craven 
| 
|-
| 1936
| ''[[The Longest Night (1936 film)|The Longest Night]]''
| Police Sergeant Magee 
|
|-
| 1936
| ''[[Mad Holiday]]''
| Mert Morgan 
| 
|-
| 1937
| ''[[Man of the People (film)|Man of the People]]''
| Joe The Glut
|
|-
| 1937
| ''[[The Good Old Soak]]''
| Al Simmons 
| 
|-
| 1937
| ''[[Varsity Show (film)|Varsity Show]]''
| William Williams 
| 
|-
| 1937
| ''[[Hollywood Hotel (film)|Hollywood Hotel]]''
| Fuzzy Boyle 
|
|-
| 1938
| ''Love Is a Headache''
| Jimmy Slattery 
|
|-
| 1938
| ''[[Of Human Hearts]]''
| 
| Uncredited
|-
|}

==References==
{{Reflist|2}}

==Further reading==
*''The Complete Three Stooges: The Official Filmography and Three Stooges Companion'' by Jon Solomon, (Comedy III Productions, Inc., 2002).
*''The Three Stooges Scrapbook'' by Jeff Lenburg, Joan Howard Maurer, Greg Lenburg (Citadel Press, 1994).

==External links==
{{commons}}
* [https://archive.org/download/TwoThreeStoogesFilms/ThreeStoogesTedHealy1933PlaneNuts19m18s.mp4 Ted Healy and his Stooges vaudeville routine from Plane Nuts]
* {{IMDb name|0372384}}
* {{IBDB name}}
* {{Find a Grave|4542}}
* [http://markmaynard.com/2013/02/ted-healys-drawing-of-wallace-beery-and-wallace-beerys-murder-of-ted-healy/ Digging though the Hollywood archives]

{{ThreeStooges}}

{{Authority control}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Healy, Ted}}
[[Category:1896 births]]
[[Category:1937 deaths]]
[[Category:20th-century American male actors]]
[[Category:Male actors from Texas]]
[[Category:American male film actors]]
[[Category:American male comedians]]
[[Category:American comedians]]
[[Category:American male screenwriters]]
[[Category:American male stage actors]]
[[Category:Burials at Calvary Cemetery, East Los Angeles]]
[[Category:Deaths from nephritis]]
[[Category:Metro-Goldwyn-Mayer contract players]]
[[Category:People from Houston]]
[[Category:The Three Stooges]]
[[Category:Vaudeville performers]]
[[Category:American people of Irish descent]]
[[Category:People from Kaufman, Texas]]</text>
      <sha1>fiphicadcsk2akh19bfpv99spw1un2r</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
