<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10.xsd" version="0.10" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <dbname>enwiki</dbname>
    <base>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.32.0-wmf.16</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="118" case="first-letter">Draft</namespace>
      <namespace key="119" case="first-letter">Draft talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2300" case="first-letter">Gadget</namespace>
      <namespace key="2301" case="first-letter">Gadget talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2302" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition</namespace>
      <namespace key="2303" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>W. C. Fields</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>211494</id>
    <revision>
      <id>854594673</id>
      <parentid>854594479</parentid>
      <timestamp>2018-08-12T13:25:33Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <ip>2600:1700:CB70:3B70:D918:F5BC:B89C:7510</ip>
      </contributor>
      <comment>/* Final years */ Fixed grammar</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="69435">{{Use mdy dates|date=December 2014}}
{{Infobox person
| name            = W. C. Fields

| image           = File:W. C. Fields 1938.jpg

| imagesize       =
| caption         = W. C. Fields, 1938
| birth_name      = William Claude Dukenfield
| birth_date      = {{Birth date|1880|1|29|mf=y}}
| birth_place     = [[Darby, Pennsylvania]], U.S.
| death_date      = {{Death date and age|1946|12|25|1880|1|29|mf=y}}
| death_place     = [[Pasadena, California]], U.S.
| resting_place   = [[Forest Lawn Memorial Park, Glendale]], California
| occupation      = Actor, comedian, juggler, writer
| years_active    = 1898–1946
| other_names     = Charles Bogle&lt;br&gt;Otis Criblecoblis&lt;br&gt;Mahatma Kane Jeeves
| death_cause =
| spouse          = {{marriage|Harriet Hughes|1900|1946}} (his death) 1 child
| partner         = Bessie Poole (girlfriend) 1 child &lt;br&gt;[[Carlotta Monti]] (companion)
| children        = William Claude Fields Jr. &lt;br&gt; William Morris
}}

'''William Claude Dukenfield''' (January 29, 1880&lt;ref&gt;"Fields always observed his birthday on January 29, and his death certificate confirms this .... When Fields married Harriet Veronica Hughes in San Francisco, on April 8, 1900, he was twenty years old and, under California law, could not enter into a marriage without parental consent. He therefore gave his birthdate as April 9, 1879, and often used this date thereafter. However, when he applied for a passport later that same year, he swore under oath that his correct birthdate was January 29, 1880." Curtis, James. ''W.C. Fields: A Biography''. New York: A. Knopf, 2003, p. 525&lt;/ref&gt; – December 25, 1946), better known as '''W. C. Fields''', was an American comedian, actor, [[juggler]] and writer.&lt;ref&gt;Obituary ''[[Variety Obituaries|Variety]]'', January 1, 1947, page 46.&lt;/ref&gt; Fields' comic [[persona]] was a [[Misanthropy|misanthropic]] and hard-drinking [[egotist]], who remained a sympathetic character despite his snarling contempt for dogs and children.

His career in show business began in [[vaudeville]], where he attained international success as a silent juggler. He gradually incorporated comedy into his act, and was a featured comedian in the [[Ziegfeld Follies]] for several years. He became a star in the Broadway musical comedy ''[[Poppy (1923 musical)|Poppy]]'' (1923), in which he played a colorful small-time [[confidence trick|con man]]. His subsequent stage and film roles were often similar scoundrels, or henpecked [[everyman]] characters.

Among his recognizable trademarks were his raspy drawl and [[Grandiloquence|grandiloquent]] vocabulary. The characterization he portrayed in films and on radio was so strong it was generally identified with Fields himself. It was maintained by the publicity departments at Fields' studios ([[Paramount Pictures|Paramount]] and [[Universal Studios|Universal]]) and was further established by Robert Lewis Taylor's biography, ''W. C. Fields, His Follies and Fortunes'' (1949).  Beginning in 1973, with the publication of Fields' letters, photos, and personal notes in grandson Ronald Fields' book ''W. C. Fields by Himself'', it was shown that Fields was married (and subsequently estranged from his wife), and financially supported their son and loved his grandchildren.

==Early years==
Fields was born William Claude Dukenfield in [[Darby, Pennsylvania]], the oldest child of a working-class family. His father, James Lydon Dukenfield (1840–1913), was from an English family that emigrated from [[Sheffield]], England in 1854.&lt;ref&gt;Simon Louvish, ''Man on the Flying Trapeze: The Life and Times of W. C. Fields'', 1997, pp. 29–30.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://articles.sun-sentinel.com/2003-04-06/entertainment/0304040528_1_fields-career-vaudeville-ziegfeld-follies|title=The Myth Of W.c.|work=Sun Sentinel}}&lt;/ref&gt; James Dukenfield served in Company M of the [[72nd Pennsylvania Infantry]] Regiment in the [[American Civil War]] and was wounded in 1863.&lt;ref&gt;Muster roll of 72nd PA, which did not fight at Lookout Mountain! A photo of James in a Civil War period uniform, c. 1900, shows him missing his right index finger. Reproduced p. 29, Louvish.&lt;/ref&gt; Fields' mother, Kate Spangler Felton (1854–1925), was a [[Protestant]] of British ancestry.&lt;ref&gt;Curtis, James. ''W.C. Fields: A Biography''. New York: A. Knopf, 2003, p. 8.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="Louvish_31"&gt;Louvish, Simon. ''Man on the Flying Trapeze: The Life and Times of W.C. Fields'', 1999, Faber &amp; Faber, p. 31.&lt;/ref&gt; The 1876 ''Philadelphia City Directory ''lists James Dukenfield as a clerk. After marrying, he worked as an independent produce merchant and a part-time hotel-keeper.&lt;ref name="Louvish_31"/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;1880 census, Philadelphia, p. 129A&lt;/ref&gt;

Claude Dukenfield (as he was known) had a volatile relationship with his short-tempered father. He ran away from home repeatedly, beginning at the age of nine, often to stay with his grandmother or an uncle.&lt;ref&gt;Curtis, James. ''W.C. Fields: A Biography''. New York: A. Knopf, 2003, p. 14; Louvish, Simon. ''Man on the Flying Trapeze: The Life and Times of W.C. Fields'', 1999, Faber &amp; Faber, p. 42.&lt;/ref&gt; His education was sporadic, and did not progress beyond grade school.&lt;ref name="Louvish_34"/&gt; At age twelve, he worked with his father selling produce from a wagon, until the two had a fight that resulted in Fields running away once again.&lt;ref&gt;Curtis, James. ''W.C. Fields: A Biography''. New York: A. Knopf, 2003, p. 12.&lt;/ref&gt; In 1893, he worked briefly at the [[Strawbridge and Clothier]] department store,&lt;ref&gt;Curtis, James. ''W.C. Fields: A Biography''. New York: A. Knopf, 2003, pp. 16–17.&lt;/ref&gt; and in an [[oyster house]].&lt;ref name="W.C. Fields Biography"&gt;{{cite news|title=W.C. Fields Biography|url=http://www.thebiographychannel.co.uk/biographies/w-c-fields.html|journal=The Biography Channel|location=UK|deadurl=yes|archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20130406054319/http://www.thebiographychannel.co.uk/biographies/w-c-fields.html|archivedate=April 6, 2013|df=mdy-all}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Fields later embellished stories of his childhood, depicting himself as a runaway who lived by his wits on the streets of Philadelphia from an early age, but his home life seems to have been reasonably happy.&lt;ref&gt;Louvish, Simon. ''Man on the Flying Trapeze: The Life and Times of W.C. Fields'', 1999, Faber &amp; Faber, pp. 10, 42.&lt;/ref&gt; He had already discovered in himself a facility for juggling, and a performance he witnessed at a local theater inspired him to dedicate substantial time to perfecting his juggling.&lt;ref name="W.C. Fields Biography"/&gt; At age 17, he was living with his family and performing a juggling act at church and theater shows.&lt;ref&gt;Curtis, James. ''W.C. Fields: A Biography''. New York: A. Knopf, 2003, pp. 24, 26.&lt;/ref&gt;

In 1904 Fields' father visited him for two months in England while he was performing there in [[music hall]]s.&lt;ref&gt;Curtis, James. ''W.C. Fields: A Biography''. New York: A. Knopf, 2003, p. 69.&lt;/ref&gt; Fields enabled his father to retire, purchased him a summer home, and encouraged his parents and siblings to learn to read and write, so they could communicate with him by letter.&lt;ref&gt;Curtis, James. ''W.C. Fields: A Biography''. New York: A. Knopf, 2003, pp. 68–69.&lt;/ref&gt;

==Entry into vaudeville==
Inspired by the success of the "Original Tramp Juggler", James Edward Harrigan,&lt;ref&gt;Trav, S.D. ''No Applause—Just Throw Money: The Book That Made Vaudeville Famous'', 1965, p. 146.&lt;/ref&gt; Fields adopted a similar costume of scruffy beard and shabby tuxedo and entered [[vaudeville]] as a genteel "[[Hobo|tramp]] juggler" in 1898, using the name W. C. Fields.&lt;ref&gt;Curtis, James. ''W.C. Fields: A Biography''. New York: A. Knopf, 2003, p. 26.&lt;/ref&gt; His family supported his ambitions for the stage and saw him off on the train for his first stage tour. To conceal a stutter, Fields did not speak onstage.&lt;ref&gt;Curtis, James. ''W.C. Fields: A Biography''. New York: A. Knopf, 2003, p. 30.&lt;/ref&gt; In 1900, seeking to distinguish himself from the many "tramp" acts in vaudeville, he changed his costume and makeup, and began touring as "The Eccentric Juggler".&lt;ref&gt;Curtis, James. ''W.C. Fields: A Biography''. New York: A. Knopf, 2003, pp. 46–47.&lt;/ref&gt; He [[cigar box (juggling)|manipulated cigar boxes]], hats, and other objects in what appears to have been a unique and fresh act, parts of which are reproduced in some of his films, notably in ''[[The Old Fashioned Way (film)|The Old Fashioned Way]]'' (1934).

By the early 1900s, while touring, he was regularly called the world's greatest juggler.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news| title=W.C. Fields Biography| url=http://www.thebiographychannel.co.uk/biographies/w-c-fields.html| journal=The Biography Channel| location=UK| deadurl=yes| archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20130406054319/http://www.thebiographychannel.co.uk/biographies/w-c-fields.html| archivedate=April 6, 2013| df=mdy-all}}&lt;/ref&gt; He became a headliner in North America and Europe, and toured Australia and South Africa in 1903.&lt;ref&gt;Louvish, Simon. ''Man on the Flying Trapeze: The Life and Times of W.C. Fields'', 1999, Faber &amp; Faber, p. 488.&lt;/ref&gt; When Fields played for English-speaking audiences, he found he could get more laughs by adding muttered patter and sarcastic asides to his routines. According to W. Buchanan-Taylor, a performer who saw Fields' performance in an English music hall, Fields would "reprimand a particular ball which had not come to his hand accurately", and "mutter weird and unintelligible expletives to his cigar when it missed his mouth".&lt;ref&gt;Louvish, Simon. ''Man on the Flying Trapeze: The Life and Times of W.C. Fields'', 1999, Faber &amp; Faber, p. 54.&lt;/ref&gt;

==Broadway==
In 1905 Fields made his Broadway debut in a musical comedy, ''The Ham Tree''. His role in the show required him to deliver lines of dialogue, which he had never before done onstage.&lt;ref&gt;Curtis, James. ''W.C. Fields: A Biography''. New York: A. Knopf, 2003, p, 72.&lt;/ref&gt;  He later said, "I wanted to become a real comedian, and there I was, ticketed and pigeonholed as merely a comedy juggler."&lt;ref&gt;Curtis, James. ''W.C. Fields: A Biography''. New York: A. Knopf, 2003, p. 85.&lt;/ref&gt; In 1913 he performed on a bill with [[Sarah Bernhardt]] (who regarded Fields as "an artiste [who] could not fail to please the best class of audience") first at the New York Palace, and then in England in a royal performance for the king and queen.&lt;ref&gt;Curtis, James. ''W.C. Fields: A Biography''. New York: A. Knopf, 2003, p. 87.&lt;/ref&gt;  He continued touring in vaudeville until 1915.&lt;ref&gt;Louvish, Simon. ''Man on the Flying Trapeze: The Life and Times of W.C. Fields'', 1999, Faber &amp; Faber, p. 495.&lt;/ref&gt;

Beginning in 1915, he appeared on [[Broadway theater|Broadway]] in [[Florenz Ziegfeld]]'s ''[[Ziegfeld Follies]]'' revue,&lt;ref&gt;Curtis, James. ''W.C. Fields: A Biography''. New York: A. Knopf, 2003, pp. 99–100.&lt;/ref&gt; delighting audiences with a wild [[Pocket billiards|billiards]] skit, complete with bizarrely shaped cues and a custom-built table used for a number of hilarious gags and surprising [[trick shot]]s. His pool game is reproduced, in part, in some of his films, notably in ''[[Six of a Kind]]'' (1934). The act was a success, and Fields starred in the ''Follies'' from 1916 to 1922, not as a juggler but as a comedian in ensemble sketches.  In addition to multiple editions of the ''Follies'', Fields starred in the Broadway musical comedy ''[[Poppy (1923 musical)|Poppy]]'' (1923), wherein he perfected his persona as a colorful small-time [[confidence trick|con man]].

His stage costume from 1915 onwards featured a top hat, cut-away coat and collar, and a cane—an appearance remarkably similar to the comic strip character [[Ally Sloper]], who may have been the inspiration for Fields' costume, according to Roger Sabin. The Sloper character may in turn have been inspired by Dickens' [[Mr Micawber]], whom Fields later played on film.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.imageandnarrative.be/inarchive/graphicnovel/rogersabin.htm|title=Ally Sloper: The First Comics Superstar?|work=imageandnarrative.be}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Films==

===Silent era and first talkies===
In 1915, Fields starred in two short comedies, ''[[Pool Sharks]]'' and ''[[His Lordship's Dilemma]]'', filmed in New York.&lt;ref&gt;Curtis, James. ''W.C. Fields: A Biography''. New York: A. Knopf, 2003, pp. 103–105.&lt;/ref&gt; His stage commitments prevented him from doing more movie work until 1924, when he played a supporting role in ''[[Janice Meredith]]'', a Revolutionary War romance.&lt;ref&gt;Curtis, James. ''W.C. Fields: A Biography''. New York: A. Knopf, 2003, pp. 106, 166.&lt;/ref&gt; He reprised his ''Poppy'' role in a silent-film adaptation, retitled ''[[Sally of the Sawdust]]'' (1925) and directed by [[D. W. Griffith]]. His next starring role was in the [[Paramount Pictures]] film ''[[It's the Old Army Game]]'' (1926), which featured his friend [[Louise Brooks]], later a screen legend for her role in [[G. W. Pabst]]'s ''[[Pandora's Box (1929 film)|Pandora's Box]]'' (1929) in Germany.&lt;ref&gt;Louvish, Simon. ''Man on the Flying Trapeze: The Life and Times of W.C. Fields'', 1999, Faber &amp; Faber, p. 272.&lt;/ref&gt; Fields' 1926 film, which included a silent version of the porch sequence that would later be expanded in the sound film ''[[It's a Gift]]'' (1934), had only middling success at the box office.&lt;ref&gt;Louvish, Simon. ''Man on the Flying Trapeze: The Life and Times of W.C. Fields'', 1999, Faber &amp; Faber, pp. 274–275.&lt;/ref&gt; After Fields' next two features for Paramount failed to produce hits, the studio teamed him with [[Chester Conklin]] for three features which were commercial failures and are now lost.&lt;ref&gt;Louvish, Simon. ''Man on the Flying Trapeze: The Life and Times of W.C. Fields'', 1999, Faber &amp; Faber, pp. 280, 282, 286.&lt;/ref&gt;

Fields wore a scruffy clip-on mustache in all of his silent films. According to the film historian [[William K. Everson]], he perversely insisted on wearing the conspicuously fake-looking mustache because he knew it was disliked by audiences.&lt;ref&gt;Everson, William K. ''The Art of W.C. Fields''. 1967, New York: Bonanza Books. p. 44.&lt;/ref&gt;  Fields wore it in his first sound film, ''[[The Golf Specialist]]'' (1930)—a two-reeler that faithfully reproduces a sketch he had introduced in 1918 in the ''Follies''&lt;ref&gt;Louvish, Simon. ''Man on the Flying Trapeze: The Life and Times of W.C. Fields'', 1999, Faber &amp; Faber, pp. 205, 312.&lt;/ref&gt;—and finally discarded it after his first sound feature film, ''[[Her Majesty, Love]]'' (1931), his only [[Warner Bros.]] production.

===At Paramount===
In the sound era, Fields appeared in thirteen feature films for Paramount Pictures, beginning with ''[[Million Dollar Legs (1932 film)|Million Dollar Legs]]'' in 1932. In that year he also was featured in a sequence in the [[anthology film]] ''[[If I Had a Million]]''. In 1932 and 1933, Fields made four short subjects for comedy pioneer [[Mack Sennett]], distributed through Paramount Pictures. These shorts, adapted with few alterations from Fields' stage routines and written entirely by himself, were described by Simon Louvish as "the 'essence' of Fields".&lt;ref&gt;Louvish, Simon. ''Man on the Flying Trapeze: The Life and Times of W.C. Fields'', 1999, Faber &amp; Faber, pp. 340–341.&lt;/ref&gt; The first of them, ''[[The Dentist (1932 film)|The Dentist]]'', is unusual in that Fields portrays an entirely unsympathetic character: he cheats at golf, assaults his caddy, and treats his patients with unbridled callousness. William K. Everson says that the cruelty of this comedy made it "hardly less funny", but that "Fields must have known that ''The Dentist'' presented a serious flaw for a comedy image that was intended to endure", and showed a somewhat warmer persona in his subsequent Sennett shorts.&lt;ref&gt;Everson, William K. ''The Art of W.C. Fields''. 1967, New York: Bonanza Books. p. 85.&lt;/ref&gt;

The popular success of his next feature film, ''[[International House (1933 movie)|International House]]'' (1933), established him as a major star.&lt;ref&gt;Louvish, Simon. ''Man on the Flying Trapeze: The Life and Times of W.C. Fields'', 1999, Faber &amp; Faber, p. 362.&lt;/ref&gt; A shaky outtake from the film, allegedly the only moving image record of the [[1933 Long Beach earthquake]], was later revealed to have been faked as a publicity stunt for the movie.&lt;ref&gt;Curtis, James. ''W.C. Fields: A Biography''. New York: A. Knopf, 2003, p. 259.&lt;/ref&gt;

His 1934 classic ''[[It's a Gift]]'' included his stage sketch of trying to escape his nagging family by sleeping on the back porch and being bedeviled by noisy neighbors and salesmen. That film, like ''[[You're Telling Me!]]'' and ''[[Man on the Flying Trapeze]]'', ended happily with a windfall profit that restored his standing in his screen families.

He achieved a career ambition by playing the character [[Wilkins Micawber|Mr. Micawber]], in [[MGM]]'s ''[[Personal History, Adventures, Experience, and Observation of David Copperfield the Younger|David Copperfield]]'' in 1935.&lt;ref&gt;Louvish, Simon. ''Man on the Flying Trapeze: The Life and Times of W.C. Fields'', 1999, Faber &amp; Faber, pp. 389–390.&lt;/ref&gt; In 1936, Fields re-created his signature stage role in ''Poppy'' for [[Paramount Pictures]].

In 1938 Fields excelled once again, this time in Paramount's sweeping musical variety anthology ''[[The Big Broadcast of 1938]]'' while starring with [[Martha Raye]], [[Dorothy Lamour]] and [[Bob Hope]]. In an unusual twist, Fields plays the roles of two nearly identical brothers (T. Frothingill Bellows and S. B. Bellow) and collaborated with several noted international musicians of the time including: [[Kirsten Flagstad]] (Norwegian opera soprano), [[Wilfred Pelletier]] (Canadian conductor of New York's [[Metropolitan Opera Orchestra]]), [[Tito Guizar]] (Mexican vocalist), [[Shep Fields]] (conducting his Rippling Rhythm Jazz Orchestra) and [[John Serry Sr.]] (Italian-American orchestral accordionist) &lt;ref&gt;[https://www.imdb.com/title/tt0029912/ ''The Big Broadcast of 1938'' on imdb.org]&lt;/ref&gt; The film received critical acclaim and earned an [[Academy Award|Oscar]] in 1939 for best music in an original song - ''[[Thanks for the Memory]]''&lt;ref&gt;[https://www.imdb.com/title/tt0029912/awards?ref_=tt_awd ''The Big Broadcast f 1938'' on imdb.org]&lt;/ref&gt;

==Personal life==
[[File:Wcfields36682u cropped 02.jpg|thumb|left|upright|W.C. Fields]]
Fields married a fellow [[Vaudeville|vaudevillian]], chorus girl, Harriet "Hattie" Hughes (1879&amp;ndash;1963), on April 8, 1900.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|title=W. C. Fields' Widow Wins – Entitled to Half $771,000, Though Long Estranged, Judge Rules |url=https://www.nytimes.com/1949/07/08/archives/w-c-fields-widow-wins-entitled-to-half-771000-though-long-estranged.html |work=New York Times|agency=Associated Press |date=July 8, 1949|page=15|access-date=October 9, 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt; She became part of Fields' stage act, appearing as his assistant, whom he would entertainingly blame when he missed a trick.&lt;ref&gt;Curtis, James. ''W.C. Fields: A Biography''. New York: A. Knopf, 2003, p. 48.&lt;/ref&gt;  Hattie was educated and tutored Fields in reading and writing during their travels.&lt;ref&gt;Curtis, James. ''W.C. Fields: A Biography''. New York: A. Knopf, 2003, p. 50.&lt;/ref&gt; Under her influence, he became an enthusiastic reader and traveled with a trunk of books including grammar texts, translations of [[Homer]] and [[Ovid]], and works by authors ranging from [[Shakespeare]] to [[Charles Dickens|Dickens]] to [[Mark Twain|Twain]].&lt;ref&gt;Curtis, James. ''W.C. Fields: A Biography''. New York: A. Knopf, 2003, p. 82.&lt;/ref&gt;

The couple had a son, William Claude Fields, Jr. (July 28, 1904 &amp;ndash; February 16, 1971)&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |first=Vincent |last=Canby |authorlink=Vincent Canby |title=Son of W. C. Fields Toasts Him in Tea – Comic's Namesake, Here for Festival, Is a Teetotaler|url=https://www.nytimes.com/1966/02/19/archives/son-of-wc-fields-toasts-him-in-tea-comics-namesake-here-for.html |quote=William Claude Fields, Jr., the only child of the man who insisted that anyone who hated children could not be all bad, sat uncomfortably late yesterday afternoon in the eighth-floor lounge at the Gallery of Modern Art, sipping a cup of tea, a beverage his father might have chosen only in extremis. |work=New York Times |date=February 19, 1966|page=12|access-date=October 9, 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt; and although Fields was an atheist—who, according to James Curtis, "regarded all religions with the suspicion of a seasoned con man"—he yielded to Hattie's wish to have their son baptized.&lt;ref&gt;Jordan, S. C. (2008). ''Hollywood's original rat pack The bards of Bundy Drive''. Lanham, Maryland [u.a.]: Scarecrow Press. p. 151. {{ISBN|0-8108-6032-5}}&lt;/ref&gt;

By 1907 he and Hattie separated; she had been pressing him to stop touring and settle into a respectable trade, but he was unwilling to give up show business.&lt;ref&gt;[[:Image:1910 census W. C. Fields.jpeg|Claude W. Dukenfield, age 30]] at 3920 North Marshall Street, Philadelphia, age 30, an actor, in the tenth year of his first marriage. His wife is not present in the household.&lt;/ref&gt; They never divorced. Until his death, Fields continued to correspond with Hattie (mostly through letters) and voluntarily sent her a weekly stipend.&lt;ref&gt;Curtis, James. ''W.C. Fields: A Biography''. New York: A. Knopf, 2003, pp. 178, 474.&lt;/ref&gt; Their correspondence would at times be remarkably tense, however, with Fields accusing Hattie of turning their son "against" him and demanding more money from him than he could afford.&lt;ref&gt;Fields, Ronald J. (ed.): ''W.C. Fields by Himself: His Intended Autobiography with Hitherto Unpublished Letters, Notes, Scripts and Articles'' (Copyright 1973. Taylor Trade Paperback Edition, 2016), p. 65. {{ISBN|1630761702}}.&lt;/ref&gt;

While performing in New York City at the [[New Amsterdam Theater]] in 1916, Fields met Bessie Poole, an established Ziegfeld Follies performer whose beauty and quick wit attracted him, and they began a relationship. With her he had another son, named William Rexford Fields Morris (August 15, 1917 – November 30, 2014).&lt;ref&gt;Gehring, W. D. (1994). ''Groucho and W.C. Fields Huckster comedians''. Jackson, Miss: University Press of Mississippi. p. 70. {{ISBN|0-585-19049-6}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.facebook.com/media/set/?set=a.770661722969661.1073741881.625725480796620&amp;type=1|title=Final Tribute to William Rexford Fields Morris: 1917–2014 - Facebook|work=facebook.com}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=xP_BclzlQ84|title=An Interview with WC Fields' 94 year old son.|date=May 29, 2012|work=YouTube}} The son had four children.&lt;/ref&gt; Neither Fields nor Poole wanted to abandon touring to raise the child, who was placed in foster care with a childless couple of Bessie's acquaintance.&lt;ref&gt;Curtis, James. ''W.C. Fields: A Biography''. New York: A. Knopf, 2003, p. 121.&lt;/ref&gt; Fields' relationship with Poole lasted until 1926. In 1927, he made a negotiated payment to her of $20,000 upon her signing an affidavit declaring that "W. C. Fields is NOT the father of my child".&lt;ref&gt;Curtis, James. ''W.C. Fields: A Biography''. New York: A. Knopf, 2003, p. 203.&lt;/ref&gt; Poole died of complications of alcoholism in October 1928,&lt;ref&gt;Curtis, James. ''W.C. Fields: A Biography''. New York: A. Knopf, 2003, p. 215.&lt;/ref&gt; and Fields contributed to her son's support until he was 19 years of age.&lt;ref&gt;Curtis, James. ''W.C. Fields: A Biography''. New York: A. Knopf, 2003, p. 347.&lt;/ref&gt;

Fields met [[Carlotta Monti]] (1907–1993) in 1933, and the two began a sporadic relationship that lasted until his death in 1946.&lt;ref&gt;Louvish, Simon. ''Man on the Flying Trapeze: The Life and Times of W.C. Fields'', 1999, Faber &amp; Faber, pp. 364–365, 472–473.&lt;/ref&gt; Monti had small roles in two of Fields' films, and in 1971 wrote a memoir, ''W.C. Fields and Me,'' which was made into a [[W.C. Fields and Me|motion picture]] at Universal Studios in 1976. Fields was listed in the 1940 census as single and living at 2015 DeMille Drive ([[Cecil B. DeMille]] lived at 2000, the only other address on the street).

===Alcohol, dogs, and children===
Fields' screen character often expressed a fondness for alcohol, a prominent component of the Fields legend. Fields never drank in his early career as a juggler, because he did not want to impair his functions while performing.  Eventually, the loneliness of constant travel prompted him to keep liquor in his dressing room as an inducement for fellow performers to socialize with him on the road. Only after he became a ''Follies'' star and abandoned juggling did Fields begin drinking regularly.&lt;ref&gt;Curtis, James. ''W.C. Fields: A Biography''. New York: A. Knopf, 2003, pp. 116–117.&lt;/ref&gt; His role in Paramount Pictures' ''[[International House (1933 film)|International House]]'' (1933), as an aviator with an unquenchable taste for beer, did much to establish Fields' popular reputation as a prodigious drinker.&lt;ref&gt;Curtis, James. ''W.C. Fields: A Biography''. New York: A. Knopf, 2003, pp. 260, 263.&lt;/ref&gt; Studio publicists promoted this image, as did Fields himself in press interviews.&lt;ref&gt;Curtis, James. ''W.C. Fields: A Biography''. New York: A. Knopf, 2003, pp. 264, 300.&lt;/ref&gt;

Fields expressed his fondness for alcohol to [[Gloria Jean]] (playing his niece) in ''[[Never Give a Sucker an Even Break]]'': "I was in love with a beautiful blonde once, dear. She drove me to drink. That's the one thing I am indebted to her for."  Equally memorable was a line in the 1940 film ''[[My Little Chickadee]]'':  "Once, on a trek through Afghanistan, we lost our corkscrew...and were compelled to live on food and water for several days."  The oft-repeated anecdote that Fields refused to drink water "because fish fuck in it" is unsubstantiated.&lt;ref&gt;Curtis, James. ''W.C. Fields: A Biography''. New York: A. Knopf, 2003, p. 230.&lt;/ref&gt;

On movie sets Fields famously shot most of his scenes in varying states of inebriation.  During the filming of ''[[Tales of Manhattan]]'' (1942), he kept a [[vacuum flask]] with him at all times and frequently availed himself of its contents.  [[Phil Silvers]], who had a minor supporting role in the scene featuring Fields, described in his memoir what happened next:

{{quote|One day the producers appeared on the set to plead with Fields: "Please don't drink while we're shooting—we're way behind schedule" ... Fields merely raised an eyebrow.  "Gentlemen, this is only lemonade. For a little acid condition afflicting me." He leaned on me. "Would you be kind enough to taste this, sir?"  I took a careful sip—pure gin. I have always been a friend of the drinking man; I respect him for his courage to withdraw from the world of the thinking man. I answered the producers a little scornfully, "It's lemonade."  My reward?  The scene was snipped out of the picture.&lt;ref&gt;Silvers, P. ''This Laugh Is on Me: The Phil Silvers Story''. Prentice-Hall (1973), p. 116. {{ISBN|0139191003}}&lt;/ref&gt;
}}

In a testimonial dinner for Fields in 1939, the humorist [[Leo Rosten]] remarked of the comedian that "any man who hates dogs and babies can't be all bad".&lt;ref&gt;Curtis, James. ''W.C. Fields: A Biography''. New York: A. Knopf, 2003, p. 392.&lt;/ref&gt; The line—which ''Bartlett's Familiar Quotations'' later erroneously attributed to Fields himself—became famous, and reinforced the popular perception that Fields hated children and dogs. In reality, Fields was somewhat indifferent to dogs, but occasionally owned one.&lt;ref&gt;Curtis, James. ''W.C. Fields: A Biography''. New York: A. Knopf, 2003, p. 393.&lt;/ref&gt; He was fond of entertaining the children of friends who visited him, and doted on his first grandchild, Bill Fields III, born in 1943.&lt;ref&gt;Louvish, Simon. ''Man on the Flying Trapeze: The Life and Times of W.C. Fields'', 1999, Faber &amp; Faber, p. 464.&lt;/ref&gt; He sent encouraging replies to all of the letters he received from boys who, inspired by his performance in ''[[The Old Fashioned Way (film)|The Old Fashioned Way]]'', expressed an interest in juggling.&lt;ref&gt;Curtis, James. ''W.C. Fields: A Biography''. New York: A. Knopf, 2003, pp. 293–294.&lt;/ref&gt;

== Illness and career sideline ==
In 1936, Fields' heavy drinking precipitated a significant decline in his health. By the following year he recovered sufficiently to make one last film for Paramount, ''[[The Big Broadcast of 1938]]'', but his troublesome behavior discouraged other producers from hiring him. By 1938 he was chronically ill, and suffering from [[delirium tremens]].&lt;ref&gt;Curtis, James. ''W.C. Fields: A Biography''. New York: A. Knopf, 2003, pp. 355–70.&lt;/ref&gt;

[[File:Chase and Sanborn Hour.jpg|thumb|Edgar Bergen and his dummy Charlie McCarthy with W.C. Fields on The Chase and Sanborn Hour]]
Physically unable to work in films, Fields was off the screen for more than a year. During his absence, he recorded a brief speech for a radio broadcast. His familiar, snide drawl registered so well with listeners that he quickly became a popular guest on network radio shows.&lt;ref&gt;[http://pappawsotr.com/wcfields.htm W.C. Fields Radio recordings] {{webarchive |url=https://web.archive.org/web/20090615080148/http://pappawsotr.com/wcfields.htm |date=June 15, 2009 }}&lt;/ref&gt; Although his radio work was not as demanding as motion-picture production, Fields insisted on his established movie star salary of $5,000 per week. He joined ventriloquist [[Edgar Bergen]] and Bergen's dummy [[Charlie McCarthy]] on ''[[The Chase and Sanborn Hour]]'' for weekly insult-comedy routines.

Fields would twit Charlie about his being made of wood:
:'''Fields:''' "Tell me, Charles, is it true your father was a gate-leg table?"
:'''McCarthy''': "If it is, your father was under it!"

When Fields would refer to McCarthy as a "woodpecker's pin-up boy" or a "termite's flophouse", Charlie would fire back at Fields about his drinking:
:'''McCarthy''': "Is it true, Mr. Fields, that when you stood on the corner of Hollywood and Vine, 43 cars waited for your nose to change to green?"
Another exchange:
:'''Bergen:''' "Why, Bill, I thought you didn't like children." 
:'''Fields:''' "Oh, not at all, Edgar, I love children. I can remember when, with my own little unsteady legs, I toddled from room to room..."
:'''McCarthy''': "When was that, last night?"

During his recovery from illness, Fields reconciled with his estranged wife and established a close relationship with his son after Claude's marriage in 1938.&lt;ref&gt;Louvish, Simon. ''Man on the Flying Trapeze: The Life and Times of W.C. Fields'', 1999, Faber &amp; Faber, p.426.&lt;/ref&gt;

==Return to films==
Fields' renewed popularity from his radio broadcasts with Bergen and McCarthy earned him a contract with [[Universal Pictures]] in 1939. His first feature for Universal, ''[[You Can't Cheat an Honest Man]]'', carried on the Fields&amp;ndash;McCarthy rivalry. In 1940, Fields made ''[[My Little Chickadee]]'', with [[Mae West]], and ''[[The Bank Dick]]'', his best-known film, in which he has the following exchange with bartender [[Shemp Howard]]:
:'''Fields:''' "Was I in here last night, and did I spend a $20 bill?"
:'''Shemp:''' "Yeah."
:'''Fields:''' "Oh boy, what a load that is off my mind... I thought I'd ''lost'' it!"

Fields fought with studio producers, directors, and writers over the content of his films. He was determined to make a movie his way, with his own script and staging, and his choice of supporting players. Universal finally gave him the chance, and the resulting film, ''[[Never Give a Sucker an Even Break]]'' (1941), was a masterpiece of absurd humor in which Fields appeared as himself, "The Great Man". Universal's then-popuar singing star [[Gloria Jean]] played opposite Fields, and his cronies [[Leon Errol]] and [[Franklin Pangborn]] as his comic foils. Typically, the finished film was sufficienty surreal that Universal recut and reshot parts of it and ultimately released both the film and Fields. ''Sucker'' was Fields' last starring film.

==Final years==
Fields fraternized at his home with actors, directors and writers who shared his fondness for good company and good liquor. [[John Barrymore]], [[Gene Fowler]], and [[Gregory La Cava]] were among his close friends. On March 15, 1941, while Fields was out of town, Christopher Quinn, the two-year-old son of his neighbors, actor [[Anthony Quinn]] and his wife [[Katherine DeMille]], drowned in a lily pond on Fields' property.  Grief-stricken over the tragedy, he had the pond filled in.&lt;ref&gt;Curtis, James. ''W.C. Fields: A Biography''. New York: A. Knopf, 2003, pp. 434–435.&lt;/ref&gt;

Fields had a substantial library in his home. Although a staunch atheist—or perhaps because of it—he studied theology and collected books on the subject.&lt;ref name="Curtis_472"&gt;Curtis, James. ''W.C. Fields: A Biography''. New York: A. Knopf, 2003, p. 472.&lt;/ref&gt; According to a popular story (possibly apocryphal, according to biographer James Curtis), Fields told someone who caught him reading a Bible that he was "looking for loopholes".&lt;ref name="Curtis_472"/&gt;

In a 1994 episode of the ''[[Biography (TV series)|Biography]]'' television series, Fields' 1941 co-star [[Gloria Jean]] recalled her conversations with Fields at his home.  She described him as kind and gentle in personal interactions, and believed he yearned for the family environment he never experienced as a child.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite episode
| title = W. C. Fields: Behind the Laughter
| episodelink = 
| series = Biography
| serieslink = Biography (TV series)
| credits =
| network = A&amp;E
| airdate = August 8, 1994
}}&lt;/ref&gt;

During the 1940 presidential campaign, Fields authored a book, ''Fields for President'', with humorous essays in the form of a campaign speech. [[Dodd, Mead and Company]] published it in 1940, with illustrations by [[Otto Soglow]].&lt;ref&gt;Curtis, James. ''W.C. Fields: A Biography''. New York: A. Knopf, 2003, pp. 415–416.&lt;/ref&gt;  In 1971, when Fields was seen as an anti-establishment figure, Dodd, Mead issued a reprint, illustrated with photographs of the author.

Fields' film career slowed considerably in the 1940s. His illnesses confined him to brief guest film appearances. An extended sequence in [[20th Century Fox]]'s ''[[Tales of Manhattan]]'' (1942) was cut from the original release of the film and later reinstated for some home video releases.&lt;ref&gt;Curtis, James. ''W.C. Fields: A Biography''. New York: A. Knopf, 2003, pp. 454–456.&lt;/ref&gt; The scene featured a temperance meeting with society people at the home of a wealthy society matron [[Margaret Dumont]], in which Fields discovers that the punch has been spiked, resulting in drunken guests and a very happy Fields.

He enacted his famous billiard table routine for the final time for ''[[Follow the Boys]]'', an all-star entertainment revue for the Armed Forces. (Despite the charitable nature of the movie, Fields was paid $15,000 for this appearance; he was never able to perform in person for the armed services.) In ''[[Song of the Open Road]]'' (1944), Fields juggled for a few moments, remarking, "This used to be my racket."&lt;ref&gt;Curtis, James. ''W.C. Fields: A Biography''. New York: A. Knopf, 2003, p. 466.&lt;/ref&gt; His last film, the musical revue ''[[Sensations of 1945]]'', was released in late 1944. By then his vision and memory had so deteriorated that he had to read his lines from large-print blackboards.&lt;ref&gt;Louvish, Simon. ''Man on the Flying Trapeze: The Life and Times of W.C. Fields'', 1999, Faber &amp; Faber, p. 471.&lt;/ref&gt;

In 1944, Fields continued to make radio guest appearances, where script memorizations were unnecessary.  A notable guest slot was with [[Frank Sinatra]] on Sinatra's [[CBS]] radio program on February 9, 1944.

Field's last radio appearance was on March 24, 1946, on the [[Edgar Bergen]] and Charlie McCarthy Show on [[NBC]]. Just before his death that year, Fields recorded a spoken-word album, including his "Temperance Lecture" and "The Day I Drank a Glass of Water", at [[Les Paul]]'s studio, where Paul had installed a new multi-track recorder. The session was arranged by one of his radio writers, Bill Morrow, and was Fields' last performance.

Listening to one of Paul's experimental multi-track recordings, Fields remarked "The music you're making sounds like an octopus. Like a guy with a million hands. I've never heard anything like it." Paul was amused, and named his new machine OCT, short for octopus.&lt;ref&gt;The Early Years of the Les Paul Legacy, 1915-1963 By Robb Lawrence. Hal Leonard Books, New York NY&lt;/ref&gt;

==Death==
Fields spent the last 22 months of his life at the Las Encinas Sanatorium in [[Pasadena, California]]. In 1946, on Christmas Day—the holiday he said he despised—he had a massive gastric hemorrhage and died, aged 66.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |title=W.C. Fields, 66, Dies; Famed as Comedian — Mimicry Star of the Films Since 1924 Got Start as a $5-a-Week Juggler – Rarely Followed Script – Raspy Remarks and 'Know-It-All' Perspective Made Him Nation-Wide Character |url=https://www.nytimes.com/1946/12/26/archives/wc-fields-66-dies-famed-as-comedian-mimicry-star-of-the-films-since.html |quote=W.C. Fields, the comedian whose deadpan gestures, raspy remarks and "never give a sucker an even break" characterizations made him a showman beloved the nation over, died today at the age of 66. |work=New York Times |agency=Associated Press|date=December 26, 1946|page=25|access-date=October 9, 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt; Carlotta Monti wrote that in his final moments, she used a garden hose to spray water onto the roof over his bedroom to simulate his favorite sound, falling rain.&lt;ref&gt;Monti, C. ''W. C. Fields &amp; Me''. Prentice-Hall (1971), p. 218. {{ISBN|0139444548}}&lt;/ref&gt;  According to a 2004 documentary, he winked and smiled at a nurse, put a finger to his lips, and died.&lt;ref&gt;Adamson, J (dir.) ''W.C. Fields - Straight Up''. ASIN 1559746777.&lt;/ref&gt; This poignant depiction is uncorroborated and "unlikely", according to biographer James Curtis.&lt;ref name="Curtis_481"&gt;Curtis, James. ''W.C. Fields: A Biography''. New York: A. Knopf, 2003, p. 481.&lt;/ref&gt;  Fields' funeral took place on January 2, 1947, in [[Glendale, California]].&lt;ref&gt;Curtis, James. ''W.C. Fields: A Biography''. New York: A. Knopf, 2003, pp. 481–482.&lt;/ref&gt;

His cremation, as directed in his will, was delayed pending resolution of an objection filed by Hattie and Claude Fields on religious grounds.&lt;ref name="Curtis_481"/&gt; They also contested a clause leaving a portion of his estate to establish a "W. C. Fields College for Orphan White Boys and Girls, where no religion of any sort is to be preached".&lt;ref&gt;Louvish, Simon. ''Man on the Flying Trapeze: The Life and Times of W.C. Fields'', 1999, Faber &amp; Faber, p.474.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Buscombe, Edward, and Rob White. (2003). ''British Film Institute film classics. T. 1''. London: Fitzroy Dearborn. p. 269. {{ISBN|1579583288}}.&lt;/ref&gt; After a lengthy period of litigation his remains were cremated on June 2, 1949,&lt;ref&gt;Curtis, James. ''W.C. Fields: A Biography''. New York: A. Knopf, 2003, p. 486.&lt;/ref&gt; and his ashes interred at the [[Forest Lawn Memorial Park (Glendale)|Forest Lawn Memorial Park Cemetery]] in Glendale.

===Gravestone===
[[File:W. C. Fields Grave.JPG|thumb|Niche of W. C. Fields in the Columbarium of Nativity in the Great Mausoleum, Forest Lawn Glendale.]]
A popular bit of Fields folklore maintains that his grave marker is inscribed, "I'd rather be in Philadelphia"—or a close variant thereof. The legend originated from a mock epitaph written by Fields for a 1925 ''[[Vanity Fair (magazines)|Vanity Fair]]'' article: "Here Lies / W.C. Fields / I Would Rather Be Living in Philadelphia."&lt;ref&gt;Reprinted in ''Vanity Fair: Selections from America's Most Memorable Magazine'', edited by Cleveland Amory and Frederic Bradlee, Viking Press (1960), pp. 102-3.&lt;/ref&gt;  In reality, his interment marker bears only his stage name and the years of his birth and death.&lt;ref name="Louvish_34"&gt;Louvish, S. ''Man on the Flying Trapeze: The Life and Times of W.C. Fields''. Faber &amp; Faber (1999), p. 34.&lt;/ref&gt;

==Comic persona and style==
In 1937, in an article in ''[[Motion Picture (magazine)|Motion Picture]]'' magazine, Fields analyzed the characters he played:&lt;blockquote&gt;You've heard the old legend that it's the little put-upon guy who gets the laughs, but I'm the most belligerent guy on the screen. I'm going to kill everybody. But, at the same time, I'm afraid of everybody—just a great big frightened bully .... I was the first comic in world history, so they told me, to pick fights with children. I booted [[Baby LeRoy]] ... then, in another picture, I kicked a little dog .... But I got sympathy both times. People didn't know what the unmanageable baby might do to get even, and they thought the dog might bite me.&lt;ref&gt;Curtis, James. ''W.C. Fields: A Biography''. New York: A. Knopf, 2003, pp. 3–4.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

In features such as ''It's a Gift'' and ''[[Man on the Flying Trapeze]]'', he is reported to have written or improvised more or less all of his own dialogue and material, leaving story structure to other writers.&lt;ref&gt;Curtis, James. ''W.C. Fields: A Biography''. New York: A. Knopf, 2003, pp. 303–307, 331–332.&lt;/ref&gt; He frequently incorporated his stage sketches into his films—e.g., the "Back Porch" scene he wrote for the ''Follies'' of 1925 was filmed in ''It's the Old Army Game'' (1926) and ''It's a Gift'' (1934);&lt;ref&gt;Louvish, Simon. ''Man on the Flying Trapeze: The Life and Times of W.C. Fields'', 1999, Faber &amp; Faber, pp. 247, 495.&lt;/ref&gt; the golf sketch he performed in the lost film ''His Lordship's Dilemma'' (1915) was re-used in the ''Follies'' of 1918, and in the films ''So's Your Old Man'' (1926), ''The Golf Specialist'' (1930), ''The Dentist'' (1932), and ''You're Telling Me'' (1934).&lt;ref&gt;Louvish, Simon. ''Man on the Flying Trapeze: The Life and Times of W.C. Fields'', 1999, Faber &amp; Faber, pp. 190, 205, 312.&lt;/ref&gt;

Fields' most familiar characteristics included a distinctive drawl, which was not his normal speaking voice.&lt;ref&gt;Louvish, Simon. ''Man on the Flying Trapeze: The Life and Times of W.C. Fields'', 1999, Faber &amp; Faber, p. 313.&lt;/ref&gt; His manner of muttering deprecatory asides was copied from his mother, who in Fields' childhood often mumbled sly comments about neighbors who passed by.&lt;ref&gt;Louvish, Simon. ''Man on the Flying Trapeze: The Life and Times of W.C. Fields'', 1999, Faber &amp; Faber, pp. 31, 346.&lt;/ref&gt; He delighted in provoking the censors with [[double entendre]]s and the near-profanities "Godfrey Daniels" and "mother of pearl". A favorite bit of "business", repeated in many of his films, involved his hat going astray—either caught on the end of his cane, or simply facing the wrong way— as he attempts to put it onto his head.&lt;ref&gt;Louvish, Simon. ''Man on the Flying Trapeze: The Life and Times of W.C. Fields'', 1999, Faber &amp; Faber, p. 211.&lt;/ref&gt;

In several of his films, he played hustlers, carnival barkers, and [[card sharp]]s, spinning yarns and distracting his marks. In others, he cast himself as a victim: a bumbling [[everyman]] husband and father whose family does not appreciate him.&lt;ref&gt;Curtis, James. ''W.C. Fields: A Biography''. New York: A. Knopf, 2003, p. 3.&lt;/ref&gt;

Fields often reproduced elements of his own family life in his films. By the time he entered motion pictures, his relationship with his estranged wife had become acrimonious, and he believed she had turned their son Claude—whom he seldom saw—against him.&lt;ref&gt;Louvish, Simon. ''Man on the Flying Trapeze: The Life and Times of W.C. Fields'', 1999, Faber &amp; Faber, p. 191.&lt;/ref&gt;  James Curtis says of ''Man on the Flying Trapeze'' that the "disapproving mother-in-law, Mrs. Neselrode, was clearly patterned after his wife, Hattie, and the unemployable mama's boy played by [Grady] Sutton was deliberately named Claude. Fields hadn't laid eyes on his family in nearly twenty years, and yet the painful memories lingered."&lt;ref&gt;Curtis, James. ''W.C. Fields: A Biography''. New York: A. Knopf, 2003, p. 329.&lt;/ref&gt;

===Unusual names===
Although lacking formal education, Fields was well read and a lifelong admirer of author [[Charles Dickens]], whose characters' unusual names inspired Fields to collect odd names he encountered in his travels, to be used for his characters.&lt;ref&gt;Curtis, James. ''W.C. Fields: A Biography''. New York: A. Knopf, 2003, p. 300.&lt;/ref&gt;  Some examples are:
*"The Great McGonigle" (''The Old-Fashioned Way'');
*"Ambrose Wolfinger" [pointing toward "[[Wolf-whistling]]"] (''Man on the Flying Trapeze'');
*"Larson E. [read "[[Larceny]]"] Whipsnade", the surname taken from a dog track Fields had seen outside London&lt;ref&gt;Curtis, James. ''W.C. Fields: A Biography''. New York: A. Knopf, 2003, p. 378.&lt;/ref&gt; (''You Can't Cheat an Honest Man''), 
*"Egbert Sousé" [pronounced 'soo-ZAY', but pointing toward "souse", a synonym for a drunk] (''[[The Bank Dick]]'', 1940).

Fields often contributed to the scripts of his films under unusual pseudonyms. They include the seemingly prosaic "Charles [[Bogle]]", credited in four of his films in the 1930s; "Otis Criblecoblis", which contains an embedded [[homophone]] for "scribble"; and "Mahatma Kane Jeeves", a play on [[Mahatma]] and a phrase an aristocrat might use when about to leave the house: "My hat, my cane, [[Jeeves]]".&lt;ref&gt;Curtis, James. ''W.C. Fields: A Biography''. New York: A. Knopf, 2003, p. 424.&lt;/ref&gt;

===Supporting players===
Fields had a small cadre of supporting players that he employed in several films:
*[[Elise Cavanna]], whose onscreen interplay with Fields was compared (by [[William K. Everson]]) to that between [[Groucho Marx]] and [[Margaret Dumont]]&lt;ref&gt;Everson, William K. (1967). ''The Art of W.C. Fields''. New York: Bonanza Books. p. 81. {{ISBN|0-517-01232-4}}.&lt;/ref&gt;
*Jan Duggan, an old-maid character (actually about Fields' age).&lt;ref&gt;Jan Duggan (actress). [http://www.omnilexica.com/?q=Jan+Duggan+(actress) omnilexica.com]. Retrieved September 26, 2013.&lt;/ref&gt; It was of her character that Fields said in ''The Old Fashioned Way'', "She's all dressed up like a well-kept grave."
*[[Kathleen Howard]], as a nagging wife or antagonist
*[[Baby LeRoy]], as a preschool child fond of playing pranks on Fields' characters
*[[Franklin Pangborn]], a fussy, ubiquitous character actor who played in several Fields films, most memorably as J. Pinkerton Snoopington in ''The Bank Dick''
*[[Alison Skipworth]], as his wife (although 16 years his senior), usually in a supportive role rather than the stereotypical nag
*[[Grady Sutton]], typically a country bumpkin type, as a foil or an antagonist to Fields' character
*Bill Wolfe, as a gaunt-looking character, usually a Fields foil
*[[Tammany Young]], as a dim-witted, unintentionally harmful assistant, who appeared in seven Fields films until his sudden death from heart failure in 1936

==Unrealized film projects==
W. C. Fields was (with [[Ed Wynn]]) one of the two original choices for the title role in the 1939 version of ''[[The Wizard of Oz (1939 film)|The Wizard of Oz]]''. Fields was enthusiastic about the role, but ultimately withdrew his name from consideration so he could devote his time to writing ''[[You Can't Cheat an Honest Man]]''.&lt;ref&gt;Curtis, James. ''W.C. Fields: A Biography''. New York: A. Knopf, 2003, pp. 373–376.&lt;/ref&gt;

Fields figured in an [[Orson Welles]] project. Welles's bosses at [[RKO Radio Pictures]], after losing money on ''[[Citizen Kane]]'', urged Welles to choose as his next film a subject with more commercial appeal. Welles considered an adaptation of [[Charles Dickens]]' ''[[The Pickwick Papers]]'' which would have starred Fields, but the project was shelved, partly because of contract difficulties,&lt;ref&gt;Rippy, Marguerite H. (2009). [https://books.google.com/books?id=2V7H0uvU5wsC&amp;pg=PA66&amp;lpg= ''Orson Welles and the Unfinished RKO Projects: A Postmodern Perspective'']. SIU Press. p. 66. {{ISBN|0809329123}}.&lt;/ref&gt; and Welles went on to adapt ''[[The Magnificent Ambersons (film)|The Magnificent Ambersons]]''.

During the early planning for his film ''[[It's a Wonderful Life]]'', director [[Frank Capra]] considered Fields for the role of Uncle Billy, which eventually went to [[Thomas Mitchell (actor)|Thomas Mitchell]].&lt;ref&gt;Mell, Eila (2005). ''Casting might-have-beens: a film by film directory of actors considered for roles given to others''. Jefferson, N.C.: McFarland. p. 132. {{ISBN|0786420170}}.&lt;/ref&gt;

==Influence and legacy==
A best-selling biography of Fields published three years after his death, ''W.C. Fields, His Follies and Fortunes'' by Robert Lewis Taylor, was instrumental in popularizing the idea that Fields' real-life character matched his screen persona.&lt;ref&gt;Curtis, James. ''W.C. Fields: A Biography''. New York: A. Knopf, 2003, p. 487.&lt;/ref&gt; In 1973, the comedian's grandson, Ronald J. Fields, published the first book to significantly challenge this idea, ''W. C. Fields by Himself, His Intended Autobiography'', a compilation of material from private scrapbooks and letters found in the home of Hattie Fields after her death in 1963.&lt;ref&gt;Louvish, Simon. ''Man on the Flying Trapeze: The Life and Times of W.C. Fields'', 1999, Faber &amp; Faber, p. 11.&lt;/ref&gt;

According to [[Woody Allen]] (in a ''[[New York Times]]'' interview from January 30, 2000), W. C. Fields is one of six "genuine comic geniuses" he recognized as such in movie history, along with [[Charlie Chaplin]], [[Buster Keaton]], [[Groucho]] and [[Harpo Marx]], and [[Peter Sellers]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=https://www.nytimes.com/2000/01/30/arts/here-a-comic-genius-there-a-comic-genius.html?pagewanted=1|title=Here A Comic Genius, There A Comic Genius|date=January 30, 2000|work=New York Times}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The [[Surrealism|Surrealists]] loved Fields' absurdism and anarchistic pranks. [[Max Ernst]] painted a ''Project for a Monument to W.C. Fields'' (1957), and [[René Magritte]] made a ''Hommage to [[Mack Sennett]]'' (1934).

Fields is one of the figures that appears in the crowd scene on the cover of The Beatles' 1967 album ''[[Sgt. Pepper's Lonely Hearts Club Band]]''.

The [[United States Postal Service]] issued a W.C. Fields commemorative stamp on the comedian's 100th birthday, in January 1980.&lt;ref&gt;Curtis, James. ''W.C. Fields: A Biography''. New York: A. Knopf, 2003, pp. 491–492.&lt;/ref&gt;

===Caricatures and imitations===
*The character Horatio K. Boomer in the ''[[Fibber McGee and Molly]]'' radio show had a persona and delivery very much like the characters portrayed by W.C. Fields.
*A caricature of Fields appears in the ''[[Lucky Luke]]'' comic book album ''[[Western Circus (Lucky Luke)|Western Circus]]'' and again in the animated feature ''[[La Ballade des Dalton|Lucky Luke: The Ballad of the Daltons]]''.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=LWVZALDUd7c|title=Lucky Luke - Ballad Of the Daltons (1978) - English 4/8|date=October 17, 2009|work=YouTube}}&lt;/ref&gt; 
*Cartoonist [[Al Hirschfeld]] portrayed Fields in caricature many times, including the book cover illustrations for ''Drat!'', ''A Flask of Fields'', and ''Godfrey Daniels!'' – all edited by Richard J. Anobile.{{citation needed|date=July 2013}}
*The TV show ''[[Gigglesnort Hotel]]'' featured a puppet character named "W. C. Cornfield" who resembled Fields in appearance and voice.&lt;ref&gt;Woolery, George W. (1983). ''Children's television, the first thirty-five years, 1946–1981''. Metuchen, N.J.: Scarecrow Press. p. 199. {{ISBN|0810815575}}.&lt;/ref&gt;
*Impressionist [[Rich Little]] often imitated Fields on his TV series ''[[The Kopycats]]'', and he used a Fields characterization for the [[Ebenezer Scrooge]] character in his [[HBO]] special ''[[Rich Little's Christmas Carol]]'' (1978), a one-man presentation of ''[[A Christmas Carol]]''.
*A 1960s Canadian cartoon series for kids ''[[Tales of the Wizard of Oz]]'' featured a Wizard with a voice imitation of Fields, a nod to the real-life choice of Fields to play the Wizard in the 1939 film classic opposite [[Judy Garland]].
* Fields is among the many celebrities caricatured in the 1936 [[Merrie Melodies]] short ''[[The Coo-Coo Nut Grove]]''. 
* Fields is seen sitting on the spectators' bench in the Disney cartoon ''[[Mickey's Polo Team]]'' (1936). 
* He appears as W.C. Fieldmouse in the Merrie Melodies short ''[[The Woods Are Full of Cuckoos]]'' (1937). 
* In the 1938 [[Silly Symphonies]] cartoon ''[[Mother Goose Goes Hollywood]]'' Fields is caricatured as [[Humpty Dumpty]], in reference to his role in the live-action film ''[[Alice in Wonderland (1933 film)|Alice in Wonderland]]'' (1933). 
* One episode of ''[[The Flintstones]]'' featured a tramp who gets old clothes belonging to Fred from his wife Wilma, then when Fred attempts to take back a coat, is trounced with the tramp's cane. The tramp has Fields' voice and persona.
*A character on ''How Can You Be In Two Places At Once When You're Not Anywhere At All'' by the [[Firesign Theatre]] features a character who speaks like W.C. Fields.
*''[[The Wizard of Id]]'' comic strip contains a shady lawyer character, a Fields caricature named "Larsen E. Pettifogger".
*In the second series of the TV drama ''[[Gangsters (TV series)|Gangsters]]'' a character named the White Devil is introduced, who styles himself W.D. Fields affecting the vocal mannerisms and appearance of W.C. Fields to confuse and confound his enemies. Played by series writer [[Philip Martin (screenwriter)|Philip Martin]], he himself is credited in the final episode as "Larson E. Whipsnade" after Fields' character in ''[[You Can't Cheat an Honest Man]]''.
* Actor Bob Leeman portrayed Fields in the 1991 movie ''[[The Rocketeer (film)|The Rocketeer]]''.
* In 1971 [[Frito-Lay]] replaced the ''[[Frito Bandito]]'' TV ad campaign with one featuring W.C. Fritos, a round, top-hat wearing character modeled on the movie persona of Fields. Also, circa 1970 [[Sunkist Growers]] produced a series of animated TV ads featuring the "Sunkist Monster," whose voice was an impression of Fields performed by [[Paul Frees]].
*Canadian actor [[Andrew Chapman]] played W.C Fields in a vaudeville-themed episode of "[[Murdoch Mysteries]]" in season 8, titled "The Keystone Constables".
*Comedian [[Mark Proksch]] impersonates Fields in a number of [[On Cinema]] episodes, included the series' Second Annual Oscar Special.

==Filmography==

Information for this filmography is derived from the book, ''W. C. Fields: A Life on Film'', by Ronald J. Fields.  All films are feature length except where noted.

{| class="wikitable sortable" width="100%"
! Release date
! Title
! Role
! Director
! class="unsortable"|Notes
|- 
| {{dts|1915}}
| (untitled film)
| Himself
| {{sort|Wynn|[[Ed Wynn]]}}
| Short film presented as part of the ''Ziegfeld Follies of 1915''; [[lost film]]
|-
| {{dts|1915|9|19}}
| ''[[Pool Sharks]]''
| {{sort|pool|The pool shark}}
| {{sort|Middleton|Edwin Middleton}}
| One reel; story by W.C. Fields; extant
|-
| {{dts|1915|10|3}}
| ''[[His Lordship's Dilemma]]''
| Remittance man
| {{sort|Haddock|William Haddock}}
| One reel; lost film
|-
| {{dts|1924|10|27}}
| ''[[Janice Meredith]]''
| {{sort|British|A British sergeant}}
| {{sort|Hopper|[[E. Mason Hopper]]}}
| extant
|-
| {{dts|1925|8|2}}
| ''[[Sally of the Sawdust]]''
| {{sort|McGargle|Professor Eustace P. McGargle}}
| {{sort|Griffith|[[D. W. Griffith]]}}
| extant
|-
| {{dts|1925|10|7}}
| ''[[That Royle Girl]]''
| {{sort|Royle|Daisy Royle's father}}
| {{sort|Griffith|D. W. Griffith}}
| [[lost film]]
|-
| {{dts|1926|5|24}}
| ''[[It's the Old Army Game]]''
| {{sort|Prettywillie|Elmer Prettywillie}}
| {{sort|Sutherland|[[A. Edward Sutherland]]}}
| Story by J.P. McEvoy and W.C. Fields; extant
|-
| {{dts|1926|10|26}}
| ''[[So's Your Old Man]]''
| {{sort|Bisbee|Samuel Bisbee}}
| {{sort|La Cava|[[Gregory La Cava]]}}
| extant
|-
| {{dts|1927|1|31}}
| ''{{sort|pot|[[The Potters (film)|The Potters]]}}''
| {{sort|Potter|Pa Potter}}
| {{sort|Newmeyer|[[Fred C. Newmeyer]]}}
| lost film
|-
| {{dts|1927|8|20}}
| ''[[Running Wild (1927 film)|Running Wild]]''
| {{sort|Finch|Elmer Finch}}
| {{sort|La Cava|[[Gregory La Cava]]}}
| extant
|-
| {{dts|1927|10|17}}
| ''[[Two Flaming Youths]]''
| {{sort|Gilfoil|J. G. "Gabby" Gilfoil}}
| {{sort|Waters|[[John S. Waters]]}}
| lost film
|-
| {{dts|1928|3|3}}
| ''[[Tillie's Punctured Romance (1928 film)|Tillie's Punctured Romance]]''
| {{sort|Ringmaster|The Ringmaster}}
| {{sort|Sutherland|[[A. Edward Sutherland]]}}
| lost film
|-
| {{dts|1928|5|7}}
| ''[[Fools for Luck]]''
| {{sort|Whitehead|Richard Whitehead}}
| {{sort|Reisner|Charles F. Reisner}}
| lost film
|-
| {{dts|1930|8|22}}
| ''{{sort|golf|[[The Golf Specialist]]}}''
| {{sort|Bellwether|J. Effingham Bellwether}}
| {{sort|Brice|Monte Brice}}
| Two reels; story by W.C. Fields (uncredited)
|-
| {{dts|1931|10|26}}
| ''[[Her Majesty, Love]]''
| {{sort|Toerrek|Bela Toerrek}}
| {{sort|Dieterle|[[William Dieterle]]}}
|
|-
| {{dts|1932|7|8}}
| ''[[Million Dollar Legs (1932 film)|Million Dollar Legs]]''
| President of Klopstokia
| {{sort|Cline|Edward Cline}}
|
|-
| {{dts|1932|10|2}}
| ''[[If I Had a Million]]''
| {{sort|La|Rollo La Rue}}
| {{sort|Taurog|[[Norman Taurog]]}}
|
|-
| {{dts|1932|10|9}}
| ''{{sort|den|[[The Dentist (1932 film)|The Dentist]]}}''
| Himself
| {{sort|Pearce|Leslie Pearce}}
| Two reels; story by W.C. Fields (uncredited)
|-
| {{dts|1933|3|3}}
| ''{{sort|fat|[[The Fatal Glass of Beer (1933 film)|The Fatal Glass of Beer]]}}''
| {{sort|Snavely|Mr. Snavely}}
| {{sort|Bruckman|[[Clyde Bruckman]]}}
| Two reels; story by W.C. Fields (uncredited)
|-
| {{dts|1933|4|21}}
| ''{{sort|phar|[[The Pharmacist (1933 film)|The Pharmacist]]}}''
| {{sort|Dilweg|Mr. Dilweg}}
| {{sort|Ripley|[[Arthur Ripley]]}}
| Two reels; story by W.C. Fields (uncredited)
|-
| {{dts|1933|6|2}}
| ''[[International House (1933 film)|International House]]''
| {{sort|Quail|Professor Quail}}
| {{sort|Sutherland|[[A. Edward Sutherland]]}}
|
|-
| {{dts|1933|6|24}}
| ''[[Hip Action]]''
| Himself
| {{sort|Marshall|[[George Marshall (director)|George Marshall]]}}
| One reel
|-
| {{dts|1933|7|28}}
| ''{{sort|barb|[[The Barber Shop]]}}''
| {{sort|O'Hare|Cornelius O'Hare}}
| {{sort|Ripley|[[Arthur Ripley]]}}
| Two reels; story by W.C. Fields (uncredited)
|-
| {{dts|1933|9|8}}
| ''{{sort| Hollywood on Parade No. B-02|[[Hollywood on Parade|Hollywood on Parade No. B-2]]}}''
| Himself
| {{sort|Lewyn|Louis Lewyn}}
| One reel
|-
| {{dts|1933|10|13}}
| ''[[Tillie and Gus]]''
| {{sort|Winterbottom|Augustus Q. Winterbottom}}
| {{sort|Martin|Francis Martin}}
| Fields as contributing writer (uncredited)
|-
| {{dts|1933|10|22}}
| ''[[Alice in Wonderland (1933 film)|Alice in Wonderland]]''
| [[Humpty Dumpty]]
| {{sort|McLeod|[[Norman Z. McLeod|Norman McLeod]]}}
|
|-
| {{dts|1934|2|9}}
| ''[[Six of a Kind]]''
| {{sort|Hoxley|Sheriff "Honest John" Hoxley}}
| {{sort|McCarey|[[Leo McCarey]]}}
|
|-
| {{dts|1934|4|6}}
| ''[[You're Telling Me!]]''
| {{sort|Bisbee|Sam Bisbee}}
| {{sort|Kenton|[[Erle C. Kenton]]}}
| Fields as contributing writer (uncredited)
|-
| {{dts|1934|4|27}}
| ''[[Hollywood on Parade|Hollywood on Parade No. B-10]]''
| Himself
| {{sort|Lewyn|Louis Lewyn}}
| One reel
|-
| {{dts|1934|7|13}}
| ''{{sort|old|[[The Old Fashioned Way (film)|The Old Fashioned Way]]}}''
| {{sort|McGonigle|The Great (Marc Antony) McGonigle}}
| {{sort|Beaudine|[[William Beaudine]]}}
| Story by "Charles Bogle" (W.C. Fields)
|-
| {{dts|1934|10|19}}
| ''[[Mrs. Wiggs of the Cabbage Patch (1934 film)|Mrs. Wiggs of the Cabbage Patch]]''
| {{sort|Stubbins|Mr. C. Ellsworth Stubbins}}
| {{sort|Taurog|[[Norman Taurog]]}}
|
|-
| {{dts|1934|11|30}}
| ''[[It's a Gift]]''
| {{sort|Bissonette|Harold Bissonette}}
| {{sort|McLeod|[[Norman Z. McLeod|Norman McLeod]]}}
| Original story by "Charles Bogle" (W.C. Fields)
|-
| {{dts|1935|10|13}}
| ''[[Personal History, Adventures, Experience, and Observation of David Copperfield the Younger|David Copperfield]]''
| {{sort|Micawber|[[Wilkins Micawber]]}}
| {{sort|Cukor|[[George Cukor]]}}
|
|-
| {{dts|1935|3|22}}
| ''[[Mississippi (1935 film)|Mississippi]]''
| {{sort|Jackson|Commodore Orlando Jackson}}
| {{sort|Sutherland|[[A. Edward Sutherland]]}}
|
|-
| {{dts|1935|7|26}}
| ''[[Man on the Flying Trapeze]]''
| {{sort|Wolfinger|Ambrose Wolfinger}}
| {{sort|Bruckman|[[Clyde Bruckman]]}}
| Story by "Charles Bogle" (W.C. Fields)
|-
| {{dts|1936|6|19}}
| ''[[Poppy (1936 film)|Poppy]]''
| {{sort|McGargle|Professor Eustace P. McGargle}}
| {{sort|Sutherland|[[A. Edward Sutherland]]}}
|
|-
| {{dts|1938|2|18}}
| ''{{sort|big|[[The Big Broadcast of 1938]]}}''
| {{sort|Bellows|T. Frothingill Bellows&lt;br&gt;S. B. Bellows}}
| {{sort|Leisen|[[Mitchell Leisen]]}}
|
|-
| {{dts|1939|2|17}}
| ''[[You Can't Cheat an Honest Man]]''
| {{sort|Whipsnade|Larson E. Whipsnade}}
| {{sort|Marshall|[[George Marshall (director)|George Marshall]]}}
| Story by "Charles Bogle" (W.C. Fields)
|-
| {{dts|1940|2|9}}
| ''[[My Little Chickadee]]''
| {{sort|Twillie|Cuthbert J. Twillie}}
| {{sort|Cline|[[Edward F. Cline|Edward Cline]]}}
| Bar scene written by W.C. Fields
|-
| {{dts|1940|11|29}}
| ''{{sort|bank|[[The Bank Dick]]}}''
| {{sort|Sousè|Egbert Sousè}}
| {{sort|Cline|Edward Cline}}
| Story by "Mahatma Kane Jeeves" (W.C. Fields)
|-
| {{dts|1941|10|10}}
| ''[[Never Give a Sucker an Even Break]]''
| {{sort|Great|The Great Man}}
| {{sort|Cline|Edward Cline}}
| Original story by "Otis Criblecoblis" (W.C. Fields).  Final starring film.
|-
| unreleased
| ''{{sort|laz|The Laziest Golfer}}''
| Himself
| (unknown)
| Footage shot but never assembled
|-
| {{dts|1942|10|30}}
| ''[[Tales of Manhattan]]''
| {{sort|Postlewhistle|Professor Postlewhistle}}
| {{sort|Duvivier|[[Julien Duvivier]]}}
| Guest sequence with Fields cut from original release, restored for home video., (uncredited)
|-
| {{dts|1944|5|5}}
| ''[[Follow the Boys]]''
| Himself (Guest sequence)
| {{sort|Sutherland|[[A. Edward Sutherland]]}}
| Fields revived his old trick pool table routine
|-
| {{dts|1944|6|21}}
| ''[[Song of the Open Road]]''
| Himself (Guest sequence)
| {{sort|Simon|[[S. Sylvan Simon]]}}
| Fields juggled for a few moments
|-
| {{dts|1944|6|30}}
| ''[[Sensations of 1945]]''
| Himself (Guest sequence)
| {{sort|Stone|[[Andrew L. Stone]]}}
| Fields revived part of his old "Caledonian Express" sketch (last appearance)
|}

==References==
{{Reflist|2}}

==Further reading==
*W. C. Fields, ''Fields for President'' (1940, 1971) Dodd, Mead {{ISBN|0-396-06419-1}}. (Humorous essays about Fields' stance on marriage, politics, finance, etc.)
*[[Robert Lewis Taylor]], ''W.C. Fields: His Follies and Fortunes'' (1949) Doubleday &amp; Co., (1967) New American Library {{ISBN|0-451-50653-7}}. (First book biography, with many firsthand quotes from friends and colleagues)
*[[Gene Fowler]], ''Minutes of the Last Meeting'' (1954) Viking Press
*[[Eddie Cantor]], ''As I Remember Them'' (1963) Duell, Sloan &amp; Pearce
*Donald Deschner (ed.), ''The Films of W.C. Fields'' (1966, 2000) Citadel Press
*[[Corey Ford]], "The One and Only W.C. Fields" from ''The Time of Laughter'' (1967) Little, Brown
*[[William K. Everson]], ''The Art of W.C. Fields'' (1967) Random House {{ISBN|0-517-01232-4}}. (First book-length examination of the Fields films)
*Richard J. Anobile (ed.), ''Drat!: Being the Encapsulated View of Life by W. C. Fields in His Own Words'' (1968) World Publishing
*[[David Robinson (film critic)|David Robinson]], ''The Great Funnies: A History of Film Comedy'' (1969) E.P. Dutton
*Jan Kindler, "Elysian Fields" from ''[[Playboy]]'' (March 1969)
*[[Bosley Crowther]], "W.C. Fields Comedy Festival" from ''New York Times Film Reviews, 1959–1968'' (1970) Arno Press
*Andre Sennwald, capsule reviews from ''New York Times Film Reviews, 1932–1938'' (1970) Arno Press
*[[Raymond Durgnat]], "Suckers and Soaks" from ''The Crazy Mirror: Hollywood Comedy and the American Image'' (1970) Dell Publishing
*[[Andrew Bergman]], "Some Anarcho-Nihilist Laff Riots" from ''We're in the Money: Depression America and Its Films'' (1971) New York University Press
*[[Otis Ferguson]], "The Great McGonigle" from ''The Film Criticism of Otis Ferguson'' (1971) Temple University Press
*[[Carlotta Monti]] (with Cy Rice), ''W.C. Fields and Me'' (1971) Prentice-Hall, {{ISBN|978-0139444548}}. (basis of the [[W.C. Fields and Me|1976 film]] starring [[Rod Steiger]])
*Richard J, Anobile (ed.), ''A Flask of Fields: Verbal and Visual Gems from the Films of W.C. Fields'' (1972) W.W. Norton
*[[Leonard Maltin]], ''Selected Short Subjects'' (first published as ''The Great Movie Shorts'', 1972) Crown Publishers, (revised 1983) Da Capo Press
*Ronald J. Fields (ed.), ''W.C. Fields by Himself: His Intended Autobiography with Hitherto Unpublished Letters, Notes, Scripts and Articles'' (1973) Prentice-Hall {{ISBN|0-13-944462-9}}.
*W. C. Fields (with Charles Grayson), ''The Bank Dick'' (1973) Simon &amp; Schuster (the August 22, 1940 screenplay)
*W. C. Fields (with John T. Neville, et al.), ''Never Give a Sucker an Even Break'' (Rupert Hughes, et al.) ''Tillie and Gus'' (1973) Simon &amp; Schuster (Continuity scripts derived from these films)
*[[Penelope Gilliatt]], "To W.C. Fields, Dyspeptic Mumbler, Who Invented His Own Way Out" from ''Unholy Fools: Wits, Comics, Disturbers of the Peace'' (1973) Viking Press
*[[Gerald Mast]], ''The Comic Mind: Comedy and the Movies'' (1973, 2nd ed. 1979) University of Chicago Press
*Donald W. McCaffrey, "The Latter-Day Falstaff" from ''The Golden Age of Sound Comedy'' (1973) A.S. Barnes
*Nicholas Yanni, ''W.C. Fields'' (1974) Pyramid Library
*Richard J. Anobile (ed.), ''Godfrey Daniels!: Verbal and Visual Gems from the Short Films of W. C. Fields'' (1975) Crown
*[[Walter Kerr]], ''The Silent Clowns'' (1975) Alfred A. Knopf, (1990) Da Capo Press
*Stuart Byron and Elizabeth Weis (eds.), ''The National Society of Film Critics on Movie Comedy'' (1977) Grossman/Viking
*[[Leonard Maltin]], ''The Great Movie Comedians'' (1978) Crown
*[[Will Fowler]], ''The Second Handshake'' (1980) Lyle Stuart
*[[Louise Brooks]], "The Other Face of W.C. Fields" from ''Lulu in Hollywood'' (1982) Alfred A. Knopf
*Ronald J. Fields, ''W.C. Fields: A Life on Film'' (1984) St. Martin's Press
*Wes D. Gehring, ''W.C. Fields: A Bio-Bibliography'' (1984) Greenwood Press
*Gerald Weales, ''Canned Goods as Caviar: American Film Comedy of the 1930s'' (1985) University of Chicago Press
*David T. Rocks, ''W.C. Fields: An Annotated Guide'' (1993) McFarland &amp; Co.
*Wes D. Gehring, ''Groucho and W.C. Fields: Huckster Comedians'' (1994) University Press of Mississippi
*[[Simon Louvish]], ''It's a Gift'' (1994) British Film Institute
*[[Simon Louvish]], ''Man on the Flying Trapeze: The Life and Times of W.C. Fields'' (1999) Faber &amp; Faber {{ISBN|0-393-04127-1}}. (New biography with new research)
*Ronald J. Fields with Shaun O'L. Higgins, ''Never Give a Sucker an Even Break: W.C. Fields on Business'' (2000) Prentice-Hall
*[[James Curtis (biographer)|James Curtis]], ''W.C. Fields: A Biography'' (2003) Alfred A. Knopf {{ISBN|0-375-40217-9}}. (''The'' definitive, comprehensive biography, with many "apocryphal" stories from previous bios corrected)
*[[Scott MacGillivray]] and Jan MacGillivray, ''[[Gloria Jean]]: A Little Bit of Heaven'' (2005) iUniverse {{ISBN|978-0-595-67454-1}}. (Authorized biography with recollections of Fields at work)
*Wes D. Gehring, ''Film Clowns of the Depression'' (2007) McFarland &amp; Co.
*Gregory William Mank (et al.), ''Hollywood's Hellfire Club'' (2007) Feral House
* Arthur Frank Wertheim. ''W. C. Fields from Burlesque and Vaudeville to Broadway: Becoming a Comedian'' (Palgrave Macmillan, 2014). xxvi, 264 pp.
*[[James L. Neibaur]], ''The W.C. Fields Films'' (2017) McFarland and Co.

==External links==
{{toomanylinks|date=July 2018}}
{{sisterlinks|d=Q352971|n=no|b=no|c=Category:W. C. Fields|v=no|voy=no|s=no|wikt=no|m=no|mw=no|species=no}}
*{{Official site}}
*{{IMDb name|1211}}
*{{IBDB name}}
*[http://www.webtrec.com/wcfields/index.html Official fan club]
*[http://www.criterion.com/asp/release.asp?id=79&amp;eid=127&amp;section=essay Criterion Collection essay by Dennis Perrin on ''W.C. Fields: Six Short Films'']
*[https://archive.org/details/fatal_glass_of_beer The Fatal Glass of Beer] [https://archive.org/details/fatal_glass_of_beer_ipod (iPod format)] at the [[Internet Archive]]
* [http://film.virtual-history.com/person.php?personid=1619 Bibliography]	
* W.C. Fields' first show for the [http://jack_benny.podomatic.com/entry/eg/2010-01-25T13_50_52-08_00 Chase And Sanborn Hour 1937-05-09 (01) Guest – Ann Harding]		
* {{findagrave|1148}}
{{Authority control}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Fields, W. C.}}
[[Category:W. C. Fields| ]]
[[Category:1880 births]]
[[Category:1946 deaths]]
[[Category:20th-century American male actors]]
[[Category:20th-century atheists]]
[[Category:People from Darby, Pennsylvania]]
[[Category:Male actors from New Rochelle, New York]]
[[Category:Male actors from Philadelphia]]
[[Category:Alcohol-related deaths in California]]
[[Category:American male comedians]]
[[Category:American male comedy actors]]
[[Category:American comedians]]
[[Category:American male radio actors]]
[[Category:American male film actors]]
[[Category:American male silent film actors]]
[[Category:American people of English descent]]
[[Category:Burials at Forest Lawn Memorial Park (Glendale)]]
[[Category:Jugglers]]
[[Category:Trick shot artists]]
[[Category:Vaudeville performers]]
[[Category:Paramount Pictures contract players]]
[[Category:Ziegfeld Follies]]
[[Category:Silent film comedians]]</text>
      <sha1>pl8vsstuq0xhb11c21v7sayzxk3mrmw</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
